Hey, guys.
Welcome to day one of your 100 day journey.
And today, we're going to learn about printing, commenting, debugging, string manipulation and variables.
So it's chockablock full of really fun stuff.
And by the end of today, you will have created a band name generator program.
So this is the final project of today.
And the idea is that let's say that your friend was starting a new band, a rock band or a classical
band, and they're struggling to come up with a good name.
So you come in to the rescue and send them your band name generator program.
So it asks you for the name of the city that you grew up in.
So mine was Bristol in the southwest of the UK.
And then it'll ask you, what's the name of your pet?
I had a pet rabbit when I was younger, and I am probably the least imaginative person.
Classic programmer personality.
So I called my rabbit.
"Rabbit".
So now when I hit "Enter", it's going to give me my band name.
And it could be Bristol Rabbit.
So that sounds pretty cool.
That could be like a a rock band.
So this is what you're going to make.
And in the process, in order to create this, you're going to learn about printing, inputting, commenting,
debugging, name errors, syntax errors, string manipulation variables, and a whole lot more.
So if you feel like you can already achieve this and you can prove it by making this program yourself,
then feel free to skip to the next day's lessons.
But for most of you, even if you've started learning Python programming, there's probably still a
lot of new things that you'll find in today's lessons.
Now, as with all the projects that we're making in this course, you get to try it out before you make
it so you can either go to the URL.
Alternatively, if you don't want to type out the full URL, you can head over to the course content
here and then click on the resources and click this link to head straight over there.
And then once you're there, all you have to do is to click run and you'll be able to preview how the
final product is going to work.
So you can type in your own city and follow the instructions until you get to the end result.
So once you're ready, head over to the next lesson and let's get started and get coding straight away.
To begin open up your browser and head over to this URL.
Now, if you didn't want to type all of that out and make some typos and errors and not get to the right
place, then simply just head over to the course resources and click on the link there.
It'll take you directly to this page.
Now, once you've clicked on the link that takes you to the starting replit, you should see something
that looks like this.
And the first thing I want you to do is to go ahead and click on the "Fork" button.
What this is going to do is it's going to create a version of that same replit that you'll see me
working through in the videos, but in this case you'll be able to edit it.
So if you want to save the work that you're doing, I recommend signing up to replit.
It's completely free.
You don't need any credit cards or anything.
Once you've created your account on replit, it will take you to the previous page where you can now
actually click the fork repl button.
And what that will do is it will create a copy of what I've created and put it into your account, and
then you'll be able to see a record of all of the code that you've written throughout the course.
In this course you'll be coding along with me on replit and completing a whole bunch of interactive
coding exercises in our replit classroom.
So go ahead, pause the video, sign up to replit and make sure you've forked the starting copy of
Day one printing start and you should be on a screen that looks like this.
And once you're signed in, then you can actually go ahead and edit the name of the replit or add a
brief description and you'll be able to access it later on through the My Repls folder.
Now, once you've done that, then let's go ahead and walk through some of the different parts of replit
that you'll be using.
First, on the left-hand side pane here, you've got some files and you can see the current file that's
open is this Python file here, and you can create new files or you can create new folders and later
on will be using these features to organize our code.
Now the other part of the left hand side pane that's really useful is the Settings tab here, and I
recommend everybody to switch their font size up to large.
This just makes it so much easier to identify mistakes and any typos you make.
Now we're going to leave everything else as it is, and you can click on the settings button to collapse
that pane so that you end up with more space for writing code.
And this area here is where you're going to be doing that.
All of your code is going to go inside here.
And once we're done with writing our code, we'll click run and it will execute.
And the results of our code will come up over on the console in the right here.
And I generally prefer to code using a darker background.
It's slightly easier on my eyes, especially when you're working at night.
So these are some of the most important parts of replit, but the important thing is it allows us to
just get started.
Now remember that the whole reason why we're learning to program is to be able to tell the computer
what it needs to do and for it to follow our commands.
So let's go ahead and tell the computer to do something, and we're going to do that by writing our
first line of code.
So in this case, I'm creating something called a print function, which is just the word "print", all
in lowercase, and then followed by a set of parentheses.
Now inside these parentheses, I'm going to tell it what I want it to print, and hopefully it's going
to output that inside our console.
So I'm going to start off by writing the classic "Hello World" inside here.
And then once you're ready, then go ahead and click Run.
After a few seconds, you should see the computer follow your command, namely printing the words that
you told it to print inside the console or the output area over here.
And once it's done, it indicates that with the little orange arrow and the way that this command works
is super simple.
You have the keyword "print" followed by a set of parentheses, and then inside the parentheses you tell
it what you want it to print.
And once you've inserted that, then when this line of code gets executed by the computer, it'll know
to simply print or output the thing that you've placed in between the parentheses.
But notice here that it's not just the word hello world exclamation mark that I've put inside my parentheses.
I've also added some quotation marks or double quotes around the word.
And the reason why I've done this is so that I can tell the computer that this bit here in between the
double quotes is not code.
It's not like print where it's supposed to do something.
This is just some text that I've made up that I want it to print out.
And these pieces of text in programming lingo is known as strings.
And you can imagine it as almost like a pearl necklace, right?
It's a string of characters.
And what the double quotes do is they basically show the beginning and the end of that string of characters.
So that means you have to be really careful when you're typing.
For example, if I go ahead and I miss out the closing double quote.
Well, now you can see that there's some changes that have happened to our code already, namely that
the last parentheses, instead of being coloured in white like the opening parentheses or how it used
to be, it's now coloured in orange.
And this is a subtle hint to us.
You're going to get really attuned to these subtle hints because they are the clues that will tell you
what might have gone wrong in your code.
If I run this code as it is right now, it's going to break.
It's going to give me a syntax error and it says something that seems like it's completely non English.
So how can we figure out what this means?
Now the thing I want you to know is that all programmers make mistakes.
We all make lots of errors, like forgetting to add the double quotes at the end of the string or forgetting
to add a closing parentheses.
These things are just common errors because we're human.
But the thing that differentiates great programmers is we're really good at figuring out what the problem
is and how to fix it.
So you can imagine that coding is just a whole bunch of problems that you have to solve.
And in this case, when we get some sort of red text on the right and our code is not doing what we
expect it to do, then all we have to do is take this entire error message where it says something,
something error, and this is some sort of message that we're supposed to understand and we're simply
going to drop it into Google.
And usually the first link you come across will be from a website called StackOverflow.com.
And this is basically the Q&A website that all developers will go to whenever something is wrong with
their code or when they can't figure out how to do something.
So if we click on this link, you can see that somebody else has also had this error.
And some kind souls have told us that the solution might be the fact that you're missing a double quote
before the end of the line.
So if we take a look back at our code, the code that generated this error looks like this.
And indeed, we are missing a double quote at the end of our string.
As you're learning to code, as you're going through your 100 days, I want you to become more and more
attuned to the color of your code.
Because one of the most helpful things that code editors such as this do for us is something called
syntax highlighting.
For example, when I was missing that double quote, it highlighted this entire thing in this orange
color.
And that is basically it telling us it seems like this whole thing is some text.
It thinks that all of this is a string and that we're missing a closing parenthesis.
So if you notice this and you're like, Wait, actually that's not right.
This part should be orange because this is what I want to be printed.
But this part should match the color of the open brace, which is white.
So there must be something wrong here.
And indeed, if you have a look at the error message, it actually has a little carat sign right here
showing you that there's something that's probably not right here and it might jog your memory that,
oh, yeah, I've forgotten a closing double quote.
And now when we run our code, you'll see that it's good as new.
So now it's your turn to try it out in a code challenge.
Head over to the next lesson.
Sign up to our classroom and then I'll guide you through getting started on your first coding challenge.
So all of that and more.
I'll see you on the next lesson.
Throughout this course, we'll be getting you involved in a lot of these interactive coding exercises.
And the idea is that you're not just sitting here watching me talk, that you're actually putting everything
you're learning into practice.
That way it actually becomes your own.
It's a great because we can give you instructions and show you what should happen if you write the correct
code, what it needs to do, and you'll be able to write your code as well as see it run in the console.
Once you're done with your code, you'll be able to submit it and see the tests run.
And if you've written the code correctly, then all of the tests will pass.
If your code isn't doing what it's supposed to.
Then when you click submit, you'll get feedback and you'll see what it's meant to do and what your
code is actually doing.
So you'll be able to use that to figure out what's wrong and fix your code.
And it's through a lot of these exercises that you're going to level up and you're going to become a
better coder.
Now, in order for you to get set up on our coding rooms, we're going to have to get you signed up
and registered with our course.
So in order to do this, I want you to first head over to codingrooms.com and then sign up for
a student account.
Now this is completely free and all you have to do is just do click, sign up, putting your email and
password, and then you can choose student for this question Who are you?
And then putting your first name and last name and click "Finish". Next,
in order to get hold of the Joining Link, I want you to go to the course resources for the current
lesson on Udemy.
So the lesson is "[Interactive Coding Exercise] Printing", and then I want you to click on the dropdown
list and you should see step one sign up to coding rooms, which you should have already done.
And then step two is join our coding room.
So I want you to click on that link.
And once you've clicked on that link, then it should automatically enroll you into our 100 days of
code, the Complete Python Pro Bootcamp, and you should now be able to see every day's corresponding
interactive coding exercises.
So for example, on day one there are four exercises and they are named exactly the same as what you
see in Udemy.
So this is interactive coding exercise one which is printing, debugging, practice, input, function
and variables and you see all the same ones over here that you'll be able to attempt.
Now the next time when you log in, all you have to do is just go into your courses and you should see
the interactive coding exercises for the 100 days of code, and you will be able to continue where you
left off.
Now let's get started with the first exercise.
That's the objective of this lesson.
So we're going to go into day one and it might be collapsed.
If so, just go ahead and expand it and then click on Exercise 1 - Printing.
And here you see the instructions for what you need to do in order to complete this coding exercise.
Now, I want you to go ahead and click on Open Assignment Workspace, and here you'll be able to see
the instructions on one side of the pane.
You'll be able to have your main.py, which is where you write your code.
So all the lines below here, you can just type your code out.
And then once you're done writing your code, I want you to test it by running your code.
So hitting this run button and you'll see the result of your code being run in the console down here.
Now once you think you've completed the coding exercise according to all the instructions over here,
I want you to go ahead and test your code and you can test your code by simply hitting submit.
Now, don't worry about all of this where it says this submission will count towards your grade for
the assignment.
There are no grades, there's no time limits.
Nobody is going to check what you've done.
It's all for the benefit of your learning so you can submit your code as many times as you like.
So once you hit submit, it's going to run the automated test that we've set up behind the scenes,
and it's going to check to make sure that your code is doing what it's supposed to do.
So, for example, in this case, my tests have not passed because there's a cross here and note that
sometimes there'll be more than one test, so you can scroll down and see the other ones.
And the reason why I didn't pass, as they've shown here, is this is my actual output.
This is what my code did and this is what the expected output is supposed to be.
And there's a whole bunch of differences.
This does not look like this, so then we have to go and fix it.
And I've left some feedback in some of the lessons to help you in case you get stuck.
But also there are hints in some of the instructions.
So just make sure that you read everything now if you want to, or if you get really, really stuck,
you can take a look at the solution.
Now, I don't recommend looking at the solution code unless you're actually just checking to make sure
that.
Something hasn't gone majorly wrong or you're not completely stuck, or just for whatever reason, I
really, really want you to persevere and try your best to actually write the code yourself and to solve
the issues and figure out how to make all the tests pass.
But if you need to look at the solution, they are available on replit.
So just click on this link and it'll take you to the solution page in order to see the files.
You can either fork the repl as you have done before.
You'll get a copy of this solution file or what I think is much simpler is simply click on show files
and then click on this main.py file and then you will see the solution code on this page without
having to fork a copy of this repl.
But you can do it any number of ways.
Whichever way suits you best is fine.
Now, once you have written your code correctly, you should be able to see all the tests pass and by
passing it means that there's a little tick along each of these.
And usually in this one there's only one test and this is passed.
So you get a score of 100%.
And the actual output that your code has created in the console now looks exactly the same as expected.
So you are now done and you can go back to your other assignments and you can continue.
So this is a really simple interface and we've switched to this from replit because replit had actually
disabled their classroom technology, which looks basically exactly the same as this.
And we wanted to provide you the best learning experience possible.
So we've switched over to coding rooms and you should be able to sign up and get started without any
issue.
Now remember at the end of the lesson, I will go through the solution with you step by step explaining
the solution as well.
So if you get stuck, don't worry, I'm here for you every step of the way.
But now it's time for you to pause the video and make sure that you've signed up for coding rooms,
already registered for a student account, and then click on the link in step two in the course resources
and sign up for our course and then go over to the first exercise printing and give it a go.
All right, pause the video now.
All right.
How did you get on?
I really hope you gave this a good go because it's in these moments where you're going to be learning
the code.
Unfortunately, no amount of listening to me talk is actually going to give you these skills.
It's only when you actually try it out and get the computer to do the thing that you wanted to do.
That's when you become the master of the computer, also known as a programmer.
So in this case, the instructions are pretty simple.
We have to use what we learn about the print statement to output these three lines and notice how in
this gif the lines are printing out in separate lines.
This one gets printed, then this one, then this one.
But because it happens so fast, it seems like it as if they're getting printed as a single block.
So we're told to write our code below this line.
And we know that in order to print something, we use the print function with a set of parentheses,
and inside the parentheses is where we tell it what we want it to print.
So in the first instance, it's day one space, then it's now it's really easy to make spelling mistakes.
But I really encourage you to actually type out anything that you put into your code rather than just
simply copying and pasting it.
Now, of course, it works exactly the same way.
I could just copy and paste the code in here, but it's often in these cases where you make mistakes,
like for example, forgetting to add the double quotes around the text that you want to print, I really
recommend just typing out the code for practice whenever you're doing these code challenges.
Now, the last line that we want to print is a little bit complicated.
It's almost like print inception, because what we want to print is this function.
This is how we write our function, and that has to go inside here, inside a set of double quotes.
So let's open up a double quotes and then write our print statement.
And in this case, I'm actually using a single quote.
And I'll tell you just in a little moment why that is.
So let's add that single quote.
And finally, the closing parentheses.
This now is the entire code that you would need to be able to print something out.
And when I go ahead and click Run, you can see that the output looks exactly the same as what we've
got here in the gif.
This is what we want.
And when I click submit you'll see that my tests all pass and I can now submit my assignment and I've
now completed the coding challenge.
Now coming back to this single quote, why is it that I've got a single quote here rather than a double
quote, which is what we've been using all this time?
Well, because in.
Python.
It doesn't actually care whether if you enclose the strings.
So these pieces of text are not to be interpreted as code inside single quotes or inside double quotes.
It is identical to the computer.
This honey badger literally doesn't care.
But if you had a set of double quotes and then you wanted another set of double quotes inside the double
quotes.
So, for example, if I replace this with double quotes, you'll see that already the syntax highlighting
is already screaming out to us.
There's something that's not quite right here because the colors are not the same as here, where the
print function is in a particular color, the parentheses are in a particular color, and the text that
is to be printed in, it's in a yet another different color.
In this case, it looks all jumbled up and we're getting some errors here.
So now if I hit run, you'll get syntax errors.
And the problem here is, of course, this is of course, our code things at the end of this string
is here.
And so it doesn't know what on earth is going on afterwards.
And instead it's seeing this as a string, this as a string, and this is being interpreted as code.
So when we want to use some double quotes inside another set of double quotes, commonly you'll see
people switch to single quotes instead.
So you could, for example, write the print statement like so and use double quotes if you want to
print those out.
Or you can do it the other way, which is what I had before, where we use our double quotes on the
outside and single quotes on the inside.
So have a play around with that, if that's at all confusing.
But once you've tried it a few times and switched it around a few times, it should become clear what
it's actually doing.
How did you get on with this challenge?
If you ever need to see the solution, it's always down here as a link.
So I hope you enjoy this challenge.
In the next lesson, we're going to get back to learning about Python and we're going to learn about
strings and string manipulation for all of that and more.
I'll see you there.
All right guys.
Let's get back to learning about a few more things that we can do with strings.
You saw in the last lesson that if we wanted to print things on individual
lines, then we actually had to write them a few times, right?
We had to write print, um,
on three lines if we wanted it to be printed one, two, three,
like so. Now in this lesson I want to show you a method where we can do the same
thing, but by using a single print method.
So saving ourselves a few characters.
So the way that we would create a new line is by writing a backslash and the N
character.
And now if I go ahead and write hello world again afterward and I hit run,
or you can always use the shortcut, which is command + enter on Mac or control +
enter on Windows.
And you can see that once that line of code has been executed,
I've got hello world printed on two separate lines,
separated by this pink \n and character,
which gets replaced by a new line.
So go ahead and give that a go and see if you can create another one.
Remember though,
it's a backslash and not a forward slash but the syntax highlighting should help
you. All right,
we can simply just add another \n and remember that unless you want a
space to appear right before where your hello world appears,
you actually don't want any gaps between each of these lines.
There we go. We've got the same result as before,
but now using only a single print statement and creating some new lines with the
\n.
Now one of the other things that we can do with strings is we can concatenate
them.
What this means is we combine different strings so that they will be added to
the end of another string. Here's an example.
Let's say that we had the word hello and I wanted to add my name to the end of
this word to make it a single string. Well,
I can combine two strings by simply using a plus sign. So I can write "Hello"
+ "Angela". Now here's a question. When this runs,
what do you think it will look like? Do you think it'll write Hello
Angela or hello Angela, all in one word? Let's see what happens.
You can see that these two strings have now been combined into one and there's
no space in between because we don't have a space character anywhere in here.
Pause the video and see if you can add a space in between.
Alright,
so there are two ways that you can do this or maybe three actually. You could add a
space to the end of hello, you could add a space to
the beginning of Angela or you can actually continue using string concatenation
by simply adding another string in between these two
and this one is just a space. So now when I run my code,
you can see the space gets inserted and this long thing gets combined into a
single string that looks like this
once this bit of the code gets executed.
If we think of strings as a string of connected characters,
then string concatenation is simply taking those separate strings of characters
and merging them into one. Now,
this is a good point to mention that in Python programming spaces are really,
really important.
And what I mean by this is not so much the spaces that are inside strings like
this one, but the spaces that you add in your code.
So here, my print statement, if I hit the backspace,
you can see that nothing happens. I can't go any further back.
But if I added a space or if I added a tab using the TAB key,
then you'll see that when I try to run my code, I actually get an error.
And the type of error this time is not a syntax error anymore.
It's now an indentation error.
And it says that there's an unexpected indent at this position right at the
beginning of the print statement. So when you're coding in Python,
it's really important that you start off all of your code at the beginning of
the line and that you don't accidentally have any spaces or any tabs that you've
inserted in front of the line of code.
And the next time you get an indentation error,
then you'll be able to look at where that error is and hopefully you'll be able to
either use Stack Overflow or just remember what this error message means and
you'll be able to fix your code.
Now this is the second error that we've come across.
The last error was a syntax error for example,
when we forgot to add the end double quotes.
And this one is called a syntax error and this one is called an indentation error.
And as I mentioned before, while you're coding,
you are going to make lots and lots of these errors and other ones.
This is the only sure thing that we know.
So it's great that you're already learning about them and recognizing them.
But how can we prevent this from happening in the first place? Well,
paying attention while you're typing helps, but we all get tired and sometimes,
especially when I'm coding at night, sometimes even when I look at my own name,
it looks like it's spelled wrong and I can't figure out left and right.
So in most cases, text editors have a lot of helpful features.
If you go into the settings bar here and you scroll all the way to the bottom,
you can see that there's something called Code Intelligence. And code
intelligence is something that is going to help you auto-complete some of the
functions like our print function here and give you some helpful information or
hints as you type.
So let's go ahead and change it to enabled and close down our settings pane.
And you can see now if I, for example, forget to add my double quotes,
then I already start to get a little red squiggly line here and a little red bit
in the right hand side of the scroll bar.
And if I hover over the red squiggly line,
you can see that it gives me the error that I would get if I ran my code right
now. And so it reminds me that, Oh yeah,
there's maybe something about my string that's not quite right.
And you can also just Google these error messages and see it in Stack Overflow
to remind yourself of what the error might be relating to.
And I can fix it without having to run my code and having it break.
Because remember that when you're writing large programs,
it's not just going to be one line of code.
You can have multiple lines of code each with their own errors.
For example, this one might be missing a double quote,
this one might be missing a plus sign,
this one might have the print function misspelled.
The next one might have a indentation that's not meant to be there,
and when you run your code like this, it'll only give you the first issue.
Once you fix that issue,
it'll continue to the next issue until you've fixed everything,
and this is really painful. But with code intelligence enabled,
every time we make an error such as an indentation error like this,
then we'll be able to hover over it and you'll see unexpected indent.
So we'll be able to fix that. If we forget to close off our print statement,
then we'll get a little squiggly line next to it.
And if we say misspelled our print statement,
we'll also get errors telling us that undefined name or it doesn't know what
this 'prnt' is and the syntax highlighting also changes and everything should
all help you to avoid mistakes and write good solid code.
So now it's time for another code challenge.
And in this code challenge,
I've got a whole bunch of broken code for you and your job is to debug or remove
the bugs from the code and make the code run without any errors.
This word debugging actually comes from a story where back in the 1980s a
moth actually flew into one of the early computers and it got electrocuted
unfortunately for the moth and for the programmer,
it meant that his code wasn't performing as he would expect it to.
So he actually had to go into the computer, pick out the moth,
and fix the wires so that it would work again.
Now we don't have any moths flying around in our code, thankfully,
but what we do have to do is we have to pick out the errors so that our code will
run in the way that we expect it to without any errors.
So head over to the next lesson and try out your first debugging exercise.
To begin,
I want you to locate the day 1.2 debugging exercise.
And now, as you did before, go ahead and read through the instructions.
Be mindful that the output must match the example output precisely.
And when you hit run, this is the outcome you're looking for.
So there's quite a few things broken here,
but I want you to have a go at fixing each line individually and pulling out the
bugs from the code. So pause the video now and give that a go.
All right.
So how did that go? If you haven't got your computer in front of you,
if you're traveling, if somehow you can't access the exercise, just pause
and when you've got time,
then complete the challenge and then come back to the course.
It is so important that you actually do some hands-on stuff.
And I stress that this is the only way that you are going to become the rock
star coder that I know you can be. Let's take a look at the code below.
You can see that when we run our code as it is right now,
we get a new error.
And this is going to point to the first of many errors in this file.
And in this case, it tells us that on line three,
so this one right here, at around this position
or somewhere around here, um, as denoted by the little caret sign,
there is a syntax error. If we study this closely,
you can see that the code highlighting seems to be suggesting that all of this
is code, but this is somehow text. So what's going on here?
Well, notice that we've only got one double quote.
So it thinks that what comes after this is the text,
but what comes before it, it thought it was just a continuation of code.
So to fix this one,
all we have to do is add a double quote right here. That changes the text to the
color that we're used to and this fixes this line.
So if we run our code now, we should get a different error. And indeed we do.
The next one tells us that on line five,
so this one right here, there is an indentation error.
There's an unexpected indent somewhere around here on line five.
So let's take a look at line five and there you go.
There's a little bit of extra space between the print and the beginning of the
line.
So now that we've fixed that one, let's click run. And it will point to
another line of code that's broken. And in this case,
it says on line seven,
which is here where there's actually no code,
there's the unexpected EOF while parsing. What does this mean?
Well, if you're not sure,
then go ahead and paste it into Google and let's take a look at what people say
on Stack Overflow. So as this person,
very kind, Felix, um, has explained, this index error
unexpected EOF
while parsing means that the end of your source code was reached before all
code blocks were completed. What is a code block? Well,
this is a code block because it's a print function,
it has a beginning and it has an end. But what does this line not have?
Well, it's got two open parentheses,
but only one closing parentheses.
So the computer thinks that you are going to continue writing something and then
close it off at the end, which is not the case. In fact,
what has happened is we simply have an extra misplaced open parenthesis.
And now if we delete that and hit run,
you'll see that we have everything printed.
But at this point, notice how on line four
which is the line that we haven't fixed yet,
it prints string concatenation is done with the 'blank' sign.
Whereas in fact, it should say plus sign.
And even though we don't see any errors being printed in our console,
you'll see that we have an output mismatch because I'm expecting to see this
line, the String Concatenation is done with the "+" sign,
but here,
the output doesn't have that part. It's missing this part.
So there's one last thing that you need to debug. And that is of course,
on line four.
And what's happening here is we have this part being interpreted as a string,
this part being interpreted a string,
and it thinks that this plus sign is just us concatenating
these two parts together,
which is why it printed out like this. But in fact,
we wanted to print out is this as text down here.
So what we have to do is to change this outer apart from double quotes
into single quotes.
And now you can see when it highlights this part,
it's all the same color including the plus sign.
Now it sees this as a complete string,
and it's not looking at this as if it's code. So now if we run our program,
you can see the entire sentence being printed out.
So if you've completed the challenge and you've gotten everything right,
then you're now done with this exercise.
If you got stuck and you want to have a look at the solution, as always it's down
here,
and it might be useful to have a look at this page to see where you might've
missed something or where you might've gotten something wrong.
So I hope you enjoyed this code exercise. In the next lesson,
we're going to learn about a new type of Python function,
which is the input function. So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Coming back to our Repl.it,
the Day 1 printing repl that you should have from previously,
I want to talk about a different function.
So we've seen the print function and all the things that we can do to strings
and use the print function and debug it.
But what if we wanted to be able to enter some data?
So if we wanted to say,
ask the user 'what is your name?' And we run this code,
you can see that being printed,
but there's no way for the user on this side to be able to give our code some
data to work with. In order to do that,
instead of using the print function,
we're going to use a different function and it's called the input function.
And notice how as I'm typing,
code intelligence is already giving me some suggestions because it thinks it
knows what I might want and it's right.
So this is what the input function looks like. This is the name of the function.
And again, it's followed by some parentheses. Inside the parentheses
is the prompt that I'm going to give the user.
So when I run this code, it will say, what is your name?
And then the cursor will stay at the end of this line because it's expecting
some sort of input. If I give it my name, Angela and I hit enter,
then this piece of data has now been passed back into my code and it now
replaces this part of the code.
So I'm passing data from over here,
back to over here where I can use it in my code.
Now notice the difference here. It looks quite similar.
When we run print, you can see it says what is your name?
and then the code execution ends and we know it ends because it's showing us
this little orange arrow.
But notice when I run input instead,
I don't see the orange arrow.
My program is actually paused right now in order for the user to provide an
input and it's only when I've given the input and hit enter
does the program end.
The input function looks pretty much identical to the print function,
but instead of the word print,
it's just got the word input. And inside the parentheses,
instead of adding what text will be printed,
we're adding the prompt for the user to give them a hint as to what kind of data
we want. And then when you run this code, it will print out the prompt,
but then there will be a cursor. In some places you'll see it like a flashing
cursor, other places,
it'll just be a solid cursor ready for the user to type in some piece of data.
So what can we do with this data? Well,
we can use it inside our code.
Remember how I said once this line of code executes and I've entered Angela as
the response to this input,
then this part of the code gets replaced by whatever it is that the user typed
in. So in this case it becomes Angela.
And what I can do with it is let's say I wanted to print something like,
hello Angela. Well,
then I can simply write Hello + input and then I'm going to close it off
with another set of brackets.
So I'm going to change my layout instead of side by side,
I'm going to change it to stacked.
And this means that I've got my code at the top and my console at the bottom.
This way my line can go a little bit longer without it rapping.
Notice what's happening here.
This is the input function that I showed you earlier on and this is a print
statement.
So we've got this nested inside the other. And now when I run my code,
what happens is it asked me what is your name?
So I'll write my name and then when I hit enter,
this part is replaced by Angela and it gets concatenated to the word hello and
the entire thing gets printed out down here.
If you find this line of code difficult to understand and to wrap your head
around,
then I recommend heading over to a website called thonny.org and downloading an
application called Thonny. It's completely free and it's available for Windows,
Mac, and Linux. And once you've installed this application,
you can go ahead and paste your line of code here and click on this little debug
symbol. And then we can click on this button,
which is called the step into button to step into the execution of this line of
code
to see how the computer is evaluating this code here step by step.
So you'll see the first thing it tries to do is it will try to run this print
statement. It looks inside, these parentheses to see what it needs to print.
So the first thing is this, Hello,
and it turns that into a string and then it looks at the next thing after the
plus sign to see what it should turn this into.
And this of course is the input function. So as I continue stepping into it,
it's actually going to execute it.
So it's going to run this input function and show the prompt, what is your name?
So that's what shows up down here.
And now if I enter a value in here and hit enter,
then that value that I put right there replaces that previous input function
and is now held inside the print statement.
So if I continue stepping through this code then you'll see it concatenates all of
the pieces together, and finally it just ends up with a simple print
Hello Angela! And if I continue stepping into it,
you'll see that line of code executed until there are no more instructions left.
So if you prefer seeing your code, um,
run like this step by step so that you can see what's going on,
then I recommend giving this a go.
But because of how easy it is to share these Repl.it code bases so that we're
working from the same place, I recommend to do most of your coding here
and only if you get stuck to take a single line of code and paste it into Thonny
to see how it's executed step-by-step. As you're learning to code,
there's going to be new concepts covered.
There's going to be things that take a little bit of thinking before you can
understand it.
So what a lot of programmers love to do is they like to comment in their code.
Now,
you might've seen this already throughout the coding exercises and the solutions
I provided. But in Python,
if you wanted a line of text to not be considered by the computer at all,
all you have to do is add the hashtag or pound sign in front of your text and
this turns it into a comment,
so something that the computer will completely ignore.
So in here you can write code as much as you like, um,
but it won't be executed and when you click run,
you'll see that this is completely ignored.
What I recommend is whenever you come across a new concept in the course to make
a comment above it so that you can explain to yourself what's actually going on
in the line of code below. This way
the next time you come across this line of code and you're not quite sure what's
actually happening here,
you can have a look at the notes that you've written for yourself in your own
words and hopefully it'll re-jog your memory and make it much easier to
comprehend what's going on.
In addition to adding a pound sign manually,
you can also highlight a line of code or simply have your cursor on a line of
code and hold down command and forward slash if you're on Mac or control and
forward slash if you're on Windows.
And if you want to go back or undo your changes,
it's simply command +z or control + z. All right,
so in this lesson we learned about input function,
we learned about putting functions inside other functions and being able to get
user input from the console by using the input function.
So now I've got a coding exercise for you in the next lesson,
and if you've commented this line of code thoroughly and you fully understood
how it works, then you'll be able to breeze through the next exercise.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
All right. So again,
it's time to put theory into practice and get some hands-on action.
You should be able to find the day 1.3 assignment which is inputs.
Click on it and you will see the instructions for this particular challenge.
And the idea is that you're going to write a program
that's going to print the number of characters in a user's name. For example,
if I input my name, which is Angela,
it should output the number six because there are six characters in the word,
Angela. But remember you can't just print out the number six,
because when I'm checking for this code,
I'm going to try a whole bunch of different names as the input.
And you're going to have to use a little bit of thinking,
a little bit of Googling and also a little bit of messing around with the code
in order to get it to work. If you need any help,
there's a few hints down here for you. And if you really get stuck,
then you can take a look at the solution,
but not until you've really given it a go. And I really,
really want to know that you've tried hard.
And the whole point of these exercises is you sit there and scratch your head a
little bit and actually give it a good go.
So I'm going to stop talking now and I'm going to let you pause the video and
try to complete this challenge. All right, good luck.
Okay. So how did that go? If you get stuck, I want to tell you
the programmers secret to getting unstuck
which is go and grab yourself a cup of tea, have a quick break,
look at something else for a little moment,
think about something else and then come back to it. Well,
the tea part is optional. Well, at least if you're outside of England,
it's optional. So let's get started solving this challenge.
So the idea is that we're going to create a program that counts the number of
characters in any user's name.
And that name is obviously going to come through an input function,
and then we're going to use a function that calculates the length of a string
and we're going to send that out as the output.
The first thing we'll probably need is some form of input function right?
And the prompt that we're going to give the user is what is your name or
something similar that asks them for their name.
And I like to add a space at the end of the prompt. This way, when you run it,
you don't actually have that cursor straight next to the, um, the question mark
which looks a bit weird. But either way, once we've entered an input,
then this part gets replaced by that input
and we're going to do something with it.
We're going to calculate the length of that string.
Now using our eyes, we can obviously see that it's six characters long.
But what if you have a really a long name?
So let's go ahead and take a look at how we might figure out,
um, how to you get a function that calculates the length of a string.
I've actually included the Google search that you might need to use.
And so let's just paste that URL in here,
and you can see that we're searching for how to get the length of the string in
Python and we're trying to get results from Stack Overflow.
The first result is a question that seems to pretty match match exactly what we
want. And the answer from user 225312
tells us that you need to use the Len function. And the way that you use it
is by passing the string inside the parentheses.
Now this part might look a little bit different from what you're used to with the
equal sign and everything.
But I have confidence that if you mess around with this code,
you'll be able to figure it out.
Just like what we did with print or input,
the Len function also has a set of parentheses and it will work its magic on
whatever it is that we put inside the parentheses. If I just put my name,
Angela here,
let's just comment out the previous line, and I go ahead and print the result of
this and then I hit run, you can see that it prints 6. Now,
if I change that to Jack, then you'll see it prints 4.
So it will print whatever it is
the length of the string that I've put inside the Len function.
So we're getting close now, right?
Because instead of printing out a string that I've hard coded here,
what I want is to take the input that the user has given me.
So something like this. Now, if you want to,
you can actually add some spaces inside here just to make it a little bit
clearer to yourself as to what's actually going on because there's three
functions here. They are all nested inside each other.
So this is the first one,
this is the one that is going to get the input from the user and replace this
part with whatever it is that they type down here.
Then that string gets calculated using the Len function to get the length of
that string. And then that number will get printed by the print function.
Now let's go ahead and hit run and let's give it a go.
So let's try Jack, hit enter.
And it tells us that it's 4.
But using the same line of code,
if we try a different name Angela, then it prints out six.
How did you get on with this? If you got stuck,
then have a look at the solution Repl.it um,
where you will be able to find the code that I've written here and a little bit
of explanation as well.
The important thing is that you really play around with this code.
Try things and make it break and make it work and just get it to do what you
want it to do.
And remember that if you ever want to visualize these things and the order of
execution, then you can always use Thonny to see that.
So let's go ahead and step in.
You'll see that it goes through Len, input, and then it's going to carry out this
functionality input. I gave it my name, hit enter.
Then it puts that inside the Len function like so,
so now the next step is this part.
We're going to calculate the length of this string.
And as I continue stepping into it, you can see that become six.
And finally we're gonna carry out the final instruction,
which is just to print six down here. Again,
this can be quite useful just to visualize all the steps that are happening
if you want to.
Once you're done, head over to the next lesson and I'm going to talk to you
all about Python variables and how we'll be able to identify pieces of data in
our code. So for all of that, and more, I'll see you there.
Now in this lesson, I want to talk to you about Python variables and it's a
really, really useful concept. But before we get started,
first I want you to head over to the course resources and get hold of the Day
1 variables start Repl.it sandbox or you can simply type the URL into the
browser.
I want you to first go ahead and fork this starting code so that you can work on
your own version of it. Now once you've done that,
then the first thing I want to do is to take a look at this line of code that
you should have already. And when we run this,
we should be pretty familiar with what happens, right?
It will ask us for our name and when we hit enter, nothing happens.
But behind the scenes,
this name or this input has now been received by this function.
But once that's done, it kind of just disappears, right?
And there's no way for us to be able to refer to it in the future. Or is there?
Well, this is where variables come in really handy.
If I give the results of this action a name,
well then I'll be able to refer to it later on.
So at the beginning of the line,
I'm going to call it name and then I'm going to add an equal sign
and what this does is it assigns whatever it is that the user typed in as the
input to this prompt to a variable called name.
So now if I go ahead and run my code again and I enter a name,
now once I hit enter,
normally there's no way for me to get hold of this anymore, right?
But now I can actually go ahead and write print.
I'm going to print the value of this variable name.
So now if I run my code and I write a name,
hit enter,
you'll see that this gets printed and I can use this at any point in my code
just by referring to the name that's attached to this value.
So it's almost like we've saved the data from this action to a name.
And if you think about it, if you had a phone book, let's say,
and you just jotted down the numbers of people,
the next time you look at this,
there's no way for you to know who's number that is, right?
In a sense it's the same thing with the computer.
Even though we've inputted this piece of data,
there's no way for us to be able to refer to this data unless we give it a name.
So in our phone book, we might say that this particular number is associated with
the name James. And in programming we would call this name James a variable.
So we could write something like James equals and then his phone number.
And this means that in the future, if we ever need this piece of data,
we can just refer to it by its name,
the variable name of James. Now,
as the name variable suggests,
it's something that can be changed or can be varied.
So for example,
just because this name is set to something up here doesn't mean that I can't
change it later on. So to make things simple,
let's go ahead and delete the input function and let's just say name is equal to
Jack. Print name.
When I run that Jack is what gets printed inside the console because I'm now
referring to that piece of data by the variable name.
But if later on I decide to give this variable a different piece of data to hold
on to,
let's say Angela and I print name at this time point after I've changed it,
what do you think these two lines will print?
What do you think will first be printed?
What do you think will be printed second? Let's hit command + enter or control +
enter and see for ourselves.
So even though they're both printing the same variable, at this point when we first
call print, it's holding on to the value of Jack,.
But by line 5 I've now changed it so that it's holding onto the value of
Angela.
This makes it a lot easier when we want to write code like what we did before.
For example,
this is the line of code that we had before and we knew that we were going to
get a piece of data from this input function and then we would calculate a new
piece of data using the Len function
and finally we're going to print everything out.
Instead of having such a long line of code, which can be quite confusing,
we can, if we wanted to, use variables to store each of these steps.
So for example,
we could say that the name was equal to whatever the user inserted as the
input
and then when we wanted to calculate the length,
then we could set that variable to equal the Len function.
And then inside the parentheses, we'll pass in the name, the value, that's stored
in the name variable right here. And finally,
all that we need to do is to print the length,
like so. So in this case,
this data is stored under this name and then that data is what's going to be
used in order to carry out this function
and then the result will get stored in yet another variable
and finally that variable will be printed out.
So let's go ahead and run this code and type in my name.
So Angela and hit enter and it does exactly the same thing,
but now we've got all of these pieces of data all associated with a name that we
can refer to at any later point in our code. Now it's time,
you guessed it, for a code challenge.
And I'm going to get you to apply what you've learned.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right guys, it's time for your final coding exercise.
So click on day 1.4 variables.
Now the aim of the game is to switch the values of these two variables around.
So if we go ahead and run our code as it is,
it's going to ask us for a value of a. Let's call it five.
And then it's going to ask us a value for b. Let's call that a hundred.
And then when I hit enter,
what you want the code to do is to go ahead and print a equals 100 and b equals
five.
So, basically switch those values around. And you're going to have to write your
code in here. And it's really,
really important that you don't change any of the code here or the code here.
Now it's easy enough to simply just write print a equals b and b equals a.
But this doesn't test you on anything. This is not the solution.
This is wrong. Don't change the code here, don't change the code here.
Instead, all
you have are these lines where you can write as much code or as little code as
you need to achieve this end. And when you achieve it,
it should look something like this.
You type a value for a, you type a value for b. And when you hit enter,
they get printed out,
but switched around. Have a think about how variables work,
how they store data. And if you get really stuck,
imagine that you have two cups; one holds a cup of milk, one
holds a cup of coffee,
and you wanna switch the contents of the cup around. How would you do that in
real life? And then try and see if you can apply that logic to the code.
Pause the video now and give this a go.
All right. So I hope you didn't cheat
and instead you actually had a think about this problem. If you got stuck,
remember how I said
if you have a cup of coffee and you have a cup of milk and you wanna switch the
contents of the cups around, how would you do this in real life? Well,
you would probably get a third cup, right?
And then you'd be able to shift the contents around.
So that's exactly what we're going to do with our code as well.
We can create a new variable called c and we can set that to equal the value that's
stored inside a. And then later on,
we can get the variable a to store the value that's currently inside b.
And finally,
we're now ready to get b to store the value that was previously inside a,
which is now contained inside the variable c. These three lines achieve this
little switch rule that we've got here.
And this is one of the most common Programming interview questions that you will
come across. And the code is super simple,
but what you have to apply here is some logic.
And I usually think about real life examples
like the cups and I hope that helped you as well.
If this was at all confusing,
then have a go at trying this out in Thonny.
But if you got it right, then congratulations.
This was actually quite a hard challenge.
You had to think about a lot of things and think outside the box as well.
So give yourself a pat on the back if you've got it right.
If you didn't get it right,
then I really recommend to put this code inside Thonny and see how it's being
moved around so that you really,
really understand what's going on behind the scenes.
And then you can move on to the next lesson where we're going to talk about some
of the rules around naming variables. For all of that
and more, I'll see you there.
Now when it comes to naming your variables,
you can pretty much call it whatever it is you want.
So instead of calling this name,
I could have just called it n and I could have called this l and as long as I'm
consistent.
So if I wanted to get the length of N then I would have to change this as well.
And if I wanted to print out L then I have to change this as well.
But there's a couple of rules that you should probably follow.
And the most important one is to make your code readable. Because if you come
back to this in six months, 12 months,
N and L is not going to have a lot of meaning for you.
So try to make sure that it actually makes sense to you.
And if you want to,
you can actually have multiple words in the name of your variable.
So for example, if you wanted to call this username,
then you would write the word user and then you would separate each of the words
with an underscore. But you can't have a space in between.
This is not valid code and if you try to run it, you'll get a syntax error.
So the name of the variable has to be one single unit and in order to separate
words in Python, we use the underscore.
Now if you want to use numbers in the name of your variable,
you can. So for example, length1,
length2. But they can't be at the beginning of the name of the variables.
You can't say 1length or 3length.
That will generate a syntax error as well. Finally,
there's certain privileged words that we use, for example,
the names of our functions like print and input.
And it's usually good practice to not use them as the names of your variables
because you can see that syntax highlighting gets messed up because it thinks
that is actually input function you're trying to create.
And even though often when you run your app, it might not have any issues,
this is really bad practice because it's very confusing.
So try to make sure that all the names of your variables get highlighted,
like the other variables in the same color. Now,
the final thing to remember is that if you decide to call your variable this
particular name, n-a-m-e, and at a later point you make a typo and you spell it
wrong, so maybe instead of name you said nama,
this is not going to work and when you run your code you'll get what's called a
name error because it says this name is not defined. And the idea is that you
would look at where the error is, line 2, print nama and you'll see,
Oh that's not right. It's meant to be spelled n-a-
m-e. So you'll have to go and fix it in order for your code to work.
Now remember that this is not because Python is doing any sort of spell-checking
for you. It's like, Oh, that's not how you spell name. No. In fact,
if you decided to call this nama and you, later on, used it as name,
there's no problems, there's no issues, no errors,.
As long as it's consistent,
this is the name that's associated with this piece of data. Later on,
when you want to use this piece of data, you use this name to refer to it.
And as long as these two spellings are identical,
then the computer doesn't care at all.
So when you get a name error in your code,
you now know it's probably because you've misspelled or mistyped one of the
variable names somewhere in your code. Now in the next lesson,
I prepared a quiz for you where you'll get to select which variable names are
valid and which ones are not good practice.
Have a go at that over on the next lesson.
All right, guys, it's time for the final project of today. So the program that you're going to be
building looks a little bit like this. And you can check it out if you head over to this link, either
by typing it in or heading to the resources page and clicking on the corresponding link.
But essentially, it's a band name generator. And it asks you for a city that you grew up in and the name of your
pet.
And then it combines those together and gives you the name of your band.
There's a couple of things to note here.
Firstly is notice when this input got triggered, the cursor actually showed up on a new line.
So if I run this again, you can see it says "What's the name of city you grew up in?"
And then the cursor is on the next line.
And what I want you to do is to go ahead and head over to this starting project.
So this is the URL
and it's also, of course, in the course resources.
And once you head over here, you can fork this code and complete your own version.
So there's a couple of steps in here as hints.
If you don't want to see these and you just want to go by the end project, you can also just delete
all of these.
But the important thing is once you've completed this project, it should work exactly the same as the
one that you see here.
And in order to do this, you're going to have to apply everything that you learned today, including
printing inputs, variables, new lines, string manipulation, debugging and a whole lot more.
So this is a time to grab yourself a cup of tea  or coffee , pause the video and tackle this final project.
All right, guys, I hope you gave that a go and you were able to complete it. If you want to see how
I've implemented it or if you want to just check to see if you have any errors or if there's something
that you're unsure about, then continue watching and I'll go through the solution with you.
The first step is to create a greeting for your program, in our case, it says "Welcome to the band
name generator."
So that's exactly what I'm going to create.
And we print these messages using the print function.
So I'm going to say "Welcome to the band name generator."
And this when I run, it will just print that message.
Now, the next step is to ask the user for the city that they grew up in. So in order to get some input
from the user will need, of course, the input function.
And we're going to ask them using the prompt, which goes inside the parentheses: "Which city did you
grow up in?"
So now when I hit run, it's going to ask me for the city that I grew up in and I'm able to add a reply
like so.
Now, that data is just going to be lost to thin air unless I capture it and I give it a name, so I'm
going to have to create a variable to hold onto the data that the user inputted.
So we'll just call that "city" and then add the equal sign (=) to assign whatever it is that the user typed
in to this variable name.
And now I have access to the city variable and I can print it or use it later on if I want to, like so.
Now, the next step is to ask the user for the name of a pet.
So we'll call that variable "pet" and we'll assign it the value that the user inputs for:
"What is the name of a pet?"
Now, step 4 is to combine the name of the city and the pet and show them their band name.
Now, there's quite a few ways of doing this, especially if you look around on the Internet.
But the way that you learn in today's lessons is using string concatenation.
So we're going to do that.
So we're going to use a print statement and tell them "Your band name could be..."
And then we're going to add the name of the city and then add a space and then add the name of their
pet.
So now when we run our code
it will ask us for the name of their city and then the name of a pet, and then it should combine those
together and show us the name of our band.
Now, the final step is that the input cursor should show on a new line like this.
So here's the cursor.
But here's the input.
Just so that you get a bit of space and you're not typing it in directly after the prompt here like
what we have.
So how do we do that?
Well, you learned about modifying strings by creating a new line using the \n.
And we can add that both to the end of the city input and the pet input.
And now when we run our code, you'll see that the cursor now shows up on the next line and our program
looks a lot better.
So there you have it.
This is how you solve this boss challenge and this is how you create the band name generator project.
So I hope you had fun with me today, learning Python and a lot of the fundamentals of Python.
And tomorrow I've got another jam packed module of really awesome tutorials and challenges and projects
for you to sink your teeth into!
I'm looking forward to seeing you tomorrow, so I have a rest now and let your brain  work on the things
that you learned while you sleep.
And I'll see you here bright and early.
Good night and see you tomorrow.
Hey guys, welcome back to Day 2 of 100 Days of code.
In today's lessons, you're going to be learning about datatypes, numbers,
operations, type conversion, f-strings, and a whole lot more.
And by the end of today,
you will have learned enough to build a tip calculator.
So it looks a bit like this. It says, welcome to the tip calculator.
It asks you for the total bill that you need to pay.
So let's say it came to $124.54 we hit enter and then it asks you how many
people do you want to split the bill between?
So let's say this five of us having the meal and it asks you finally,
what percentage tip would you like to give?
So let's say we give a 12% tip.
Now it's going to calculate what each person should pay,
taking into account all of these pieces of information that you've put in.
So I know that I'm pretty bad at math,
especially when it comes to splitting bills.
And I'm normally the person who just says, yeah,
just tell me what I need to pay so I don't have to calculate it.
It's like the bad-at-math tax that I pay.
But in order to build this, you're going to need to learn some new skills,
including working with numbers, converting data types from one type to another,
and a whole lot more. So if you feel like you can tackle this, no problems.
Then feel free to skip today's lessons.
But I bet that there'll be loads of stuff that you'll come across in the
upcoming lessons and coding exercises that's really going to make you a better
developer. So once you're ready to get started,
head over to the next lesson and let's start coding.
Yesterday you saw that we could use the Len function to get the number of
characters in a string. So for example, when I write Len,
hello and I print this out,
we end up with 5. There's 5 characters in the string hello.
Now here's a question.
What happens if instead of counting the number of characters in a string,
what if I put in a number instead and I wanted to know how many digits are in
this number? Now if I go ahead and run this code,
you'll see that it actually crashes.
I get a whole bunch of red text and it tells me that there is a type error and
something about the type int. So what is all of this about?
Well, in order to understand it, we first have to learn about data types.
Now on day 1, we already explored this data type called strings.
Now you're probably not going to be surprised to learn that there's a whole lot
more other data types out there.
And today we're going to explore some of the most important and some of the most
basic data types such as strings, integers, float, and booleans.
And we'll explore each of these in detail.
So go ahead and get hold of the day 2 start coding sandbox and go ahead and
fork your own copy of it. Now once you've done that,
let's take a look at some of the data types.
So we already learned about strings, right?
And we know that this is just a string of characters.
So the word hello is comprised of these five characters strung together.
And we always know that strings, when we create them,
we have to create them with these double quotes around.
Now because this is a string of characters,
we can actually pull out each character individually. So we could, for example,
instead of just writing hello, we can add some square brackets.
So take a look on your keyboard and see where those are.
And inside the square brackets, we can put the index or the position of the
character that we want. So, for example,
if I wanted to have the first character out of this word hello,
I would put zero right here.
And if I go ahead and print what this actually will give me,
you'll see that you get capital H because that is the first character of this
string.
And it's really important to remember that programmers always start counting
from zero because we work with binary, zeros and ones.
So whenever you want to get hold of the first character or the first of
anything, it always is at zero.
So this method of pulling out a particular element from a string is called sub-
scripting. And the number in between the square brackets determines
which character you're going to pull out,
and it just goes up from zero to one to two and so on and so forth.
So whenever you get a result that's just off by one,
then remember to check whether if you've started counting from zero or if you
started counting from one.
Now you can of course extend this and get hold of the last character.
So pause the video and see if you can change the code so that 'o' gets printed
out here. All right,
so this is a simple as simply counting from zero, one, two, three,
four. So if we change this to four and we run our code,
then you'll see that 'o' gets printed instead of the H.
So by using these square brackets and putting a number inside,
we're able to dissect our string and pull out individual characters as and when
we need it.
And this will come in really handy in a lot of the programs that you'll write in
the future.
Now it's important to remember though that just because I can write a number
like "123",
as long as it's kept inside these double quotes,
then this is not treated as a number by the computer.
It's treated just as any other piece of text. You can't, for example, say,
um, what is "123" + "345".
If I try to print this, what do you think will happen?
Do you think it will give me 123 + 345
in the traditional sense,
like calculating it or do you think it'll do something else? All right,
let's hit run and we get 123345.
So it's basically just concatenated these two strings together,
just as we have done with other strings like hello and world, right?
Because it sees the datatype of these two pieces of data as strings.
When we use the plus sign,
it will actually just concatenate these two things instead of doing a
mathematical operation. Now if we want to do that,
then we actually have to declare our number as a number data type.
So one of the most common that you'll see is called an integer.
So this is programming lingo for just whole numbers, numbers
without any decimal places.
And in order to create an integer or declare an integer data type,
all you have to do is just write the number without anything else.
So now if I just write the numbers, 123 + 345
and then I go ahead and print this,
then you'll see that we actually get 468.
So it's actually being calculated because I've got actual numbers instead of
strings.
Just as we have some useful things that we can do with strings.
There's some really handy things that you can do with integers.
Commonly when we write large numbers,
at least in the UK or in the US, we'd like to put commas in between the
thousands.
So when we think of large numbers with these commas in between to split it into
an easier to understand number. In Python,
we can replace those commas simply with underscores and it will be interpreted
by the computer as if you had written this.
So the computer actually removes those underscores and ignores it.
The benefit is just for us humans to be able to visualize it more easily.
So I mentioned that all whole numbers
no matter if they're positive or negative, are called integers in programming.
So what do you call it when you actually have decimal places? Well,
they are called a float and this is short for a floating-point number.
So for example, if you had um, the numbers of PI,
you have 3.14159
and this, because it has a decimal place, is now a float data type.
So if you think of the decimal point as being able to float around the number
because it could occur at any point,
then you've got yourself a floating point number.
Now the final data type is something called a boolean.
And this is very simple. It only has two possible values,
true or false.
Now note how these values always begin with a capital T or capital F and they
don't have any quotation marks around them or anything.
So this is actually a data type which is going to be used a lot in your programs
to test if something is true,
if something is false and for your program to respond accordingly.
So we're going to be using this a lot more in the future.
Now that you've seen a lot of the basic data types, strings, integers, floats,
and boolean,
I want you to head over to the next lesson where I've got a quiz for you to see
if you've made this knowledge your own. So head over to the quiz and give it a go.
Previously we saw how the Len function gives us a type error when we give it a
number instead of a string.
So let's talk a little bit more about data types and functions.
And the way I think about functions is kind of like some sort of fancy machine
that you might see in a factory, right? So in this case,
we've got some sort of machine that's going to take potatoes into chips and we
don't really care how it does it,
but it's probably going to have to peel the potatoes, wash the potatoes,
cut it up, fry it,
and then finally return it to us as an output in the form of fries.
And if this is the first time that you're watching one of my tutorials, um,
this is probably a health warning. I talk about food a lot. Um,
so be prepared if you haven't eaten.
Now let's say that we took the same machine that normally processes potatoes and
we decided to get a rock and we just pass this through the function,
then we're getting an error, right? This is basically what happened here.
This length function doesn't like working with integers.
And by forcing this through,
we end up with an error and our code breaks and it gives us this thing, a type
error.
Now do you remember previously we had this challenge where we asked you to get
the um, get an input from the user, what is your name?
And then we use the length function to get the number of characters of their
name. And let's just save that to a variable. Let's call it, um,
num_char equals this.
And then we print your name has plus num_char, number of characters + characters.
So in this case you would expect it to prompt the user to enter their name.
Let's say I entered my name Angela,
and the length of that string would be 6
so this would be equal to six. And so this would get substituted in here.
And then with string concatenation, we end up printing
"Your name has six characters." But this is not what happens.
And I know that some of you might have tried this for the previous challenge and
you would have gotten a type error.
So it tells you that you can only concatenate strings,
not integers. So in this case,
we were concatenating a string to an integer.
This is what we get. We end up with an error.
So how can we prevent these type errors and how can we see the data type that
we're working with? Well,
we could use a function called type,
which basically will check whatever you put between the parentheses and give you
the type of data that it is. For example,
if I go ahead and just comment out this line of code
which breaks and go ahead and put num_char,
so this particular piece of data inside this type function,
and then I'm going to print the type of num_char.
And now if I hit run, let's enter my name.
And you can see it's telling you that this is an integer.
So adding a string to an integer doesn't make any sense,
which is why you got the type error.
Now every so often when you're writing code and you're not quite sure what the
type of data of something might be,
then you can simply just put it inside a type check function,
right? Like so. And then you'll get an answer.
Now in addition to type checking,
we can also do type conversion or you might hear it called type casting where we
change a piece of data from one particular data type to another.
So it, for example,
we know that this variable num_char has the data type of integer.
If we wanted to turn it into a string so that this line of code wouldn't break
anymore,
then we could convert it into a string by writing str
and then inside the parentheses, we put in the variable that we want to convert,
which is called num_char. And now we save this into a new variable,
we'll call it new_num_char.
And once we've converted this into a string and stored it under this name,
then we can use it inside our print statement, new_num_char,
and now it won't break anymore. And it tells us your name has six characters.
So in this case we've taken a integer data type,
put it inside the parentheses of a str function,
which takes a object in between the parentheses and converts it into a string,
which we then store inside this new_num_char
and we can now use it in our print statement because all the data types of all
the pieces of data that we're adding together have the same data type, string.
Now you're not limited to only converting numbers into strings.
You can convert a whole bunch of different data types.
So let me go ahead and comment out this code and I can show you that
let's say that we had a variable a, which we set two a number,
right? 123.
And if I do a type check on a and print this,
you'll see that as you would expect, it should give you integer, right?
A is an integer.
But now let's say I converted a into a string by wrapping it inside the string
function, then hit enter. You can see it's now of type string.
Now I can do this with other things as well. So for example,
I could turn my whole number here into a float and when I run my code,
now we see that the type of my variable is a float
and that's pretty straightforward, right?
But let me ask you two quick questions before we wrap up.
What will this line of code print? Alright, you guessed it,
this will print 170.5 but what's actually happening behind the scenes is we're
converting this string 100.5 into a floating-point number and then we're adding
70 to 100.5 and finally we're printing the results.
But what about this line? What will print here? Have a guess.
Well, this time we get 70100. So in summary,
you can use the type function to investigate the data type you're working with
and you can use functions like string, int, or float to convert to that data
type. In the next lesson, I've got a coding challenge for you.
So head over there and we'll get started.
All right, now
it's time to put what you've learned into practice by clicking on the data types
day 2.1 code challenge.
In this challenge,
the idea is that you are going to be given a random two-digit number,
so something like 39, and your code that you'll write
will be able to add the first digit to the second digit and end up with a
numerical result. So for example, if the input was 39,
then 3 + 9 would be equal to 12. So the output would be 12.
And if the input was 26,
then your code needs to print 8 to the console.
So you're going to need to think about type checking, type conversion,
as well as everything that you learned before.
And then you're going to write your code below this line without changing any of
these lines. So pause the video now and give this code challenge a go.
All right. So how did that go? Did you manage to do it? If not,
have a cup of tea or give yourself a little bit of a break,
think about something else and then come back to it and try it again.
If you've already
given it a good go and you want to see what the solution might be,
then follow along with me.
So the first thing we know is that we're going to have a variable
that's going to be equal to a two-digit number.
But remember that that could mean anything. That could mean an integer,
that could mean a floating-point number, that could even mean a number as a
string.
So it might be helpful to actually find out the data type of this two-digit
number that we get. And to do that, we of course use the type function, all
lowercase. And then in between the parentheses,
we add the thing that we want to check. So it's this variable.
And then let's go ahead and print the result into the console.
So now let's run our code and let's type a two-digit number,
say 56.
and we get the result that the type of this two-digit number is a string
because, of course, we're getting hold of this through the input function and the
user could be typing anything into this input, a string,
their name or a number.
So now that we know that this variable has the datatype string,
then you can think of a little bit about what we know we can do with strings.
We can subscript strings, right? So if we had a string like hello,
and we want it to get a hold of the first character, we could put zero there.
And when I print this,
we'll get H being selected out of this string.
So if we know that we can subscript strings to get a hold of a particular value
at a particular position just by using subscripting like this,
then we can do the same with our two-digit number.
So we could say two_digit_number, let's get hold of the first digit.
So let's call it
first_digit equals two_digit_number [
0],
and then the second_digit could be two_digit_number [1].
Now,
when I go ahead and print these two items,
first_digit and second_digit,
then you'll see that if I enter a number like 87,
then my first digit is 8 and my second digit is 7.
So now I can probably start thinking about adding those two digits together.
For example,
we can say that result equals first_digit plus second_digit.
But of course, when I run this right now and I print the value of result,
you'll see that for a number like 87
what I will get is just a eight concatenated to seven,
which turns it back into 87, which is not what I want at all.
Especially after all of my hard work separating out the digits.
What I want to do instead is to turn each of these,
which currently has the data type of string,
so I can demonstrate that to you by saying type of first_digit,
you can see it is a string.
So if I could only change first_digit and second_digit from string data types
into an integer data type by using the type conversion that we learned about
in the last lesson, well then once I do that,
then this plus sign has a whole different meaning because now it's going to add
this first_digit to the second_digit instead of concatenating it.
So now if I go ahead and print the results,
then you'll see that for the same number
87, my result is now 15.
I've now managed to achieve what the code exercise wants me to do.
So did you manage to get it right? If not,
go ahead and have a look at the model solution
and I've written some comments for each line of code that walks you through each
of the steps.
Now notice that instead of converting the second_digit here,
you can also do it up here, like what you see right here.
So I have a play around with the code,
especially if you struggled with this and didn't manage to get it right.
And then once you've understood what's going on here line by line,
if you need, have a look at the previous videos,
then go back to the code challenge and attempt it again.
And only once you're happy that you really understand everything that was
covered in this challenge,
then head over to the next lesson where we're going to talk more about
mathematical operators
like the plus sign and others that you can use in your code. So for all of that
and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In the previous lesson we saw how we could use the plus sign either to
concatenate strings together or as a mathematical operation where we add two
integers or two floats, basically two numbers together.
In this lesson I want to show you some of the other mathematical operators that
you have access to
in addition to adding. The next obvious one is subtraction.
So 7 - 3 , you would just use the minus sign,
but then when you get to multiplication it's a little bit weird. Um,
instead of using the x or some sort of time symbol,
you actually use the asterix.
So you would say something like 3 * 2 and that would be 3
times 2.
Now the final one is division and that's done using the forward-slash, so 6
/ 3 and when that prints out,
it'll give you 2.
Now one thing to notice here is that whenever you're dividing things,
you actually always end up with a floating point number.
So you can see even though six divides into three cleanly,
we're still getting 2.0. And in fact if I put a type check around this division,
you'll see that it will print float instead of integer.
And this is just something that happens with division in Python.
But at the end of the day, you get the result that you need and it doesn't really
matter whether if it's a float or if it's a integer.
Now the last one that's really useful is two asterisk signs and this gives you
access to the exponents or when you want to raise the number to a power.
So for example,
if you wanted to get a hold of 2 to the power of 2, then you would write it
like this and 2 to the power of 2 is of course basically just 2 times 2
which is going to be equal to 4.
Now if I change this to 2 to the power of 3,
then that's going to be 2 times 2 times 2. So that should be 8 and so
on and so forth.
Having the exponent being built into the language is one of the reasons why
Python is really loved by a lot of data scientists and mathematicians because
it's really optimized towards manipulating and handling numbers. Now,
one of the things that you have to be careful about when you are doing these
mathematical operations is when you have more than one operation on the same
line of code, then there's a certain level of priority.
So some of these operations like division or multiplication are going to be
first class,
whereas other ones are going to be more economy like the plus and minus.
And the rule that you might've remember from high school is something called
PEMDAS.
It basically states the order of priority is parentheses,
exponents, multiplication, division, addition and subtraction.
So the things that happen first are the things inside brackets, then it's our exponents,
then it's our multiplication and division.
And finally, the lowest priority is our addition and subtraction.
Now it's a little bit deceiving because of this order.
It makes it seem like as if multiplication happens before division,
but actually they are equally important.
And when it actually comes to your calculations,
the calculation that's most to the left is the one that will be prioritized
between multiplication and division.
So let me give you a real-life example to make this more clear.
Let's say we had a line of code where we wanted to multiply 3 * 3 +
3 / 3 - 3.
If I was to execute this entire line of code and print it out into the console,
here's the time where you play computer again and guess using what you've
learned here, um,
what exactly will be printed because you will get a number printed,
it will calculate this entire line of code for you. But the order matters.
Is it going to first add 3 to 3 then multiply the result by 3 or is
it first going to divide through by 3 and then add 3 to it?
What is the order?
And I want you to really pause the video and have a little play with it on pen
and paper before you come back and we'll show you the result.
Using our rule, PEMDAS,
we can see the first thing that happens is what's in the parentheses,
so that doesn't matter. The next thing, our exponents,
we don't actually have an exponent here.
We don't have 2 to the power of 3 or something to the power of anything.
So we can ignore that as well.
So the next level is the multiplication and division.
And as I mentioned, they are all equal importance.
So this 3 * 3 and 3 / 3 are both equally important,
but the calculation goes from left to right.
So the first thing we see is actually the multiplication. So if it helps you,
you might want to add LR to the end of this mnemonic.
So it becomes PEMDASLR, or at least that's the way I would think about it.
So even if this was division and this was multiplication,
this calculation will always get executed first.
Coming back to the question I asked you, what do you think this number would be?
Let's go ahead and comment out all the other code and run this line of code and
it will give us 7.0. Now if math is not your strong point, don't worry,
it's not mine either and you're the sort of person who would prefer to see it
visualize. Then I recommend again putting this line of code in Thonny,
and then go ahead and clicking on the debugging symbol and then just step into,
so press F7 or this button multiple times and you'll see it evaluate
this line of code step-by-step.
So first it looks at the entire thing and then it goes from left to right.
And the first calculation is 3 * 3 and that is the one that's going
to execute first and it becomes 9.
Next it's going to look along this line of code and see that the next most
important thing is this division here, 3 divided by 3.
So it's going to carry out that next and that becomes 1.
So now 9 + 1 is going to be the next thing because it's the most to the
left and then it becomes 10 - 3 and we finally get the result of 7.
So now here's another challenge for you.
How can you change this code so that instead of getting 7,
we get 3?
How can you change this line of code given what you know about PEMDASLR?
See if you can figure it out. Pause the video now.
Alright, so this will involve a little bit of trial and error.
And the most important tool we have access to is the parentheses or the
brackets. This means that we can actually isolate bits of our code,
which normally have very low priority and turn them into higher priority
operations. So in this case,
we know that 3 * 3 is going to happen first,
and then the multiplication, and then the addition on the left,
and then the subtraction.
But if we added a set of parentheses around our 3 + 3,
then out of all of these calculations,
this particular one suddenly becomes the highest priority and it will happen
first.
So if I change what I've got in Thonny to our new version and go ahead and debug
through it,
the very first calculation it's going to perform is this 3 + 3  inside
the brackets and we end up with 6.
So then it's going to go again from left to right,
prioritizing multiplication and division.
So then it's 3 * 6  is 18. 18 / 3 is 6. 6 - 3 is
3. Just by isolating certain calculations,
you can elevate it to right at the top of the priority list and you will be able
to perform the calculation that you need.
Now that you've learned a lot about calculations and performing mathematical
operations using Python, I've got another code challenge for you.
So head up to the next lesson and you'll be able to discover it there.
All right. So in this code challenge,
click on the date 2.2 BMI calculator code exercise.
So the goal of the challenge is to be able to work out somebody's body mass
index based on their weight and height that they input.
So the body mass index is basically a way of measuring somebody's body
composition that's kind of independent of their height, right?
If two people are both 60 kilos
but one of them is tall and the other person's short,
then the shorter guy is probably a little bit more overweight, right?
So if you take a look at this chart here, let's say, um, for me,
my height is around 1.8 meters and about 60 something kilos.
So I'm in this normal weight bracket of BMI 18.5 to 25.
So this is a really helpful tool for, um,
healthcare professionals to figure out whether if somebody is underweight,
normal weight or overweight,
that is based on their height and weight. In our program,
we're going to calculate this. So when we run our code,
you can see it's asking us for an input, height in meters.
So mine is 1.8 and my weight is say 63 kilos.
And when I hit enter,
ideally, I would like to get my BMI printed out as a whole number like this.
So how can we achieve this? Well, firstly,
you have to take a look at the equation that's used to calculate the BMI.
It's somebody's weight in kilograms
divided by their height squared.
Then once you've got the result,
we want it to be printed as a whole number or as an integer.
So you'll have to think a little bit about type conversion,
you'll have to think about the mathematical operations that we learned about in
the last lesson and combine everything you've learned so far in order to solve
this code challenge. So pause the video now and give that a go.
[inaudible]
All right. So now that you've had a go at it,
I'm going to reveal of solution. In our code
we've already got access to the height and the weight as variables,
so we can simply use them straight away. So for example,
I could just print the height and it would be equal to whatever the user typed
in when they were asked for it by the input. So in this case,
my height would get printed out as 1.8.
If we can access the height and weight,
then we can calculate the BMI by simply replicating the mathematical equation
here.
So we know that the BMI is equal to the weight divided by the height squared,
so we can take the weight and then we can use the forward-slash for divide.
And then we can divide it by the height squared.
So we're going to use the exponent operator to the power of two.
So this is how we could work out the BMI,
but you'll see that if we actually run this code right now
we'll actually get an error.
And what it's going to tell us is that on line 8,
so right here where our equation is, there's a type error.
And it saying that you're trying to use the exponent or the power function for a
string and an integer.
So the 2 is the integer,
but this is still a string. And we can confirm this
if we check the type. So type of height,
let's comment that out, and let's print this.
Then you'll see that when we enter some numbers here,
the type of height and weight in fact is string because they came from the input
function,
which we saw in previous lessons. Before we can actually just simply run this
equation and get the values we want,
we have to convert all the strings into other data types,
right? Now the weight is probably okay as an integer or a whole number because
it's already pretty accurate, 80 kilos or 85 kilos.
We don't necessarily need any decimal places.
But the height on the other hand definitely needs to be a floating-point number
because if it was an integer, then there would only be height of one meter,
two meter, three meter, four meter.
And because most people lie between one meter and two meter, then we really,
really need those numbers after the decimal place
in order to get an accurate calculation. So the height
definitely needs to be a float and we can convert it into a float using this
line of code here,
where we're converting the string into a float. And the weight
you can either convert it into an integer or a float. It doesn't really matter.
So now if we run our code again, you'll see we no longer have any errors
and we're now able to print our BMI.
Let me enter my height and weight again.
And you can see I'm getting this BMI with a massive list of numbers afterwards.
So in our result, we said it should be a whole number.
How can we convert this BMI into a whole number? Well,
we can turn it into bmi_as_int and convert this floating-point
number, the BMI with all of its numbers after the decimal place, into an integer
a whole number,
which will just simply cut off everything that's after the decimal place.
And now if we print this bmi_as_int,
run our code,
then you'll see that we get a whole number being printed out,
which is now our BMI. In the next lesson
I'm actually going to show you how we can round these floating point numbers so
that when it's 19.5 or above,
it becomes 20 when it's 19.4, 19.3, and then it gets rounded down.
But for now, this is all that we want.
We wanted you to be able to cut off the end and turn it into a whole number.
If you want to have a play around with the solution code,
then head over to this Repl.it over here and you'll be able to see the solution
code with a lot of comments
explaining the code line by line and showing you some different ways of doing
things. For example,
instead of converting the weight and height in line on the line where we're
actually doing the calculation, you could do it beforehand. Alternatively,
instead of using the exponent operator
because something to the power of two is simply just something multiplied by
itself, right? Then in this case,
you could also just do height_as_float times height_as_float.
Have a play around with this code and make sure that you're comfortable with
everything that's here.
And if you got anything wrong at all in the code challenge,
then go back and fix it. Now in the next lesson,
we're going to be talking about more mathematical operators
such as rounding numbers instead of just cutting off the end.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In the last challenge where we calculated the BMI,
you saw how when we had a number that had a long list of numbers after the
decimal point. For example,
if I had divided 8 by 3 and I print this out,
you'll see that the value is 2.666666 and if we had just turned this 8
divided by 3 into an integer, right now it's a floating point number,
but if I convert it into an integer,
you'll see that all it does is it just chops off everything after the decimal
point. Instead of what we would traditionally do,
which is to round the number.
So if it's 2.5 it would go to 3, if it's 2.4 it would go down to 2.
Now in Python it's super easy to round numbers.
All you have to do is to use the round function like this.
If we write round(8 / 3) then it's going to round it into a
whole number and you'll see that instead of 2 we actually get 3 now
because 2.6 recurring becomes 3.
Now if you wanted to, you can actually go a step further.
You can specify the number of digits of precision you want to round it to.
So if I said I want to round it to two decimal places,
then I could write (8 / 3, 2) and then the number of places
that I want around it to.
So now our 2.666 recurring becomes 2.67 because I said we should round it to 2
decimal places. So if it makes it easier,
it might be easier if I write it like this.
So 2.666666666 and I'm going to round it to two decimal places
and again, I get the same result,
2.67. Now another way of modifying numbers is instead of dividing,
say 8 / 3,
we can also use the floor division,
so where you have two forward lashes instead of just one.
Now we know that whenever we divide any number by any other number,
the result always gets turned into a floating point number.
Now if you didn't want that and you just wanted an integer,
so a whole number chopping off all the numbers after the decimal in place,
you can just use the floor division like this.
And in this case, you would get 2 straight away without having to convert it
into an integer. And in fact,
if I go ahead and check the data type of the result of this calculation,
you'll see that it's actually an integer
whereas if I had just used the single, um, forward slash division,
then I get a floating point number with decimal places.
Even if this is a clean division, say 4 / 2,
this is still going to become a floating point number and the number is going to
be represented like this, 2.0, like so.
Now if we had saved the results of this calculation into a variable instead,
then one of the things that you can actually do is to continue performing
calculations on this variable. So for example,
I could do 4 / 2,
which is going to be equal to 2. But then if I want to divide it by the 2
again,
I could actually say result /= 2. And when I now print results,
I'll actually get 1 because it's 4 / 2 then divided by 2
again. Now very often when you're writing code,
say for example if you're keeping track of the user's score,
so you could have score = 0 to begin with and every single time in
your code say a user scores a point,
then you can get hold of this score variable again
and instead of saying score now equals the previous value of score plus one,
you can simply use this shorthand, +=,
so +=1. And now when we print score,
you'll see that it's actually equal to 1.
So instead of using +=, you can use -=,
which just takes the previous version of score and removes 1 from it.
*=  and /=.
So this is really handy when you have to manipulate a value based on its
previous value, which you'll have to do a lot in programming.
Now the final thing I want to show you is something called F strings and this
makes it really easy to mix strings and different data types.
So far, up to this point,
if we wanted to print, uhm, something like your score is,
and then we wanted to print the score we have to write plus,
but of course because these are different data types,
this is a string and this is an integer, we got a type error.
So we've had to convert this into a string before it will actually successfully
print when both the datatypes match.
Now this is quite painful and understandably a lot of programmers will need some
slightly more convenient way of incorporating things that have different data
types. Let's say um, the score is equal to zero. Um,
let's say the height is equal to 1.8 and isWinning is equal to true.
So here we've got a integer, a float, and a boolean,
and we want to mix it all into a sentence that is a string and get it printed
out.
So instead of having to convert all of these and use a whole bunch of plus
signs and then you have to convert everything into a string,
it's really, really painful, right?
So what we can do instead is use something in Python known as an F string.
And when an F string allows us to do is in front of a string like this one,
we type the character 'f' and it's really important that it goes in front of the
double quotes or a single quotes if you want to write your strings like this.
But I like to use double quotes and a lot of other Python programmers do too.
So essentially you're adding just the character f in front of the string,
and now this is an F string and you can start adding various values into this
string. So for example, if I wanted to write,
your score is equal to this variable score,
then I can put that variable inside a set of curly braces like this.
And now when I print my string, this one right here,
you'll see that it says your score is zero and it does all of the converting and
all of the stuff behind the scenes and you don't have to worry about any of
this. So if I want to continue along,
I could say your score is this,
your height is adding the height and then you are winning is then let's add
that final boolean value
and get it to run.
You can see that our entire string now prints out your score is 0,
your height is 1.8 you are winning is True.
So all of these different data types got combined into a string by using an F in
front of the string and then using these curly braces to place our variables
into this string. By using f strings,
you cut down on a lot of the manual labor of inserting different data types into
a string.
And this is going to come in really handy just about on the next lesson where
I've got a coding challenge for you.
Head over there and complete the challenge.
So you should see day 2.3 Your Life in Weeks, and this is the challenge that we're going to complete
in this lesson.
The idea is that there's a really great article by Tim Urban of Wait but Why on visualizing your
life in weeks.
And I was reading this recently, and it really made an impact on me, especially when you see that
a whole life from age 0 to 90 can be mapped out like this in weeks where every week is represented
by a little checkbox and you can see each of these boxes right?
This is like how many weeks you have in your whole life, and it's not as small as I thought it would
be.
I thought each of these boxes would be like invisible because they're so tiny because
I have so many weeks in my life, but it's actually not true.
There's actually not that many.
So in today's coding challenge, what I want you to do is to create a program using the mathematical
operations that you learned about, as well as the fstrings that you learned about in the last lesson
to tell us how many days, weeks and months we actually have left
if we were lucky enough to live until 90 years old. The code is going to ask you for your current age,
let's say that I'm 12, and then it's going to calculate the number of days, weeks and months you have
left in your life if you lived until 90. And then it's going to print it out to you
like so.
And the important premise of this code challenge for all of the test to pass is that there are 365 days
in the year, 52 weeks in a year and 12 months in a year.
I know that because of leap year, it's actually a little bit more than that,
but for this exercise sake, let's just call it 365, 52 and 12.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge and then head back over here and we'll walk through
the solution together.
All right.
How did that exercise go?
I'm sorry, it's a little bit dark making you think about how many days, weeks and months you have left
in life, but you can think about it as a motivation, right?
If I only have 400 months left, I don't know if I want to spend one of those months just watching Game
of Thrones.
Maybe I want to do something for other people.
Maybe I want to create something.
So how are we going to calculate this?
Well, we've got hold of the age from the input, but you might remember from previous lessons that
the input always creates a string data type.
In order to do your maths, we do still have to do a type conversion, so we have to change our age
into a number.
So let's call it age_as_int, age is never going to be a float, right?
Because not many people are going to tell you that they are 56.4 years old, so we're
going to accept this as a whole number. So we'll convert our age into an int.
Now the next stage is we have to do some calculations.
We have to calculate the number of years left, right?
So let's call it years_remaining and that's going to be equal to 90,
so we're presuming we're going to live to 90, minus age_as_int.
So now that we've got the number of years remaining, we can calculate the number of days, weeks and
months left.
So days remaining is going to be equal to years remaining multiplied by 365 because there
are 365 days in a year, and then we can do the same for weeks.
And months.
So now that I've got hold of the number of days remaining, weeks remaining and months remaining, then
I'm ready to actually use it inside my string.
But before we do that, it's always helpful to check your code as you go along to make sure that it
works exactly as you expect it to.
So let's go ahead and try to print what is the number of months remaining.
So if we go ahead and run our code and let's say that we're 80 years old, right?
Which means that we'll have 10 years remaining and we'll have 120 months remaining.
So all of that looks pretty good to me.
So the next thing we have to do is to somehow output this sentence where it says you have x days, y weeks
and z months left.
So let's copy that and paste that sentence in here.
And then I'm going to turn it into a string by wrapping it inside a set of double-quotes.
Now that I've got a string, I can turn it into an fstring by putting the card to 'f' before the string.
And instead of having x, y and z, I can replace them with some curly braces inside of which I can
put my variable names.
So I'll change this to days_remaining, this to weeks_remaining and this to months_remaining.
So now that I've got my string, I have two options: I can either just wrap this inside a print statement
and print it as it is.
But what I think might actually make it easier to read is to save it inside a separate variable called
message.
And then in the next line, I can simply print my message.
It does exactly the same thing, but I think this is a little bit easier to read.
So now let's go ahead and run our code and see if we get any errors.
It's asking us for our current age, let's say, was 67 years old.
Well, then we only have 8,395 days and 1,196 weeks and 276 months.
So I hope you managed to get this code challenge right
and even though the challenge is a little bit dark,
well, at least remember that when you become a really good programmer, you'll be able to cut down
on a lot of the boring things and repetitive tasks in life.
So at least you'll be claiming back some of those days, weeks and months.
So I hope you had fun with me on this code challenge. In the next lesson,
I've got a quiz for you. So head over there and give it a go.
Hey, guys, welcome to the final project of today, and in this final project, we're going to be building
a tip calculator.
So the final output is going to look like this.
It's going to print
Welcome to the tip calculator.
And it's going to ask you for an input for how much the total bill came to.
Let's say that we and a couple of friends went out for lunch and it came to 124.
56 dollars.
And then it'll ask you, what percentage tip would you like to give?
So let's say we want to give a 12 percent tip.
So we enter 12 and hit enter.
And then finally it asks how many people are splitting this bill?
Let's say there's seven of us and then hit enter.
Finally, it's going to tell us that each person should pay about $19.93.
Notice how the final bill, even though after all of these calculations, it's probably got more numbers
after the decimal point, we only want two decimal places of accuracy, so it should be rounded to two
decimal places.
The second thing to remember is that these are percentages, and in order to calculate a percentage of
something, you can multiply a number by the percentage number divided by 100.
Let me show you this in a little bit more detail.
If you head over to replit/appbrewery/tip-calculator-start, then you've got
these starting file for this project.
And here I just want to quickly show you how the math works, because this project is not about testing
your math.
It's about seeing how well you've understood the programming concepts.
Let's say that we had a bill of $150.
If we were to apply a 12% tip on top of that, then 12% is going to be equal to twelve
divided by a hundred, which is equal to 0.12.
Now the next step is we can multiply 150, the total bill, by 0.12.
And this will give us what 12 percent of 150 is, which is 18.
Now we of course, have to add the tip onto the final bill so it becomes 150 plus 18.
So $150 with a 12 percent tip is equal to $168.
Now, a shorthand way of doing all of this is simply multiplying 150 by 1.12.
So the 1 is 150, and then it's 0.12 on top of that.
So when we do this, it gives us pretty much the same number.
Now, if during your testing and your coding you come across some sort of number that looks a little
bit strange because you think 150 multiplied by 1.12 should actually equal 168
precisely.
So what are all of these extra numbers at the end?
Now, the short answer is you don't have to worry about it.
It's simply related to how Python processes these floating-point numbers.
If you're really interested and you want to read about this, then I'll link to this page in the Python
documentation where they tell you why this is happening.
But be warned, it's pretty dense and it's pretty heavy.
But the final conclusion is it's just the way that Python is approximating this number.
So you don't actually have to worry about this.
Now, once we've gotten to 168, the next step is to split it between five people.
So 168 divided by 5 is equal to 33.6.
Now, what we want to show the user is we want to show them the amount that they have to pay with two
decimal places of accuracy.
We want to say something like 33.60 if this is the case, because that's normally
how we represent numbers when it comes to money.
So what I want you to do is to also be able to round any of these numbers to two decimal places.
If you have successfully created this program, then it should work exactly as this example version
would, which you can find if you go to tip-calculator-end.appbrewery.repl.run, and
you'll be to see the formatting where it actually tells you each person should pay this particular dollar
amount and it's rounded to two decimal places.
And this is the amount after taking into consideration these three different inputs from the user.
Have a play around with the final product and then have a think about how you would create this program
step by step and then give it a go by forking this starting repository to your own account and then
try to achieve this result.
This is going to test everything that you've done so far including fstrings, including complex
mathematical operations,
including PEMDAS and calculating numbers and the order in which mathematical operations are run by
a computer, as well as everything you learn in the previous lesson and the previous days as well. I think
this is going to be a lot of fun and the end result is going to be kind of useful the next time that
you need to split the bill between friends.
So I'm going to let you pause the video and get on with it.
And then once you're done, if you want to, head back over here and I'll walk through the solution with
you. But I really recommend you giving it a good go before you come back.
So pause the video now and I'll see you later.
OK, so we've seen how the program is supposed to work and we're trying to create it from scratch by
reverse-engineering it essentially. The first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to fork the starting
project and create my own version of it which I can edit.
Now, the first thing our program should say is welcome to the tip calculator.
So that's easy enough.
We just have to create a print statement.
Perfect.
And if you're creating a really enthusiastic tip calculator, you can replace the full stop with an
exclamation mark.
OK, so let's run it step by step to make sure that we don't have any errors along the way.
So the first step seems to be working. Now
the next step is to ask the user for some input.
And we want to know what was their total bill, what did it come to?
So let's go ahead and create an input and ask them what was the total bill?
And then we'll add a dollar sign or whatever currency it is that you prefer to work with.
Because when we actually run this, you'll see that the input will go straight after the end of that
string,
so at the dollar sign.
So now we can enter a dollar amount like this, but it's not really saved anywhere.
This data just disappears because we haven't stored it inside a variable.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Let's call this variable bill and we'll set it to equal whatever the user typed in to this input.
Now, remember that this bill is going to have a data type of a string, right?
So if I go ahead and hit run and let's just type some numbers in here, you'll see that the data type
of the bill is, as we said, a string. In order to be able to do math,
you might remember, we have to change this into a number format,
so a float or an int.
Now, in this case, because the bill is likely to have numbers after the decimal place, it's probably
better that we turn it into a float so that we get the most accurate result possible. Now that we're
done with the bill,
the next question the tip calculator should ask is what percentage tip would you like to give? 10, 12
or 15?
Or you can, of course, switch this up depending on how much tip you normally give.
So the next line is going to be another input.
Here, I'm asking the user, how much tip would you like to give and giving them some examples. And
notice how in my examples, I don't actually have the percentage sign here because I don't really
want them to type the percent sign into this input because if they do when they say 12%,
this is going to be really hard for me to turn the 12% into an actual number.
So you could, in your input message, say something like how much tip would you like to give 10,
12, 15?
Please don't add any percentage signs.
Just add the number or something like that.
But again, once we've done this, it's not stored anywhere unless we add it into a variable.
Now we've got a bill that stores the total bill as a float and we've got a tip which is going to be
a whole number, 10, 12 or 15,
right?
So depending on what you think is best, you can either turn this into a float or in my case, I'm probably
going to convert it into an integer.
So now we're onto the final step, which is how many people to split the bill between.
So let's go ahead and create a variable called people.
And I'm going to add an int wrapper around this input so that even in the very beginning, we know that
we have to convert the number of people into a whole number because I've never had a meal with
3.5 before.
So the input is going to be how many people to split the bill.
And at this point, they should enter the number of people which will turn into an integer stored inside
this variable called people. So now that we've got all the data collected from the user, we're finally
ready to do some math.
And we said that the way to work out the tip is by multiplying it by 1. and then the number after
the decimal point is whatever percentage they decided to give.
So it would be 1.1 if it was 10 percent and 1.15 if it was 15 percent.
Let's go ahead and calculate the bill_with_tip.
So remember how we said that before the tip percentage is equal to the whole number, 10, 12 or 15,
divided by 100, which turns it into 0.1, 0.12 or 0.15,
and then once this calculation is done, we can multiply it by the bill. And then finally we add that
to the original bill.
So let's go ahead and print this and just check to see that it looks sensible.
So bill_with_tip is what we're going to print.
And let's put some easy numbers in there.
And let's say that the bill was a hundred dollars and the tip was 10 percent.
So then the 10% of hundred dollars is ten dollars.
So the bill_with_tip,
that's what's going to be printed next, should be 110. So we can type anything in here because
we're not using it.
And you can see that this calculation, bill_with_tip, is 110, which is what we want.
Now, there's a lot of other ways that you can express this.
For example, you could say, bill * (1 + tip/100).
So this would actually give you the same result as well.
But remember what we said previously about how Python is a little bit weird with floating-point numbers.
But essentially this is still giving us the same result, which is 110.
So you can choose whichever way you find most intuitive.
And if you want, you can even split this up into several steps, right?
We could say that tip_as_percent is equal to tip/100.
And then we can multiply the bill by the tip_as_percent to get the total tip amount.
And then finally, we can get the total bill by adding the bill to the total_tip_amount.
Feel free to do this whichever way makes sense to you, but I'm going to leave it with as many steps
as possible so that you can actually work through the logic if you got stuck on this math.
Now, the next thing we need to do is to divide the total bill by the number of people.
So if we had five people, then we would divide it five ways,
right?
So let's call this bill_per_
person, which is going to be equal to the total bill divided by the number of people.
Now, at this stage, this bill_per_person is a floating-point number, so it could have many, many
digits after the decimal point.
If we want to round this to two decimal places, then you might remember from some of the lessons today,
we have access to a function called round.
And here we can add the number that we want around, which is the bill_per_person,
and then after a comma, we can specify how precise, how many numbers or how many decimal places do
we want to round this bill to.
And in our case, it's two decimal places.
So now this is the final amounts, which I'll call final_amount which is the bill_per_person rounded
to two decimal places.
And we can now finally print this to the user and say each person should pay...
And remember, you can either use string concatenation which will require you to convert this number
into a string again, or use the trick that we learned in the previous lessons where we can create an
fstring by adding F in front of the string and then using some curly braces to insert the final amount
right here.
And we can write the final_amount dollars or we can put a dollar sign in front and maybe a colon here.
And now if we clear our console and run our code, then you'll see it work.
So welcome to the tip calculator.
What was the total bill?
Let's make up some random number.
What percentage tip?
Let's say we're going to get 15 and then we're splitting it between five people. And it calculates everything,
doing all of that maths.
And finally, it rounds it to two decimal places, giving us the final amount each person should pay.
But what if we test it out with the initial numbers?
Let's hit, run and let's try to put in 150 dollars as the total bill, and then we're going to give
a 12 percent tip and we're going to split it between five people.
Notice that is telling us that each person should pay $33.6.
But normally, we're used to seeing that rounded to two decimal places.
But we have that round function here already.
So why is it not doing its job?
Well, if you think about it, the result of this calculation is just 33.6. There's
nothing after the six, but we want it to display a zero. And this is a formating problem rather than
a mathematical rounding problem.
So what do we do?
Well, we go to our good friend Google whenever we're stuck and we're going to search for how to round
number to two decimal places in Python.
And if we take a look at the first Stack Overflow question, you can see that this person had pretty much
the same problem that we had.
And if we're scrolling down, you can see that the solution is to use some sort of formatting. And we
can try out each of these examples one by one in code to see how they work,
and we can also take a look at the documentation that they link to.
So the actual way that we do this is by using a colon and then dot and then we specify that after the
dot, we want two decimal points in our float. And we use the format function to do this.
So instead of using round, we can create this final amount variable by creating a string using that
format, :.2f, and then we can use the format function to pass in that bill_per_person.
And now when we run this again, using the same inputs, we now get a .60 at the very end
and this is basically turned this bill_per_person, which is a float into a string.
And that string is abiding by this particular format, which is the two decimal places.
How did you get on with this project?
Did you manage to get it in one go without having to look at the solution? If you got stuck at any point
or if your code didn't work as you expect it to,
this is a time to go back to it, fix it, and make sure that you've understood everything that's been
covered through this exercise.
But if you already created it and it's working perfectly, then you're ready to go out there with your
tip calculator in hand.
Remember that you can save the URL of your tip calculator in your phone as a bookmark.
So the next time you go out and have dinner or lunch with friends, then you can crack open your own
tip calculator and figure out the final bill.
So I hope you had fun building this project and doing all of the coding exercises and learning about mathematical
operations, fstrings, data types, type conversion, and all of the things that we did today. Have a rest
and I'll be back tomorrow teaching you about conditional statements and how we can get the program to
do different things depending on certain conditions or certain parts of our code.
So I bid you good night and I'll see you tomorrow.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 3.
Today you can learn all about conditional statements,
if else, else if, logical operators, code blocks, scope,
global and local name spacing and a whole lot more.
And by the end of the day you will know enough to be able to build this awesome
Choose your own adventure game.
So this is what it looks like when it loads and our mission is to find the
treasure. So it tells us your at a crossroad, where do you want to go?
Left or right? Let's say I want to go left. You come to a Lake,
there's an Island in the middle of the Lake. Type
wait to wait for a boat, type swim to swim across. I'm going to wait for a boat.
You arrive at the Island unharmed, there's a house with three doors, one red,
one yellow and one blue. Which color do you choose?
Let's choose red. And unfortunately, it's a room full of fire. Game over.
So this game lets the user make decisions and depending on what they've chosen,
it continues the game storyline. If you want to have a go at this game,
you can head over to treasure-island
-end.appbrewery.repl.run and have a play around with the game.
And once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and we're going to start picking up the skills
that's going to be required in order to build this game.
So I'll see you on the next lesson.
Here's a question. Have you ever sat in your bath and wondered,
why is it that no matter how forgetful I am,
my bath never overflows like this?
This is something I was thinking about the other day and I realized that it's
not because I'm particularly diligent. I forget stuff all the time. I mean,
pizza, anyone? This is what my pizzas usually look like. Um,
but the reason why a bathtub or the sink doesn't overflow is because of this
fantastic piece of engineering, the overflow.
So this means that whenever the water reaches beyond a certain level about here,
the water starts overflowing
so the bathtub doesn't overflow and annoy your neighbors downstairs.
In fact, we could represent this mechanism with a conditional statement.
When the water level is say greater than 80 centimeters,
then it should drain the water.
But if the water level is not greater than 80 centimeters,
it should continue filling up the tub.
This type of conditional statement is known as an if/else statement.
Depending on a particular condition,
we would do either A or B.
And when we want to write Python code to represent this,
it looks something like this.
There's the keyword if, and then the condition that we're testing for and then a
colon and after the colon we've got an indented block of code which should be
executed if this condition is met, if it's true.
But if it's not true,
then we will skip to the else block and it's just the else  keyword with a colon
and then this code block would execute if the condition is false.
So we could represent that previous bathtub situation with code that looks a bit
like this.
Let's say our water level is at 50 centimeters and then we would test if the
water level is greater than 80 centimeters. Well, if that is the case,
then we should drain the water.
But if it's not greater than 80 centimeters,
in other words else, well in this case,
we should just continue filling up the bathtub.
Let's put this into practice with a real life problem.
Now let's say that you've gotten a job at a theme park and your first job of the
day is to write some code that replaces the ticket box.
Now there's a couple of things that you'll need to think about. Firstly,
in order for somebody to actually purchase a ticket to go on the rollercoaster
ride, they will need to be over 120 centimeters.
So we have to check what their height is because if they're too short,
then we won't be able to sell them a ticket anyways. In the course resources,
I've included a link to this flow chart that I've created on draw.io.
This is a really,
really useful tool for creating any sort of flow charts or diagrams and it's
really easy to use. Now, if we take a look at this flow chart,
this is basically the logic that we have to program using our,
if and else statements.
If the person who's trying to purchase a ticket is not over 120 centimeters,
then they can't ride on the rollercoaster.
But if their height is greater than 120 centimeters, then they can ride.
So let's try it out. If you head over to the starting Repl.it,
you'll find some starting code in there and you can go ahead and fork this
Repl.it.
All that I've got here is a print statement that says "Welcome to the
rollercoaster" as well as an input asking the user for their height in
centimeters and then converting the string into a whole number, an integer, and
then I'm storing it inside this variable called height.
Now we're going to check whether if the height that the user has typed in is
greater than 120. So we use the keyword if and then we check if the height is
greater than 120 and then we add the colon and now when I hit enter,
you'll notice that the code editor has automatically indented me slightly over.
I'm not over here because in Python the spacing and indentation is really,
really important.
It tells the computer that the code that I'm about to write is what should be
executed when this condition is met.
So what should happen? If your height is over 120 then we will just print
You can ride the rollercoaster!.
But what should we print if height is not greater than 120? Well,
in this case, we would use the else statement to catch when that happens.
And it's really important that you don't write the else here because this is
indented over. Instead,
you want it to be at the same indentation level as the if statement.
These two are essentially a pair, if and else. Now,
after the else keyword,
we again add a colon and then we hit enter and we're now indented again.
And here we can write the code that should happen if this condition is false.
"Sorry, you have to grow taller before you can ride."
So the really important things here are the condition which we're testing for, is
the value of height greater than 120, the syntax of this code
so the keywords
if and else as well as the colons that come after each of these lines.
And finally also the indentation.
Everything that is indented after the
if is a block of code.
So this is indented and it's effectively inside this
if. So
this line of code lives inside the else statement.
This block of code lives inside the if statement. And if you mess up on the
indentation then you're probably going to get an indentation error telling you
that this line 5 probably should be indented.
But when we do actually correct it and we hit run,
let's say that our height is 130 centimeters,
then we get back, you can ride the rollercoaster.
But if our height was say 90 centimeters,
then we get a different outcome. We get, sorry,
you have to grow taller before you can ride. So by using,
if and else statements we're able to get our code to do different things,
either printing this line or printing this line depending on a condition that
we're testing for. Now, when we use this greater than sign,
effectively what we're saying is that is the height greater than 120 which means
that it does not include 120. In fact,
if I run this code and if I type in my height as 120 then actually goes into the
else block and prints this.
So if we wanted to include 120 centimeters so that all the people who are
exactly 120 centimeters can ride the rollercoaster,
then instead of just using a greater than symbol,
we have to write greater than or equals.
So these two symbols have to be next to each other.
And now when I run my code and I write 120, you'll see that it's now falling into
this block of code and it's telling me that I can ride the roller coaster. Now,
these are called comparison operators and we've already seen greater than, so
lesser than is pretty self explanatory.
But we've also seen greater than or equal to and lesser than or equal to.
So if you want to include a particular number, a particular value,
when you do these comparisons, you would be using these instead.
Now in this table, there's also the equal to and not equal to.
For example,
if you wanted to check if somebody's height is equal to precisely 120 then you
would use two equal signs. And very often it gets a little bit confusing,
especially if you're new to programming when you're typing equal signs,
because sometimes we're typing one and other times we're typing two.
It's important to remember that when you have one equal sign,
it means that you're assigning this value to this variable.
But when you have two equal signs,
you are checking to see if the value on the left is equal to the value on the
right and they're completely different. Now,
the good thing is that when you get it wrong,
usually you'll get enough clues in the error to actually hint to you,
Hey, maybe there's something that's wrong here, right?
Cause the syntax doesn't look right. For this to be a condition,
it has to be something that evaluates to true or to false.
And height =120 does not evaluate to either.
So by changing it to this,
we're saying if height is equal to 120 then we'll execute this line of code
or any other lines which are in the same block of code.
But if the height is not equal to 120 then we're going to execute this block of
code. So if I write 120 then that works.
But if I write 121 then it does not work.
Similarly, you can also check for not equals to, which just flips it around.
But in our case, it makes sense to say if the height is greater than or equals
120 then you can ride the rollercoaster.
But otherwise you cannot ride the rollercoaster. By using,
if and else statements,
we can get our computer to do different things and respond differently depending
on different conditions. So in the next lesson,
I've got a coding exercise for you. I'll see you there.
All right guys, it's time for yet
another code challenge to test and see if you've learned what was covered in
previous lessons. So head over to the assignment
that is a day 3.1 odd
or eve. Have a read of the instructions and try to see if you can create a
program that checks whether if a number that you input in the console is odd
or even. Now the thing to remember here though
is that we're introducing something called the modulo
and you can create the symbol by simply typing the percentage sign. Now,
what the modulo does is it will divide a number
say seven by another number
let's say two, and then it will give you the remainder of that division.
So seven divided by two, seven split into portions of two is two plus two plus
two plus one, right?
So seven divided by two can be divided three times with a remainder of one.
And that's what the modulo gives you.
So you can also type code straight into the console like I'm going to do now;
7 % 2. It gives me 1.
Now it's the same thing if you try to divide by other numbers,
let's say 7 % 3. Well,
that is three plus three plus one, right?
So seven modular three will also give me one.
So this is a way for us to divide a number by another number and get the
remainder.
And you're going to be using this modular to solve this code challenge.
Have a read of the instructions,
have a look at the examples and see what it is that we're expecting to be
printed in the console here.
And then go ahead and write your code and see if your output matches what it is
that we're expecting. So 56 should be even,
so you should be printing "This is an even number" based on that input.
Pause the video now and give this code challenge a go.
All right.
So I mentioned that the modulo gives us the remainder, right?
So what do we know about even numbers? Well even numbers they're always divisible by
two. If we pick any even number, say 54,
and then we do modulo two, so 54 divided by 2,
it should always give us zero
as long as that first number is even so 68 % 2
again it zero.
But then when we come across an odd number, say 53 % 2,
then this is now going to give us 1.
We can use our code to check for when the result is zero,
in which case it's a even number. And when the result is one,
in which case it's an odd number. If you have gotten stuck until this point,
and this is a really great time to pause the video again and go back and give it
another go. And then we'll go through the solution together.
We can simply write an if statement to check if the number that was inputted is
divisible by two with zero remainder.
Well, in this case, then we can pretty much be sure that this is an even number,
because as we've shown, all of the even numbers when they divide by two,
there's always no remainder. So in this case, let's add a colon.
We can print pretty confidently that this is a even number.
Now,
what about the cases where the number when divided by two is not equal to zero?
Well, then it's probably going to be an odd number. So in this case
we can use an else statement to catch that.
And when we have an odd number, we'll simply print
this is an odd number.
So that's it. Just four the lines of code using what we've learned about if, else,
and also the comparison operator. Now,
if you got stuck on this and you needed to watch the solution,
then I recommend really going back to your code and playing around with it so
that you can get the code to work. And then try and see if you can test if a
particular number is cleanly divisible by three by four by five,
and then see if the final program actually works in the way that you expect it
to. But once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson where we're going to talk about even more complex
ways of using if and else statements. So for all of that
and more, I'll see you there.
In previous lessons,
we learned about using the if and else statements to check whether if somebody is
over 120 centimeters or not and allow them to actually purchase a ticket if they
are over a certain height. Now in addition to the height,
there's another condition that we need to check for, namely their age.
If somebody is over 18 years old and they should be paying the adult price,
which is let's say $12. But if they are 18 or under,
then they should only be paying $7. So how can we represent this extra condition
that we need to check for in our code? Well,
we could use something called a nested if/else statement.
We've seen our,
if/else statements look like this where it's only got two choices.
If this condition is true, do this, otherwise do that.
But in a nested if statement, once the first condition has passed,
we can check for another condition. And then we can have another if/else statement
inside this if condition. In order for this thing to happen,
this has to be true and this also has to be true. In order for this to happen,
this condition has to be true but this condition has to be false.
So essentially the computer first looks at the larger picture,
which is this first condition and decides on whether if it should go into the
else block here or if it should go into the nested block inside the if
statement.
So now this is what our flow chart looks like. In the first if statement we check
whether if their height is over 120 centimeters. If no,
then the if statements all end. You can't ride, you can't buy a ticket.
But if yes,
we actually take them to yet another if statement where we check their age.
If their age is 18 or under, then we give them a $7 ticket.
If they're over 18 then they have to pay $12. So the place where we're going to
nest our if statement is inside here. Notice how it's indented.
So it's already inside this if block,
and this already has to be true.
Now here we're going to create another if and else statement and the condition
checks for their age. So we better ask them for an age.
Let's say age equals convert the inputs to an int and "what is your age?"
So now that we've gotten hold of their age,
we can see if their age is less than or equal to 18. Well in this case we're
going to give them the $7 ticket.
But else namely, if this is not true,
if their age is over 18, well, in that case, we're going to give them the $12
ticket.
So now we have a nested if statement,
because this if and else statement lives inside this if statement.
So this condition will only be checked if this is already deemed to be true.
Now let's say our situation got a little bit more complex. The boss comes over,
checks our code and says, wait a wait, wait, wait,
there's actually more price tiers than that. In fact,
if you're less than 12 years old, you pay $5.
If you're between 12 and 18 you pay $7 and if you're over 18 then you pay the
full adult price,
which is $12. Now there are three possibilities,
so how do we represent this in our if statement? Well,
we could use something called the elif. Instead of having a simple if/else statement
where there's only one condition. If it's true, do this.
Otherwise do that.
You can add as many elif conditions as you want. So we can check for condition
1. If that's true, then do a, but if that's not true,
then we can continue and check for condition 2.
If condition 2 is true, well then we can do B. And finally,
if none of those conditions were true, we can do this final thing.
Our flow chart now looks something like this and this is the logic that we're
trying to program. Once we're inside this nested if statement,
we're going to check if the age is under 12 in which case they should pay $5. If
they're between 12 and 18 then they should pay $7 and finally if they're over 18
then they should pay $12. Now the first thing I'm going to check is if the age is
less than 12. Under this condition,
they should pay $5. So let's change that to five.
Now the next condition should be created using an elif,
which stands for else if. So it means,
if this is not true else if, can you check if this is true?
Well in that case then we should do this. For example,
if the age is not less than 12, so they're over 12, then are they under 18? Well then
this condition basically catches everybody who's between 12 and 18. And finally,
if they're not less than or equal to 18 and they're not less than 12 then that's
everybody else who is over 18.
Now remember that we can use as many elif conditions between the if and else as we
like.
So I could add another elif that checks whether if the age is less than,
say, 22 well in this case, do something else.
And then I can keep going with these elifs until I'm done with all my
conditions. So have a play around with this code,
write it yourself, see if it makes sense,
and then mess around with the elifs so that it does what you expect it to do.
And then once you're ready,
go ahead and head over to the next lesson where I've got a coding challenge for
you.
So now that you've learned all about if, elif and else,
as well as nested if statements,
then I've got two code challenges coming up for you. In the first one, in the
code challenge that's called day 3.2 BMI calculator
2.0,
this is going to be an upgraded version of the BMI calculator that you created
yesterday.
Instead of just working out the BMI value of somebody,
we're going to give them an interpretation.
You might've come across a BMI chart that looks like this,
where it divides up people's BMI and tells them whether if the underweight,
normal weight, overweight, et cetera. And this depends on the value of the BMI.
So if the value of the BMI is less than 18.5,
then they are underweight. If they're over 18.5,
but below 25, then they have a normal weight.
So your job is to not only create a BMI calculator,
but also to give them the corresponding interpretation message.
Now it's really,
really important that you use the words here that are highlighted in bold in your
interpretation, that based on a particular height and weight,
you actually give them the correct interpretation.
Pause the video and try to give this challenge a go.
All right. So how did you get on?
There was a little bit of a revision from what you've done previously.
Hopefully you've been able to calculate the BMI without much trouble and then
use what you learned about if, elif and else to provide the user with the
corresponding interpretation for the BMI that they have.
Let's start out by calculating the BMI. And the BMI,
according to this equation is equal to the weight in kilograms
divided by the height squared. So we've got the weight already,
and then we divided by the height to the power of two.
Now, notice how I've already converted these inputs to floats.
So we don't have to do what we did previously when we were calculating the BMI.
Now what the exercise does mention though
is that we should round the result of the nearest whole number.
But you probably remember how to do this right? Using the round function.
So if we wrap the entire equation inside a round function,
then it's going to round it to the nearest whole number.
So if this is what you got stuck on, then head back to your code and just fix it.
Now, once we've calculated the rounded value of BMI,
the next step is to give the user an interpretation message based on their BMI.
So let's start with the first one.
If the BMI is less than 18.5,
well then in this case, they're actually underweight, right?
So it will print something like your BMI is,
and then inside here we'll insert the value of their BMI.
And this of course is using f-strings, so let's add an F to the beginning.
Your BMI is this particular value and you are underweight.
Now,
what if their BMI was between 18.5 and 25?
Well, because we've already checked that their BMI is less than 18.5,
then if this is false because it's jumped to the next level,
then we don't actually have to check this.
All we have to do is check that it's still below 25. And to do that,
we're going to use an Elif.
So elif BMI is less than 25, well then in this case,
we're going to print you bmi
is this particular value, and you have a normal
weight. If this is a little bit mysterious to you,
why it is that I'm not checking that their BMI is over 18.5,
but below 25 and I'm simply just checking that it's less than 25,
then I recommend having a play around with the code as it is right now,
and trying out some different values for BMI.
Just change this to say 18,
and then try maybe something like 22 so that it's caught by each of these
conditions. And then you'll soon realize that this
if, elif, else is an entire group of statements,
and it's going to check this one first and only if this fails,
when it's false, does it go and check the next one.
So then this is only going to be printed when their BMI is over 18.5,
but below 25. And once you're comfortable with this,
then the rest of the statements should be pretty easy.
All right,
Now,
once we've reached here and their BMI is not less than 35 and we want to catch the
remaining cases where the BMI is over 35,
then all we have to do is add an else statement.
That's all we have to do.
We've managed to check for those people that have BMI less than 18.5.
If it's not less 18.5, well, is it less than 25?
So this will print when the BMI is greater than 18.5,
but less than 25. And we've done that for all of these separate statements.
If you struggled with this code,
then I recommend having a look back at the previous lesson where we talked more
in detail in terms of if, elif and else.
If you struggled with this challenge,
then have a go at pasting the code that's in the solution into the Thonny code
editor. And instead of having the BMI being a workout value,
just set it to some different numbers. So for example, if we start out testing,
if the BMI is equal to 18,
which of these will it fall into, then we can click on the debug step into each
of these. And you can see that when it evaluates this condition,
is the BMI less than 18.5, well,
18 is less than 18.5. So this is true.
And in that case, it's going to execute this line of code.
So it is going to print out your BMI is 18, you are underweight.
And then it's done. That's the end of the code. Now,
if we change this to say 22 however, and we click on debug,
then it's going to evaluate the first condition, is 22 less than 18.5 and
that's going to be false.
So then it skips to the next elif that it can find
and it checks whether if the BMI 22 is less than 25.
So now it's going to execute this print statements.
Have a play around with that
if it's still a little bit mysterious to you and hopefully,
once you're done there,
then you'll be ready to move on to the next code challenge
which is a little bit more challenging. For all of that and more,
I'll see you there.
Hey guys. So I've got another code challenge for you. And this one,
as the title suggests, this is a difficult challenge,
and this is something that I expect some of you might need to spend 15,
20 minutes on. Others might need to spend 30, 40 minutes on,
and it might just be something that you need to have a think about, get stuck,
come back to it after a bit of a break or sleep on it,
come back to it the next day. It's not easy,
but what I'm trying to say is really,
really give it all you have before you check the solution video,
because it's a really, really interesting challenge.
So the idea is that we want you to write a program that works out
whether if any given year is a leap year.
We know that a normal year has 365 days,
but leap years have an extra day in February.
And the reason is actually really, really interesting. If you're interested,
there's a really good explanation of how leap years work and why we have them at
this YouTube link. So just go ahead and copy this URL and check it out.
Now, the way that you work out if a given year is a leap year,
so let's say we pick one out of thin air, 2020,
is that on every year that is evenly divisible by four,
so that means divisible by four with no remainder.
Then that is a leap year, but except the years
that is also evenly divisible by a hundred,
unless the year is also evenly divisible by 400.
Now 2020 divided by four is equal to 505.
So it's evenly divisible by four. There's no remainder.
But the rule says that even if it's divisible by four,
if it's evenly divisible by a hundred,
then that is still not going to be a leap year.
So let's try that 2020 divided by a hundred equals 20.2.
So this is in fact not evenly divisible by a hundred.
So that means it is still a leap year. But then it says
unless the years also evenly divisible by 400.
So 2020
divided by 400 is not evenly divisible.
So it is in fact, still a leap year.
The trickiest part of this entire challenge
I would say is getting your head around these three sentences: a year that is
divisible by four with no remainder is a leap year,
except if it's also divisible by a hundred. In that case,
it's no longer a leap year,
unless that year also happens to be evenly divisible by 400 then it is still a
leap year. What I recommend doing is a)
if English is not your native language
then have a look online for the rules for determining a leap
year in your own language, because these words, except
and unless, are so,
so integral to how this algorithm works. And you really,
really need to understand exactly what it means.
Then what I recommend you doing is to go ahead and create a flow chart,
just like what I've done in previous examples.
Head over to a website like draw.io,
or simply just write it on a piece of paper.
Draw it out and visualize what this actually means in terms of your code.
Now, if you really get stuck on that,
I've also created a flowchart for you.
So if you actually get stuck creating the flowchart,
there is one there that you can refer to as well.
But it's a really good exercise
creating your own flowchart based on what it is that you want your program to
do, and your algorithm or your code should correctly tell us whether
if it's a leap year or not a leap year. So it just has to print out leap year
if it is like 2400, and if it's not a leap year,
like 1989, then just print, not leap year.
This is the time to pause the video and really give this challenge
everything you've got. I'll see you back here once you're done.
[inaudible]
All right. So how did you get on? As I mentioned,
this is a really difficult challenge. If you haven't managed to solve it,
then try to come back to it a little bit later on and spend more time on it.
This is a decisive moment. Don't give up on yourself. Keep going.
I'm always going to be here for you with the solution.
You're not going to get stuck. It's really,
really important to try and solve it yourself. Now,
the first thing I mentioned is turning this rule for determining whether if a
year is a leap year or not into a flow chart.
So I've created one which I linked to in the challenge
and it's very simple.
We start off by asking ourself is a particular year that we have in mind,
um, let's say the year 2000, is it cleanly divisible by four?
Which means can you divide it by four with zero remainder?
Well, if the case is no, then it already is definitely not a leap year.
But if the case is yes, then we have to ask ourselves some more questions.
Namely, can we divide it by a hundred with no remainder?
Well, if we can't, then it's definitely a leap year, but if we can,
then we have to check yet again. Can we divide it by 400 with no remainder?
If the answer is yes, then it's a leap year. If the answer is no,
then it's not a leap year. Let's try and code that logic out,
keep your flow chart up somewhere so that you can write your code while
referring to the diagram.
We start off by checking whether if the year that came in through the input is
divisible by four with no remainder.
And you might remember from our previous code exercise
that the way we do this is using the modulo. So year
modulo four will give us the remainder.
So if the remainder is equal to zero, well in that case it's cleanly
divisible by four. And you can check this out yourself in the console.
Let's say,
if you have 8 % 4, 4 goes into 8 cleanly,
there's two four's in an eight. The remainder is zero.
Whereas 9 % 4, 4 + 4 is 8 remainder 1.
So if the remainder from the year divided by four is equal to zero,
then it is cleanly divisible by four. So in this case,
we'll have to go into yet another if statement.
But if it's actually false, then it's definitely not a leap year.
So the else statement that matches this
if statement is going to tell us for sure that this is not a leap year.
But if it is true, then we have to check the next thing. Is it cleanly
divisible by a hundred?
So we check if the year % 100 is equal to zero.
And if the answer is yes,
then we have to check that year against another question. But if it's no,
then it's definitely a leap year. In this case that will lead to an if statement
if it's true, but if it's false,
then we can simply print leap year because that's what it's going to be.
The final question that we have to ask ourselves about the year is,
is it cleanly divisible by 400?
So now if year % 400 is equal to zero,
well, in this case, if it is true,
then it's definitely a leap year.
If it's false, then it's definitely not a leap year. So, you can print
lear year if it's true, otherwise or if it's false,
then we can print not leap year.
And that's it.
That's all the code that you would need in order to represent this logic.
Now there's plenty of other ways you could have written your code,
but this is probably the most readable. Now,
if you've written some different code
but it still uses these rules to work out
whether if a given year is a leap year and it's correct,
then that's fine as well.
There's plenty of ways that you can solve this challenge.
The most important thing I want you to take away from this code exercise is that
you can turn any sort of logic into a flowchart to be able to visualize it.
And once you've got your logic straight,
then converting it into code is much, much simpler.
If you haven't figured out the logic and then you try to start writing code,
then it's going to be a mess.
So first, get to the stage of being able to create your own flowcharts and then
take those flow charts and turn them into code.
If you got stuck on this challenge
or if you didn't manage to complete it for some reason,
head back to it now and give it some extra attention, because this is really,
really important. It's in these moments, these code challenges,
where you are actually going to a level up as a programmer.
It's not during the tutorials,
it's not during the videos where I explain things to you.
It's where you actually write the code yourself.
I hope you had fun on this code challenge and you managed to complete it,
be it with hints or without hints. On the next lesson, we're going to take the
if statement one step further and I want to show you how you can have multiple
if statements and tests for multiple conditions.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now in the last lesson,
we saw how we could use if, elif, else to check for multiple conditions.
But in this case we're only checking one condition even though we have multiple,
because if this first condition is true,
then we would do whatever it is we need to do and then we would bypass
everything else.
Now what if you were in a situation where you need to check for multiple
conditions even if the previous one was already true?
Coming back to our rollercoaster ticketing problem,
if you're going on a good rollercoaster ride,
you'd probably want to keep a picture for the memories, right?
And our rollercoaster is no exception.
We want to be able to charge users an extra $3 if they want to purchase a ticket
that includes a photo. Now,
this is quite interesting because this is completely independent of their age or
their height.
Even if we've already gotten their age and height and determined their ticket
price, this is an extra question. Do you want a photo or not?
Yes or no. If you do,
then we're going to add $3 to your existing ticket price.
To do this, we would write multiple if conditions.
If condition 1 is true, then do a,
but then the code is going to go to the next case and check if condition 2 is
also true,
in which case it will do B and if the final condition is also true,
it's going to do C. Whereas on the example on the left
here, only one of these things, A, B, or C will be carried out.
Comparing the example on the left where we're using
if, elif, else, only one of these things A,
B or C will be carried out. But on the right hand side,
all three conditions are checked and if it's so happens that all three
conditions are true, then A,
B and C will all be executed.
Currently, our code operates like this. We check for their height.
If they're over 120 centimeters,
we check their age and depending on their age,
we give them a different price ticket.
What we now want is even after we've checked for their ticket price,
we want to ask them a question, do you want photos with your ticket?
And if the answer is yes, then we're going to add $3 to that bill,
no matter which type of ticket they've got.
And finally we give them the total bill. If they say no,
then we jump straight to the total bill and just tell them the price of their
ticket. So how do we implement this in our code?
Well, first let's change these print statements.
Instead of giving them the bill at each of these steps,
I'm going to tell them which type of ticket they're eligible for.
So the next thing to do is to ask them whether if they want a photo or not.
So I'm going to need to use an input, but the question is where do I put that?
Now the correct answer is that it has to be at the same indentation level as
this if block. So you can imagine this whole thing with the,
if elif and else as sort of belonging together.
Because they all relate to one thing:
what is their age and which type of ticket are they eligible for. Now,
outside of that if statement,
I'm going to create an input and ask the user,
do you want a photo taken? Type Y for yes or N for no.
And then I'm going to save their input inside a variable called wants_photo.
So now I'm going to use an if statement to check what their answer was.
If it was true, then I'm going to add $3 and if it was false,
I'm just going to skip to giving them their ticket price.
So here is where I write my if statement.
Notice how it's at the same indentation level as this previous set of if
statements.
But it's not at the same indentation level as this set of if statement.
So essentially what's happening is once I've checked their age,
then I'm going to check whether if they want a photo or not.
And this is going to apply to everybody no matter their age.
So if wants_photo is equal to Y,
well in this case I'm going to go and add $3 to their bill.
But how can I add $3 the bill when I don't have a variable to vary?
So instead of using these print statements,
I'm going to create a variable up here called bill and
I'm going to set it to equal zero.
Now in addition to printing to the user how much their ticket is,
I'm going to set the bill to the price that they're supposed to pay.
So if age is less than 12 bill is equal to $5, if age is less than 18 then bill
is equal to $7, and finally for everybody else,
the bill is equal to $12. So now depending on these conditions,
the variable bill is going to be changed to a different number.
But once we land in this if statement,
I'm going to have to add $3 to their bill
no matter which value it is at the moment.
So effectively, what I want to do is bill equals the current value of bill plus
$3. So if bill was $7,
then this new value bill should be $10. If bill was $12 then it should now be $15.
Now in Python as well as many other languages, there's actually a slightly shorter way
of writing this.
When you want to increase the current value that's held in a variable and you
wanna save it back into the variable,
you can simply write plus equals.
So bill += 3 is the same as bill = bill + 3.
Now, no matter what the value of bill is before it reached this if statement,
I'm still going to add $3 to it. Now after this
if statement is completed,
I don't actually have to write a companion else statement because in this case,
if the answer is no, then we're simply going to do nothing.
We're not going to do anything to the bill. Instead,
I'm just going to skip ahead and print to the user their final bill.
And I'm going to use fstrings to insert the value that the bill variable has
into this print statement. Now for your code to work,
the indentation matters a huge deal because the computer will think you want
it to do different things depending on the indentation.
So notice how this indentation shows that this bill plus three is to be executed
when this condition is true,
but this print statement is not indented to the same level and effectively it's
going to happen after this if statement has been executed.
So you can play around with indenting this print statements, un-indenting it
and see what the difference is.
But now I'm going to go ahead and hit command
+ enter or control + enter on Windows to run my code and I'm going to go ahead and
try and get a ticket.
So let's say that I am 21 years old,
tells me the adult tickets at $12 and then it asked me,
do you want a photo taken? So yeah, I would love to have a photo taken.
And it tells me that my final bill is 15,
so I forgot a dollar sign here.
But effectively it's now added the $3 to the $12 because of this additional if
statement. So if this concept is still a little bit confusing to you,
then I want you to really study this flow chart and just look at the difference,
um, and visualize it because the,
if elif else statement is only ever going to be true in one of these arrows,
right? You can't be less than 12 and 18 and over.
And similarly,
it doesn't make sense for you to have two different ticket prices.
But with the want photos,
this condition has to be asked no matter whichever branch they landed on.
So it's a completely separate from this if statement.
And once you've had a look at this flow chart,
then compare it against the code and the way that the code works should be a lot
more obvious. And once you're happy with the code and this concept,
then I want you to head over to the next lesson where I've got a code challenge
for you. So for all of that, and more, I'll see you there.
All right, guys, are you ready for another challenge? In this challenge,
you are going to be building a Pizza Order program.
So we're going to ask the user what size pizza they want, small, medium,
or large, whether if they want to add pepperoni to it and whether
if they want extra cheese.
So based on the user's input for each of these variables, and the inputs going to
come in the form of a single capital letter, S, M, or L, Y or N.
Based on their input,
we're going to try and figure out what the final bill is going to come to.
And you can take a look at the prices over here.
So, if you want to add pepperoni for a small pizza, it's a $2, medium,
or large pizza is $3, and an extra cheese is $1 for any size.
So you're going to use what you've learned about multiple if statements,
as well as everything from previously in order to be able to create this so that
if the user types in, for example, this input,
large, pepperoni with no extra cheese, then it should print out
Your final bill is $28. Have a look at the examples and the hints
and go ahead and solve this coding challenge.
All right,
so this one shouldn't be too hard and we're going to start off by creating our
first if statement where we're going to check out what is the size of the pizza
that they chose so we can assign the price to that pizza.
If the size is equal to S, that means they ordered a small pizza,
well in this case, the price should be $15, right? Now,
we're going to create a variable up here before the if statement so that we can
keep track of the bill.
So size S, the bill is going to be increased by $15.
Now you can, of course, simply just set the bill to $15 in this case,
but because we've got a lot of things that can change the bill,
it's easier to simply just add 15 to what it is currently using the plus equal
sign that you learned about.
Then we're going to check with an elif. Elif
the size is equal to M, so if they chose a medium pizza instead,
then the bill is going to increase by $20 instead.
And finally, for all other cases, namely,
if they'd got a large size pizza,
then we're going to increase the bill by, um,
$25. Now,
notice how here you could have also used an elif and said elif size equal
to L, um, well, in that case,
the bill increases by $25 and you don't actually need an else statement.
It's not required.
If you feel like it's easier to read like this, small,
medium, large, and what should happen for each case,
then you can just leave it like this. But of course,
there is an argument to be made that the user might have typed something wrong,
right? They might've typed a lowercase letter,
they might've typed a completely different letter. So in future lessons,
we're going to show you how you can catch these cases and how you can deal with
it. But for now, let's just keep our program as simple as possible.
If they type the wrong letter, instead of S, M, or L,
then we're just going to overcharge them.
So now that we've established what the basic price for their pizza is,
we're going to look through the ad-ons.
We're going to see if they said they wanted to add pepperoni.
So if add pepperoni is equal to Y, well,
in that case,
we're going to need to check if they have a small pizza or a medium,
or large pizza, 'cause the price is different.
So we're going to have a nested, if function in here.
We're going to say if add pepperoni is equal to Y,
and then if the size is equal to S, well,
in this case, we're only going to add, um, $2 to the bill.
But if the size was any other size, basically medium or large,
so we can catch that using just an L statement
instead of creating three separate, if sizes S, if sizes M, et cetera.
And in this case, we're going to add $3 to the bill.
So now we've got this case covered.
The final thing is whether if they said they wanted extra cheese or not.
So if they did, in fact, want extra cheese,
well,
in that case, all we have to do is just add $1 to the bill.
So these are three separate sets of if statements;
this one, this one, and this one.
And by the end of all of these if statements,
as long as we're at the right indentation level
namely right next to the gutter here,
then we can go ahead and calculate their bill and print it out for them.
So we can say print,
and I'm going to use an f-string to insert the bill in here, print
Your final bill is,
and then I'm going to add a dollar sign, and then inside the curly braces,
I'm going to put it in the current value of the bill after all of these
calculations. So did you manage to get it right?
Did you manage to use a combination of if statements and elif statements,
um, nested if statements, or did you do it in a different way?
And it's totally cool if you did. As long as it does what it's supposed to do,
then it doesn't really matter whichever format of your code
you decide to go for it. And as a matter of fact,
there's loads of ways that you could have written this code to get this
functionality. Some of them will be slightly more readable,
some of them will be slightly less readable.
So, it's a case of you making a good judgment on that and choosing the code that
makes the most sense to you. Now in the next lesson,
I want to talk a little bit about combining different conditions so that we can
use something called a logical operator to check for multiple conditions in the
same line of code. So, for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson,
Now up to this point, you've seen us use if statements,
else statements, elif statements,
multiple if statements as well as nested if statements.
But the thing that we haven't been able to do thus far is to check for multiple
conditions in the same line of code.
So how would we be able to combine different conditions and say, well,
is the pizza large and the user wants pepperoni and extra cheese all in the
same line of code? Well,
to do this we would need to learn about the logical operators.
So there's three of them that are really useful: and, or and not.
So let's take a look at the first one.
When you combine two different conditions using an and operator,
they both have to be true,
both A and B for the entire line of code to be true.
If just one of them is true, say A is true and B is false,
or A is false and B is true, then the overall thing evaluates to false.
So if we take a look just inside the console,
and in fact, I'm going to clear the console, and I write some code here.
Let's say that, um,
A = 12 right? Now let's say that I wanted to check whether if is A greater
than 15? Well that is going to be false.
Now what about is A greater than 10? Well,
that's going to be true.
Now if I combined this using an and statement, I could say,
well is A greater than 10 and A is less than 13 and hit enter, then I would get
true because both A is greater than 10 and A is less than 13 are true.
So in this case, when both conditions are true,
then this entire line gets evaluated to true.
But see what happens when just one of them is false.
So is A greater than 15 and A less than 13? A is greater than 15 is false,
A is less than 13 is true and now we get false.
So that's what happens when you combine different conditions using and. Now if
you only needed one of the conditions to be true,
then you could use the or operator instead.
So if a C or D were true or if they're both true,
then it'll evaluate to true.
It's only when both C and D are false
does this statement actually become false.
Now the final one is the not operator and all that this does is it basically
reverses a condition. So if the condition is false,
then it becomes true. If it's true, then it becomes false.
If I wrote not
and then I wrote the condition A is greater than 15. A greater than 15 is
definitely false, 12 is less than 15. But by putting the not there
it's going to reverse this, so going from false to true.
So when I hit enter, you'll see it is now true.
Coming back to our rollercoaster ticketing,
let's say that the rollercoaster company decided that for everybody who was
having a midlife crisis, they would give them free tickets.
And according to Wikipedia,
midlife crises typically occur when you're a 45 to 55 years old.
Let's see if we can incorporate this into our code.
So let's say that in addition to these existing price categories,
what if you had to add a separate price category for those people who are aged
between 45 and 55 and those people get to ride for free?
Do you think you would be able to change the code using what you've learned
about logical operators in order to incorporate this addition to our program?
Pause the video and give that a go.
So we've currently got three conditions: age,
less than 12, age between 12 and 18, and finally everybody else.
Now instead of just finishing up there,
let's go ahead and add another elif.
And here we're going to combine two conditions.
We're going to say if the age is greater than or equal to 45 and the age is less
than or equal to 55, then we get to catch that midlife crisis window.
Well,
in this case, we're going to print something like-- we're going to say "Everything's
going to be ok. Have a free ride on us!"
And in fact,
we don't need to modify the bill in any way because we know that with
if, elif and else statements is that once this condition matches,
then everything that's inside this block,
so everything that's indented inside this elif is going to be carried out
namely printing this out,
and then it's going to skip the rest of this if/else block and continue on.
Now, if they want to photo this,
they'll have to pay $3 but at least their ticket is free.
And we've been able to do this because we know about the and logical operator.
In the next lesson,
we're going to practice using logical operators and more by completing another
code challenge. So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
All right guys, it's time to show what you're made of.
Here's another code challenge. And this one is again,
another difficult challenge and the arms really show you just how difficult it
is, but you're going to flex and you're going to get stronger.
And it's only through struggle that you're going to become a better coder.
So in this code exercise, we're going to build a love calculator.
And the way that it's going to work is the same method that I used when I was
10, pretty much.
And I really recommend reading up on this particular Buzzfeed article,
which is of course, very reputable
and it's going to tell you exactly how this program is going to work.
So once you've managed to scroll past all the GIFs, it will tell you, um,
the method. So you write your name, his or her name,
and then the words true and love. Now,
then you are going to count the number of times T-R-U-E occur in both of
your names. And then you're going to count the number of times,
L-O-V-E occur in both of your names. Once you've got those numbers,
so here T-R-U-E adds up to six, L-O-V-E adds up to three.
Then you'll get the percentage that you are compatible with this other person.
So not only did you get to learn Programming on this course,
you also get the discover your destiny.
The idea is that we're going to convert this very time-consuming process into a
computer program. So once you've understood how it works,
you're going to write the code for it. Now,
in order to be able to calculate the love score,
there's two important things that you should read in the hint.
One is you will need to use the lower function, and all that this does is it
takes a string, let's say we've got the string Angela.
And notice how that first letter is a capital A.
If I write .lower parentheses,
then it will reduce all of the capital letters to lowercase letters.
And if you were wondering how you would've known to use this,
then you can head over to the Stack of flow question
in which somebody asks exactly this question, how do you turn something
that's uppercase into a lowercase character in Python.
The second function you'll need is the count function.
And this will give you the number of times a letter occurs in a string,
which is super useful when it comes to this particular challenge. So again,
let's use our string, Angela, and then I'm going to write count.
And then in between the parentheses,
I'm going to specify what it is that I want to count.
So let's say I want to count the character A inside this string,
and I hit enter. It comes up with one,
even though you can see there's actually two A's in the string, in my name,
it only counts one lowercase a. So that's why this first step was super,
super useful.
So let's say lower_case_name equals, um,
Angela.lower. And then,
um,
let's go ahead and do lower_case_name.count,
and then we're going to count for a again. Now you'll see it gives us two,
because we were able to convert everything to lowercase,
and then use the count function to check the number of times the character a
occurs in this string. And again, I've linked to a Stack Overflow question
which is how you might've found out to use this count function and how you might
use it in terms of code examples. Now,
there's a second step to this challenge
because not only do we want to know the love score,
we also want to give the user an interpretation.
So the interpretation is here. For love scores that are less than 10 or greater
than 90, the message is going to say "Your score is X." And of course,
replace that X with the actual score. You go together like Coke and Mentos.
Now, if their love score was between 40 and 50,
the message is going to read your score is, whatever it may be,
you are all right together. And finally,
for all other scores, the message is just going to give them their score.
Your score is XYZ. In this case, there's two inputs,
somebody's name, and then somebody else's name.
And then you're going to check for the number of times T-R-U-E occurs in
both of those names, L-O-V-E occurs in those names,
then you going to combine these digits together to get a love score.
Pause the video now, have a look at everything that's in the instructions,
read it all and then go ahead and give that a go.
[inaudible]
All right. So the first step is to work out the love score, right?
So we need to figure out how many times each of these letters occur in these
names.
The first thing that we need to do is to combine the names,
because we're looking for the number of times,
let's say a T occurs in these names and we're treating them as one string,
right? So I don't wanna check it separately and then have to add it together.
So let's call it a combined_string and lets set that to equal name1 + name2.
And this is just going to concatenate those two strings together
so we'll be able to check them only once. It makes it more efficient,
right? The next step is to guard against cases
where the user is inputting their name like this, which many people do,
or they might even write it like this.
So we have to turn everything into lowercase.
So let's call it a lower_case_string
and that will be combined_string. lower just as I demoed previously using
this lower function. So now we've got everything in lower case,
we're going to start checking for this first word,
T-R-U-E. So let's first check
how many times the letter T occurs in this lowercase string of both people's
names.
So we can say lower_case_string.count
and then inside the parentheses, we specify the string we're looking for
which is 't' and then I'm going to save this to a variable
which I'll just call 't' again. And then we're going to repeat this several times,
hopefully for practice sake, you'll type it all out. But in my case,
I'm just going to copy and paste it, which is usually error-prone,
but we'll try to be careful.
So now that we've got the number of times 't' occurs, 'r'
occurs, 'u' and 'e' occurs, we can now add it all up.
So let's say true = t + r + u + e.
So now we've got the first digit of our love score and we have to go ahead and
do the same thing for L-O-V-E. So again, for time sake,
I'm just going to copy that and then go ahead and change this to l,
o, v, e and l, o, v, e.
And then I'm going to go ahead and calculate the total for that
which is going to be l + o + v + e.
And now I've got both of these numbers and I'm going to try and concatenate them
together to achieve this two-digit number.
To do that, I'm going to create a love score variable
that's going to keep hold of this.
And then I'm going to say true + love.
And remember that at this stage, both true and love are actually integers.
That's how we were able to add them together.
So if I want to turn them into a string in order to be able to concatenate them
together, I have to convert them to strings.
The final thing we have to do is just to go ahead and print this love score.
So we're not going to print anything else for now.
Let's just go ahead and test it out. So let's run our code
and let's type my name and then
their name, Jack Bauer, of course. And then it gives us the score.
So five, three.
So that means everything so far has pretty much worked.
So now all we have to do is use our knowledge of if statements to give a
corresponding interpretation or a message.
If the score is less than 10 or greater than 90,
so if love_score is less than 10 or love_score is greater than 90,
so we're using that logical or operator here to check if either this condition
or this condition is true. And if you find it helpful,
which I usually do,
it's easy to wrap these conditions in their own set of parentheses.
Now, Python doesn't actually care. Either method works.
But for us humans, this is a little bit more readable.
So under this condition,
what we're going to print out is
Your love score is,
and then we'll insert the love_score variable here,
and we're going to of course be using f-strings, so let's add that.
And then we're going to write you go together like Coke and Mentos.
So that's our first condition done. Now,
the next condition is what if their love score is between 40 and 50.
So let's go ahead and add an elif here.
Elif
the love_score is greater than or equal to 40
and the love_score is less than or equal to 50,
so that catches the cases where the love score is between 40 and 50.
So both of these conditions must be true for this statement to fire.
And in this case,
what we want to do is we want to print out this sentence.
So your score is,
let's just insert the love_score in here.
[inaudible]
Your score is this particular love score. You are alright together.
Now the final thing we said is if it doesn't match any of these conditions,
then the message is just going to be their score.
So that means we can catch everything else using an else statement
and we can simply just print "Your score
is this particular number."
Now at this stage, you might think you're done, but if you actually run it,
you're going to get an error. So let's go ahead and test it with the same names
as before.
You can see that we get a type error on line 27,
and it says that the comparison less than is not supported between instances
of string and int.
So the problem here is that in order to concatenate these two numbers,
we had to turn them into strings.
So that let's say that this number was equal to five and this number was equal
to six. Then instead of getting 11, which is not what we want,
we actually get 56 'cause they're both strings and these strings get concatenated
together.
But the problem occurs on the next step because we wanna compare the love score
against an actual number, then if it's a string,
it's not going to work. So in order to solve this,
then we actually have to convert the love score into an integer.
So you could use a separate step.
So the int_score equals int
and then we wrap it around the love score. Alternatively, um,
and a lot easier is to simply just wrap that whole line inside a set of brackets
and convert the whole thing into an integer on the same line.
It depends on how comfortable you are with this code as to which option you'll
choose. Now that we're done here,
let's go ahead and run our code again and let's just check it out.
Your score is 42. You are all right together.
So now our code seems to be working and we've now completed this code challenge.
How did you get on with this challenge?
Did you manage to get everything right?
Did you get stuck at certain places?
Have a think about which parts of this challenge were the hardest and see if you
can review some of those concepts so that the next time you encounter them,
you'll be able to tackle them with confidence.
Hey, you've reached the final project.
And as you've seen at the beginning of today's lessons, I showed you what we're going to be making,
which is a sort of choose your own adventure game.
I don't know if you've ever read those.
Choose your own adventure books where you flip to a different page if you make a particular choice.
And then the story kind of evolves as you make your choices.
Now we're going to make a very simple version of that using what we've learned about conditionals.
If else, Elif statements as well as everything we've done previously.
So you've already seen what the final outcome should look like.
And if you want to review it again, just head over to Treasure Island Dash and Run.
And here you'll see essentially the game in action.
So it starts off asking you, you're at a crossroad.
Do you want to go left or right?
And then you have to type your choice.
If you selected left, then it's going to take you to a lake and it asks you whether if you want to
wait for a boat or swim across.
So let's go ahead and wait for a boat.
And then the final step is it asks you which door would you like to go through?
Red, yellow or blue.
Now, depending on your choice, you'll either end up with game over or you'll end up with winning the
game.
So the basic setup for this game looks something like this, and I've included a link to this flowchart
in the starting rappel.
So Rappler slash Abra slash Treasure Island start.
And of course, you'll find all the links in the course resources as always.
But if you scroll down, there's a link right here that takes you to this flowchart.
Now, the first question you're going to ask the user is to make a choice between left and right.
Now, you can use my wording if you want.
You're at a crossroad.
Where do you want to go?
Type left or type right.
But I think the fun part of this challenge is really creating your own story, right?
But somehow get them to choose between left and right.
If they choose right or any other condition for that matter, tell them that they've lost game over
for some sort of reason.
In my case, if they had chosen right, the reason is because they fell into a whole game over.
But I think you're far more imaginative than I am, so go ahead and use all of those skills and make
your game really fun.
Now, if they've chosen left, on the other hand, then we're going to take them to another question
that asks them whether if they want to swim or whether if they want to wait for a boat and if they swam,
then it's going to be some form of game over.
There's crocodiles, there's whatever it may be, but they can't continue.
But if they chose wait, then we take them to the third and final question, which asks them to choose
between three doors and if they choose any door other than the yellow door, then they would lose.
But if they chose the yellow door, then they somehow win.
Now notice how each of these just says game over, game over, left or right.
But, you know, the idea is really to use your creativity and make this game really your own.
Now, one thing to remember, though, is that when the user types in a answer, let's say left or right,
they might type it like this with an uppercase R, or they might type it like this all lowercase.
Have a think about how you might make sure that no matter which version they typed, you're still going
to be able to catch their command, essentially.
So have a think about what you've learned in the previous lessons and take a look at this flowchart.
Then head over to the starting project and you can get started writing your code.
Now, if you had over here and what you see is sort of like a mumbo jumbo bunch of characters, then
the reason is probably because there's not enough space for this ASCII art of a treasure chest to display.
So you can either do as I did, reduce the size of the console, or alternatively and probably easier
is to change the layout to stacked, make it go at the bottom.
Collapse this left hand pane and then you've got as much space as you have to work with.
Now ask zero is really cool because it basically just uses a bunch of characters that you know and love,
like the comma and the equal sign and all of these things that together make up a picture.
And you can find your own Asgard.
If you just go to ASCO, UK slash art and you'll see a whole bunch of different topics.
And they've grouped a lot of things together into individual pages.
So if you wanted a rhino ASCII art, then you can find a whole bunch of rhinos that people have drawn.
But the easiest way is of course using command F if you're on a mac or control F if you're on a Windows
machine, and then just search for the thing that you want.
So for example, I went and searched for treasure, and down here I found this brilliant treasure box
ASCII art, which is what I'm using to print inside this print statement.
Now notice how there's three single quotes that are at the start, and there's three single quotes at
the end.
Basically, what the single quotes allow you to do is to create multiple lines of a string, essentially.
So notice how if I go ahead and delete all of these single quotes and I only had a set of double quotes,
then it actually doesn't quite work.
It gets quite confused because it thinks that this is where the line ends.
But in fact, I wanted to print all of this out.
So to do that, instead of using a double quote, I use three single quotes and at the very bottom I
tell it, Well, this is the end of my multi block string by using three single quotes as well.
So have a go at running that and you should be able to see that in your console.
You get this little Treasure Island ASCII art being printed along with the two sentences that begin
the game.
So have a look at the flow chart.
Have a play around with the ASCII art and also have a look at the final version of the app so that you
can go ahead and create your own version to complete this challenge.
Pause the video now and give that a go.
All right.
So let's see if we can replicate the functionality or the logic that's shown in this diagram into our
Treasure Island game.
So the first thing it has to do is we have to ask the user whether if they want to turn left or right.
And after we ask the user this question, we're going to want to capture the input.
Right?
So let's go ahead and create an input function and ask our question.
Now notice how when I use my double quotes around my string, the double quotes that are inside the
double quotes are interpreted as code because it actually thinks that this is the end of the first string.
This is the second string and this is the final string.
This is how the computer is going to see it.
Now, previously you saw that we could do the trick where we change this to single quotes instead.
But if, like me, you have this case where you have the yaw with the apostrophe, then it's going to
think that this is actually the end of the first string.
This is the second string and this is the third string.
So this doesn't actually really help us.
Now, what we can do when we want to tell our computer that what I'm writing is actually not code,
just see it as text.
You can get it to ignore a symbol afterwards by using the backslash.
So this way it basically escapes the string and it will see it as text.
And now we have a complete string like this.
And this is just going to be interpreted as a text because we told it to with the backslash.
Now, of course, there's other ways that you could have gone around this.
You could have just simply said you are at at a crossroad rather than using the apostrophe.
But more often than not, you'll need to use a symbol that you'll need to escape.
And you can do that with the backslash.
So that's just a quick tip.
Now, at this point, the user is going to type a message left or right.
So let's go ahead and save that to a variable.
Let's call it choice.
One equals their input.
Now, remember how I said they could be typing the answer as right or as right?
So how can we make sure that when we're doing our checks using the if statement, we ignore the casing?
Well, one way of doing this is we can simply use the lower function to change their input no matter
how they wrote it.
Right, Right or right, it should all be converted into lowercase to this version.
That way we have one thing that we can consistently check for in our IF statement, which is coming
up next.
So we can say if choice one.
Is equal to.
Remember the double equals is checking whether if left hand side and right hand side is equal and the
single equal sign is assigning the right hand side to this particular variable name.
Now, if choice one equals the string, right, then it's pretty much game over for player.
So let's go ahead and add our colon and print something like Game Over.
Of course, we can elaborate this a little bit more as to why was it game over?
Well, because you fell into a hole.
This is like the game from the eighties.
Lots of holes.
Um, so you fell into a whole game over.
But what if they had chosen left instead?
Well, that takes them on to the next question.
So that's the option that will allow them to continue along the game.
Now, in this case, we could use an L statement and say, Well, if they didn't choose right, then
they probably chose left right.
But they could have also chosen like a option that was completely not listed.
They could have just written something like this and it would still trigger the L statement.
So what we should actually do is to switch it around.
So namely, we should say if choice one is equal to left, well, in that case, then they continue.
In the game, but otherwise, namely, if they chose right or anything else for that matter, then it's
pretty much game over.
So this format makes a lot more sense if you want to continue along the left side of the branch this
way.
Now, another thing that you might have realized because we learnt about combining different conditions
is instead of using the dot lower to change the input to lowercase, you could have also said if choice
is equal to left or if choice one is equal to left spelt like this, that will both work.
But I think in terms of synchronous and less code writing, I think this makes a lot more sense to me.
So I'm going to continue with this version.
But if you did it the other way, that's perfectly valid as well.
Now, if that choice one was left, then they get taken to the next question.
Do you want to swim or do you want to wait?
So let's go ahead and continue the game and create another input.
In this input, we're going to ask them a question and say, You've come to a lake.
There is an island in the middle of the lake type, wait to wait for a boat type swim to swim across.
Cool.
So we've actually got the same problem as we had before, namely that this is being interpreted as code
rather than as a continuous single string.
So do you remember how we fix this previously?
And if you got stuck on this, I recommend having a go at this yourself before I show you the answer.
All right.
So previously we said we were going to switch it to single quotes instead so that these double quotes
become interpreted as just normal strings.
But of course, we've got this.
You've we could, of course, change it to you have instead of you've.
But if we want to escape the string, we just add a backslash and now everything is coloured in this
sort of pinkish colour to indicate it's all interpreted as a string, which is exactly what we did previously.
Now, in terms of this input, they're going to type weight or they're going to type swim.
So let's go ahead and lower the casing for it as well.
And then we're going to save it inside a choice.
We're going to say choice to now be really careful and mindful of your indentation, because if you
wrote it like this, then it's going to be creating some errors for you because this choice two input
line has to run when this choice one is equal to left.
Otherwise we're going to get an indentation error.
So let's go ahead and indent it here to show that this part is inside this if statement and will only
be executed if this is true.
And then we get to check our choice two.
So if choice two is equal to weight, then it means that the game will continue.
But else.
So if they typed swim or anything else for that matter, then the game is going to end.
So we're going to print and tell them that something terrible happened.
You got attacked by an angry trout.
Game over.
Now we can continue along this path.
So we're down to here now.
And the final question we're going to ask the user is which door do they want to choose?
So here I'm going to use an input to send them the message that you arrive at the island unharmed.
There is a house with three doors, one red, one yellow, one blue.
Which color do you choose?
Now I'm going to save their choice inside a variable called Choice three lowercase, the answer that
they provided.
And finally, I'm going to use if elephant else to check which one they chose.
So if choice three is equal to red, elif, choice three is equal to yellow.
Life.
Choice three is equal to blue.
And then I've got ALS.
So here are four possible things that could happen if they chose red.
Then I'm going to tell them that it's game over, but it's going to be some sort of creative version
of game over.
So maybe something like it's a room full of fire.
Game over.
If they chose yellow, on the other hand, well, that's going to be the room where the treasure exists.
So I'm going to print.
You found the treasure.
You win.
If they chose blue, they also end up with game over.
And I have to give them a different reason.
Now, if you had decided that if they chose anything but yellow, the way that they're going to game
over is the same.
Say, if you if you chose red, it's a room full of fire.
Game over.
If you chose blue, it's a room full of fire.
Anything else.
It's also going to be fire game over.
Well, then you could just use if and else.
But if you wanted each choice or each door to have a different outcome for the user, say the red door
has fire, the blue door has beasts.
And if they chose the wrong door, then they're going to get something like you chose a door that doesn't
exist.
Game over.
So can you see that depending on whether if you want to give the user a different print statement based
on their choice, then you would use if elif else.
But if you actually just wanted to give them the same feedback, which is game over, then you could
just use if and else.
Now let's run our game and just make sure that it works.
So I'm going to go left because I know it continues and then I'm going to wait for the boat and that
allows me to get to the final condition.
And if I choose yellow, I know that I'll win.
Now, if you want to change the formatting, because having the input at the end of the sentence doesn't
look as good as letting the user type it on a new line like what we've got here.
Then you can simply, if you remember, just add the new line, which is backslash n at the end of your
inputs.
Like so.
So how did you get on with this challenge?
And if you didn't manage to do it right or if you've done it right.
Go back and try and modify it.
See if you can add some more conditions or see if you can make the game over messages a little bit more
interesting than what I've written.
See if you can modify and make it really your own.
Have fun with that.
And in the next lesson, I've got more exciting things coming up for you, so hopefully you've schedule
some time for tomorrow to complete the next day's lessons.
But for now, it's Goodnight for me.
Hey guys, welcome back to 100 Days of Code.
Today is day 4,
and we're going to be focusing on randomization in Python,
and we're going to be learning about Python lists.
Now randomization in any sort of programming language is really,
really useful because if we want to create a game,
if we want a program to do something different each time,
then we need to introduce a little bit of randomness, right?
So we're going to be looking at using the random module in order to achieve
this. And by the end of today,
you will have learned enough to be able to build this Rock-paper-scissors game.
So it starts out asking you, the user, type 0 for rock, 1 for paper or 2
for scissors. So I'm going to go forward with 0 for rock.
And it shows me using ASCII art that this is what I chose, rock.
And then the computer chose scissors and rock beats scissors. So I win.
Now you can run this as many times as you want.
If I choose paper and the computer chooses rocks, then I win.
If I choose paper and the computer chooses paper than it is a draw.
But if I choose paper and the computer chooses scissors, then I lose.
So this is a pretty simple game,
but we're going to get the computer to play this game with us.
And we're going to do that by learning about randomization, lists and a whole lot
more. I hope you're ready.
And once you are, then head over to the next lesson, and let's get started.
One of the first things I want to talk about is randomisation.
And this is a concept that we're super familiar with.
Randomization is really,
really important when we want to create computer programs that have a degree of
unpredictability. Now, the biggest category of that is, of course, games right?
Can you imagine if you had to play Tetris and every single time,
the block that fell down was like predictable.
You always knew that it was going to be a T and then it was going to be an L
like, there would be no fun in that right?
So how do we create this randomness for our programs? Now in nature and in our
everyday lives, it's really easy to create randomness.
If you splash some paint on a canvas, that's going to be pretty random.
If you take a look at the TV static from the analog TVs,
that's also a whole bunch of randomness there.
But when we're talking about computers,
then these machines are what we would call deterministic.
They will perform repeatable actions in a fully predictable way.
So how do we wrangle these machines that operate basically on ones and zeros to
get them to create some random numbers? Well,
there's a whole bunch of maths that can be applied to create what are called a
pseudo-random number generators.
And the one that Python uses is something called the Mersenne Twister.
And if you really want to read about it,
then you can have a look on Wikipedia and take a look under the algorithmic
detail. But to be honest, it's a little bit too much information for anybody,
unless you're really interested in these types of number generators.
But what I recommend though,
is a free video from the Khan Academy where they explain pseudorandom number
generators, and it's really well produced.
And it tells you a lot of different aspects of pseudorandom number generation.
Have a look at that
if you're interested to learn a little bit more about pseudorandom number
generators. We've talked a lot about randomness,
but lets see it in action.
Let's write some code and produce some random numbers. Head over to the Day 4
starting Repl and then go ahead and fork your own copy.
We know that we want to get hold of some random numbers,
but we don't really want to implement the Mersenne Twister ourselves because
it's horrendously complicated using lots and lots of math and probably it'll
take us months to write the code for. So how can we get random numbers?
If you think about it, it's a little bit like searching for something in Google.
The Google algorithm is horrendously complicated and it's taken them years and
years to refine and perfect to such an extent where I think Google knows me
better than myself because when I search for something,
it always gives me the most relevant results.
And if you're questioning the complexity of the Google algorithm,
just go to Bing and try searching for something and see how relevant the results
are. So they have the super complex algorithm,
which we're never going to get a chance to see, let alone understand.
And yet every day we're able to search things on Google and use this Google
algorithm to get the things that we want,
like the air speed velocity of a laden swallow.
Now we can do the same thing when we want to generate random numbers. Because
this is such frequently needed functionality,
the Python team have already created a random module.
So if you head over to askpython.com and search for the Python random module,
then you'll be able to see the documentation for this random module.
And you can see that it contains a whole bunch of functions that you can use
that allows you to generate random integers,
so random whole numbers or random floating point numbers.
So let's see how we can tap into this random module. In order to tap into the
random module, we first have to import it.
So we write import random. And now we're able to use this random module in our
main.py code.
We can start using the documentation to generate a random integer. For example,
they show us in the code snippet here that we could generate a random integer by
using the randint function, providing an a and B.
And it will return a random integer between a and b,
including both of those numbers.
And there's even a little bit of code snippet to show us how it's done.
So this line of code generates a random whole number between 100 and 200 and
including those two numbers. So it could be anything between those two numbers.
So let's see if we can implement this in our code.
Let's say that we want to create a random integer and we use the same code that
we saw in the code snippet where we say random,
that's tapping into this module here, .randint.
And then we at a set of parentheses and then we specify the start, and
then the end.
So this is basically a range of numbers that we're specifying, any integer
between 1 and 10.
And now we can go ahead and print our random integer, just like that.
And every single time I run it,
you'll notice that I'll get a different number or maybe sometimes the same,
but it's a random number between the range that I've specified.
Now I've mentioned that the random module is a Python module.
So what exactly is a module? Well,
you've seen that we've mostly been writing our code all on the same page in a
sort of script style, right?
And everything just kind of gets executed from top to bottom.
But sometimes your code will get so long because you're trying to create
something complicated and it's no longer possible to understand what's going on
in such a large piece of code.
What people will do in that case is to split the code up into individual modules
where each module is responsible for a different bit of functionality of your
program. And if you have a complex project with many, many modules,
then you could have collaboration on your project, right?
Lots of people could be working on it, each person working on a different thing.
Say if a factory was building a car,
it wouldn't make sense for one person to build the entire car from wheels,
axles to chassis, that's crazy.
Instead you have different people working on different modules like the tire
module or the chassis module or the engine module.
And then once they put everything together,
you end up with the final car or in our case, the final program.
So we know that the random module is a module that the Python team created to
make it easier for us to generate our random numbers without needing to get into
the complexities of all of the math that's required to generate pseudorandom
numbers.
But how can we create our own modules and how do modules work anyways?
Well, it's actually very simple. If you go ahead and click on the files icon,
you can see, we currently only have one file that we're writing in,
which is main.py,
the Python file. And the main.py is the entry point to our program.
This is the file that will be executed when we run our code. Now,
if I go ahead and click on this icon to add a new file,
let's say I call it my_module.py and I create a new Python file.
And inside my module, I'm going to maybe work on something else.
Let's say I want into the store, the value of PI.
Okay. I think that's all I remember.
So I know the value of PI and I want to be able to use it in my different
programs. Now that I've created my_module.py, well,
now I can use my module wherever I want just by importing it. So I could import
my_module. And now down here, I can say,
let's go ahead and print my_module.pi.
And now if I go ahead and comment out of this code and hit run,
then you'll see,
we get that value of PI that got dragged in because I imported my module,
but now we've got our code separated out into separate modules that are
responsible for different things.
And that is how the random module works as well.
So I'm going to go ahead and delete all of this stuff relating to PI,
but you can keep yours if you want, if you wanna keep it for reference.
Coming back to creating random numbers.
We've seen how we can create random whole numbers,
but what if I wanted to create a random floating point number? Well,
it tells me how to do it in the AskPython documentation.
And all I have to do is use the random module that contains the random function
and it will return a random floating-point number between 0 and 1.
But it's really important to note that in this case it doesn't actually include
1. So it goes up to like 0.9999999, but not including 1.
Let's go ahead and try that out.
So we'll say random_float = random.random
and then I set of parentheses. And this will give me output some sort of number
in the interval between 0 and 1, but not including 1.
So let's go ahead and see if it works.
First,
we print a random integer between 1 and 10 and then we print our random float
between 0 and 1. And every time we run the code,
you'll notice that we get different random numbers.
Now here's a question.
This random function always generates a number between 0 and 1 and it has
many decimal places.
But what if I wanted a random floating-point number between 0 and 5?
How might we do that? Now
it's not as complicated as you think it is and you'll be able to do it just by
looking at the code you've got here.
Have a think about it and see if you can come up with the answer.
I'll go through it with you afterwards. Pause the video now and give that a go.
All right.
So we know that this random float can be anything between
0.000000
to 0.999999..., effectively repeating right? Now
what if we were able to multiply this random number by a number?
Let's say that I multiply the random_float by 5.
Well, what if this random_float was no 0.1? Well,
0.1 times 5 would be 0.5.
But what if the random_float was 0.4? 0.4 times 5 would be 2.
Or what if it was 0.9?
0.9 times five is 4.5.
So effectively by multiplying this random_float by 5,
I will end up with random numbers,
but of course they're now floats, right? So it could be 0.000
... all the way to 4.999999
and et cetera, et cetera.
So this is how we can expand that range from 0 to 1 all the way to 0 to
5, but not including 5.
So what can you do with random numbers? Well,
if we think back to our love calculator that we made in the last lesson,
um, I mean, its kind of based on pseudo-science right?
Like just because you have a certain number of letters that exist in the word
true and love,
it doesn't mean that you're actually going to be more compatible.
I'm sorry to break anyone's heart out there. But if it's random anyways,
then why don't we just use a random number generator saving ourselves all of
that trouble from counting Ts and counting Us.
We can instead just simply say love_score =  random.randint between
1 and 100. And then go ahead and just print "Your love score is",
and then let's insert our love score and turn this into an Fstring.
Let's print that. And you can see that we're getting a different love score
every single time I run this code. It's between 1 and a hundred
and you know,
who can tell that this is any different from the previous method, right?
So we can use our random number generator for this. We can use it for,
um,
creating a dice or flipping a coin or we can use it in games that we create.
If you head over to the next lesson, I've got a code challenge for you
where you are going to be building a program in order to pick from heads or
tails and help the user out when they don't have access to a coin. For all of
that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now, if you head over to the course resources, you'll be able to find a link to this first code exercise.
And the idea is that you're going to create basically a virtual coin-toss program so that when you run
the code, it should give you tails or heads depending on which random number was generated.
Try to use what you've learned in the previous lesson to complete this challenge.
So pause the video now and give that a go.
All right, let's go through the solution together.
So first, make sure you've forked your copy of the exercise so that it's under your own username, and
then we're going to go to main.py where we always write our code.
Now, in order to use the random module, we first have to import it.
So the module is called random.
So we write import random. And now using the random module, we can now tap into randint, which will
generate a random integer between a starting number and a ending number
and it's inclusive of both numbers.
So let's call this the random_side.
And using this random_side, we can use an if statement to check well if the random side that was
generated is equal to one, well, in that case, that means we should print that we generated heads.
So that's the part of the coin which normally shows a person's face.
Now we can use else to catch the situation where we get a zero, and in this case, we'll print tails instead.
So that's all there is to it.
And of course, as always, there are many, many ways that you could solve this challenge.
And if you're creative or if you looked around and you found a different way, then that's great.
But this is how we would do it using what we learned in the previous lesson.
So how did you get on with it? If you got stuck or if you forgot how to do certain things or if some
parts of your code didn't work or if you had errors, then this is the time to go back and fix it so
that you actually understand what's going on and we can proceed.
So once you're done, head over to the next lesson
and we're going to learn about Python lists.
Hey guys. Today I want to talk about something that is really, really important
and you're going to use many, many times in the future,
and this is the concept of the Python list.
And the list is what you would call a data structure.
What does that mean? Well,
it's just a way of organizing and storing data in Python.
Now we've already seen ways of storing single pieces of data,
and that was done through the simple variable where we just said a =
3 or b = hello.
But that's just storing one piece of data, right? Be it a number or a string.
But sometimes you might want to store grouped pieces of data,
data that has some sort of connection with each other. For example,
if you wanted to store all of the names of the States in the US then it doesn't
really make sense to store them all individually because they kind of belong
together, right? They have a relationship to each other.
So it would be nice if you had a variable that was called States_in_the_US and
then you would be able to store all of the names of the States together in one
variable. Now, in other cases,
you might also want to have order in your data. So for example,
if you were storing all of the people in a virtual queue,
then you want to be able to keep hold of the order in which they join the queue.
You don't wanna let the last person somehow skip the queue because you don't
have a good data structure, right?
This is why we need to learn about lists. And lists look pretty simple.
It's just a set of square brackets with many items stored inside.
And those items can be any data type. They can even have mixed data types like
you could store strings together with numbers or a set of booleans.
It doesn't really matter.
But what does matter is the syntax. In Python lists always start with a open
square bracket like this and a closing square bracket like this.
And then in between you have your items separated by a comma.
So pretty simple. In order to store it inside the variable,
then its the same way as we've done before.
The only difference is the right hand side of the equal sign.
This is the list data structure.
If we stored a bunch of fruits, for example,
than it might look something like this: Cherry,
Apple, Pear, separated by a comma inside a set of square brackets.
Let's take a look at this using real code.
Now I'm going to go ahead and comment out the code from our previous lesson on
randomness
and you can do the same if you wanna keep a note of the previous code and use it
as sort of a live textbook where you can comment out of the code or comment it
back in in order to see how it works or you can delete it.
It's totally up to you.
Now let's say that I wanted to store all of the names of the States of US.
Previously, without knowing about this list data structure,
we might've written state1 = Delaware,
state2 = Pennsylvania and so on and so forth.
And we would create as many variables as we have States.
But now that we know about lists,
then we can just create a single variable and we call it states_of_america.
And now we can create a list by creating a set of square brackets and inside
those square brackets, we add our items. So again,
the first item is the state of Delaware,
which is going to be a string and then we've got Pennsylvania,
et cetera, et cetera. And we can continue this list just by adding commas,
adding a piece of data, adding another comma, adding piece of data.
And this way we end up with a list data structure.
Now,
one of the interesting things about the United States is that the different
States in the US actually joined the union at different times.
You can actually head over to Wikipedia and watch this little animation and see
each state join the union and at which time point they did
so. The order of this data is now kind of pretty important because if we wanted
a list of US States that are in the order that they joined the union,
then the order in which they're stored in our data structure is now also
immensely important.
And this is another thing that you get with lists.
You can use a list to store many pieces of related data,
but they also have an order.
And the order is determined by the order in the list.
So this is the first piece of data, this is the second piece of data.
And when you store it inside the variable,
that order is not lost and you'll be able to use it later on when you need the
list.
Here's a list of States of America ordered by the date that they joined the
union. And you can see that if later on,
I decided that I wanted to know which was the state that joined first,
then I can print this variable states_of_america.
I can add a set of square brackets,
and then I type zero as the index of the piece of data
I want to pull out from my states_of_america list.
So now if I go ahead and run this code, you can see it prints out Delaware.
And if I keep increasing this number,
you can see that it's going through my list in the order that it was saved.
So you might be wondering,
that's kind of weird that you typed zero and you got Delaware,
right? Surely, Delaware should be the first item in the list.
Well, this is a kind of peculiarity with computers and programming languages.
You'll tend to find that programmers start counting from zero.
So Delaware is at zero, Pennsylvania is at one and New Jersey is at two.
And this idea, it might seem a little bit weird at first,
why is the first item at position 0?
But if you think about that index number, that 0, 1 or 2,
instead of being the position,
actually being an offset or a shift from the start of the list.
Well then in this case, Cherry is right at the beginning of the list,
so it has a offset or a shift of 0.
But Apple is shifted from the beginning by 1, Pear shifted from the beginning
by 2 and so on and so forth.
Then it kind of makes more sense that the first item in the list is at the
beginning of the list. So it has no offset. So it's 0.
And you'll find that in many, many programming languages,
there are similar data structures to lists
and this is how they're usually ordered starting from 0 and then adding by
1.
Now you can see that when you want to get hold of a particular piece of data
stored inside a list,
what you do is you get the name of the list and then you add another set of
square brackets. So whenever you see square brackets,
you should be thinking to yourself, oh,
this might be related to a list because when you create the list,
you use square brackets. And when you try to get items out of the list,
you also use square brackets.
And then inside of the square brackets is where you put the index or the offset
of the item that you want. So if we wanted New Jersey,
it's offset from the beginning by one two.
So now this part of the code is equal to New Jersey.
And we could,
if we wanted to save it into another variable or we could simply print it as we
did before. Now,
in addition to using the positive index,
so say 0, 1, 2, 3,
you can also use a negative index.
So if I wrote -1 or -2, then it actually starts counting from the
end of the list. So if I wrote states_of_america
[-1] as the index, then I get Hawaii.
-1 is the last item in the list because you can't really have minus zero.
That's not actually a real thing in math. Now,
as I continue and I go to -2,
then that's Alaska, -3 will be Arizona and so on and so forth.
So you can have positive indices and negative indices.
But so far we've only been pulling things out of our list by using our square
brackets and the index.
But you can also change the items in the list using very similar code.
For example,
if I decided that Pennsylvania is actually not spelled Pennsylvania and I wanted
to change it to Pencilvania,
then I can simply write my code like this.
I get hold of my list. And then using the square brackets,
I get hold of the item at index 1, which is this one.
And then I set it equal to a new piece of data.
So now if I go ahead and print my states_of_america list,
you'll see that the list looks a little bit different now.
Instead of Pennsylvania, it's now Pencilvania.
So you can alter any item inside the list
pretty easily using this kind of syntax.
You could also add to the list if you wanted too. So for example,
if you wanted to add an item at the end of the list,
which is what happens most commonly, right?
If you had a list of people who are cuing in your shop,
then every subsequent person usually gets added to the end.
If you have a new state that joined America,
then it's probably going to be added after Hawaii. How do we do that?
Well, we can write the name of the list
and then we use a function called append and append
will add a single item to the end of the list.
So let's say that Angelaland is joining the United States of America.
So now once I've appended Angelaland to the end of my states_of_america list,
and I print the states_of_america, you can see, there it is added at the end.
Now there's actually a whole load of other functions that you can use in
addition to append. And you'll find this on the documentation for Python.
In addition to the append function that we saw just now where we add an item at
the end of the list,
there's a whole load of all the functions that you can use with lists.
For example, you can use the extend,
which adds a whole bunch of items at the end of the list. And in this case,
what you're actually adding is going to be a list.
So I would be creating the list using square brackets and then adding my items
in here.
And now what's happening is I'm extending this states_of_america list with this
additional list. So now if we print the states_of_america,
you can see that these two items that used to be inside of the list have now
been added to the previous list
and it's now extended it by two more items.
But the important thing is you don't have to memorize these functions.
That's the whole point of documentation and why we have Google because there's
too much information in the world for you to memorize.
And it's a very inefficient way of learning.
And if you tried to memorize every single method, it's not impossible,
but it means that you don't have space in your brain for the important stuff,
which is how things work.
How do you actually use it to do what you want it to do?
So what I recommend when you come across a new thing, such as,
um, the list data structure is to just have a look through the documentation,
read through it and see what are the possible things you can do.
And once you've got the idea of this is possible,
then the next time when you need to use it inside your code, you'll know, ah,
I remember this is possible.
And all you have to do is just be able to use Google,
to find the exact bit of the documentation
and then implement it. Programming is kind of like an open book exam.
You shouldn't need to memorize anything.
You should spend your time trying things out and try to get things to work
instead. Now that I've introduced you to this new data structure,
the mighty list,
it's time for a code exercise to see if you can use it in practice.
So head over to the next lesson and give the challenge that go.
So the code challenge that you're about to do comes from a really interesting phenomenon that you might find
in London.
I live in London and it's well known as a big financial district.
So when you head over to the city or the financial area in London and you go into a restaurant, you
might see a strange thing happen.
You might see a whole bunch of people in suits who look very much like the financial banker types. At
the time when they actually need to pay the bill
you see everybody pull out their business cards and put them into a bowl.
So what's actually going on here?
A friend of mine told me apparently there's this game that the rich banker types play where it's kind
of like Russian roulette with the bill.
So everybody puts their business card in and the person's card who gets picked out has to pay for everybody's
bill, which is kind of crazy.
But then again, it's finance.
So in today's challenge, this is what we're going to replicate with code. Head over to the course
resources and click on the coding exercise to bring it up.
Now, go ahead and fork your own copy of it so that you can make amendments.
Now, the idea is that once you've completed the challenge, you should be able to type in a whole bunch
of names as an input with a comma and a space separating each name.
And then the code will pick a random name from the one that you've given it and tell you who is going
to buy the meal.
Now, there's two lines of code here that you might not have seen before.
Now this is something called split, and this allows you to split a string into separate components
based on some sort of divider.
So in this case, notice how it says hello, from, AskPython.
Now, if we use the split on this string, then it will divide it up into a list and separate out all
the words that are divided by this split character, which is the comma.
Now, similarly, over here, when we give the input, it's going to be in the format like this; everybody's
names separated by a comma and a space.
So now if we use the split on a comma and a space, then it will take out the comma and the space and
it will put everything else as separate items inside a list.
So what I recommend doing before you get started writing the actual code is to test it out.
So printout what names actually looks like.
So if we go ahead and run this code and then we type a bunch of names separated by a comma.
so Angela, Ben, Jenny and then hit enter,
then we hit the line where it prints names.
Now names, as you'll see, is now a list with all the names I typed in.
And while previously they were separated by a comma and a space, they are now all individual items
in a list.
The idea is that you've got all of these items inside a list,
how can I pick a random one out of it using a random index based on the number of items in the list
which of course can change?
And then how can I get a random name as the output and then print so-and-so is going to buy the meal
today?
So have a think about it,
have a pause and then see if you can complete the challenge.
So now that we've got the list as a starting point stored inside names, how can we go about generating
a random name and picking it out of the list?
Well, we know that we can pick a item from the list by adding a set of square brackets and then a index
number.
So in this case, it should print the first item out of the list which is going to be just the word
Angela. And I can run this to prove this to you.
You can see that names is a list of all the names, Angela, James, Ben. Names at position zero
is Angela, the first item.
Now, how can we get a random number to replace that number zero?
Well, we could use our random generator.
Let's go ahead and import the random module and we can say random.randint and then we can specify
the start and end.
So the start is probably going to be zero because that's where we start counting with our lists.
But what is the end?
Well, the end should be the position of the last item.
But how can we know that position?
What is that X going to be?
Well, what if we got hold of the number of items in the list?
So do remember how previously we learned about the len function?
Well, the len function can be used to get the number of elements in a list or the number of characters
in a string.
And if you take a look at this Stack Overflow question, then you'll see it in action.
All that we have to do to get hold of the number of items inside this names list is to write len
(), and then inside it we put names.
Now we can either store this or print this. Llet's go ahead and first print with the value of this is
going to be. Let's go ahead and comment out this line of code and then run our code, and then give everybody's
names separated by a comma, hit enter.
And you can see that this line of code has printed three.
So the length of my names list is three.
So now that we've gotten hold of that, then we can probably use that number that comes from this len
function inside our random generator, because we know that we can use this to get the total number
of items in list.
So in this case, that would be one, two, three, four, five.
This last item is not at position five, though, right?
It's at position zero,
one, two, three, four.
So we always need one less than the total number of items.
And the range of random numbers we would want is num_items -1.
Now, this line of code will allow us to generate random numbers between zero and the last index, and
I can store that inside a random choice variable and print my random choice.
So if I run the code again
and it prints one this time,
but the next time, it might be zero or two, because those are all the possible choices for a three
item list. Now we can use that number to actually get hold of a particular item in our list of names.
So we can say names[], and then we're going to use the random choice to get hold of
the random item. And then we can go ahead and save this as the person_who_will_pay.
And we can print
person_who_will_pay + "is going to buy the meal today."
So now let's go ahead and run our code again and then give everybody's names separated by a comma, and
then it says James is going to buy the meal today.
And now we know that we've completed the challenge.
Now, you'll notice that in the instructions, I told you that you're not allowed to use the choice
function.
And the reason for this is because if you search AskPython and you search for the random module
and you scroll down, you'll find that you can actually generate random items from a sequence such as
a list by writing random.choice, and it will actually pick an item from that list.
So let me demo what our code would look like instead. Instead of needing all of these lines of code,
all we have to write is random.choice()
and then we put our names list inside. And now it will do exactly the same as before
but with far less code. But this, of course, doesn't test whether if you've understood how indices
work with lists and whether if you're comfortable with the idea that the last index is actually one
less than the total number of items because we start counting from zero. I've made it a little bit
harder than it needed to be just to see how good a grasp you have on lists.
Now, I hope that you managed to complete this challenge.
If not, don't worry.
Go back to it and see if you can replicate the logic that we talked about just now.
And if you really struggle visualizing what these lines of code are doing, then you can always pass it
through Thonny and use the debugger to step through it one step at a time and see what's happening at
each stage.
Now on the next lesson, we're going to see some more advanced parts of lists in action, namely how
to nest lists inside other lists.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now, when you're working with lists,
one of the most common errors you'll come across is something called the index
out of range error. In fact, by this point,
you might have already seen it. Now, what does it mean though? Well,
let's take all the states_of_america and let's delete the line where we added
Angelaland and Jack Bauer land.
So we go back to the original. And you might remember that there are 50 States in
America. But if you don't because you are a programmer,
it's as easy as writing len and then passing over the states_of_america
which will print 50.
So now that we know that there are a total of 50 items in this list,
and remember, because we start counting from 0,
Hawaii is actually at index 49.
So if we print states_of_america and then we try to get the item at the 49,
we hit print, you'll see that we get Hawaii printed.
Now what if we went one beyond that?
What if we tried to get the one at index 50,
somewhere out here, what do we get instead? Well, we get an error.
It's called an index error. And this is because it's beyond Hawaii and there's
nothing there as we can see with our own eyes.
But when you're working with large lists and you're not always looking at the
data,
then these errors can be a little bit more confusing. Very frequently when you're
working with lists, you'll end up with an off by one error.
So it's unusual that you'll try to get something at index number 90 because
that's just way beyond your list size.
But very frequently you might end up in a situation where you have some sort of
value saying num_of_states = len
and then we pass over the states_of_america.
So this is going to be equal to 50.
And then we pass that inside here as the index num of states.
And then we hit run and we get the same error, right? On line 16
where we try to get hold of this index in this list. It's again,
list index out of range.
And this is an off by one error because all we need to do is just simply minus
so that 1 becomes 0 and 50 becomes 49.
And then we get rid of that error.
Now it might be easier if we work with something a little bit simpler.
Recently I was reading online and I came across the so-called Dirty Dozen where
the environmental working group,
a bunch of people, crunch through a whole lot of data, probably using Python.
And they released their Dirty Dozen, a list of the fruits and vegetables that have
most pesticides. And its kind of crazy that they actually washed and peeled all
of these foods and then tested them for pesticides.
And the list looks something like this where strawberries are apparently one of
the worst offenders for pesticides.
So let's create a list of the dirty dozen,
but you'll notice that some of these are fruits like strawberries,
apples, and the other ones are vegetables.
So how can we use our lists to still keep them inside the same sort of
container, the dirty dozen,
but somehow separate them out into fruits and vegetables?
Well, we could just simply create two lists,
fruits and vegetables. But these two lists kind of have a relationship,
right?
That kind of related because they're all on the list of high-pesticide foods.
So how can we have lists within a list? Well, that's,
what's called a nested list. Instead of our original dirty dozen,
we could create a new list called dirty_dozen,
and we set it equal to a list that contains two lists.
It contains fruits and it contains vegetables.
So now what effectively has happened is we've inserted this list inside here and
then we've inserted this list inside here.
So we now have a list that contains two lists.
And if I go ahead and print out this list, you'll be able to see its structure.
And it looks like this.
You'll notice that there's two brackets at the beginning and at the end
and the reason is because this is one list,
this is another list and this is also a list.
So this is yet another way of using lists and showing you the flexibility of
this particular data structure.
It's something that you're going to use a lot when you're writing Python code.
Now that we've talked more about index errors,
how to fix them and also nested lists,
you're ready to go to the next coding challenge.
So head over there and give that a go.
All right guys, it's time for another code challenge.
So head over to day 4.3 treasure map
and take a look at what is happening here
first. Notice how we've created three lists here for you; row1,
row2, row3, and they've got some blank tiles in here,
and these were just created with emojis.
So if you just search for emoji, um,
and you come across the list of emojis,
then you can simply just copy and paste them right into your code like that.
So depending on whether if you own a Windows or Mac,
you will see the emojis display a little bit differently,
but it doesn't really matter what it looks like.
All that we want to do is to create almost kind of like a,
a chess board or a map like this.
So we have three rows and then we create
another list that includes all three rows.
So this map is actually a nested list because row1 is a list, row2 is a
list, et cetera. And it's all put inside a list.
Then we go ahead and print it so that we add a new line in between each row.
And the final outcome looks something like this.
So if we go ahead and just run the code, you'll see that we have almost like a,
a chess board or essentially a three by three square, right?
And the sort of way that we're going to navigate this map is by using some
indices. So we're going to say that this is column one,
two and three, and this is row one, two and three.
Now, if you've ever played chess, or if you played chess with a computer,
you will know that the different moves or the different positions are often mapped
out using letters and numbers. So for example,
if you want it to move to this square then it would be b4, right?
Or if you want it to move to this square then it would be h3. In our  sort
of 3x3 map
the way that we navigate is first by specifying the column,
the horizontal column, and then we specify a number for the row.
So for example,
if I wanted to place my X,
X marks the spot of my treasure at this particular position, then it is one, two,
2 on the horizontal, so column number two, and then one, two,
three, row number three. So I would write that as 23.
And if I wrote 31
then it means I want column three and row one.
So I want you to mark this spot here. So when you run the code,
the idea is that you should be able to specify a location using that two-digit
system, and you should be able to place an X at that location. Now,
in order to do this, it will need you to review what you know about lists,
what you know about using the index to change a particular item in a list
which you saw in previous lessons,
and the added complexity is here
we actually have a nested list. So lists inside lists.
So have a play around with this code and that's the really important word. It's
play, right? There is nothing that could possibly go wrong.
Just try some different lines of code,
try doing some different things and see if it actually prints out the outcome
that you want, where, you know, when you specify a location,
that's the place that gets marked with the capital X.
Pause the video and try to give this challenge a go.
All right. So let's try and solve this.
So notice how at the very bottom of the code, I've got another print statement
which is going to show us the outcome of whatever code it is we write here.
The first thing we probably want to do is get hold of the input position,
right? We know that input always takes in a string.
So even if we typed 23 that's not going to be the number 23,
it's going to be the string with two and three inside the string.
Something that looks like this.
Now we can use what we've learned in previous days and previous lessons to split
that string so that we end up with a horizontal position and a vertical
position. That way we know, well, which column are they interested in
and which row are they interested in. In order to do that,
we tap into this position. And in order to get the horizontal
which we mentioned is the first digit,
then we go ahead and get the zeroth item out of that string.
Remember the string looks like this.
So the zeroth item out of the string is this one.
And then the vertical is going to be the one at position one. Now, of course,
these are still strings as they stand right now.
We've just split up this two-digit string into horizontal and vertical.
So this one, if 23 was the input would be equal to 2,
and this one would be equal to 3.
Now,
once we've gotten hold of the horizontal position and the vertical position,
then we can go ahead and start specifying positions in our list.
So we know that we've got our map, right?
Which is here, this nested list.
And remember that it contains three rows. Now,
if we wanted to get hold of the first row,
then we would write map[0].
If we want to get hold of row2,
then we would write map[1] and map[2] to get row 3.
Now remember that this is the vertical position.
So this is the that we're going to be getting hold of. Or in this example,
it would be the number three, right?
So we could say map passing in the vertical position,
but there's just one problem
and I'll show you if I go ahead and print this map at the position vertical.
Let's put in the example number, which is 23.
And you'll see that the problem is that list indices must be integers,
whole numbers, not a string. Remember that
we said these are still strings. So to convert them into integers,
we use that integer conversion that we've seen before.
So now both the horizontal and vertical are integers,
and we can run this code again and see how it performs.
Let's put 23 in there, and
we ended up with the error that we learned about in the last lesson
which is an index error. So it's out of range. So what's going on here?
Remember that in our example where the number is 23, well
then the horizontal is the first number. So it's going to be 2.
And then the vertical is going to be the second number,
so it's going to be 3.
And then we try to get a hold of that particular row from our map.
Now, if we pass 3 into our map,
then you can clearly see what's going to happen. There's 0, 1, 2,
there is nothing at position three.
There is nothing that has been offset from the beginning by three, right?
So that doesn't exist.
And this is why we get our index out of range error.
So what do we have to do instead? Well,
we have to remove one from it to shift it to row three,
because that's really what we're interested in when we're writing this here, right?
We can do the same by substituting the three with vertical
so it'll work with any number. And now if I run my code again, type
23,
then you can see that I get no more errors and it actually prints out a row that
I've selected, which is row three.
Now you can of course change these just to make it a little bit more clear to
yourself what's actually going on here. Let's type 23 again,
and you can see that this is what's being printed.
Now the next step is once I've gotten hold of row 3,
how can I get the horizontal tile?
So the horizontal tile we're interested in is the second one.
So it's actually this one. So when we write
23, then it's this tile that we're interested in.
So instead of printing out this row 3
which we selected by writing this code,
we can save this as the selected_row. And then inside the selected_row,
we can get to the tile at the horizontal position that was specified.
So we could say selected row at the position of the horizontal - 1.
This works the same way because our numbers that we're entering here,
row one, two, three, or column one, two, three, they don't start from zero.
So we have to shift it down by one in order for it to work.
So, now once we've gotten hold of the selected row using the vertical,
and then the selected tile using the horizontal, well,
now we can actually change it.
And the thing we want to change it to is a capital X.
So now if I go ahead and run my code,
then you can see it works just as the instructions want it to work.
So here's our map. Where do you wanna put the treasure? If I write
23, then it will put the treasure on column number two, row
number three. Now, if I run this code again and I say, well,
now I want to put it in column number one, row number three,
then there it is.
So this is now working for any possible combination that we come up with
as long as we're using the coordinates of our map.
Did you manage to get it right? And did you write the code in a different way,
perhaps? Because there's many, many ways of doing the same thing.
And the easiest thing that I can spot right now is what if we didn't need to
separate this into two lines? Instead of creating a selected row,
we could simply just tag on this at the end,
get a hold of this particular row from the map,
and because this is going to turn into a list,
namely one of these, well,
then we can simply just use another square bracket to specify the column.
And then we set that tile to a capital X.
So depending on which format you find it easier to understand,
you can keep your code either like this or like this.
This is obviously a lot more succinct,
but it depends on whether if this logic actually makes sense to you.
So have a think about what happened here,
and if you didn't manage to complete the exercise, then try to give it another go.
Now in the next lesson,
we're going to tackle our final project of the day.
So once you're prepared and once you're happy that you have understood
everything that we've covered so far,
then head over to the next lesson where we're going to get started building our
rock-paper-scissors game.
All right, guys, so now that we've loaded up all the knowledge that we need into our brains, it's
time to tackle the final project of the day.
And as I showed you in the beginning of the day, it's a Rock Paper Scissors game that we can play
with the computer.
So the game starts out by asking you to type 0 for rock, 1 for paper, or 2 for scissors.
So let's go ahead and type two for scissors, and then it's going to show you a graphic of your choice scissors,
and then the choice the computer made, which is rock. And of course, rock beats scissors
so you lose.
What this game boils down to is some way of randomly making a choice between rock, paper, or scissors
and then comparing that choice that the computer randomly generated against your choice.
And then based on the rules of rock, paper, and scissors, determining whether if you won, you lost or
whether if you had a draw.
While I was looking around, I actually came across the world rock paper scissors association.
And they have the official rules of the state of Rock Paper Scissors.
If you're not familiar with this game, it might be worth checking out this website.
Here are the three shapes of rock, paper, scissors.
And then the rules are that rock wins against scissors, scissors wins against paper, and paper wins
against rock.
Having all of this in mind, head over to replit/@appbrewery/ rock-paper-scissors-start
and go ahead and just fork the starting project.
Now you'll notice that in the starting project, I've already got the ASCII art for rock, paper and scissors
in here and they're each saved to a variable.
So what that means is that you can start out by just having a go at printing out let's say a rock.
And remember that these are variable names.
They're not strings, so they don't need the double quotes around them.
So let's run that.
And you can see what we get printed is the particular ASCII art that I chose in my print statement.
So this is already yours.
But as you'll notice, there's no other logic that I've provided you and you are going to rely on what
you learned in the previous days and most importantly, what you've learned in today's lessons to be
able to complete this challenge.
And it's worth comparing the outcome against the game of Rock Paper Scissors that I'll link to.
There's a couple of things to think about, namely, how are you going to decide who won or who lost?
How are you going to get the computer to choose a random shape, rock, paper, scissors, and how you
actually get this game to work in the same way that is demoed in this final version?
I'm going to go quiet now and I'm going to let you pause the video.
And I want you to spend at least ten or fifteen minutes working on this.
And if you get stuck, just try some things out or maybe watch some of the previous videos in the day
and just try to give it your best
go, and do a lot of struggling.
Hopefully you're going to succeed.
And once you're done, head back over here and I'll go through the solution with you.
So pause the video now.
All right, so we know that we've got all of this ASCII art, but for the moment, I'm just going to
start off by putting down the basic logic of this game.
And it's really helpful for you as well if you start thinking about breaking down the larger problem,
which is making the Rock Paper Scissors game into smaller problems that you can solve, like generating
a random number between one and three.
So we have some sort of proxy for Rock Paper Scissors. And then maybe thinking about putting down
the logic, well, if the computer chose scissors and I chose paper, then I'm going to lose.
Or if the computer chose rock and I chose paper, then I'm going to win.
And putting that down on a flowchart using draw.io or something like that can make this challenge a lot
easier as well.
But without further ado, the first thing I need to do is to produce a user choice.
Now, this is going to be the one that the user chose when they typed in a value.
And in order to get the value from them, I'm going to need to use a input.
And inside the input, I'm going to put the following prompt asking the user, what do you choose?
Type 0 for rock, 1 for paper or 2 for scissors.
Now, once I get hold of this input, hopefully, if the user is following my instructions, they're going
to type some sort of number, either zero or one or two.
Now that I've gotten hold of what the user wants to choose, the next thing to do is figure out what
the computer is going to choose.
So I'm going to make another variable called computer_choice and I'm going to generate a random number.
So to do that, remember, we have to import the random module.
And then we can start using it to generate random whole numbers by using random.randint.
And then the range is going to be between zero and two, because this is what I asked the user to do.
Type 0 for rock, 1 for paper, 2 for scissors.
So the computer is also going to choose between 0, 1 or 2.
Now that I've got the computer_choice, I'm actually going to just print it out for now instead of printing
out the actual shape, I'm just going to print out the number.
So computer chose and then let's go ahead and add a fstring.
And of course, that requires the F in front of the string.
So now if we just play the game as it is, remember that testing up while you're developing it is really,
really good practice.
It picks up on the bugs that you make along the way instead of waiting until the end when you've done
everything
and then it doesn't work and you have to untangle all of the lines of code.
At this point, I've already realized that it's actually not so great getting the user to type on this
line.
What I would much rather is to start a new line for them to type their answer on.
So if I run the code again, then it should look a bit like this.
My prompt is now here. So I'm going to choose 0 for Rock.
And then it tells me that computer also chose zero.
So in this case, this would be a draw.
But if I played this game again, you can see that the computer is probably going to choose something
different.
So I chose rock again
the computer chose 1, which is paper.
So now we can start thinking about how do we compare these two choices and how can we define the logic
of Rock Paper Scissors?
So I know that paper beats rock, scissors beats paper and rock will beat scissors.
So if zero is rock, one is paper and two is scissors, then two beats one and one beats zero.
So that's very simple for us to check in terms of using if statements,
right?
We could simply just check
well, if the computer choice is greater than the user choice, well then this probably means that the
computer wins.
But this is not true in all cases, right? Because if the computer chose 2 for scissors and the user
chose 0 for rock, then the user should win rather than the computer winning.
So we actually have some exceptions to this rule.
How can we catch the exceptions before we go down to this level of generalization?
Well, we could instead of using this as an if, we use this as an elif and we create another if statement
which says, well, if the user_choice is equal to zero, so if the user chose rock and the computer_choice
was 2, well then this means that in this case, the user actually wins.
Now, if we're thinking from the perspective of the user when they're playing this game, then they
don't really care if the computer won or the user won. They want to know, did they win or did they lose?
So let's change this wording a little bit.
We'll say, instead of user wins, we'll say you win.
And if the computer wins, then we'll say you lose.
So now if we run our program and test it out, so let's say I'm going to type 0 for rock and the
computer chooses 2, but we actually get an error.
It tells us that the greater than comparison is not supported between instances of int and string.
What's going on here?
Well, remember that we get our inputs as a number, but the input is always going to be a string.
So if we want this to be a number,
then we're going to have to wrap it inside an int.
So now we turn it into a whole number.
Now, this might be a good point to address
well, what should happen if they typed something that wasn't 0, 1 or 2, whether they typed 34?
Well, then naturally they should probably lose,
right?
So we can add an else statement addressing this situation. So we could say else we just print
You typed an invalid number.
You lose. Cool.
So that sorts that out.
Now let's run our code again and see if it works.
What do you choose?
Type 0 for Rock.
I'm going to choose rock again.
Computer chose zero and it tells me that you typed an invalid number.
Well, actually, zero is not an invalid number.
So what's going on here?
Well, it's because it didn't fit this criteria.
So I had zero,
computer had zero, and it didn't fit this criterion because zero is not greater than zero.
So it basically defaulted to the final else statement.
But what's actually happening here is that that was a draw.
Computer chose rock,
I chose rock.
That's a draw in the official rules of Rock Paper Scissors.
So how do I catch that?
Well, I could create another elif statement which says, well, if the computer_choice is equal to
the user_choice, well, then we're going to print
it's a draw.
Now, let's test our app again and see if there are any other situations where our code is not behaving
properly.
I'm going to choose rock again, computer chose rock as well.
And I guess it's a draw, so that's pretty good.
Now, if I choose 0 and the computer chose 2, then this is going to be the statement that gets
triggered and I win.
So that's pretty good.
Now, what if I chose 2 for scissors and the computer chose 0?
Well, in this case, rock beats scissors
so it should actually say I lose.
But instead it says you typed an invalid number.
So it defaulted to the else statement again because this particular situation is not caught by any of
these statements.
So what do we have to do instead?
Well, we actually need another elif to say, well, if the computer_choice was equal to 0 and
the user_choice was equal to 2, well, this means that rock beats scissors
so I lose and the computer wins.
Now, the final one that we need to catch is this case.
If I type 1 for paper and computer chooses 0 for rock, it again defaults to the else statements
whereas in fact in this case it should tell me that I won.
So what's missing here?
Well, it's the partner to this particular statement.
If computer_choice is greater than user_choice then I lose.
But on the other hand, if the user_choice was greater than the computer_choice, then I actually should
win.
So now the final thing we might have to fix is this else statement now actually never gets called because
this is what happens.
So let's say that I choose 456.
It tells me that computer chose 2, I win.
What's happening here?
Well, it's actually this particular line that's being carried out.
user_choice is greater than computer_choice.
This is not what we want.
We want it to default to
You typed an invalid number.
You lose. So we can actually just use else in this situation.
We actually need to provide a condition.
We're going to use elif to check if the user_choice is greater or equal to three,
now, the computer will never choose anything other than 0, 1 and 2
so we don't have to check that one.
But the user could choose something above 3 or below 0.
So we can use an or statement to catch this. Or if the user_choice is less than zero,
well, in this case, you typed an invalid number, you lose.
But that's not all that we have to do.
If we hit run and we again type some extraordinarily large number, you'll see that it still says
computer chose 1.
You win.
What's going on?
We have this statement that should catch this situation, but it's right at the bottom.
So it's not going to be checked until one of the previous ones are checked.
Namely, it's one of these that's going to be the problem.
So what we have to do is we have to move this statement above all the lines so that we first check if
the user_choice is greater than three or less than zero.
And if that's not true, do we actually continue checking to see who won the game.
Now, finally, we can run our code type an invalid number and get you typed an invalid number. You lose.
So now that we've actually got our logic all sorted out, the next step is to include our images.
And to do that, we have to somehow match it up with these numbers we have,
right? 0, 1 and 2.
Now, there's many, many ways that you could do this and you could solve this project.
But the easiest way is probably putting the game images into a list where we have rock as the first
one, paper as the second one and scissors as the last one.
So we're using the fact that lists have a order that is always going to be followed. So we can now get
hold of the rock picture by getting game_images[0].
We can get scissors by doing game_images[2] and so on and so forth. And we can match those up to our
choices, the user_choice and the computer_choice.
So when the user chooses a number, then we're going to print from the game_images and we're going to
use our little square brackets to select the image we want from this list.
And the one that we want is going to be based on the user's choice, right?
0 for rock, 1 for paper, 2 for scissors.
So we're going to put user_choice as the index to pick out an image from game_images. Now down here for
the computer_choice, instead of printing the number that the computer chose, I'm going to delete that
and add a little colon.
So that way it's going to show computer chose
and then I'm going to print the image of the choice that the computer made.
So I'm going to add another print statement,
I'm going to tap into the game_images and then inside some square brackets, I'm going to use the computer
choice which is going to be between 0, 1 and 2 as the index to pick out the corresponding image
from my list game_images.
So now we're finally ready to run our code and I'm going to choose 0 for rock and the computer chose
paper.
So paper beats rock, I lose.
Let's try this again.
I'm going to choose scissors and computer chose scissors.
It's a draw. But we have also introduced a bug.
So if we test this using a number that's outside of this range, 0, 1 or 2,
so let's try 5. And we hit enter,
what do we get?
We get a index error.
So what has happened here?
Well, this is up to you to debug.
Well, this is a really good opportunity for you to practice your debugging.
So think about what has
changed since the last time we tested this and how you can fix the code so that it works as expected,
so telling us that you typed an invalid number, you lose whenever we type a number that's above or
equal to three or less than zero.
So I want you to pause the video and see if you can debug this challenge so that when you type in 5,
you get this printed. Pause video now.
All right, so what's going on here, because we tested this and it worked, but in between that time,
we also added this line because we wanted to get a hold of the game images based on the user's choice.
Now, at this point, the user's choice is unchecked by the if statement.
So it could still be equal to 4 or 5 or 10 or a million.
So if in that case, it tries to get hold of the fifth image from the game_images list, well, it doesn't
exist.
There's only 0, 1 and 2.
So to fix this, we need to move this if statement so that it gets checked before this line of code
gets carried out.
So let's go ahead and cut this line of code out and put it right above this print statement.
So in this case, if the user types in a choice that's above or equal to three or less than zero,
we're going to print this.
But else, if they typed in any other number, then we want the rest of the code to continue.
So let's select the rest of the code, hit tab and tab it over
so that is included under the else statement.
Now let's go ahead and change this from elif just to an if because we're no longer checking it as another
else-
if statement. It is just a straight up
if. So, in this case, if they typed a 5, then it will go into this basket and it will finish there.
But otherwise, it will go into this basket and it will continue checking later on.
So did you manage to debug your code and figure out the issue?
This is one of the most important skills
as a programmer. You have plenty of opportunities coming up to practice your debugging.
And if you ever want more practice, head over into the Q&A and see what other students have issues
with and see if you can help them out by practicing your debugging skills.
Now, we have completed the project by using everything from lists to randomization to variables to
if statements and a whole lot of logic.
So how did you get on with this project? If you struggle
this is the time again to go back to it and maybe map things out using a flow diagram or try to run
the code using Thonny to see how it does it step by step.
But the important thing is that you got to write your own code and you got to make it work.
And this is the only way that you'll understand what's going on so that you can continue on.
And as things get harder, you'll be able to learn more because you've already understood all of the
previous knowledge.
So I hope you had fun with me today
learning and building, and hopefully I will see you tomorrow bright and early.
So that's good night from me for today.
All right guys, well done for sticking it through.
You are now on day 5 of 100 Days of code.
And today I've got a fun project for you.
And the inspiration for the project comes from the fact that all sorts of
companies seem to be getting hacked these days. Everything from Ashley
Madison to Verizon,
everybody seems to be really bad at keeping your password safe.
So, how can we make sure that these hackers who are in hoodies and wearing face
masks, don't get to you and your account? I
don't know why hackers are always portrayed like this? I mean,
they're in their own house. They don't have to hide their face.
But at least they are conscious of not spreading germs and staying warm.
So that's good. But how do these hackers get into your account anyways?
Well,
one of the most common reasons is password reuse. Using the same password on 20
different sites from Google to Facebook, to Skype, to Spotify,
to all the random services that we sign up to.
The problem is that when one of these sites get hacked,
then the email and password combination you used to signup is compromised.
So all a hacker has to do is try out those credentials on a bunch of other
websites and see if they work. So how would you know,
if your email and password is on a database somewhere? You can head over to have
ibeenpwned.com, notice the spelling there,
and type in your email to see if it was involved in a website that had been
hacked.
So let's try an email here: elon@tesla.com
And it tells us, Oh, no, it seems like this email has been pwned.
And these where the websites which got hacked
potentially leaking this email and it's associated password.
I actually recommend you to try out your own email addresses right now and see
which services you signed up to have been compromised.
But if you want better security,
then you'll actually need unique passwords for each and every website.
And they should really be strong passwords, not 12345
6, or qwerty. If I just called out your password,
please change it.
Now what we're going to be building is exactly that. We're going to be building a
password generator,
something that's going to generate strong passwords with letters and symbols and
numbers. First, they ask us how many letters would you like in your password?
I would like 12. How many symbols would you like? I would like 2.
And I would also like 2 numbers in my password.
And then I hit enter and it gives me the password that it has generated with two
symbols, two numbers and 12 letters.
So that's a pretty strong looking password
if you asked me. Now I can use this and update my passwords to something very
strong and very secure.
So this is what we'll be building by the end of today. But in order to do it,
we first need to learn some new skills and new concepts.
So head over to the next lesson and let's get started.
The first topic I want to talk about today is the concept of loops,
things that have to happen over and over and over again.
The first type of loop I want to introduce you to is something called the For
loop. And it can be used really easily in combination with something we learned
in yesterday's lessons, which is lists. By using a
for loop like this
we can go through each item in a list and perform some action with each
individual item.
So let's try it out in practice. In order to follow along
go ahead and fork the day 5 start rebel.
And once I've explained the concept, then I want you to try it out yourself.
But first, let's say we had a list called fruits and it contained three items,
apple, peach, and pear.
If we wanted to access each item in this list individually and print it out one
by one, then we would use a for loop.
So if we start out with the keyword for,
and then we give a name to a single item.
So in this case, we might call it fruit.
And then we use the in keyword
and finally the list that we want to loop through,
which is our fruits here.
Now we cap it off with a colon and we go on to the next line and notice how it's
indented there.
Now I'm going to go ahead and print the value of each of the fruit variables.
And if I run this code,
you'll see that it loops through my list of fruits and for each of the fruits
inside the list, it prints it out into the console,
apple, peach, pear, in that order. Now,
the important thing to realize here is that basically you can imagine that
behind the scenes, what this code is doing is
it's taking this list of fruits
and it's a signing a variable name, fruit, to each of them.
So the first time this runs fruit is equal to apple,
the second time this runs fruit is equal to peach,
and we can see this even more clearly
if you run it through the Thonny IDE,
which I told you about at the beginning of the course. Now,
if I go ahead and click on the debug icon and I step into each of the steps,
you can see first it establishes that we have a list of three strings,
apple, peach, pear, and then we go into the for loop.
Now notice on the right here I've got all the variables being accounted for.
And the first one it's noticed is the variable fruits,
which holds a list of strings. Now,
as I continue into the for loop,
notice how it's going to look through this list of fruits
and it's going to assign the variable name fruit to each of the items starting
from the first one apple.
So now by the time it's reached line 3,
we've already got this variable called fruit
that's been assigned to the value of apple. And so at this point,
printing out the value of this fruit
it's obviously going to print out apple and you'll see in the next step.
There we go. Now, once I'm done here,
then it's going to loop back to the start of the for loop
and now this variable fruit is going to be assigned to the next value inside the
list of fruits.
So now notice how the variable fruit is attached to the value peach,
and then it continues this and so on and so forth until it prints out each one
of the fruits.
And this really emphasizes the most important aspect of loops.
The loop allows us to execute the same line of code multiple times.
In this case, we're executing the print statement three times,
but our for loop isn't limited to just executing a single statement.
We don't just have to print out the name of an item in the list.
We can execute a whole block of statements multiple times,
and we can do many things inside this for loop and by inside, I mean indented.
So let's say that in addition to printing out the fruit,
I'm going to write another print statement and I'm going to not only print out
the name of the fruit,
but I'm also going to say fruit + + "Pie."
So when I run this code, what do you think will happen?
Well, it prints out apple, and then it prints out Apple Pie
And then it goes back to the start and it assigns the variable fruit to the next
item, peach peach pie, pear pear pie.
So this is how we can implement a simple for loop that loops through a list
and assigns a variable name to each of the items in the list in order,
and then inside the for loop after the colon, after some indentation,
we can do something with that temporary variable for each of the items.
Now I've been talking a lot about the concept of being inside a for loop versus
being outside a for loop. And this is really, really important.
Whenever you see a colon say in our if statement that we saw previously,
or the for loop that we're using here,
the indentation is really,
really important because if it's indented,
then it means that it's inside the for loop and these instructions
all get carried out for as many times as the for-loop will need to repeat.
Now, if I decided that I wanted to say print my,
uh, fruits,
so my list of fruits up here, and I put it inside my for loop,
so indented after the for loop, then as you can imagine,
it's going to print that for as many times as the loop runs,
which is going to be three because there's three items in our list. Now,
if I had indented that back to the beginning,
so now it's no longer inside the for loop,
then it's only going to print once and it's going to print it after the for
loop is done. So notice how it's doing the whole Apple, Apple pie,
et cetera. And then once the loop is finished,
then it jumps to the next line and carries out this instruction.
So the indentation is really, really important,
and you have to be really careful with this.
Have a play around with this code
and if you're still struggling to see how it works
then move the code over to Thonny and step through each step one at a time and
see how it works.
But I hope you're starting to see how loops are really handy at executing an
instruction over and over and over again,
getting the computer to save us time and energy.
A really good example of when loops would come in really handy is,
you know, how Bart Simpson gets punished
and it has to write out a sentence over and over again on the Blackboard. Well,
if only Bart was a programmer, then he would be able to use loops to do this
and he would be able to chill in the corner. Now,
once you're happy with this type of for-loop,
then head over to the next lesson where I've got a coding exercise
that's going to put your knowledge to the test. All right.
So I'll see you there.
Head over to day 5.1, the average height exercise.
Now the instructions are that you're going to write a program
that's going to calculate the average student height from a list of heights.
So for example,
let's say we had a list of student heights that looks something like this,
then you're going to be using a for loop,
hopefully, to figure out the average.
And the average can be calculated by adding up everybody's height and then dividing
it by the number of students inside the list.
And then I want you to round it to the nearest whole number.
Now,
notice how we've got some starting code here.
And this is just for us to be able to input a list of student heights for testing
and see if your code actually works. So if you go ahead and run the code,
then you'll notice that it asks you for a list of student heights.
And the input is going to look something like this.
They're just going to be a bunch of numbers separated by a space.
So if I go ahead and paste that in there, then I hit enter,
then notice how this line on line five is going to print it out just as a normal
list full of numbers. Now,
Python has some really useful functions as we've seen.
We've seen that we could use the len function to calculate the size of a
particular list.
So if I go ahead and print my length of student heights,
and then I paste my student heights in here,
then you can see that I get five printed by calculating the number of items in
here. Now, Python also has something called sum,
and this gives us the total of all the items from a list.
So in this case, all of these added up would be 857.
Now your job though,
is to figure out how these functions actually work under the hood.
In order to fully complete this challenge,
you can't use the len function or the sum function.
Instead, you have to figure out another way through the use of for loops
where you can add each of the items inside the list together,
and you can use a for loop to figure out how many items there are in this list
and use that to calculate the average. So you can't use either of these
functions
and instead, you have to rely on what you learned in the last lesson to complete
this challenge. So have a think about it, and once you are ready, give that a go.
Now,
we know that we can't use either of these functions,
the sum function or the length function, because if we could,
then this challenge would be super easy and we would be able to calculate the
average by getting the total height, by getting the
sum of all of the items inside student heights.
And then we can calculate the number of students
by using the length function
to calculate the number of items inside the list.
And then we would get the average height
by dividing the total height by the numbers of students.
And then we would be able to round this value off and print it out.
But this, as you noticed, doesn't use a single for loop.
And the last thing we learned about was a for loop.
So this is definitely not the right way to solve the challenge. It works,
but what I wanted you to do is to figure out how the sum and the len functions
work under the hood. How is it actually implemented?
And to do that, we have to use a for loop.
So let's have a think about how we would first tackle this one,
where we get the total of all the items inside student heights.
So we basically want to add each of them together until we get the total.
Now, we can do this by simply using a for loop as you've learned in the last
lesson. So if we start off total_height as zero,
and then we write a for loop and we say for height in student_heights,
and then we add a colon,
then now we're going to loop through each of the heights inside this list
and we're going to add it to our total height.
So we can say total_height equals previous value of total_height plus height.
Or as you might remember,
the shortened version of this is just total height plus equals each of the
heights.
So now we can go ahead and check whether if this works by printing out the final
value of total_height. And notice how I'm doing it outside the loop
by making sure that it's not indented like this.
So let's run our code and I'm going to paste in those numbers as the demo
numbers. And then we get the value
total_height is 857, which if you take a calculator,
you'll be able to verify its exactly right.
So now we've basically replicated how the sum function works.
And now that we can try and replicate how the len function works.
We know that
basically the len function figures out how many items are in a particular list.
How can we do this using a for loop instead? Well,
what if we do something similar to what we did above where we start off the
numbers of students as zero,
and then we write a for loop for students in student heights, and inside our for
loop
all that we do is that we add one to our numbers of students each time
our for loop runs. And if you remember from the last lesson,
I said that the for loop will run for as many times as there are items inside
the list. If there are five items inside the list,
then the for loop is going to run five times,
which means this line of code is going to be called five times,
which means we add five to our numbers of students
and we end up with the total_length of the list.
So now let's go ahead and print this number of students out and run our code.
And I'm going to paste in the same
five numbers in the example input.
And you can see that the first value that comes out is my total height,
the second value is the length of the list, the number of items in the list
which is five, we can verify that. And the final one is the average
which matches up with the example output.
So now let's get rid of our print statements by commenting them out.
Now,
one of the things I want to point out to you that you might've noticed is that
in the first for loop, even though we're looping through the same list,
I've called each of the items height.
And in the second for-loop I've called them students. Now,
whatever we name each of the items inside the list, it's totally up to you.
If you could call it h, you could call it x,
you could call it basically anything you want
as long as you are consistent with using it inside the for loop.
So if you're calling each of the items inside the list
h, then when you're using it inside the for loop,
when you're modifying it or doing something with it,
then you are going to refer to it by the same name. Now,
usually it's a good idea to give it the name
which is the singular form of each of the items in the list.
For example, previously, we had a list of fruits. So each item was called fruit,
the singular form. And in this case, we have a bunch of heights,
so each of them I've called height. In the second for loop
I've decided to call each of the items a student. Now, in this case,
even though you have two for loops, you can call them the same thing.
But sometimes I find it a little bit confusing to have the same name in two
for loops. I prefer it this way, but it's totally up to you.
Just follow the good practice of using a singular form of whatever is contained
in a list when you write a for loop like this,
and you'll have less trouble down the line.
So now that you've gotten a taste for for loops,
it's time to complete another challenge
which is going to stretch you a little bit further. Head over to day 5.2 highest
score,
and we're going to get a list of students scores,
and it's a list of numbers again.
The idea is that you are going to write some code
that's going to output the highest score in the class.
So you're going to look through this list
using a for loop and figure out which of the scores inside the list is the
highest value. Now we can see pretty much at a glance that inside this list,
91 is the highest. But remember that when you test your code,
you won't be able to see the input. So you won't be able to cheat that way.
Instead, you have to do this using code. Now, just as in the last lesson
I mentioned that Python has some pretty useful functions that help us do a lot
of these commonly needed things very easily
such as the sum and the len functions, well, in this case,
there's actually something called the max function.
So if we pass a list,
let's say the student_scores list into a max function
and then I go ahead and print out the maximum value from my list of student_
scores. So let's run this code and I'm going to use the example input,
so a bunch of numbers separated by a space, and hit enter,
and you can see it tells me that 91 is the highest value.
Now there's also the min function
which basically will give me the lowest value inside a particular list,
which in this case is 55, but that's too easy.
I don't want you to use the max or the min functions. Instead,
you have to use what you've learned about for loops to replicate the underlying
functionality of this max function.
Because people tend to use Python to do a lot of data manipulation,
to do a lot of mathematical calculations.
It has a lot of these convenient functions for you.
But let's say you moved to a different language and you work on something else,
then these might not exist.
So understanding the underlying logic and being able to write out the code
using things that every programming language has like the for loop will mean
that you will become a much, much better programmer in the process.
So try and replicate the functionality of the max function and the output should
have the words
The highest score in the class is : and then a space and then the actual max
value. So this is what should happen. Pause the video now,
and have a think about how you would write your code in order to get hold of the
maximum value from a list.
All right. So did you manage to complete this challenge? If not,
and if you want to see how I do it, then continue watching along.
The first thing we want to do is we probably want to get a hold of each of the
scores inside our list of student scores.
So I'm going to write something like for score in student_scores,
so again,
keeping that convention of singular from plural. Now,
inside the loop, what can I do? Now
let's say I had a variable called the highest_score,
and I'm going to start it off as zero. And then inside my loop,
I can use an if statement to check, well is the current score that I'm looping
through greater than the highest score that I've got.
Well then if so, that means that this current score should actually be the
highest score.
So I can set my highest_score to equal,
single equals mean assign, double equals mean checking, remember?
And this loop will continue running until I've checked through all the scores
inside my student_scores,
and I've got the highest score stored inside this variable.
So now I can go ahead and print the sentence;
The highest score is this particular value.
So I'm going to use an f-string to insert my highest_score variable inside here.
And if I run my code and use this example input, then you can see
it tells me the high score in the class is 91,
which matches exactly with the example output. Now,
if you're at all confused about how this code works,
then I recommend again, pasting it into Thonny like this.
So you've got a list of scores and then you've got the code in the solution and
click on debug.
And you can see how we actually step through each of the stages where we start
off with a highest score being equal to zero, so that's where it is,
and then we continue into the loop where we go through each of the scores inside
the student_scores, so the first one is going to be 78.
So now we've got this variable score which is tied to the value of 78.
And then we go and check if the score,
which is 78, is greater than the highest score, which is zero. Well,
that's obviously true, right? So if that's true,
then it's going to carry out the next line of code,
which is that the highest score is now equal to score.
So now notice how this highest_score variable is going to update to the first
value because 78 is greater than zero.
Now we go back to the start of the loop and we go to the next value,
65. And 65 is now checked against the highest score. Is 65 greater than 78?
Well, no, that's not true. So this is false.
And so the highest score is left alone. And we continue back to the next value.
So now our score is equal to 89 and our highest_score is still equal to 78. Is 89
greater than 78? Yes.
So now we reset the highest_score to the new value,
which is 89.
And it continues this loop until it gets to the end and it's found the highest
value and it prints it out into the console.
Play around with the debug and step through each of the stages to see how it
works and compare it with what's happening with each of the variables on the
right. This is a really,
really useful way of wrapping your head around all of this complex,
looping and conditionals. And once you've understood everything that's going on,
then you can continue to the next lesson where we're going to talk about another
type of for loop, the for loop using a range operator.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.
Now up to this point,
we've only been using for loops in association with lists.
So we've been looping through the list and getting hold of each of the items in
the list and then doing something with it, right?
But we're not always going to be working with lists and using for loops.
Sometimes we might want to use a loop completely independent of a list.
And a good example of this is when Carl Gauss the German
mathematician was just a child when he was 10 years old,
his math teacher gave him an exercise that she probably thought would tie him up
for it a little while.
And the idea was to get him to add all of the numbers from 1 to 100.
So 1 + 2 + 3 + 4 + 5, et cetera,
all the way until a hundred.
And even though she thought this would keep him busy for an hour or so getting
this young child to add up these numbers and I can have some peace and quiet
scrolling on Facebook,
but unfortunately he came back to her within two minutes and gave her the
answer. So how did he work it out? Well,
here's actually a really smart kid and he figured out that if you flip the
numbers around, so 100 + 99 + 98,
and you'll look at both of these two lines,
you can see that 1 + 100 = 101, 2
+ 99 = 101, 3 + 98 = 101, basically,
if you tie all of these numbers together,
there's actually 50 pairs of 101.
So he could simply just do 50 multiplied by 101 which is 5,050.
And that's how he figured out the answer.
But we can actually outshine Gaus because we can do this calculation in less
than a minute, just by writing a few lines of code. But in order to do this,
we first have to learn about using for loops with the range function.
Now the range function is something that is really, really helpful
if you want to generate a range of numbers to loop through.
And the syntax looks something like this.
So we've still got our for and our in keywords highlighted in blue,
but instead of looping through a list,
we define how our loop is going to work by creating a range.
So in this case,
I'm creating a range between a and b and then I'm going to get hold of each
number in that range and do something with that number.
So for example, if I wrote for number in range,
and then my range is going to be 1, 10.
So this is going to be the range that I'm going to create between 1 and 10
and then I want to get hold of each of the numbers inside that range.
And this is going to be between 1 and 10 and not including 10.
So if I go ahead and print out the number that I create from my for loop,
then you'll see that what happens is it prints 1 2 3 4 5
6 7 8 9, but not the last digit, which I've included here.
So if I wanted all of the numbers from 1 to 10,
I actually have to set a range between 1 and 11.
And now when you run the code,
you can see that it goes from 1 all the way up to 10.
Now by default,
the range function will step through all the numbers from the start to the end,
and it will increase by 1. Now,
if you want it to increase by any other number,
then you have to add another comma to the end of it and specify how large you
want the step to be. So let's say we changed the step size to three.
Now, if I rerun the same code,
you'll see that it goes from one and then it steps by three to four and then it
steps by three. And then it steps by three, finally to 10.
Now let's come back to the problem that I mentioned at the beginning of this
lesson.
How can we add up all of the numbers from 1 to 100 by using code?
Well,
it's going to involve a for loop and it's going to involve the range function
because we're going to get hold of every number in the range between 1 and
100,
so we need to write 101. Once we've got hold of all of these numbers,
it's as simple as using a accumulator,
so let's say a total = 0. And then inside the for loop,
so that means indented,
we're going to say total += number.
So now it's going to add every number in this range to the total starting from
zero.
And this is basically going to give us the sum of every number from 1 to 100.
So let's go ahead and print it out and see if it matches Gauss's value.
And there you have it 5,050.
So now that we've beaten Gauss at his own game of math using programming,
let's head over to the next lesson and try to complete a challenge using the
range function to see if you managed to internalize and understand everything we
talked about in this lesson. So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Click on 5.3 adding evens.
The exercise is kind of similar to what Gauss had to do that I showed you in the
last lesson, but in your case,
I want you to calculate the sum of all the even numbers from 1 to 100,
including 1 and 100. So for example,
it might be two plus four plus six plus eight,
and so on and so forth until you get to a hundred.
It's a little bit more complicated than what the ten-year-old had to do.
And the important thing to remember is that there should only be one print
statement in your output.
It should just print the final total and not every step of the calculation.
So have a think about how you might solve this challenge,
pause the video and try to give this a go.
All right.
So there's actually quite a few ways that you could have solved this challenge.
Now,
one of the ways would have been using what we learned from the last lesson and the
ability to create a range function using a different step size.
I'll show you what I mean.
So let's create a full loop where we say for every number in the range between
1 to 100, so that's 101,
then we're going to do something with each number, right? Namely,
we're probably going to create a variable called total
and then we're going to add each of the even numbers together and accumulate it
inside this variable.
Now remember that I mentioned that the range function actually has a third thing
that you can add to it, not just the start and the end,
but also the step size. so we can change the step size to two,
and then now what it's going to do is it's going to go through 1 to 100 and
it's going to increase the step size by two.
So that means if we print this range as it is right now,
it's going to give us one plus two which is three, plus two
which is five and so on and so forth.
But if we change the range to start off from two
which is the first number that we have to start adding in our sequence, and then
increase it by two every single time,
then we end up with a range that includes all of the even numbers up to a
hundred. And I'll show you if I run this code right now.
So the next part is simple. All we have to do is to add the number to
the current total. So total += number.
And then finally outside the for loop,
you can go ahead and print that total. Now,
when I go ahead and run this code now, it's going to give me just the total.
Now remember that the indentation really matters because if I have it like this,
then it's going to give me the total for every step of the calculation,
because it's now included in the for loop and will be executed for as many times
as the for loop runs. But if I remove the indentation, then the
for loop is just this and this is outside of it
so it's only going to give it to me once everything has been done
and I've got the final total. And it's the correct solution.
But you might have also done it in a different way.
You might have said for a number in range,
1 to 101,
and you had some sort of another total, let's call it total2
and started at zero,
and then we say that if the number % 2 is equal to 0,
so if it's even essentially,
then we're going to add this number to the total2.
Finally, outside of the if and outside of the for,
we're going to print the final total. Now,
if I just run the code, then you can see
I get exactly the same number as before.
So if you chose to solve this challenge in either of these ways,
then you've succeeded. They're both right.
And there's probably even other ways that you could solve this as well.
But these two, I suspect will be the most popular approaches.
Now in the next lesson, I've got another coding exercise for you
and it's probably one of the top interview questions that programmers get asked
when they're being interviewed for a job. So head over there and give it a go.
All right guys, I've got a fun coding challenge for you today,
and it is a problem called fizzbuzz.
Now this is probably one of the most asked questions at interviews for
programmers because it tests the way that you think,
and it allows the interviewer to see how you use your logic to solve a problem.
And the problem we're going to tackle is a children's game called
Fizzbuzz. Last time I checked the programmatic solution was actually up on
Wikipedia.
So I recommend reading the Wikipedia article only after you've solved this
Programming challenge. The rules of fizzbuzz are really simple.
Basically, you have a bunch of kids who sit around in a circle and going
clockwise. The first kid says 1, the second kid says 2.
But then when a kid encounters a number that's fully divisible by three,
then instead of saying that number, he's going to say Fizz.
And when the number is divisible by five,
instead of saying the number, they should say Buzz.
And if the number is divisible by both three and five, for example, 15,
then they should say Fizzbuzz.
So your program is going to replicate this for all the numbers up to and
including a hundred. To start off, it will probably look something like this.
It's going to print one, and then on the next line
it will print two and then fizz,
because three is divisible by three. And then four,
and then five is divisible by five so it's a buzz.
And then six is fizz because it's divisible by three and so on and so forth.
This is what your program has to do. Take a look at the instructions,
make sure that you understand what it is that your program has to do
and then pause the video and try to give this a go.
All right. So the first thing we have to do is to create a range, right?
So let's say that for number in range, and our range is between 1 and 100,
so we have to include 101 in here.
And what we want to do is we want to check whether if the number's divisible by
three, divisible by five,
or if it's divisible by both three and five.
Now we could write our code by doing this in order, right? We could say
if number % 3 is equal to zero,
then it's divisible
by three.
So you might think that you could write the code like this,
but there is a crucial problem in the logic here
namely that we know that the if, elif, else statements will stop
once it's found one statement that's true. For example,
if we take the number to be 15,
15 divided by three is equal to zero
so it's going to carry out whatever instruction is inside this if statement
and then it's going to be done with it. It's going to skip this one
and crucially, it's going to skip this one
which is what we really need. Instead of structuring our code like this,
what you might have done and what you should've done is in fact,
have this at the top.
So first check if it's divisible by three and by five,
and then if that is not true,
then check to see if it's divisible by five and then divisible by three or the
other option works as well.
You could do it like this. Because these two have no overlap in terms of the
results and then it doesn't really matter.
So now we can finally write our code because we can say, well,
if the number that we're currently encountering is divisible by both three and
five, then we have to print Fizzbuzz.
If it's only divisible by three, then we're going to print fizz.
And if it's only divisible by five, then we're going to print buzz.
All right.
Now that still leaves the remaining numbers, right?
Because the remaining numbers
which don't fit any of the criteria should just be printed out as the number.
We can catch that quite easily with an else statement that catches basically every
other number, in which case, we're just going to print the number.
So now, if I go ahead and run this code,
then you can see that all the way from 1 to 100,
it's been able to work out which ones are fizz, which ones are buzz,
and which ones are fizzbuzz. How did you get on with it?
If you got stuck or if you don't understand why this logic matters,
then I want you to try both versions that I showed you and see it
step-by-step using the Thonny program just as we did before.
That way you can visualize what's actually happening in terms of the logic and
how it's flowing from one step to the next, to the next. Now,
once you've done that, then go back to your exercise and try to complete it.
It's really, really important that you don't just say, "Oh yeah, I understand
now." It's a really good idea to make sure that your code actually works at the
end of the day and to write the code yourself. Today
we've learned all about loops and we're going to apply it in our final project.
So that's what's waiting up for you in the next lesson.
So head over that once you're ready.
Now that we've learned all about loops in Python,
we're finally ready to tackle our final project of the day,
which is the PyPassword generator.
Our program will ask us how many letters would you like in your password?
So I will say I would like a long password, let's say 14.
How many symbols, 3, how many numbers, 4,
and it's going to generate me a password that is almost completely impossible to
crack by any hacker, no matter how talented they are.
So the project of today is to build this password generator.
If you head over to this particular Repl.it,
password-generator-start, then you'll see that here
I've already included for you a list of all the letters in the alphabet from A
to Z, including the uppercase and lowercase letters.
I've got a bunch of numbers and a bunch of symbols that are usually accepted by
websites in the passwords.
And I've also created the inputs that you saw when we did the demo.
So it's going to ask us how many letters, how many symbols, how many numbers,
and then you're going to turn all of that knowledge as well as using these
lists
and what you've learned about loops into the same password generator that you
saw in the final demo.
So have a play around with the final demo yourself,
and then have a think about how you might be able to achieve this goal of
creating a random password for the user based on the number of letters,
symbols, and numbers that they want.
Now there's two levels to this project.
You can either go for the easy version where all you have to do is generate your
password in sequence. So for example, if the user wanted four letters,
two symbols, and two numbers,
then it might just look like this four letters and then two symbols and then two
numbers. So they're in sequence right? First, you've got the letters,
then you've got the number of required symbols,
and then you've got the required numbers. So this is the easy level.
And then there is the hard level. And the hard level requires you to generate the
password in a completely random order.
So instead of having it being, letter symbol number,
it should be maybe letter and then a symbol and then a number,
then a letter, then a symbol and then a number.
But notice how this is completely random.
Every single time you generate it,
the order of where the symbols and where the numbers appear in your password are
completely random. So for example,
if you look at the demo version and I do the same thing,
four letters, two symbols,
two numbers, where the numbers and where the symbols occur are completely
unpredictable. And every single time I generate a new password,
it's going to switch it up again.
So that's the hard level. I recommend trying the easy level first
and then once you've managed to do it, then take yourself up to the hard level
if you think you're up to it. But remember that if your doing the hard level,
you might have to do a little quick Google around in order to figure out how to
do something that you might not have seen before.
But it's all part of the challenge and I hope you'll take it on with vigor.
So pause the video now and try to complete the final project.
Alright,
so let's first tackle the easy level where we're just generating a password
with the required number of letters and then the required number of symbols and
then the required number of numbers.
So let's go ahead and tackle this one first.
Now we know that we've got these lists which we can draw from,
and we know that we can use the random module to get hold of a random item from
the list. So all we have to do is first get four random letters.
So let's say that we had a password
which just started out as an empty string.
Then we can use a for loop to loop through all of the characters that we need to
create for our password. For example,
I might say for char, short for character, in the range of,
um,
from 1 to the number of letters that the user wanted.
So in this case, if the user wanted four letters,
then it will be a range from one to four, but not including four.
So it's actually from one to three,
which has only three characters. In order to modify this,
we have to do what we did always before,
which is just to add one to the end of our range.
So now we're going to create a range based on the number of letters that the
user wanted.
And I'm just going to go along with the assumption that the number of letters
equals four. Let's just pretend that's what the user will enter.
So then this range becomes 1, 2, 4 + 1 which is 5.
So the range is in fact going to be 1 to 4. For every single number in that
range from one to two to three to four,
I'm going to generate them a random letter,
and I'm gonna pick it out of this list of letters. To do that
I can either generate a random number and use it as the index or you might've
seen previously
I showed you the random.choice function. And inside this random.choice,
we can pass a sequence
which in our case is the letters list.
Then it will look through this list of letters and it will give us a random item from
that list.
So now that random letter is going to be something that we're going to need to
add to our password, right?
So we can set this equal to a random character.
And now let's go ahead and just print it out.
Right?
So let's say we want four letters in our password and we can type anything for
the other ones, but notice how when the for loop runs,
it's given us some random characters that it's picked out of our letters list.
So there's an a,
there's a capital P there's a d and there's a capital J. How can we add each of those
letters to our password? Well,
we can use the string concatenation that we learned very early on in Day 1.
We can say password equals the previous password
plus the random character. Of course,
the shortened version of this is just password+= random_char.
And now let's go ahead and instead of printing the random character,
let's print the password at each stage of the loop.
Right?
And again,
I'm going to choose four letters and you can see that the first time the loop
runs I get an M. So password is equal to M. The second time I get a Q
so I add the Q onto the M, I get MQ and so on and so forth until I get these four
characters in the beginning of what seems to be my random password that's going
to be generated.
Right
Now, if you wanted to,
you can actually simplify this down to just one step,
because instead of having this intermediary,
which is the random character variable,
we can simply just replace it with the code, like this.
So in this case, we're getting a random choice from our letters list,
so we get a random letter, and then we add that to our password.
Now that we've done that for the letter,
then it's pretty easy to see how we can continue doing this for the symbol and
the numbers. We just have to keep adding it to the end of our password.
So let me quickly write out the code for this.
Right?
So now when the user requests that they want four letters in their password,
then we generate a range from one to five.
And then for each of those positions,
we generate a random letter in order to fill the password.
And then we add on the required number of symbols and the required number of
numbers. And finally, we print out the final password.
Let's go ahead and run this code. And again,
I'm going to choose four letters, two numbers, and two symbols.
And I end up with my final password,
which fits exactly that criteria and it looks pretty random.
But the only problem is that if a hacker knew that you always have two symbols
at this position, and two number at this position,
then it's very easy to crack that password because in order to get the last
digit, for example, they only have to try nine different variations, 12
3456789.
And this just limits the strength of your password. In order to tackle that you
would have to tackle it at the hard level,
which is how do you get a password that has all of these letters and numbers in
a completely random order. To do that
we mentioned that you have to do a bit of googling because it might require
something that you haven't done before. But in essence,
you've got access to everything you need to perform the logic.
So if you haven't given that a go,
then this might be a good time to pause and have a think about how you might
structure the logic or how you might create a flow chart to express this logic
that you would want. And once you've done that,
and if you want to see the solution and walk through it with me,
then come back here and I'll show you how to do it, but first give it a go.
Right?
All right. In order to tackle the hard level,
what we essentially need to do is instead of adding each of these letters into a
string, we actually want to add it into a list.
So I'm going to copy all of this that's here,
and I'm just gonna comment it out and I'm going to paste it under my hard level and
work on it here. So instead of using a password string,
I'm going to create a list and to better describe it
I'll change my variable name, the password list. So now,
instead of using password to add each of these letters and numbers and symbols,
I'm going to be adding it to my list.
Right,
Right
Now, to add things to a list,
you can use the same syntax that you did with strings,
which is to add the new item into the list and to update the old list.
You might be more familiar though with the syntax
which is append and both of these work.
You can use either of them if you want, but they'll end up doing the same thing,
which is to add each of those things you've generated in the order that you've
generated to your password.
So we end up now with a list with four letters,
two symbols, and two numbers,
all stored as strings because of the quotation marks around them.
So now that we've got a list, well, then we have to think about, well,
how can we shuffle our list,
how can we mess up the order of the items in our list?
And that might take you to Google and you might search for something like how to
change the order of items in a list.
And then we also have to add our keyword, which is Python,
because there's obviously a lot of other programming languages.
And we come up against our first Stack Overflow question,
how can I reorder a list? Well, that sounds kind of like what I want to do,
right? So if we scroll down,
you can see that the way to do it is either using a for loop,
like so, or
to simply use the shuffle function.
This is a much simpler way because it allows us to update the existing list just
by calling the shuffle function on it.
And this one actually requires us to create a new list and we have to create a
bunch of random numbers for the order,
and then to reorder them using a four loop.
So I'm going to go with this version and let's try it out.
Instead of printing password_list,
let's print the password_list before the shuffle,
and then let's use the random.shuffle and pass in the password_list.
And then let's print the outcome of that shuffle,
so let's print the password_list again.
So now you can see that we've got a version before,
and then we've got a version after.
So if I run my code and I write again, four letters,
two symbols, two numbers,
you can see that previously it was ordered in the order that we added each of
the characters. After the shuffle
they're now pretty much random. There's letters in random places,
there's symbols in random places.
So if only we could turn this back into a string,
then we've got our password that's nicely shuffled.
So how can we turn it back into a string? Well,
we could simply use a for loop, right?
We could say for each, um,
character in the password_list,
we're going to add it to a variable called a password,
which is going to start off again as a empty string
and then we're going to add to it.
So we're going to say password += char in our password_list.
And now if I go ahead and just print my final password,
I'm going to add a fstring as well.
Let's say your password is,
and then let's insert the password.
And now if I run my code and let's say,
I want 12 letters, uh,
three symbols and four numbers,
then it's going to generate me a entire password
that's completely randomized in terms of the orders of the symbols and the
numbers.
And I've now solved the hard part of this challenge project.
Did that make sense to you? Did you manage to get it
to do what you want it to do?
If you're at all confused about the code that we've covered here,
then be sure to check out the final project that I've got here,
which is the App generator end,
and take a look at how the easy level is implemented,
how the hard level is implemented and try switching it around so that you really
get to understand it.
Try instead of maybe getting the user to tell you how many letters,
how many symbols, how many numbers, instead just define those yourself
or use a random number of letters, numbers,
and symbols. Play around with the code until it starts doing what you want it to
do and it starts making sense.
But I hope you had fun building this project with me today and learning all
about loops. On the next lesson
we're going to be learning more about these things that we've been using a lot,
which is Python functions. So I'm going to bid you goodnight for today,
and hopefully I'll see you bright and early tomorrow,
and we'll learn some new skills and work on some new projects.
So that's all from me, goodnight from Angela.
Hey guys,
welcome to Day 6 of 100 Days of code. And well done from making it this
far.
So today we're going to talk about code blocks and indentation as well as
functions and also a different flavor from the for loops that we saw yesterday.
Today
we're going to talk about while loops as well. And to learn all of these things,
we're going to use the help of something
that's very similar to Karel the robot.
And this is something I use when I first learnt how to code
and it's one of my favorite tools for learning programming
especially as we get into more difficult concepts like functions and while loops
et cetera. And by the end of the day, we're going to be writing the code
that's required to instruct our little robot to be able to complete any
randomly generated maze. So that's the goal
and if you head over to the next lesson,
let's get started and let's start learning about some of these things.
The first concept I want to introduce you to is something called functions.
And just as we perform many different functions could be mother, father,
son, daughter,
we can also get our code to perform different pieces of functionality.
Now, if we think back,
we've actually already come across functions and I've been referring to them
every time we've needed to use one.
If you take a look at this link in the course resources
which takes you to the Python documentation,
then you can see that Python has a whole bunch of built in functions that we've
been using. For example, the len function,
which gives us the number of items in a collection or the int function
which turns something into an integer or the print function,
the range function, and other ones that we haven't seen yet.
If you head over to the Day 6
starting Repl.it and go ahead and forward a copy of it.
Then we can start typing one of the functions that we've been using a lot,
which is the print function.
And the reason why we know it's a function is because it's the name of a
function followed by a set of parentheses.
Now we know that if we put something inside these parentheses,
say, for example, hello, then when I run the code,
whatever is inside those parentheses
will get outputted over here in the console.
Now all of the functions work pretty much the same.
So if I wanted to use the len function to see, well,
how many characters are there in this word Hello? I, again,
put my hello inside the parentheses because of the parentheses
we know that this is a function and then I can save the outcome of this length
function to a variable, say,
let's call it number of characters, num_char.
And then I can go ahead and print it in order to view it inside the console.
So let's print the num_char,
and now you can see that this len function gets to work, calculates the
number of characters, it's five, and then it gets printed.
So all of this functionality has been achieved by these built-in functions from
Python, like print and len.
Now what if we wanted to make our own functions?
How would we do that? Well, if we want to make our own function,
we first start out with a keyword,
which is called def.
And this is because we're creating or defining our function.
Now, after the def keyword,
we can give our function a name and I'm just going to call it my_function.
Now, the thing that differentiates a function from a variable, however,
is the parentheses. So after the name comes the parentheses,
and now the final thing,
the finishing touch to our function definition is a colon because that says
everything that comes after that line and is indented belongs with the
function.
Let's make a really simple function that just has two lines of code.
Maybe it prints Hello and then it prints Bye.
So now I've created my function,
I've placed the lines of code that are associated with this function all indented
after the definition. But notice how,
if I go ahead and run my code, actually nothing will happen.
And the reason is because we haven't yet executed the function.
Now we can define lots and lots of functions ahead of time.
And it's only when we actually need it
do we go ahead and trigger it and to trigger it or in programming lingo,
we would say to call the function,
all we have to do is type the name of the function,
which is my_function
and then to add the parentheses and any necessary inputs. In our case,
our function doesn't require any inputs so we can leave the parentheses blank
again. And now if I go ahead and run my code once more,
then you'll see that by the time the computer reaches line 5,
it's going to search for this thing called my_ function.
It sees that it was defined right here on line 1
and it goes through all of the content and executes them in turn, line by line.
And that's why we get hello and bye being printed here.
So just to recap, this is how we create a function in Python.
There's two steps to it. The first step is to actually define the function,
to specify what it should do.
And we do that by first using the def keyword and then we give our function a
name. So for example, in this case,
I called it my_function and then comes a set of parentheses and a colon.
And then after that, we get to put the lines of code
which will be included in this function. And remember that these lines of code
which goes into the function
which will be carried out when this function is triggered
must be indented like this.
So once you've defined the function, you've created the recipe,
the next step is to actually use it, which in programming lingo,
we would say calling the function. And we call the function just by specifying
the name and a set of parentheses.
And once the computer sees this line of code it'll know to go and carry out all
the instructions inside
where we defined our function. And to learn about functions,
I'm to introduce you to something that's very similar to Karel the robot.
The robot is going to be something that is just going to perform the tasks that
we want it to, and no more and no less.
So for example,
if we wanted a robot to go to the store and pick up some milk for us,
we can't simply just tell it, Oh yeah,
just go and buy some milk because it won't know how to do that
unless
we give it specific instructions such as leave the house,
walk two blocks to the right, walk four blocks back and then two blocks to the right.
When you go to the store,
give them some money and then take the milk and come back.
We have to program each and every step. But say,
if this functionality of getting the robot to go and pick up some milk for us is
needed every single day
then we have to write out all of those instructions day after day,
day after day. And at some point our fingers are going to hurt, right?
We're typing so much code that's repeated because we don't have a way of bundling
all of those instructions together. And that's where functions come in.
Functions will give us a way of referring to all those instructions
at the same time.
That way we can give our robot a single instruction and it will carry out all of
those little steps for us and get us some milk.
Now to try this out yourself,
I want you to head over to the course resources and click on the link that takes
you to Reeborg's World.
Now Reeborg's World is very similar to Karel the robot that I showed you
earlier on,
but it allows us to write Python code. And it's very easy to get started.
Now we've got this area here which we're going to use to write our Python code.
And then once we're done, we can click on play to
run the Python code and see the instructions carried out by our robot.
But if you click on Reeborg's keyboard,
you can see all of the functions that we can use to command our robot,
like move or turn left, or build a wall, et cetera.
Let's see if we go ahead and run this line of code here, move.
What happens? When I click play
you can see that our robot moves forward in the direction that it's facing by
one step. So if we wanted it to move, say for example, three steps,
all we have to do is the call the move function three times.
Now let's reset by clicking the return button to return our robot back to the
starting position.
Now let's click play again in order for our robot to carry out the new
instructions.
Notice how all the instructions were carried out very quickly. To execute each
instruction one step at a time, line by line,
we can use this step-through button.
This button allows us to see how each instruction is executed and after each
instruction, it pauses and highlights the next instruction.
This is very helpful for debugging.
So notice how we're highlighting line 2. So if I click on step again,
it's going to carry out that function and then it's going to carry out line
3 and finally it reaches the end.
And that's the end of our code. Now,
in addition, we can use some of the other commands in the keyboard
for example, turn left.
If I decide to say move three times and then turn left and then maybe move three
times again, can you predict which square the robot is going to end up in?
Are you ready? Let's go ahead and run the code. There we go.
We end up on the square 4,4.
It moves three forwards turns left and then moves three steps again,
because that's what we told it to do with our Python code.
So now here's a question. If you take a look inside the set of commands,
you'll notice that there is move and there is turn left. But there is no turn
right and there is no turn around.
So how could we use a function to create those commands?
Because, of course, we could just simply write,
turn left and then turn left again.
And this would effectively turn the robot around, right?
But if we want to do that many times, say for example,
if we wanted to go to three, turn around, go back to one, turn around,
go back to three, then we would have to write code that looks a bit like this.
We would have to say move
two times to get to square three, turn left, turn left,
and then move two times again to get to one and then turn left,
turn left again in order to turn around.
This is all the code we would have to write to achieve this kind of effect.
But instead of all of this, we could just define a new function.
So we use the def keyword to say that this code is defining a new function
called turn_around
and this function is simply going to be turn left twice. And remember, all the
code that's going to go inside the function has to be indented.
And now instead of writing, turn left, turn left,
we can simplify our code by telling it to call the function,
turn_around, and we can do that here and we can do that here.
So now when we run the code,
you'll see that it does exactly the same thing as before,
but this time we've cut down two lines of code.
So instead of eight lines of code for our instructions,
we only now need six lines.
And you can see that the more that you need to use this function,
the more typing it will save you. But more important than reducing
the number of lines of code is that our code has also become a lot more
readable.
So the turn_around function is much more clear than having turn left twice.
Now let's see what happens when we use the step through button.
Look closely at how each line in our code is executed.
So now what we're going to carry out the move by one, move by one
and now it's going to call turn_around, that function. And it jumps over to find
this function and carries out the code inside in turn from the top to the
bottom. So turn left, turn left. And now once that function's done,
it goes back to where it was before and continues running, move, move,
and then turn around again.
So here's your challenge.
Try and create a separate function that turns our robot to the right.
Pause the video,
head over to the course resources and click on the link that takes you to
Reeborg's World
and then go ahead and create your own function called a turn_right.
Right.
All right.
So this should be pretty simple because all we have to do is to define a new
function called turn_right
and this function is going to simply be turn left three times
Right?
because turning left three times is going to effectively turn our robot
right.
So even though we only have this one way of turning our robot,
we can define our own functions to give it many,
many other commands that it could use.
So now using this turn right function,
see if you can write some code that makes our robot draw a little square going
from here to here then to here and back to the beginning.
Once you're done and you hit play, this is what should happen.
So pause the video now and see if you can complete that challenge.
Right?
All right. So let's go from the beginning.
We start out facing right at the position 1,1
one in order to draw the square, starting from this way,
we have to first turn left
and then we have to move one step and that should take us to here.
And now we have to turn right, move
one more step, turn right again,
move one more step and finally turn right for the last time and move one more
step.
So using our awesome function means that we don't have to right out turn left
three times each time we need to turn right.
So our code can just be eight lines long instead of 14 lines long
and we're using our function to cut down on a lot of typing.
But not only are there fewer lines of code,
look how much more readable our code has become thanks to our turn right
function. It's now so much easier to read, turn right,
and understand what it needs to do rather than seeing turn left three times in
the code.
So now it's easier to read and it's easier to follow the logic in our code.
In the next lesson,
I've got a challenge for you. Head over there and apply what you've learned
about functions to try and solve it. I'll see you there.
All right. So now that you've learned about functions,
I have a coding challenge for you. If you head over to this link,
which is in the course resources and head over to this challenge
which is called Hurdle 1,
the idea is that we've got a robot here which needs to do a number of hurdles to
jump over each of these barriers, to get to the final goal here.
Now you need to use your knowledge of functions
as well as some of the things you've learned before, such as the
for loop or the range function, to be able to achieve this.
Now, remember that you can tell the robot to move by typing, move(),
and when that's run, it will move by one space.
And you can also use, say,
turn_left to get the robot to turn left.
And in this case, when I run the code,
it's going to move one space and face to the left.
In order to complete this entire challenge,
you can see there's a number of steps that the robot has to go through before it
can get to this final goal. And if you were to write out each of these steps,
like I have done here one after the other, it would take many,
many tens of lines of code. And that's not what we're about. We're programmers.
So we're born to be lazy.
Try and see if you can minimize number lines of code while still keeping your
code readable and understandable by somebody else and be able to get your robot
to complete these instructions and take the robot to the final goalpost.
And once you've completed the challenge successfully,
you should get a green popup that says you're at the correct X and Y position.
So pause the video now,
head over to this link and give this challenge a go.
Right.
All right. So how did you get on with this challenge?
How many lines of code did it take you to tell this robot to get to the goal?
All right. Let's have a think about how we might tackle this.
We know that out of the things that we can tell the robot to do, the most useful
things are to move and to turn left.
But because the robot doesn't have a builtin turn right function,
then we have to define that ourselves.
And the reason why we need to do that is because you can see that at several
points during the hurdle, we'll have to turn right. For example,
when the robot is here at 2, 2, it will have to turn right,
and then move and then turn right again and then move.
So let's create a new function called turn_right.
So we start out with the def key keyword and then give our function a name which
is going to be turn_right.
And then we add the parentheses with nothing inside
because we're not passing any inputs to this function.
We're just going to use this function as a way of defining turn left three
times. So when you turn left three times, of course you turn right.
And now we have the ability to turn right.
So notice how this is the code block for our turn right function
and it ends at the last line, which is indented, which is line 4.
So every subsequent line
which starts at the very beginning of the code file next to
the left margin is outside this code block and it will act independently.
So in fact,
the first line of code that actually runs in our file is going to be this line
6. And you can see that when I press run,
you can see that's the first thing that gets highlighted.
And if I go through this step wise,
you can see the first line is going to be line 6 and it tells the computer to
go and find this function called turn_right. So if I skipped to the next step,
it's found that, and it's going to start going through lines 2, 3,
and 4,
turning our robot three times until it has turned right. Now that we have the
ability to turn right,
let's have a think about how we might be able to get our robot to make one jump.
Let's see. The first thing we'd probably want our robot to do is to move forwards
by one step, which should take it here.
And then the next thing we want it to do is the turn left so that it faces the
top.
Right?
And once it's in this position,
then we want to get it to move forward one step,
and then we'll probably want it to turn right. Now,
notice how I'm actually testing my code at pretty much every other line that I
write.
And this means that you don't end up in a situation where you get to the end and
you've written lots and lots of lines of code, and it doesn't work.
In which case you have to comb through all of the code you've written and find
out where the problem is. So in this case,
we've only got four lines and we've been testing it step wise.
So we can see that we're on track and our robot is now turned to the right,
ready to move one more step.
And then once it gets to here,
we have to turn right again and move one more step.
Right?
And now it should end up here, but let's just check it out.
So our robot turns left turns right, turns right again.
And it ends up here facing the bottom.
So the final thing we need to do is to get it, to turn left once more,
so that it will face the forward direction.
Right?
So once you've confirmed that your code is working,
then you should really think about what is the next step,
because we've managed to make one hurdle. And notice how,
when we're at this position, 3,1, this particular square,
it's almost the same as if we were at 1, 1,
because we have to move one step again, turn left, move, turn right, move,
turn, right, move, turn left.
So it's basically repeating all of these instructions, rather than executing
these instructions six times, because there are six hurdles.
So if I go back and I start,
then you'll see that this code actually will complete the challenge.
Right?
It says I'm done. And we're at the correct position,
but notice how many lines of code we've got.
We've got something like 58 lines of code.
I know I've left some spaces in their so that you can see which parts are
repeating, but still that's a massive amount of code for something very simple.
Now we know that we can use functions to package
a set of instructions together under one name,
just like what we've done here with the turn_right.
We've packaged the three lines of code turn left, turn left, turn
left into a single function called turn_right
so that when we need that functionality, all we need to do is just the call
the function and add the parentheses at the end.
So we can do exactly the same thing with this set of instructions,
which basically gets our robot to perform a single jump.
So let's create a def and let's call this function jump.
And then lets add the parentheses and the colon. And very importantly,
all of these lines of code must be indented. So to indent
a whole block of code together,
you hold down the command key and click the left square bracket or the right
square bracket. On windows it's holding down the control key and again,
the last square bracket or the right square bracket.
So now this basically says that all of these instructions live inside this block
of code called jump. And when we call jump,
then it will carry out all of these lines of code.
So now what we could do to complete the challenge is to simply call this
function jump six times.
Right?
And so now we could again solve this entire problem using just 21 lines of code.
And we managed to complete this challenge using two functions that have repeated
instructions and then calling the jump function six times.
But because we've learned about loops and the range function,
we know that we can actually cut this down even shorter.
So instead of calling jump six times,
we could actually write a for loop that loops through and calls this jump
function
six times. We could say something like for step in,
and remember that these two key words come from the
for...in loop and they always have to stay the same.
And then after the in keyword,
we define the rules for how many times we want our loop to repeat.
In my case, I'm going to use in range function.
And I'm going to say from 0 to 6,
but not including 6. So in this case it will be 0, 1, 2,
3, 4, 5.
So that actually going to happen six times.
And now I'm going to add the colon. And finally,
inside this for loop,
I'm going to call jump just once. Now,
watch what happens. First it starts off at the for loop,
it calls jump and it goes through this once and then it comes back loops again,
calls it the next time. And then again,
the third time in the loop, fourth time in the loop,
fifth time in the loop and six time in the loop.
How far did you manage to get?
Did you get stuck on this section where we needed to create the for loop?
Well, in that case,
I recommend going back to the lesson where we covered for loops and reviewing
the for loop and the range function in detail before you come back and try to
solve this challenge again. It's really,
really important at this stage that you've understood and you've mastered some
of these ideas because we're going to be using them more and more in the future.
Really make sure that you've understood things before you keep going.
In previous lessons,
I've already mentioned how important it is in Python to be aware of your
indentation. So we know that when we create a function like this,
that every line that comes after this definition
that is indented is going to be inside this function.
So by indented, I mean
it's shifted to the right by four spaces like this.
So if you imagine each dot as a space, then this is a single block of code.
And if we want to continue adding to this block of code inside my function,
then we would continue adding lines of code, which are indented.
So you have to almost visualize for yourself this invisible line around these
blocks of code, which are indented. Now,
if my code was written like this on the other hand,
then the block of code is in fact only this part. And this print statement will
not get triggered when this function gets triggered because it's independent
from this function because it's not indented. Now, a simple way
that I like to think about this kind of indentation is kind of like the file
structure you see when you go into finder on the Mac,
or when you go into Explorer on Windows.
If we have a function,
it's kind of like a folder and anything that goes inside the function,
for example, if I throw this file inside the function,
then you notice that it gets indented, right?
And this way it shows to you very,
very clearly that these two files print-
hello and print-world are living inside this folder,
my function. And this is the equivalent of this code.
We have this folder say, my_function, and it contains these two lines of code.
Now, on the other hand,
if I take this print world and I put it outside of the function folder,
then you can see that this is completely independent from that folder.
And it's now indented at the same level as the function.
So this is the equivalent of this code, where we've got this print-
hello being inside the
my_function and this print-world being outside and at the same indentation level
as this function definition. Now,
the indentation gets a little bit more complicated when we have other blocks of
code. So for example, the, if/elif/else statements.
They have blocks of code,
which need to be indented to be inside the block.
For loops need to be indented to be inside the loop.
And it's very important that you get used to looking at blocks of code like
this. So for example, if we were to expand our simple
my_function and add a whole bunch of code into it,
then we would have to indent all of those lines of code by four spaces
represented by the four dots here. Now, if we wanted to have
another block of code inside this if statement,
then this line has to be indented,
a further four spaces.
So this is the function block,
this is the if block,
this is the elif block and you have to be able to see all of this while just
looking at the indentation. If we wanted to represent this,
then it's almost like creating a new folder. Let's call it the
If sky == clear.
And this if block goes inside my function, so it's indented.
Now, if I wanted to have a print statement,
let's call it print-blue inside this if statement.
So this is what should be executed if this function gets called
and if the sky is equal to clear, well
then this line is indented twice.
And that is the equivalent of four spaces in our code, like this.
Now, every time I've talked about indentation,
I've been talking about spaces and actually there's two ways of creating
indentation. You don't have to just use spaces.
You can also use tabs and that's created using the tab key on your keyboard,
which can look a little bit like this.
Now there's a lot of debate around spaces and tabs where some people prefer
using spaces to indent, other people prefer tabs to indent.
And there's a lot of people arguing in the coding community.
And I think this excerpt from one of my favourite shows really demonstrates this.
Richard what's wrong? Nothing, nothing, literally. It's all good.
Come on. Oh my God. Your roommates are right. You really hate spaces.
No, no, no, no. I don't. It's not hate, hate is a strong word. Um,
truth be told I do have a slight preference for tabs,
but that's only because I'm anal
and because I prefer precision.
Well, not to pick a fight here,
but if you really care about precision why don't you use spaces?
But whatever, once it goes through the compiler, it's the same thing, right?
Yeah. Yeah. Technically, yes.
Right.
I guess I just, I just don't understand why anyone would use spaces over tabs.
Like if it's all the same,
why not just use tabs? Because it could look different on other people's
computers. Tabs create smaller file sizes. All right.
I run a compression company. Trust me.
I've devoted my life to minimalizing file sizes. It's what I do. I mean,
I do not get why anyone would use spaces over tabs. I mean,
why not just use VIM over Emacs? I do use VIM over Emacs. Oh, God help us.
Okay. Uh, you know what? I just, I don't think this is gonna work.
I'm so sorry. Uh, I mean like what,
we're going to bring kids into this world with that over the head.
Stuff's not really fair to them. Don't you think? Kids?
we haven't even slept together. And guess what?
It's never going to happen now because there is no way I'm going to be with
someone who uses spaces over tabs.
So should you be using spaces or should you be using tabs?
The age old question and the extent to which people obsess over this question,
it really shows in this 2017 Stack Overflow developer survey,
where they are asked the developers, do you use spaces or do you use tabs?
And then they compare it against their annual salary
and somehow have managed to show that the people who use spaces seem to earn a
lot more than the people who use tabs.
Now the official guide from the Python community is in fact to use spaces.
So if you click on the section, tabs or spaces,
they tell you in no uncertain words,
that spaces are the preferred indentation method.
And in fact, in Python 3,
you can't mix a code file that uses tabs and spaces for indentation in the same
file. And it also tells you that in order to indent a line of code,
it should be indented using four spaces,
so four hits of the space bar. Now,
for a lot of people, that may seem quite inefficient because I have to hit my
space bar
four times in order to achieve a single indent.
And you've seen how much we indent throughout our code. So it seems very,
very inefficient.
But luckily in most code editors,
they actually have a setting that allows you to indent using spaces,
changing the indent size to four.
And when you hit the tab key,
it will automatically insert four spaces,
which you can tell when you're trying to highlight this space,
you can see the cursor is jumping four times.
This means that you get to hit tab once and that your code is in line with the
guidance because the hind the scenes
your code editor is inserting four spaces.
So I hope that clears up a little bit on tabs versus spaces.
And I highly recommend you to head over to the course resources and click on the link
to go to the style guide for Python code and take a look through the parts about
indentation. Now in the next lesson, I've got a quick quiz for you
to test your knowledge on indentation. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right guys, in this lesson
I want to talk about the while loop, the loop that will continue going while a
particular condition is true.
This is a really simple version of a robot that's using a while loop.
So in this case,
the instruction would be while you are plugged into the wall and you have
electricity move forwards. So this is what happens.
It will stop once it pulls the socket out of the wall and it stops receiving
electricity. Let's compare this against the
for loop that we've seen before. So we've seen sort of two flavors of the
for loop: one where we're looping through a list of items to do something with
each item in the list,
and the other is using a range function where we create a range between a and b
and then we use every number in that range to do something. For example,
in this case would be to print it out. The while loop looks
something like this. And in this case,
while this particular condition is true,
then we go inside the loop and we do something repeatedly.
And it's only when the something becomes false does the loop stop.
So let's take a look at what the code would look like in real life.
So here I have the Hurdle 1 challenge that you did previously.
And for this
we created a for loop in order to get our robot to jump over the hurdle six
times to get to the final destination.
Now we could also do the same thing, but using a while loop.
And this is how we would do it.
Let's say we create a variable called a number_of_hurdles,
and we set that equal to six because there are six hurdles.
And then we use a while loop to loop through these hurdles until this goes down
to zero. So we can say while number_of_hurdles
Right,
> 0:
and then we get it to do something. Well in this case,
what we need it to do is to perform the jump function.
And at the end of the loop, just before we go back to the beginning,
we're going to decrease the number of hurdles,
Right
by one., -= 1.
So now let's go ahead and delete this version using the for loop. And in order to
better visualize what's happening here
I'm actually also going to add a print statement to print that variable.
Right?
So now let's step through this.
And the first time we enter the while loop, number_of_hurdles equals six,
six is greater than zero.
Then that is a go ahead to jump into the loop and execute these three lines of
code. So now we go in and it performs the jump function.
And then once that's done, it comes back, goes onto the next line,
number_of_hurdles minus equals one, so six should become five.
So now when it executes this print function, we should see five printed.
So lets move this little pop up away on the side and let's keep going.
So now it's gone back to the beginning of the while loop and it's testing this
condition once more: is the number of hurdles, five, still greater than zero.
Well, so if it's true,
then it goes into the while loop again and performs all of those lines of code.
So now it's minus one and it should now be four.
And it keeps on going until the point where this condition number_of_hurdles
greater than zero becomes false.
So now this is the moment where we're going to subtract a further one from our
number of hurdles, which is currently one.
So that should take it down to zero. And once that's done,
this condition is no longer true. Zero is not greater than zero.
Zero is equal to zero, but it's not greater.
So now this is false and we exit out of the while loop and we end our program.
This is what the syntax for the while loop looks like. First,
we have the while keyword and then we have some sort of condition that we're
going to test.
So previously you saw it was number of hurdles being greater than zero,
and whenever that condition is true,
then it's going to look inside the while loop at the indented lines of code to
carry out those instructions, to do this, then do this, then do this.
And finally, when it gets to the end of the while loop,
it comes back to the beginning and tests this condition again.
And if it's still true,
then it's going to go through and loop and loop and loop until this condition
becomes false at which point it ends an exits the while loop.
So now coming back to our Reeborg's World,
I want you to click on this dropdown and go to hurdle number 2.
Now this is a little bit different.
And if you want to see the explanation for this exercise,
then simply just click on this 'World Info' and you'll see the explanation.
So essentially this hurdle's race is a little bit different from the last one.
Whereas the last one
we knew that we had to always complete six hurdles to get to the goalpost.
In this case, we no longer know where the flag is going to be.
So it could be here, it could be here, it could be here, et cetera.
And it's going to be set randomly to one of these positions.
But what we now get is some sort of condition called at_goal.
And if this at_goal is true then it means our robot has landed on a flag.
But if this at_goal is not true,
then it means that it's not yet reached the flag.
So we can use our knowledge of while loops as well as this condition to use our
code that we had from previously to get our robot to complete this hurdle race.
So you should still have the code from the previous challenge up
and all you have to do is to think about how you would create a while loop so
that when you run this program and the flag is set randomly...
So this time it was set to be here, but the next time I run it,
you can see it's now set here. It doesn't matter where the flag is,
your robot should be able to detect if it's at flag, if its at the goal,
and if it's not then it should continue jumping.
Pause the video quickly and see if you can complete this challenge and then come
back and we'll walk through the solution together.
Right?
All right.
So first things first, we know that we're going to need to use a while loop and
the condition that we're going to be testing for is this one, at_goal.
This condition can be true or it can be false.
And basically we're looking to see while at_goal is not equal to true,
so while our robot is not at the goal,
then we want to perform the jump function.
So we're going to jump for as many times as it is required until this at_goal
becomes true.
Another way of expressing this at_goal is not true is to say while not at_goal.
So this is what they mean by the negation of this condition.
Either way of testing this will work. And now if I hit run,
you can see that even though we only need to perform one hurdle,
as soon as our robot gets here and it checks that at_goal is true then it will
stop this loop.
But if our loop goes on for much longer, say the goal is over here,
then once it reaches here and at_goal is still false,
then it's going to continue jumping until at_goal becomes true.
So that required a little bit of mental jujitsu
I think because this entire condition has to be true,
but this at_goal is actually going to be false until the moment where we
reached the goal. So by adding this not
we effectively flip this at_goal. So if it was true,
becomes false or if it's false becomes true in order to continue jumping while
we're not at the goal.
I prefer this particular type of syntax because it reads more like English: while
not at goal then perform jump.
And if it is at_goal then it will stop.
And one of the things you might be wondering right now is,
so I've learned about the for loop and I've learned about a while loop.
And if I can use both of them, why would I choose one over the other?
When would I use a for loop? And when would I use a while loop? Well,
what I would tend to say is that for loops are really great
when you want to iterate over something and you need to do something with each
thing that you are iterating over. So for example,
if you're iterating through a list and you're saying for each fruit in our list
of fruits and you want to be able to say, I don't know,
do something with each of these items in here. For instance,
it can be as simple as just printing it. Well,
then this will require a for loop.
You can't do this very easily using a while loop. Now,
similarly we've used the range function, right?
So for range from one to six print each number in the range.
Well this it's also easy to do with a for loop.
Now you want to be using a while loop when you don't really care what number in a
sequence you're
in, which item you're iterating through in a list and you just simply want to carry
out some sort of functionality many,
many times until some sort of condition that you set.
And this is also a good point to mention that while loops are a little bit more
dangerous than for loops because in for loops, you're setting ahead of time
how many times something is going to run.
It's going to stop once it reaches the end of the list of items in this case,
and it's going to stop once it reaches the upper bound of the range in this
case. But for while loops,
they will continue running until this particular condition switches to false.
So if you have some sort of condition that actually never becomes false, well
then your while loop becomes something known as an infinite loop. Because let's
say that our while loop tested while five is greater than three,
then carry out these three lines of code. Well,
five is always going to be larger than three until the end of time.
And so that means your code is also going to run until the end of time,
which is probably not what you want in most cases. If
instead of saying, while not at_goal, I said, while five is greater than three,
then you're going to see this robot perform this jump until eternity.
And it's basically going to stop only once it's crashed and timed out.
Now every single program at some point in their lives will create an infinite
loop. Don't worry about it. Just quit the program,
restart and try to prevent this from happening in the future.
And very often I find that it's really helpful when you don't know why you're
getting an infinite loop to simply just print out your condition.
So in this case, if I printed out five greater than three,
then it's always going to print true.
And it's never going to become false basically. In the next lesson,
I've got more exercises coming up for you, namely hurdles 3 and 4.
So head over there and put what you've learned about while loops into practice.
All right guys, it's time for yet another coding challenge.
And this coding challenge is going to put into use what you've learned about
while loops,
while also testing some of the previous knowledge you got on functions.
So I want you to head back to Reeborg's World and change to hurdle number 3.
And take a look at the premise for this particular race.
Right?
Essentially what's happened this time is that the wall placement has become
random. So let's say we restart this game, you can see that in this case,
there's a wall here, one here, one here, one here. There's four in total.
But if we try a different version,
then you can see that there is different wall placement each time.
Not only don't we know where the wall is going to be,
we also don't know how many walls there will be.
So code such as what we did before using a for loop
telling our robot to jump six times is not going to work.
And instead, we're going to have to use the conditions
whether if front is clear or whether if there's a wall in front or whether
if we're at the goal and also their negations,
so not front is clear, not wall in front,
not at goal. See if you can use what you've learned about while loops
as well as your previous knowledge on if statements and functions to complete
this challenge. When you have written the correct code,
no matter what kind of wall situation or hurdle setup they have,
it should always be able to get to the goal.
And while I've been looking at this challenge, I know there is a very,
very simple way of bypassing this challenge,
which is simply to get the robots go up here and all the way down here,
going past all the hurdles.
But that's not the point of the challenge. In order to complete this challenge,
you must get your robot to follow the path that set out in the dotted lines
instead of bypassing it and doing something completely different
just to get to the final goal. Pause the video, have a think about this,
have a read of the world info popup here,
and then think about how you can solve this challenge. So give it a go now.
Right?
All right. So essentially, if we don't know where the walls are going to be,
then we have to test to see if there is a wall in front,
or if there is no wall in front.
And if there is a wall in front, then we're going to jump.
But if there's no wall in front, then we're just going to move forwards.
And we're going to do this and test this for as long as we're not at the goal.
So we're going to need a while loop
that's very similar to our previous while loop that I showed you in the demo. While
we're not at goal or rather while
this particular condition is not true,
then we're going to repeat and loop some lines of code.
The first thing we're going to do is we're going to use an if statement to check
whether if there is a wall in front.
So I'm going to say, if wall in front,
if this is true,
then I'm going to perform the jump function and get it to jump over the wall.
But if there is no wall in front, so namely else,
well, in this case, we're simply just going to move forwards.
And because our jump function is always going to get us to face the right way,
which is this direction here towards the goal,
then this move forward by one function is always going to take us in this
direction.
So let's take a look at this code and let's step through it step by step.
So the first thing we're going to check is are we at the goal. At_goal is going
to be false. So not false is going to be true.
So while this condition is true,
we're going to carry out all the lines of code inside.
So that means we should jump into this if statement and check
is there a wall in front? So at this point,
this should be false because there is nothing in front.
So it should bypass the if statement and it should go to the else statement.
In which case it should move forward by one step. So that's the end of one loop
and we go back to the beginning: are we at the goal yet? Nope, we are not.
But now when we run into our if statement,
this check should now come up as true,
because there is a wall right in front of our robot. So in this case,
it's going to go into the if statement and perform the jump function.
Now our jump function that we defined previously actually gets us to move
forward by one step first,
before we actually hurdle over this wall. So in this case,
if we try to do the same thing,
then it's actually going to hit our robot into a wall.
We have to modify our jump function by removing this first move function.
So instead we get it to just turn left, go up, turn right,
go right, turn right, go down and then turn left to face the right direction.
This is a pure hurdle without that extra step in the beginning.
And instead we're going to only move if there is no wall in front.
So we've changed the code.
Let's back it up and try this again with a different setup.
And in this case, you can see as my code is going through the different steps,
it's checking to see if there's a wall in front. If there is,
then it's going to jump over it. If there isn't,
it's just going to move forward by one step and then it's going to reevaluate.
So this way, once it gets to here,
it's actually going to reevaluate the while loop quite a few times
and every time it's going to be the else statement that fires.
It's going to move, move, move, move, move until it hits a wall again
and then it's going to jump over and take us to the finishing line.
Did you manage to get this correct? Did you manage to get the solution right?
If not be sure to review the previous lessons on the while loop so that you
familiarize yourself with it
and also if you got stuck on changing the jump function,
then be sure to remember that whenever you get stuck,
it's important to test your assumptions. And in this case,
you could have pressed the step-through button many times to see which line of
code is being triggered at which point,
and which is the moment where our code actually fails
so you can figure it out and fix it.
Now on the next lesson, I've got yet another code challenge for you.
So head over there and give it a go.
All right guys, it's time for the final hurdle
before we get to our goal post. In this lesson,
I want you to switch over to the final hurdle challenge, which is hurdle 4.
And in this particular version of the hurdle,
the wall that the robot has to jump over to now has a variable height.
So the height of each of these hurdles is completely random,
the position of the hurdles are random
and also the number of hurdles is also going to be random.
You can see that every single time that this regenerates,
it comes up with a completely different set of hurdle profiles.
And now we can't just jump because we don't know what the height will be each
time.
So we have to use what we've learned about while loops to modify this jump
function and see if we can get the jump to jump as high as necessary
depending on the height of these walls. Just as a reminder,
in order to complete this challenge,
you should take a look at the Reeborg's keyboard window and go to this tab called
conditions and see that you can check if the front of the robot is clear,
if it's right is clear, if there's a wall on the front,
if there's a wall on the right and various other things.
The ones that are probably going to be the most useful is this top row here.
So I want you to take a look at these conditions,
see how they're spelt and how you can use them,
and then try to use them and test them out using your Reeborg robot.
Now, the goal is of course
to reach this final flag going over various hurdles
using this dotted line as the path, which is going to be different each time.
Just as a head up, this is going to require you to modify this jump function.
Have a serious think about it because it's not easy
and you're going to need to use more while loops to achieve this end outcome. And
try to see if you can solve this challenge in the least lines of code possible.
So I managed to do it in as little as 24 lines of code,
so see if you can aim to achieve that.
Pause the video now and give this challenge a go.
Right?
All right.
So the key difference between this particular hurdle and the previous version is
that the height of the wall is now random. Instead of just jumping over one
square, where we turn left, move, turn right, move, turn right move,
we have to now see if the right side has a wall,
or if it's completely clear. Now, in this case,
what I want to happen is I want to turn my robot to the left first of all,
and then I want to check if there is a wall on the right.
So I can use this condition wall on right to achieve this.
And if that is true,
then I want to continue moving forward until there is no longer a wall on the
right, in which case I'm going to turn right turn right
and then start going down. So let's modify this jump function.
We definitely need the robot turn left, but after it turns left,
we're going to use a while loop to say that while there is a wall on the right
then in this case, we're going to move forwards.
So we're going to go up in this direction basically
because we've turned left already.
Let's test this out and let's run this code.
You can see in this version of events,
my robot is going to keep going until the very end of the screen.
This is not what we want.
So what we want to do is when this is no longer true,
it's going to skip to line 10. So at this point,
there is no longer a wall on the right,
because otherwise it would have continued looping and calling this line 9
where it gets it to move forward. When there's no longer a wall on the right,
then we want to do what we did previously
which is to get our robot to turn right move,
and then turn right. Now at this point, we have to move down the wall.
And what we're going to check is whether if the front is clear,
because it's only when we reach the very bottom here, when the front is blocked,
do we actually turn left again and continue back to our while loop here to move
forward. To do this we're going to add yet another while loop.
And in this case, we're going to use the front_is_clear condition.
While the front is clear,
we're going to get the robot to continue moving forward.
So once it's turned to face this direction, and there's no wall in front,
it's going to keep going until this is no longer true.
And that is the end of our jump.
So now we've basically modified this jump function to take into account all of
these new things such as while there's a wall on the right
then continue moving upwards, while the front is clear when it's coming down
then continue moving downwards. And then at the very end,
we're going to get our robot to turn left so that we're ready to go and check if
we're at the goal. And if we're not at the goal,
then we're going to check if there's a wall in front,
if there is a wall in front that we're going to jump,
otherwise we're going to continue moving forwards or rather to the right to get
to the goal. So now this is the final code.
And depending on the number of spaces you've added in here,
obviously it's a little bit easier to read if you actually have it like this.
But depending on how you've spaced things out in your code,
you should end up with anywhere between say 20 to 24 lines of code.
So I want you to be able to see all of these lines of code on the right when we
run this code.
And I've actually got a typo in here that it's going to tell me.
So it's going to say invalid syntax
and the problem is just because I forgot a colon here. If you get that
pop-up invalid syntax
be sure to check if you have any problems in here and it can get a little bit
complicated if you leave your code for a long period of time before you test it.
So test your code after every little iteration
and then when you actually get something like an invalid syntax,
you'll be able to catch it more easily.
So now let's go ahead and regenerate our map and let's try it again.
So when we're going to make a jump and then we're gonna turn right,
and we're going to keep going down until we hit the wall and we turned left,
and now we're not out the goal, and there's still a wall in front.
So we make another jump and we go down this much, much larger wall.
And then we continue this process of using several while loops,
checking if there's a wall on the right, checking if the front is clear,
checking
if there's a wall in the front in order to achieve our goal and get to our final
destination. Now for your code to successfully complete this challenge,
the line that your robot draws should follow the line that started here,
just like what you see here.
So instead of going just over the top and getting to the final goal,
it should follow each of these steps and finally
you should get that green pop-up where it says it's at the right position.
So did you manage to complete this challenge?
If not, be sure to review the lesson on while loops and just have a play around
with while loops.
Try some of the different conditions and see what happens when you run the code
and see how the robot behaves so that you get a good grasp of how these things
actually work.
Now on the next lesson is our final project and we're going to get our robot to
be able to navigate a maze all by itself using what we've learned
including functions as well as while loops, as well as using good indentation.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right guys, it's time for the final project of today.
And the goal is to be able to write some code here in Reeborg's world,
to be able to get our the little robot
to be able to navigate to the goal and go through a maze
no matter what the maze look like. So if you go back to Reeborgs world,
if you already got a link open..
if you don't, then simply click on the direct link in the course resources
and it should take you here.
And we've got the maze selected in the dropdown, which is right here.
Here, we have a maze. And even though the maze doesn't change,
the robot does. The direction that the robot is going to face is completely
random, the position of the robot is also random.
So you can see every time I restart the game,
it will face a different direction. So in this case, it's facing up
But the next time it might be facing down, in this case.
And it's also always going to start at a random location in the maze.
If you click on the world info,
it will tell you that the secret to getting the robot to complete the maze is to
get it to follow along the right edge of the maze.
If it starts anywhere in the maze and it just continues following along
the right wall,
it should eventually get to the final destination.
For example, like this. Now in this case,
the robot is not making a beeline straight to the exit as if it could see what
we can see, but it is following a strategy or rather what you would call in
programming, an algorithm.
And the algorithm here is to simply follow along the right edge of the wall.
And if the right side is clear,
then continue going right until it's no longer clear at which point it should
just go straight. And if you can't go straight and you can't go right,
then the last option is to turn left.
It's almost like the robot is getting a set of instructions in terms of
hierarchy. The most important telling it to turn right if it can,
if it can't turn right then go straight ahead. And finally,
if it can't turn right or go straight ahead,
then to turn left as a last resort.
So you're going to need to use a lot of the functions that you saw previously
such as move, turn_left, and testing
whether if the front is clear or the right is clear,
or there's a wall in the front or a wall in the right. And whether
if the robot is the goal. Think about how you can use a while loop
and also the conditional
if, elif, else statements to achieve this goal and get our robot
to be able to go to the final destination
no matter where it starts out and what direction it's facing.
Pause the video now
and try to use what you've learned to complete this final project.
[inaudible]
All right. So did you manage to complete this challenge? If not,
let's work through the solution together. The first thing we need to do,
which we've always pretty much needed completing each of these challenges, is we
need a way to turn right. So I'm not gonna type it all out again.
This should be already pretty clear; turn_right
is just turning left three times. Now,
the next thing we need to do is we need to tell the robot to do things and to
check for things until it reaches the goal.
We know that we have this test called at_goal.
So we can use a while loop to get the robot to continue working until it reaches
the goal. To define that, we could say while not at goal,
so basically keep repeating the instructions inside this while loop until at_goal
becomes true and not true is false.
So once this condition becomes false, then our while loop stops.
So what we were told in the world info is we should follow along the right edge.
We should test to see if the right side is clear, and if it is,
then we should turn right and go straight.
So that basically means moving right.
Let's use an if statement to test
if right_is_clear and in this instance,
so in this if block, we're going to say well turn_right
using our prebuilt function up here.
And then once you're facing the right then move forwards.
This should achieve a right move, so from here to here
for example.
Now let's test this and see what happens. In this case, the right is clear
so it moved right The right is not clear
so it doesn't know what else to do
and it's now stuck in what we would call an infinite loop.
And it will never stop until the browser actually forces it to by crashing.
So what we have to do instead is we have to provide an alternative condition;
when the right is not clear, what should it do?
So we're going to provide that condition by using an elif statement.
And what we want to say is if the right is not clear,
well, then maybe you should check if the front is clear.
And if that is the case, then simply just move forwards.
Now, this would work unless we're in the situation that we're in right now
where we're boxed in
and the only side that's clear is actually the remaining one, which is the left.
That's why we have to put in the last line of code
which is going to be an else statement. So in all other conditions, um,
when the right is not clear and the front is not clear,
so once both of these have been checked and they're false,
then actually just turn left.
So now
you can see that when our robot is able to go right,
it will try to follow along the right wall.
But when it can't go right, it will go forwards instead.
And when it can't go right or go forward, then it's gonna turn left
and hopefully the next time it checks the loop,
the front will be clear and it will be able to move forwards.
So notice how our robot is somewhat haphazardly navigating through this maze,
but it is following the algorithm that we specified,
which is to follow along the right-handed wall until you reach the goal.
And that's what these few lines of code does using our while statements, our if,
elif, else statements and also our turn_right function.
Now, while everything seems to work all right,
there are select cases where the robot might start out in a position and face a
particular direction that gets the robot into an endless loop.
So here's an example.
Let's say the robot starts off at this particular position facing down.
If we go ahead and let the robot run the code,
you can see that firstly, there's over a thousand steps in the code.
And what happens is because the robot doesn't have a wall on it's right,
it's going to keep looping through the circle because after all we're telling it
if your right side is clear,
turn right and move. And the right is always clear when it's inside this
boundary box. So depending on where the robot starts out,
it might get itself into what we call it an infinite loop,
because you can see the code just goes again and again,
through this while statement, and the robot's never going to be able to escape
from this position.
So this is one of the things that happens to your programs.
Sometimes there are edge cases which you might not have thought of
but it's only through testing the code do you discover them.
Now this particular issue I would say is more of an intermediate debugging
problem.
So if you're somebody who's already really comfortable with Python and you want
to try out debugging this particular problem,
then I've included some problem worlds for you to test your code against.
Now,
if you are somebody who is still getting to grips with Python,
I would say this is not the right time point to tackle this challenge,
and I would go ahead and make a note to yourself that once you've completed day
15 and you're firmly within the intermediate territory of Python to come back to
this problem and to continue to debug this particular edge case.
Now, if you are a beginner, I recommend to skip the rest of the video
but make a bookmark and make a note here so that you know to come back. Now,
if you are more of an intermediate programmer,
then let's go ahead and debug this.
So what you can do with Reeborg's world is you can actually create a file to load
up a particular map and robot position.
So what I've done is I've created a bunch of problem worlds for you to test your
code against that we know if you use a normal code,
it's definitely going to get into an infinite loop.
So what you need to do is head to the course resources for this lesson
and then download the zip file
which contains three problem worlds for you to test your code against.
And then in Reeborgs world, you're going to click on additional options,
open world from file and you're going to select that folder
which hopefully you've unzipped, and go through each of these problem worlds
testing your code in all of the cases. Now, when you open this up,
you can close off this box and the robot will start at a particular problem
position, facing a direction that is going to cause it to go into an
infinite loop. And you can know this ahead of time
because when you actually go to start the robot and you hit play, when you
see the number of steps here over a thousand,
it usually means that you're probably in a situation where it's going to turn into
an infinite loop.
So write your code here and then test it to make sure that the step count goes
down below 1000 and your robot doesn't get stuck in this endless circle. Now,
because the different problem worlds can have different solutions,
but what you're aiming for is one solution code that solves all of the problem
worlds,
I want you to test your code against all three of these problem worlds I've
created for you.
So here's the time, if you want to tackle this challenge, to go ahead and pause
the video and see if you can debug this pretty hard problem.
It took me a while. So I think it's going to take you a while as well.
But you might be smarter. It might take less time. So good luck,
pause the video and we'll go through the solution together a little bit later
on.
All right. So first let's try and figure out what the problem is.
The problem here is that every time when the robot's right side is clear,
our code tells it to turn to that direction, move forwards,
and then check to see if it's at the goal. So it's not, and again
the right side is clear so it turns right and moves, turns right and moves,
turns right and moves. So basically in any of these four positions,
depending on the way it's facing,
there might not be a wall on the right side of the robot.
So that is the key to solving this bug.
We have to get our robot to a starting position where it has a wall on the right
side of the robot.
Now I've been thinking about various ways of doing this and the shortest most
succinct way that's also most understandable, I think, is this.
So if we create another while loop before this while loop runs,
so remember the code goes from top to bottom,
it's going to hit this while loop first.
And we check while the front is clear,
well then the robot is not next to a wall, right? Such as in this case.
Well, if that is the case, we're going to tell our robot to just move forwards.
So this means that our robot is going to seek out a wall. So in this case,
for example,
it's going to go forwards until it reaches a wall.
So it's going to loop through that loop twice and it moves twice until it hits a
wall in front. Now this is the point which we want,
because we want to make sure that now that it's hit a wall in front,
that it's definitely got a wall on the right side of the robot. So what do we do?
Well, once it's hit a wall, so it's exited this while loop,
we're going to tell it to turn left.
So this loop makes sure that the robot has a wall in front of it.
And once it's found a wall in front, we tell it to turn left
to turn that wall on to the right side of the robot.
So now you can see we're going through this while loop. First front is clear,
so it's going to move.
And then front is still clear after that one move
so it's going to move again until it's hit a wall in front. Now,
at this point,
it exits the while loop and it goes to the next line of instruction
which tells it to turn left. Now that the robot has turned left
it now has a wall on the right side and it enters the next loop.
So in this loop, if the right side is clear, turn right and move.
If the front is clear, just simply move forward, otherwise turn left.
So as long as the robot started in a position where there is a wall on the right
side of it, right next to it, it's never going to get into that infinite loop with
this code. So this is one solution to this problem.
Now there's lots of other solutions,
but you gotta make sure that your solution works in every single one of these
test cases.
So we can go ahead and open up problem world 2 where the robot starts at a
different position, facing a different position,
and we want to make sure that still we don't have an infinite loop. In this case,
it doesn't. So that's great. And finally, let's test the last one,
which is a problem world 3,
and now we can run our program and you can see it's also less than a thousand
steps. So, it works.
So this is a bit of advanced debugging because we're now testing our
code against various terrible scenarios where the robot starts off at a position
where it's really dangerous and can get into these infinite loops. Now,
if you didn't manage to get the solution,
don't despair and don't be too hard on yourself. This is a really,
really hard one.
And it took me a long time to find a solution that I think is readable and
explainable and sort of makes sense.
Now, it might be that you should put in a note in your calendar to come and
revisit this issue in a week
once you've had some time to think about it, and to really digest and understand
the solution, then write the code yourself.
Because you would have forgotten exactly what the code was,
but you will still remember how it works. So if that is a case,
this is what you should do. If you solved it by yourself, then congratulations.
This is really, truly quite a difficult task.
Hey guys,
welcome to Day 7 of 100 Days of code.
Now,
today we have a whole day dedicated to a really cool project.
And what we're going to be building throughout this day is basically Hangman or
the code equivalent of this game.
So the way the game works is you have to guess a word and for every wrong
letter you submit,
you end up taking a life away from this little man. And of course,
the longer it takes you to get to the word,
the more you put your little man in danger.
This is what the final completed project is going to look like.
We're going to have some really cool ASCII art like this hangman logo up here
and it's going to ask us to guess or a letter. So let's try A,
and you can see that's not in the word.
So we lose a life and it starts drawing our little hangman.
So let's try another letter, E. There's a lot of Es in there.
So we managed to get that. Let's try a T,
Right?
And I think I know what the word is now just before my little man is going to
die. I think it's beekeeper. There we go. We got it.
So if we had lost just one more life,
the leg would have been added and we would have lost,
but we managed to get there in the end.
So this is what the completed game looks like and how it plays out.
And you can go over to the final URL and run the code and see it in action if
you want to. But just by building this game,
we're going to be able to review and test ourselves on a bunch of concepts that
we've already covered,
like for and while loops or if and else statements, lists,
strings, the range, function, modules, and much, much more.
So I hope you're as excited as I am to get started on this project,
and once you already head over to the next lesson and let's begin.
All right guys. So before we get started with our project,
it's really important that we're all on the same page and we understand how the
code is going to work because we know how the game works.
So I recommend that if you've never heard of this game hangman,
then before you continue to just head over to the Wikipedia article on hangman,
and it might be even easier if you select your own language
because I know that it has a different name in different languages. Now,
if you've never played this game,
I always recommend just go and give it a go online.
So a link to this address, and if you click on single player untimed,
you can see that you have a word that you have to guess,
and then you start picking some letters. And if it's right,
then it goes in and if it's wrong,
then the hangman gallows start being drawn and our little man is at risk of
being hung. Once you understand how the game works,
it's time for us to examine what the logic for our program is going to look
like. And to do that, we're going to use flow chart programming.
So it's very simple.
It just means that we can draw out a flow chart to represent the logic of our
game. At this point,
I want you to pause the video and have a quick think about how you would program
hangman.
Try and come up with a flow chart that represents the logic of this game.
Break it down into little steps. What needs to happen first,
what needs to happen when the user makes a guess, and what should happen when the
guest is incorrect, when should the game end? Pause the video
now, take a pencil and a piece of paper, or use draw.io to create your flowchart.
Right?
So how did that go? Did you break down the problem?
It's really important to say that there's no single right answer here.
And there's loads of ways that you could have done this,
but let me show you my approach,
which is how we'll write our program over the next couple of lessons.
So this is what it looks like from start to end.
And if we zoom in a bit, let's go through this flow chart
step-by-step so we're all on the same page. At the start of the game
the first thing we do is to generate a random word. Let's say, in this case
it was the word mouse.
Now the next step is to generate as many blanks as the letters in the word.
So we have these blanks to show the user
how many letters are in this word that they need to guess. They don't get to see
this, but they get to see this. And the next step they get to
guess a letter.
So let's say the user in this case guessed the letter O. Well,
the next thing we have to check is, is the guessed letter actually in the word?
Well, in this case, o it is indeed in mouse.
It's the one at the second position.
And so we go down this path and we answer yes to that question.
So now we to replace that blank with the letter O.
Now the next stage is we have to check are the blanks filled, are all of these
blanks removed because in that case,
it means the user is guessed all of the letters correctly? Well at the moment,
it's definitely a no, cause we've only guessed one letter.
So then we go all the way back to the beginning and we ask the user to guess
another letter. Now at some stage of the game,
all the letters will be guessed. And then we can answer yes to this question,
which means it's game over. The user has won because they've guessed all the
letters correctly. Now,
if we go back to the part where we ask the user to guess a letter,
and they guessed a letter, say the letter z
which doesn't actually exist in this word mouse, while then in this case,
we go down this right path to answer no
and the user loses a life,
which means we start drawing out a hangman figure. Now,
depending on whether if they have run out of lives,
if the hangman man has been drawn completely, then they would go down this path.
But at the moment they've only lost one life and this figure is not complete
so the answer is no.
And that means we go back to the beginning and we get them to guess the next
letter. Now,
if at the stage where they've exhausted all of their lives and the hangman
figure is complete, well, then it's the end of the game
and they've basically just lost without having guessed
all of the letters in the word. So this is the logic,
and you might need to come back to this video a few times
if you get stuck along the way just to review how the program flows.
But it might also be worth creating your own flow chart or simply downloading
this completed flowchart I have here in the course resources.
It's a really useful tool to come back to and refer to as you're writing the
code,
because this will give you an overview of what you're trying to get your code to
do.
And hopefully this is going to make it easier for you to complete the upcoming
challenges in this project. Once you are ready, head over to the next lesson,
and let's get started.
All right guys. So to get started head over to the starting Repl.it file
which you'll be able to find in the course resources,
and you should see a pretty much empty file as well as three to-dos for you to
complete. All I've got here is a list of three words,
ardvark, baboon, and camel.
And we're going to be choosing a random word from that list
and then we're going to ask the user to guess a letter,
and then we're going to check if that letter matches one of the letters in the
chosen word.
So we're basically just tackling the first part of this flowchart up to about
here. Once you've completed all three to-dos here,
you should have something that will function more or less like this.
So this is the end result of step 1
and it should ask us to guess a letter. So let me try a.
And it shows me that this a matches with the first letter in the word,
as well as the fourth letter in the word.
So I'm pretty sure that the word that it picks randomly was actually ardvark.
Essentially, your code is gonna loop through each of the letters in the chosen
word,
and then check it against the word that the user entered and report back
whether if it matched any of the letters in the word. Now,
if you need a hint,
then head over to the course resources and you'll see a link that's marked as a
hint. And once you click on it,
it'll take you to this page where it talks about how to use the for loop
with a list in Python. Have a read through the section and then go back,
try to tackle the to-dos and see if that helps you. All right.
So have a play around with the final version and once you're ready,
go-ahead fork a copy of the starting file for day 7 step one,
and tackle the to-dos one by one. Good luck.
All right.
So how did you get on? Now if you got stuck or you want to see maybe how I did
it, then continue watching and I'll go through the solution with you.
So first things first, head over to the link and fork your own copy.
Once you've done that, we're going to tackle the to-dos one by one
in order. The first one
asks us to randomly choose a word from the word_list and assign it to a variable
called chosen_word.
So in order to randomly get an item out of the list,
we're going to need to import the random module.
And once we've got hold of that, then we can say random.choice
and if we put inside the parentheses
the list that we want to randomly choose from,
then we should be able to get hold of a single item from this list randomly.
And then finally, we're going to assign it to a variable called chosen_word.
So let's call that chosen_word and then set it to equal this result.
So that's to-do 1 completed. The next todo we have to ask the user to guess a
letter and assign their answer to a variable called guess. And finally make that
guess lowercase. In order to ask the user for anything,
we're going to have to create an input. And let's say,
"Guess a letter:"
And then we can assign their answer
which will replace this line of code with a variable called guess.
So we'll just set that equal to guess. And finally,
we're going to make this guess lower case and we do that by writing .lower.
Now step 3 ask us to check if the letter the user guessed,
which is this guess variable, is one of the letters in the chosen_word.
So this randomly chosen word could be any one of these: ardvack, baboon, or camel.
And we have to somehow check if this letter
which is stored inside this variable guess matches any of the letters inside
this list of words. So, as I mentioned as a hint,
you can have a look at this document from Google for education,
which talks about various things in Python.
And the part I wanted to draw your attention to is the for loop
which we covered previously. So we know that we can use the for loop like this
to loop through a particular list and get hold of each of the items in the list,
like this. So in our case,
all we have to do is say for letter in chosen word,
so this is going to go through this chosen word letter by letter
and each time the loop runs,
we'll get hold of one of letters inside the word.
So the first time that letter variable will equal a, the next time
it will be equal to r and so on and so forth.
So now inside our for loop
we can check to see if the letter that we're currently looking at is double
equals to the letter that the user guessed and in this case,
well then that means its a match, right?
So we're going to print either a match or in my case, I'm just going to write,
uh, Right. And else, namely if it doesn't match,
then we're going to print wrong. That's it.
That's all we have to do to complete all three to-dos.
And now if I run this code,
you can see it's going to ask me to guess a letter. So let's put a,
and then it goes through this loop line by line
to check against this letter that I've guessed. So I'm guessing in this case
the chosen word is aardvark.
So when the loop is running through the first letter a and a match,
so it says right. Then the next time it's looking at the letter
r, a and r does not match
so we get wrong and it continues until it finds all the matches and all the ones
that don't match. Now, if you want to check your code against mine,
simply head over to the URL that's listed in the course resources under app
brewery/day-7-Hangman-1-End
and here you'll be able to see all the code that I went through with you just
now. Now, if you had any issues
understanding how the code worked or how to get to the final solution,
and if you're at all confused,
I recommend putting the code through Thonny and just clicking on the debug to go
through each of the steps one by one. So in this line,
we're going to use the random module and get hold of a random item from this
list.
So, in this case, it's picked camel. And now that camel is going to be equal to
the variable chosen_word.
So on the next step we ask the user to guess a letter.
And once we step into that,
it's going to print that out into the debug console.
And if I put a and hit enter, then guess is now equal to a,
and there's our second variable guess, which is equal to a.
Now we fall into our for loop. And if we step into the loop,
then you can see that the chosen_word is going to be replaced with camel and
letter is going to be replaced with each of the letters in the chosen word one
by one. So the first time loop runs, it's going to be c,
and then it checks to see, well, if c is equal to guess,
which is a, does that match? No, it doesn't.
So it jumps to the else part and it prints out wrong.
And then the loop is going to restart from the top
and we're going to go to the next letter in the chosen word,
which is a. Now in this case, the letter is a
and the guest is a and so that should match. And so it should print,
right.
And then it basically steps through all of these again and again
until we get to the end of the word and we get this printed out.
So have a play around with that and the debug console to wrap your head around
it. And once you're confident, you know, what's going on,
then head over to the next lesson and let's complete step 2.
All right. So now that you've tackled step one,
let's continue building out our project by doing step two. Again,
we have three to-dos in the starting file.
And what we're going to try and do here is we're going to generate a list with
as many of these blanks
which is represented by an underscore string as there are letters in the chosen
word. So for example, if the chosen word was apple with five letters,
then we should be able to create a list with five items and each of them being
an underscore. So then in the next stage,
we can replace some of the items inside that list with the correct letter
if the user guesses it right. So for example,
if the word was apple and the user guessed the letter p,
then we should be able to loop through each of the letters in the word.
And for every letter that it matches,
we replace the underscore with the actual letter.
So then we end up with a list that looks like this. Finally,
you're going to print that out and we should be able to see it in the console.
In the starting file, you'll notice I've added a little bit of testing code
which is just a print statement telling us what the chosen wood is,
and this will make it easier for us to debug and figure out if our code is not
doing what we want it to do. So once you've completed all of the
to-dos in step two, then this is what you should get. In this case,
the chosen word is baboon. So if,
I guess the letter b, because I'm cheating
and also because I'm trying to test the code, and I hit enter,
then you can see that it should print out a list with one,
two, three, four, five, six,
six items in it because there's six letters in baboon,
and each of the letters which I've guessed correctly in the right
are replaced in the list in the correct position. B occurs in the first and the
third letter,
so that is what's showing up in this list and everything else is still the
underscore because they're blanks and still need to be guessed.
Have a play around with the final version of the code
and once you're ready, head back, fork
the starting project and complete the to-dos in order. Now,
if you need a hint and you get stuck,
be sure to check the course resources for a link that links to again,
a Google for Education page
and have a read through the section on the range function that we learned about
in previous lessons.
Remind yourself of how it works and then go back to your code and try to tackle
it and see if you can get it to do what it needs to. Good luck
and I'll see you on the other side,
All right, let's go ahead and run through the solution together. Firstly,
I'm going to fork my own copy of the starting file for step two
and then I'm going to take a look at to-do number one.
So the goal is to create an empty list called display,
and for each letter in the chosen word,
remember that a random word from this list,
we're going to add an underscore to this list called display.
So it tells us that if the word was apple,
then display should contain five underscores representing each letter the
user needs to guess.
Let's go ahead and just click run before doing anything first.
And this print statement will execute and it'll tell us that the solution is
ardvark. This is a seven letter word. So in this case,
we would need to create a list with seven underscores and seven items.
Let's go ahead and create an empty list called display.
An empty list is just a set of square brackets with nothing inside.
Now, for each letter in the chosen word,
we're going to add a underscore to this list.
How can we add something for each letter?
The simplest way is to simply use a for-loop. Now, in this case,
we have a choice.
We can either use the style of for-loop that we used previously down here,
which is a way of looping through a list.
So we could say for letter in chosen_word,
so it's going to run this for as many letters as there are in this word.
And for every single letter,
we're just simply going to take our list, display, and add a item to it.
And that item is going to be the string, underscore.
So now if we go ahead and print out our display and see what we get.
The solution is baboon
which has six letters and display gets printed with one, two, three, four,
five, six underscores inside.
Now notice how here we're not actually using this variable letter that gets
created. We're looping through every letter in the chosen word,
but we're not doing anything with each of the letters. So we can in fact
just replace it with an underscore. Now, alternatively,
we could have created this for loop with a range function as well.
And remember that the range function creates a range of numbers from zero up to
a particular number that you specify. So we could have also,
instead of looping through the chosen word, use range and inside here,
we could have put the length of the chosen word.
So then our range would be between zero and the length of the chosen word.
So it was a baboon then it would be from zero to six, but not including six.
Remember that's how the range operator works.
So it would be zero and then it would be one and so on and so forth until it
gets to five.
And so that would be a total of six loops adding six of these underscores.
So given that I've updated this for loop, if we run it again,
you can see its exactly the same,
it will create as many underscores in the list as there are letters in the
chosen word. So it doesn't actually matter in this case
which version you went for, either this version of the
for loop using the range function or the previous one
which just looped through the list. It's your choice. They both worked the same.
So now let's move on to to-do number two.
Now we have to loop through each position in the chosen word
and if the letter at that position matches the letter the user guessed,
then we're going to reveal that letter in the display at that position.
So basically we're going to replace the underscore with the letter that the user
guessed if they guessed it right.
So now this is probably the hardest part of this whole step because in order to
do this,
we actually have to change this for loop to
one that uses the range function because we need to get hold of the position
when the letter and the guess actually matched. That way
we can tap into the list and change only the item at that particular position.
So let me show you how the code would look.
Instead of saying for letter in chosen_word,
we would say for position in range
and the range is going to be between zero and the length of the chosen_word.
And once we've got that, then the
for-loop is going to run for as many times as there are letters in the word and
for each of those letters
it's going to give us a number, a position to work with.
So the first time it runs it position is going to be equal to zero because we'll
be looking at the first item in the chosen_word,
which in this case would be a.
And then the next time the loop runs position becomes one
and we'll be looking at the second item in the list.
Now we no longer have that letter to work with,
which is why we get an error here.
So how can we get hold of the current letter in the chosen word
given that we know the position? Well,
it would be as simple as saying letter = chosen_word
[position].
Now we can check to see if the letter is equal to the letter
the user guessed.
Then we can get hold of our display and get the item at the current position and
then set that to equal the letter.
And we can get rid of the else statement entirely.
So now notice that we're using the length of the chosen word in quite a few
places. So if you want to,
you can actually simplify the code by simply creating a new variable called word
length.
And now every time we need to use the word_length,
we can just refer to that variable
Right?
which should make our code a little bit easier to read.
Finally, all we have to do for step three is just to print our list
which is called display. And then when we run our code,
you should be able to see that if the solution was camel,
initially, our display starts out with five blanks because there's five letters.
And then once we've guessed a letter,
then it will replace that letter at the correct position in that display list.
So a only matches the second letter,
so that second blank gets replaced by this letter.
And again,
I recommend to review the code if it's at all confusing or if you didn't manage
to get it first time through the Thonny IDE just to see it step by step and see
what's actually happening. We've chosen our random word,
which in this case turns out to be camel.
And once we get into our display,
it starts out as an empty list.
But as soon as we calculate the word length,
then we can go ahead and loop through the range of numbers from zero to the
length of the word, which is five. And it will run the code in the
for loop
which is just to add the underscore to this list five times.
And finally, once it's done, it's going to print it out.
So this is what we get, five blanks for the word camel.
Now it asked the user for a guess.
So I'm going to guess that letter a and enters this final for loop.
This is where it's really interesting.
So we're going to step into it to see it in more detail.
So now the range is a range between zero and the word length.
So the word length is five
so that range becomes from zero to five not
including five. So zero, one, two, three, four.
And that is going to make the for loop run five times.
The position starts out with zero. And when position is zero
then it's going to go into this next line, line 18, and put zero here as the
position. And then we go into the chosen word,
which is camel and pick out the item at position zero.
And so this letter becomes equal to the letter c because that's the letter at
position zero of the word. So now in our if statement,
we check to see if the letter, which is c, is equal to the guess,
which is a. Well in this case, c does not equal a
so we go back to the beginning of the for loop and we go to the next number in
the range, which is now one.
And we're going to repeat this again and again. But in this case,
notice that the letter at position one of camel is equal to a.
So now letter is equal to a and guess is equal to a.
So if those two are equal, then this
if statement is true and we end up going inside it to carry out this
functionality. Our letter is equal to a,
and we're going to look at our list, which is called display, this one,
and we're going to replace that second character with the letter that was
matching. And it's going to do this again and again
until we've looped through five times through all of the letters in the chosen
word
and finally we print the final version of display with the correct letters
replaced. Have a play around with this
if you're at all confused and it might be that you need to look up some stuff on
Stack Overflow,
or you might need to review some of the lessons that we've done before on things
like range functions and for loops, just so that you're really,
really certain that you know
what's going on and only then should you continue to the next step.
Take a moment with this and I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right. So up till now,
our game is not actually particularly fun and it's because we haven't enabled the
repeatability.
So we need our game to allow the user to guess the next letter and the next
letter
and keep going until they either die or they get to the solution.
So in this case, the solution is ardvark.
So I'm gonna guess a letter, a,
and that gets replaced in the correct positions.
And now I'm allowed to guess again.
And I'm going to keep going until I've filled out all of the characters.
So I'm almost there just need a 'k' now
and we should complete the entire game.
And it tells me that it's complete and that I've won
and the game finally ends and exits out of the loop. In order to achieve this and
make our game more like a game, we have just one to-do.
Now,
the idea here is you're going to use a while loop to let the user guests again
after they've guessed before. Now the loop should only stop
once the user has guessed all of the letters in the chosen word,
and this means that the display list should have no more blanks in it.
And then at that point,
you can tell them that they've won. Now in order to do this,
and as a quick hint, you might need to have a read of, again,
the section which I'll link to in the course resources. And specifically,
I want you to focus on this 'in' key word,
because we mentioned it previously in the course only briefly.
So I want you to read through this part and see how that works,
because you'll need it in order to get this to work. Now,
the other thing to remember is that you have the negation in Python.
So you can say,
if something is not true and then to do something or other.
So the not is the negation and this basically flips whatever is here.
So it could be, um, a = 3.
If not a > 1.
So in this case, a is three, three is greater than one. So this becomes true.
But because there's a not in front of it, then this entire thing becomes false
and so this if statement won't be carried out in this case.
But if this was zero and zero is not greater than one,
so this is now false and not false becomes true
and now this if statement will be carried ouit.
So that's how you use the negation. And finally,
you might need to remind yourself of what we learned in yesterday's lessons and
how the while loop works. Essentially,
you want to be able to get this part to repeat itself again and again and again,
until
all the blanks in the display is gone and they're filled.
And at that point, the user has won. And remember,
you don't have to worry about punishing the user for wrong answers just yet,
we're going to do that in the next step.
But for now, focus on this one to-do and see if you can solve this challenge.
All right, so let's go through the solution together.
Now we know that the part that we need repeating is this part where we ask the
user to guess a letter again and again
until they filled out all the blanks in this display.
The first step is to wrap a while loop around this block of code so we can
select the entire block of code and you can either indent it individually or
just select all of it and hit command and the right square bracket.
And that will shift everything by one indentation level
and that effectively puts it inside our while loop.
So now we have to define our while loop.
So while something is true or while something is false,
repeat this code again and again. So what exactly is our condition?
We know that we only want our loop to end once there are no more blanks
contained inside the list called display.
Why don't we create a variable which we'll call end_of_game and set that to
false
to begin with because it's not yet the end of game. And while it's not yet at the
end of game, so while this is false. So you can either say while
end of game is equal to false or alternatively
and I think slightly easier to read is you could say while it's not at the end
of the game, then repeat this continuously. Now,
if we were to run our code right now
it would actually loop on until forever.
It would not stop because nowhere in our code,
do we actually flip the switch and change this true.
So when is it actually the end of the game? Well,
it's when display has no more blanks.
So why don't we check at the very end after we've printed the display to see if
blanks are not in display.
So remember this in key word comes from Python and it basically allows us to
check to see if a particular element exists inside a particular list. So in this
case, we're checking if curly exists in list and there it is.
I can see it as one of the elements. So this is going to be true.
Now, if blank
in list is no longer true, well,
that means that we've gotten rid of all the blanks and we replaced them with
letters that the user has guessed.
So now this is the condition for the user having won.
So we can flip the end of game to true
and this will mean that this is last time
our while loop is going to run and we're going to print "You win."
That's it, that's all we needed do. And if it's helpful,
you can again, take this code, put it into Thonny and run through it
using the debug step-by-step to see what it's doing. Now
the important thing here is to realize that while statements require some sort
of change to happen inside the while loop
that changes the condition that the while loop is dependent upon
and it means the code exits the while loop. So in this case,
it's when there are no longer any more blanks inside the display list.
But in later steps,
we're going to change that so that when the users has run out of lives,
then it's also going to be the end of the game and they will have lost.
So take a moment, review this lesson,
make sure you understand everything that's going on.
Then head over to the next lesson and we'll tackle the next step.
Well done for getting to step 4. Now in this step
when you take a look at the starting file,
you'll see that I've incorporated a bunch of ASCII art,
so art that's created using strokes of the keyboard.
And you can see that this represents the stages of our hangman game starting from
where they have all six lives and then going down in lives until they have
no more lives, where the hangman character is complete.
This has been included as a list and inside the list
each of these pieces of art is a single string.
So we're going to be printing it out in this step,
and we're going to be using it to give the user feedback.
So the to-dos for step four include creating a variable called lives to keep
track of the number of lives and lives should be equal to six.
Now in the next to-do,
we're checking to see if the guess is actually not a letter in the chosen word,
then we're going to reduce that variable lives by one.
So eventually it's going to step down all the way to zero.
And when that happens, the game should stop and it should print "You lose."
Now, this part is really important because we want the game to stop
when the lives has gone down to zero.
So the code should exit the while loop and print "You lose."
So in addition to winning as a condition to ending the game,
losing is also a condition for ending the game. Now,
the final to do is just to print the ASCII art from stages
which is this list up here,
and the stage should represent the current number of lives
the user has remaining. So this way,
when we actually play the game and we get all the letters wrong,
each time a new piece of the hang man is going to be drawn until eventually we
end up with the entire drawing complete and the game ends,
and it tells us that we lost. If it's helpful,
refer to the flow chart. And once you're ready,
go ahead and fork the starting code and tackle the
to-dos one by one. Good luck and I'll see you on the other side.
All right. So make sure you've given it a good go before you come over here,
because I'm about to reveal the solution. In terms of step 4, here
I've got a forked copy of the code. And if I scroll down to
to-do number one, this is pretty simple.
It just tells us to create a new variable called lives
and this variable is going to be the one that's going to keep track of the
number of lives the user has left. And to start off,
it's going to be equal to six. Now we move on to to-do number two.
And it tells us that if the guess is not a letter in the chosen word,
then we have to reduce the number of lives by one.
Now it might be really tempting to put this as an else statement here,
because if the letter is equal to guess,
then well obviously it matches. Well then else, that means it doesn't match.
But check out what happens here if I just print a simple statement.
So now if I hit run and we take a look on the right side,
you can see that if I guess a,
then you can see that we get 'no match' printed five times,
and that should show you that this is actually not where we want to write the
code for to-do number two,
because remember to-do number two says if the guessed letter is not a letter in
the chosen word, then we should reduce the lives by one. But actually in fact,
what's happening here is it's looping through the entire word length,
and for each of the letters in that chosen word,
if the letter doesn't match the guess,
then it's going to trigger this else statement.
This is not what we want because in this case
a does in fact match a letter in the word baboon,
but we're getting no match being called five times.
So instead, we wanna write it outside of the for loop,
so at the same indentation level,
and the hint is that the to-do is actually at the same level as where your
answer code needs to go. So here,
we're going to write an if statement and we're going to check if the guess is
not in the chosen word.
And basically this does a separate check.
It goes through this entire word and checks
if the guessed letter exists in there at all.
And if this is true,
then we're going to reduce the number of lives by one, so -= 1.
Now, if at this stage
after we've taken a life away and the number of lives goes down to zero, well
then the game should stop and it should print "You lose."
So let's add another if statement in here that checks whether if the number of
lives is equals to, double equal to, zero.
And if this is the case, then we should exit the game. And remember to do that
we need to exit the while loop.
And the while loop is dependent on this variable end_of_game
which starts out being false. And when we want to exit the game,
when it is in fact the end of the game, we switch it to true. Like,
for example, in this case, when the user has won. So here,
when the lives is equal to zero, we can say, end_of_game = True,
and we're going to print "You lose."
So that's all that's needed to tackle to-do number two.
So now let's run our code again.
And you can see that if I keep guessing the wrong letter six times,
then eventually I exit out of my while loop.
You can see my prompt showing up again.
And this means that we've now come out of the game and it's told us that we've
lost.
So now all we have to do is tackle to-do number three.
We have to print the ASCII art from the list called stages
that corresponds to the current number of lives the user has remaining. Now,
luckily for you,
I've arranged each of these pictures in descending order of lives.
So when you have a full six lives,
the image at index six is the starting image.
And when you have no lives,
so the image at index zero is the one where the hangman is fully drawn.
So all we have to do down here is to simply just the print
the stages,
and corresponding to the current number of lives.
So we put lives inside the square brackets.
And now if we run the code again and we keep guessing,
you can see that we're going through our hangman picture until we are fully
drawn and we lose and it's the end of the game.
Have a quick review of the solution
and if you want to see this code that I've written,
then as always, head over to the course resources,
and you'll find a link to Day-7-Hangman-4-End
and you'll be able to see all the code that I've written in there, including,
um, helpful things like a print statement that you can activate,
which just shows you the current position,
the current letter and the letter that's being guessed.
So you can see as the loop is going on
what's actually happening and it'll make it easier for you to debug any problems
in your code. So if you had any problems in the code that you wrote,
this is a really useful line to be able to help you debug what's gone wrong.
Hopefully you manage to do thi okay,
and once you've had a quick review and you're happy with everything that's been
covered in this lesson,
then head over to the next lesson and we're going to complete the final step,
step five of our hangman project.
Hey! Well done for getting to the final step of the hangman project.
Now in step five,
we're going to complete the project by improving the user experience of our
game. Pretty much up until now, we've already got the game functioning,
but we were working with just three words, right? Ardvark, baboon,
and camel. And at some point,
the game gets pretty tiring when you're only guessing these three words.
And in fact,
the words were chosen so that if you see seven characters and you know
it's ardvark,
six is baboon, five is camel to make it easier for you to debug the code as
you're creating it. And very often when we're writing code, it really,
really important to help yourself when you're creating the code.
And only once you've got all the logic down and everything's working as expected
then to actually add the full functionality.
So inside this step five starting code,
if you take a look at the files over here, you'll notice two extra files.
One is hangman_art.py,
and here I've moved the hangman stages and all the drawings as well as a logo in
ASCII art. So when we actually launch our game this time,
then we're going to get the high man logo printed out like this at the beginning
of the game.
Now the second file here it is hangman_words.py.
And this word list now expands on what we had before.
And it's now a huge list of words, sorted alphabetically
which we're going to draw upon and replace this previous very simple word list.
The first to-do is to update the word list
to use the one from here instead of this one.
So deleting this line and replacing it with that. And to do this,
you might have to look up on previous lessons where
we talked about how to use modules in Python and how to import different files.
Now, if you get stuck on how to do that,
take a look inside the course resources
and there's hints that take you towards documentation on how to do this.
Now, once you've tackled to-do number one, scroll all the way down to find
to-do number two, where we're going to import the stages from hangman_art.py
and this is the same thing using modules and import. To-do
number three is to import the logo.
So one, two, three are all to do with modules and import.
And then once you get to to-do number four,
we're basically going to improve the user experience to let the user know that
they've entered a letter that they've already guessed before.
And when that happens, we're going to print the letter and just let them know.
You don't have to punish them and
you don't have to take away a life and you don't have to restart the game.
It's just the gentle nudge and let them know that they've really guessed that
letter. Now on to-do number five and the final to-do, we're going to let the user
know if the letter that they guessed is not in the chosen word.
So in this case,
we're going print out the letter that they guessed and let them know that it's
not in the word,
just a little bit of feedback to make the game a little bit easier on the user.
So once you've done all of that,
then you should end up with a game that's like this. So,
because there's so many words, I think it's really,
really important that you actually have this line of testing code to tell you
what the solution actually is
so you can test all parts of your game because you know what the word actually
should be. So let's guess a letter that's not in that word.
Let's try a, and you can see the game tells us "You guessed the letter a,
that's not in the word. You lose a life."
And we end up with the head already drawn in the hangman.
So now let's guess a different letter. Let's guess a t.
Then you can see that works as expected. But what if we try guessing T again?
Well, then it tells us you've already guessed t and it shows us the blanks
including the t. Now if they guess a letter
that's actually not in the word, so say a, well, in this case,
they're gonna lose a life because it's actually not in the word and we're going
to take away a life.
So have a play around with the end version of the game. And as always,
all the links are in the course resources. And once you're ready,
then go ahead and fork the starting file and give this a go.
Alright. So let's go through the solution together for this final step.
The first step tells us to update the word list
to use the word list from hangman_words.
And it's actually got exactly the same name.
So we don't even have to change it all that much.
But what we do have to do is to make this error go away.
If you haven't already, go ahead and delete this line in your code
where you've got the word list using the previous three words.
And instead, we're going to import the hangman_words.
And now we should be able to tap into this word list by writing hangman_
words.word_list.
And this is the same way that we use the random module.
So we imported the random module and then when we needed it, we simply said
random.choice. So choice is a function inside the random module,
and we can access it like
so. Now if you want it to be a little bit simpler in terms of the code that you
write and you don't want to rewrite hangman_words
dot such and such, then instead of just importing hangman words,
you can actually instead write from hangman
words import the word_list.
So now we can get rid of this part and we can just use the previous code that we
had on line 7.
Using that you can do the same thing for
to-do number two. From the hangman_art
you can import the stages and that will make this error go away. And for
to-do number three,
you can again say from hangman_art
import the logo.
And then we can just print the logo.
Now notice how we're importing, um,
two different things from the same file, hangman art.
So if you didn't want to write it twice,
you can in fact also just say from hangman_art import logo,
stages, and this will import both the logo and the stages
and you'll see that there's no errors down here.
If that's at all confusing,
be sure to read through the documentation that I've linked to in the course
resources that talks all about Python modules and importing
so you can familiarize yourself with this once more. Now on to-do four,
we're going to check to see if the user has entered a letter that they've
already guessed. And if it's a letter that they got right,
then we're going to print the letter and let them know. To do this,
we're going to check through the display,
which is a list of letters that they've already guessed.
And we're going to check to see if the guess is in the display list,
well, in this case, they've already guessed that letter and it's a correct one.
So we're just going to print out the feedback that, um,
"You've already guessed
and then we'll put in their guessed letter."
Now, however, if the letter is not in the chosen word,
then we're going to print out the letter and let them know that
"You guessed this particular letter,
that's not in the word.
You lose a life." That's it.
That's all we have to do and if we run our app as it is now,
then you can see that the solution is stymied.
So if we just check, um,
against s then that's being added,
and if we get a letter wrong,
then we get told that's not in the word. You lose a life.
And our hangman is being drawn out.
And if we guess a correct letter that we've already guessed like s again,
then it tells us that you've already guessed that letter.
Now you can either choose to keep all of these print statements
if it helps you understand what's going on, or alternatively at this stage,
it might make things a little bit confusing and you can just comment it out.
Have a look at the final version
by going to the course resources where I'll link to the completed code that I've
written here. And you can have a read through it and compare against yours.
But essentially this is all there is to this project
and you've now completed it in its entirety. Once you're happy with your code,
go ahead and remove all the comments that are no longer useful like all the
to-dos and the testing code
because if you wanna play the game for real, then that's just cheating.
If you want to leave in some of the comments that lets you know
what each part of code does so that when you come back to it,
it's easier to understand, then feel free to do that.
But the final thing that I wanted to show you is what if you wanted it to be
able to clear the screen after every answer,
because you can see that some point you have to keep scrolling and it gets a
little bit confusing as to which stage you're in.
So one of the things that you can do is you can tap into the replit module
and you can import a function called clear.
Once you've imported this clear function,
then you can go ahead and add it just after the user has made their guess.
So you can call it just as you would any other function
now that you've imported it into this file. And when you run the code now,
you can see that after every guess, it's going to clear the screen.
So guess a letter, let's guess a different letter.
Now that means we don't have this backlog of previous guesses and we can
actually see what's going on at each stage. In the course resources,
you'll also find a link to the final completed code on the day seven hangman final,
and feel free to modify this code to, your heart's content, make it
do whatever it is that you want to do and push the boundaries of your
programming skills
if you want to. Well done for getting this far and well done for tackling this
challenge. Rest easy, and I'll see you tomorrow.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 8 of a 100 Days of Code.
And today we're going to be looking at functions that allow you to give them
inputs. And once we've learned all of that and we've grasped it,
then we're going to be building a cipher program.
And the cipher program is called Caesar cipher.
So Caesar cipher is a really quite ancient type of encryption.
So the story goes that, um,
when Caesar wanted to send highly sensitive military messages,
he would encode his message so that each letter would be shifted by a
predetermined amount.
So let's say that we wanted to encode the letter "A" and we shift it by three,
well
then A becomes D, B becomes E and so on and so forth.
And this is what the final version will look like.
Let's go ahead and encode something.
So I'm going to type encode to start encrypting a message.
And then I'm going to type my message with no spaces in between.
And then I'm going to give it a shift number.
So this is going to be a number that
the recipient and I are going to agree on so that we know how to decode the
message. Let's put that at nine.
And then it's going to give us the encoded results
which is something like this.
And this will be the message that I'm going to transmit to my friend,
either through a letter or through an email
and it means that whenever somebody comes across this message
they won't really know what's going on unless they knew the shift number.
So let's say that I am my friend. I've just received this message.
And I'm going to go ahead and type yes to go again
and in this case, I'm going to decode instead of encoding.
And then I'm going to paste the message and hit enter.
And of course, the shift number is nine and now I have the decoded results
which I can read and understand. By the end of today,
you would have learned about functions with input,
you'll know what the difference is between arguments and parameters.
Once you're ready, once you're loaded up on coffee,
then head over to the next lesson and let's get started.
To get started we're going to learn more about functions.
And previously we learned that functions are a really handy way of taking a
complex set of instructions and packaging them together inside a block of code
that has a name given to it.
And when we need all of the lines of code that's packaged inside this
function,
all we have to do at any point later on in our code is just to call the function
by typing its name and then a set of parentheses.
And when this line of code is run,
it's going to search for where this function is defined, which is up here,
and then it's going to execute all the lines of code that are contained within
it. Now it's been a little while since we've seen functions.
So I want you to go ahead and find the starting replit for day 8
which is at this URL
and then fork it to create your own copy. To begin,
I want you to create a new function called greet,
and I want you to give it three lines of print statements,
telling it to do three things. And finally, once you're done,
go ahead and call the function so that it gets executed in the console.
So pause the video and give that a go. All right.
So to create a function, we of course need a def keyword.
And we know it's a keyword, because as soon as we type it,
it changes to the blue color. And after the key word,
we get to give our function a name. So in my case, it's called greet.
Now after the greet, we add a set of parentheses after the name of the function.
Finally,
we add a colon and we enter into the block of code because we're indented over.
Now,
the first thing I'm going to do is to create a print statement that just says
Hello. And then I'm going to say, well,
how do you do? Nobody in England actually says this,
but I always see it in the learn English books, which is quite funny.
I think people will give you a very strange look
if you go to somebody at the bakery and say, well, how do you do? But anyways,
now finally, we're going to add a final print statement,
keeping in line with the Britishness of my function,
going to ask about the weather.
Now this line, on the other hand, is something that you will often hear a British
people say. They're obsessed about the weather,
mostly because it's terrible all the time.
So now that we've created our function,
it's time to actually trigger the function or what we see in programming lingo,
call the function.
And we do that by calling the name of the function and then adding a set of
parentheses. And now once the code reaches line six
it's going to search for this greet function, which it'll find over here
and then it's going to carry out each of the lines of code one by one.
So let's run the code and you should see each of the three print statements
being called. So that's pretty simple.
Notice that every single time I call the greet function,
it's going to do the same thing, right?
It's just going to print out those three lines of code. Now, in reality,
it's very rare that you'll want to repeat the same instructions every single
time when you call a function. It would be nice, wouldn't it,
if we could modify some of the parts of the code inside the function and allow
for a little bit of variation. For example,
it would be nice if we could greet somebody by the name so that it could say,
hello Angela, instead of just, hello. How do you do Angela?
So that it could change each time I call this function.
Maybe next time it will be, how do you do Jack Bauer, et cetera.
So how can we achieve this kind of functionality? Well,
we need to look more closely at these parentheses.
Now what we can do is we can actually add the name of a variable inside those
parentheses to start giving our functions some inputs.
So let's say that there's a variable called something that's going to be passed
to my function. And this something can then be used inside this block of code,
this function.
And I could do something with it. Now in order to actually pass this value
when I call my function, I have to add the data inside the parentheses.
So let's say I decide to pass 123 over, well
in this case, when this line of code gets triggered,
the computer is going to search for where this function is declared,
which is up here, and then it's going to pass over this piece of data,
123, over to this variable called something.
So now, effectively, inside this function called my_function,
we now have a variable called something that's equal to 123
and that can then be used inside the block of code to do something with that
piece of data.
Now it's a bit like plugging in a USB stick into a computer.
If we took a different piece of input,
we would end up with a different file being shown by the computer.
So this means the computer can do something different depending on the input that
we give it. And if we change that input,
then it will receive a different piece of data.
So in addition to a simple function,
we can also create a function that allows for input.
And to do that you saw earlier on the syntax is again the same as before we use
a Def to create the function.
And then let's just give it a slightly different name to differentiate it with
the previous function, greet_with_name.
And then inside the parentheses, instead of leaving it blank,
we get to create the name of the variable that's going to be passed over.
So let's just call it name because that describes the data that's going to be
received. It's going to be the name of the person that I wish to greet.
So now let's add a colon and finally we can create our print statements.
So I'm just going to copy these print statements from above and now,
instead of having these names hard coded in here, I'm going to delete it
and I'm going to replace those names with the value of this variable.
So I'm going to put it in using an fstring like this,
and then I'm going to do the same down here.
Right?
When we actually call this function,
it's also going to be a little bit different from previously on line six.
So now firstly, the name of the function has changed.
But notice how it's expecting some sort of input inside the parentheses.
And it tells me that it wants to receive a name.
It's when we call the function that we actually pass over the piece of data
that's going to be stored inside this variable. Let's give it my own name,
Angela. And now when I hit run,
I want you to predict what's going to happen,
what's actually going to be printed.
So let's go ahead and comment out the previous line of code and now run our code.
And you should see that it says, hello Angela, how do you do Angela.?
So this piece of data has basically been inserted under this variable name
and then it's been put into both of these print statements. Now,
if I go ahead and call this function with a different piece of data,
say a different name,
then it's going to use that piece of data to modify this function
so it does something a little bit different.
So this way we can create one function that carries out some instructions,
but every time we execute it, it gets a modify it a little bit
by changing the inputs.
When we're talking about functions with inputs,
there's two things that we're working with
that's really important to differentiate.
So we know that when we call this function and we pass over this piece of data,
effectively
we're creating a new variable called something and we're setting it to equal this
piece of data that we're passing it. Now in programming lingo,
you'll hear this being referred to as the parameter and this piece of data
being referred to as the argument. Now,
the argument is the actual piece of data
that's going to be passed over to this function when it's being called.
Whereas the parameter is the name of that data
and we use the parameter inside the function to refer to it and to do things
with it. Now very often on the internet when you come across
somebody explaining something
be it on Stack Overflow or in some piece of documentation,
you'll hear them referring to these two types of things,
the parameter and the argument.
So if you need to, come back to this lesson and remind yourself the difference
between those two things.
The parameter is the name of the data that's being passed in,
the argument is the actual value of the data. Now,
sometimes people also get confused on the internet between these two words,
but as long as you know what they means, then you'll be in a good place.
In the last lesson,
we saw a very simple form of a function that allows for an input.
Now in this lesson,
I want to take it even further and I want to create a function that allows for
multiple inputs.
So let's comment out of the previous line of code and let's create a new comment,
functions with more than one input.
And I'm going to create a new function called greet_with.
And in this case, it's going to take two parameters.
It's going to be name and location. If you remember,
this is how we added a parameter previously. Now, as a challenge,
I want you to quickly think about how you might add two parameters,
one's called name and one's called location, into this function
declaration. Pause the video, have a brief think,
and then we'll go through it together. All right.
So we know that if we wanted to add one parameter name,
then this is how we would do it. We would just add it inside the parentheses.
Now, if we wanted to have more than one parameter,
all we have to do is just add a comma and then add the second parameter which we
said was going to be called location.
So now this particular function is going to take two inputs,
the name and the location. And then inside this function,
we're going to use the name to print something like hello name,
and then we're going to print and ask them,
what is it like in their particular location.
See if you can modify this to use the actual parameters and to replace them with
print statements so that we use these parameters inside of our function.
Pause the video now and give that a go. All right.
So essentially we want to create a print statement here and print statements
print strings so we have to add some quotation marks around that text.
And then finally,
I'm going to use a fstring to replace this parameter name inside this string so
that the data that gets passed in gets replaced here, and it says,
hello, whatever their name is.
And then I'm just going to do the same thing over here
and notice that with replit and a lot of other text editors,
you can simply highlight a word or highlight or a sentence,
and then use the open curly brace to actually add brace around both sides of the
word. And you'll notice that I did the same thing with the quotation marks.
So it highlight the whole sentence and then hit the double-quote key
and it will keep adding quotes around both sides of your highlight.
But I only actually need one.
So that is our function completed.
And now it means I can call this function by calling greet_with,
and it's going to prompt me to add both of these inputs.
And the first piece of data is going to be the name
and you can see it's giving you a hint by underlining the name of the parameter
here. And let's put Jack Bauer
and then we can add the second piece of data and separate it with a comma.
And now you can see this underline has moved to the location parameter.
So again, a hint as to what kind of data it wants.
So let's say that Jack Bauer is nowhere. Now,
if we go ahead and run this code,
then you'll see that it's going to print hello and replace name with Jack Bauer.
And then what is it like in nowhere? So no
where gets replaced with this location.
So that means that you can now put in as many pieces of inputs as you want and
modify the functionality of your function to make your function do different
things each time. Now here's a question.
What happens if I call the same function greet_with,
but I switch the order of the data that I give it.
So let's say the first piece of data I give it is nowhere,
and then the second piece of data is Jack Bauer.
So we've just switched the order of these pieces of data. Now,
what do you expect to happen?
Pause for a moment and have a think about what you expect to be printed in here
and then continue. All right,
so let's click run and you can see that it's now complete nonsense.
Hello, nowhere. What is it like in Jack Bauer? And what actually happened here
is it takes the position of the data, looks at both of these arguments,
and the first argument gets assigned to the first parameter
the second argument gets assigned at the second parameter. So in this case,
when it's actually gone in here, name is now equal to nowhere,
which is why this line printed thi.sAand Jack Bauer is now assigned to location
which is why it printed this second line like so. And in Python programming,
this is called a positional argument because when we call the function,
we haven't specified anywhere which particular parameter we want to associate
these pieces of data with. So it's just gone and looked at the position.
Now this is the default way of calling functions, because on one hand,
when you're typing out the code,
you get the hints here as to which piece of data you need to enter.
But also you can refer to the function and look at the order of the parameters.
Even if we had more inputs, let's say in this case, we had a,
b and c, and we put the arguments one, two and three,
then it means that our variables that gets created
will be a equals one,
b equals two and c equals three.
Now, if we switch around the order of the arguments in the function call,
now what will happen is a is going to be equal to the first argument.
So a is now equal to three, b as equal to the second argument and c is equal to
the third argument. So it might be doing slightly unpredictable things in here.
So whenever you're creating code and you're using these positional arguments,
and you're just inserting the data one by one like this,
and it does something completely unexpected,
then be sure to check your positioning and to make sure that it matches with the
position of the parameters. Now,
what if you wanted to be more clear when you actually call the function
so you don't ever encounter this problem? Well,
you could use something called keyword arguments instead. So now,
instead of just adding the arguments into the function call like this,
we can actually add each of the parameter names and an equal sign to say that
the first parameter a
should be equal to one, b should be equal to two and c equals to three.
And now when we actually change the order around,
it doesn't matter how we order it,
it still going to abide by these bindings. So c
will still be three and a will still be one.
As a challenge, I want you to take this previous function,
greet_with_name and location,
and I want you to call this function down here, but this time,
instead of using positional arguments, I want you to use keyword arguments.
So pause the video and try and give that a go.
All right. So when we call the function, we still use the name.
So it's greet_with, so everything up to the first parentheses is the name.
And then we add in each of these parameter names,
and then we add an equal sign and finally, we give it the actual value.
So let's say Angela,
and then the location is going to be equal to London.
Now, when I hit run,
you can see it does pretty much the same as before. It puts Angela into the name,
London into location. But this time if I switch the order around it
no longer matters. And when I hit run again,
you can see it does exactly the same thing,
because it now knows which argument is associated with which parameter.
So this can make your code less error prone
but it does make each line of code longer.
I recommend using your judgment to figure out when you want to use which type of
argument and depending on the need, you can pick between these two.
Now in the next lesson, I've got a coding exercise for you to put into practice
everything that you've learned so far.
Head over there when you're ready and let's give it a go.
All right. So in today's coding challenge,
we're going to do a little bit of wall painting.
And the idea is we're going to create a program that helps us calculate how many
cans of paint we need to buy for a given surface area of wall.
The maths involved is very simple
and I'm going to talk you through it if you're not confident with maths.
But essentially we want it to be able to use our inputs
to modify our function so that it does something every single time we use it.
Go ahead and click on day 8.1 area calculation,
and we're going to complete this coding challenge. So firstly,
you'll notice that down here on lines, 10, 11, 12, and 13,
I've got some code that's going to help us check your solution.
And we're going to use your function to actually calculate the number of cans of
paint we need to buy.
You're basically painting a wall and the instructions on the paint cans says that
one can
can cover five square meters of wall. Given any height and any width, your
program needs to calculate how many cans of paint you need to buy. The maths,
as I say, is pretty simple.
All you have to do is multiply the height by the width to get the area of the
wall, and then you simply divided by the coverage per can.
We said that five square meters per can, so
it means you are always going to be dividing by five.
So let's say that we had a wall which was two meters high and four meters wide,
and the coverage, as always, is going to be equal to five.
Then the calculation would be a simple as 2 x 4 divided by 5,
which is 1.6. So we need 1.6 cans of paint,
but because you can't buy 0.6 can of a paint,
I've tried this in the store. They said no and they told me to go away.
So we actually have to round up to the nearest whole number.
So in this case, we need to buy two cans. Now,
the really important thing to draw your attention to is down here
I actually call the function.
So I'm calling the function and I'm giving in some named arguments.
So this is really, really important. If you review the previous lessons,
then you should know what name you need to give your function and what
name you need to give the parameters for the code to actually work without any
errors. Remember to take a look at the example inputs down here
and example output because you need to print out something along these lines.
So it should say you'll need X cans of paint depending on your calculation.
And finally, if you need a hint as to how to round up a number,
then you can either go ahead and Google for it, use Stack Overflow,
that's probably the best way, or you could give it a guess. And finally,
if you really get stuck,
take a look at the hint section. And once you're done,
then come back over here and we'll walk through the solution together.
Pause the video now and go ahead and complete this coding exercise.
Yeah.
All right. So, did you manage to get that right? If not,
take a look at this video and then once you're done,
take a look at the solution code and try to compare against your code to see if
there were any errors that you made. Now, this challenge is pretty doable.
All we have to do is to create our function and we create any function using def.
And how do we know what name to give this function? Well,
we take a look at where the function was called down here,
and you can see that it's called paint_calc.
So this is what we have to give our function as the name.
And then we of course have our parentheses, our colon, and then inside here,
we're going to do all the calculations. Now,
the next thing we have to look at is what name we should give our parameters.
And you can see I've got named arguments here.
So that means each of these are going to be the names of the parameters; height,
width, and cover.
So the parameters are going to go inside the parentheses height, width, and cover.
And it's only if we actually spell these parameters exactly the same as what we've
got down here in the arguments will our code actually work.
Now let's go ahead and take the height and multiply it by the width to get the
area. So area = height * width.
And then with that area, we can divide it by the coverage per can.
So let's call it num_of_cans = area
/ cover.
And now remember that this is going to be a decimal number occasionally like
here,
and we have two round it up to the next whole number.
If we take a look at this particular Stack Overflow,
you can see that the question is exactly what we want, right?
How do you round up a number in Python? And if you did some Googling,
then this might have been the Stack Overflow question you would have landed on.
And essentially it tells us you have to import maths, and from the math module,
you use a function called ceiling. And then inside the parentheses,
you put in the inputs. To do that,
we first import math.
It's math without the 's.' And then we can call it a math.ceil and wrap this
result around the parentheses.
So this is going to take the result here from a decimal number to
a whole number by rounding it up to the ceiling.
So now we're finally ready to give our output,
so we're going to do that by printing it.
So we're going to print and I'm definitely going to need an f-string.
So I'm going to put an F in there and paste this string.
And instead of having the hard-coded five here,
I'm going to put in the num_of_cans instead.
So now when this line of code on line 17 calls
paint_calc passing in each of these arguments,
then it's going to be able to run this function here and print out how many cans
of paint I'll need. Now, all we have to do is test our code.
So let's hit run and let's put in a random height.
Let's say it's five meters high and three meters wide.
And it tells us that we need three cans of paint.
So five by three,
the area is 15 square meters,
15 divided by five is three. Now,
what if we had a decimal number?
Let's say we had a height of 7 and a width of 13.
Then in this case, it tells us we need 19 cans.
So 7 times 13 is 91. 91 divided by 5 is 18.2 and 18.2
round it up is 19.
And we've now completed this challenge. Did you manage to get it right?
If not, be sure to watch this video and see if you can go back and fix your code
and you can compare it against the solution code I've got here by going to this
link right here.
And once you're done, head over to the next lesson where I've got a slightly
harder coding challenge for you.
All right, so in the next coding exercise, we're going to be building a prime number checker. And a
prime number, just to remind you, is a number that is only divisible by one and itself.
So, for example, two is a prime number because it can only be divided by one and two.
Three is also a prime number,
similarly, it can only be split into three equal sized chunks.
But four, however, is not a prime number because while it can be divided by one and four, it can
also be divided by two.
So two times two is four. Essentially a prime number is a number that can't be broken to smaller
parts other than one and itself.
And it's this property of prime numbers that makes them really useful to everything from cicadas to
Bitcoin and also encryption in the computer world.
So if you head over to day 8.2 prime number checker, you'll see the starting code including
the number that we're going to be sending over and checking.
And then, of course, the line eleven where we actually call this function and pass over the number. So
this part is really important when you are creating your function.
The idea is that you're going to be creating a function here that checks whether if the number that's
passed in is a prime number or not.
And if you take a look at this chart, then you'll see all the prime numbers up to 100 highlighted in
yellow.
There's a couple of things you need to remember.
One is that you'll probably need to use the modulus, which we've seen before.
And if you can't remember how to use that, then take a look at this link.
Now, the second thing is that make sure that you name your function and parameters the same as what
you see here where it's called.
And finally, try to use the same wording as the example outputs, namely, if it is a prime number print
"It's a prime number." in this exact wording.
And if it's not a prime number, then print "It's not a prime number." with this exact wording.
And finally, if you're still not quite sure how prime numbers work, then be sure to check out the
Wikipedia page.
And if your first language is not English, then be sure to switch to your native language just to know
what it is because I know it's called different things in different languages.
Pause the video,
have a good think about this and see if you can solve this problem.
All right, so let's think about how we might tackle this. The first thing I'm going to do is I'm going
to create a new function called prime_checker to be in line with this line, because I'm calling a
function called prime_checker
and then I'm passing in an argument to the parameter called number.
So now that we've created our function, the next step is to figure out, well, what do we do in this
function?
Now, I mentioned that every prime number can only be cleanly divided by itself and one.
So that means that if it's divided by any other number other than these, it will have a remainder.
So we know that we can use the modulus to check what the remainder is of a division.
So we know that, for example, if we divide six by two, then it equals three with no remainder because
six is divided into two three times, while seven divided by two equals one because there's a remainder
of one, because two times three is six and then six plus one makes seven.
So we can use the modulus to check whether if the number that we're passing in here can be divided by
all the numbers all the way down to two.
So, for example, if number was equal to seven, well, then what we would want to do is we would want
to do seven divided by two and then see if there is any remainder, and then seven divided by three and
see if there was any remainder, and then seven divided by four...
and then we just go up two, three, four, five, and six.
And now we've basically divided seven by all the possible values other than one and seven.
So if any of these has zero as the remainder, then it means that it does cleanly divide by one of these
numbers, which means that it's actually not a prime number.
But if all of these have a remainder, then that means seven is a prime number, which we already know
it is because we can see it on this graph.
So how can we go through this process of getting this number divided by numbers starting from two
all the way going up to the number minus one?
Well, we could simply just use a for loop, right?
So we create a for loop and say for i which is going to be this number that we're going to divide
by, in,
and that number is going to be a range of numbers.
And the range starts from two because we're not going to divide it by one.
We already know that all numbers can be divided by one. And we're going to put the range all the way
up to the number.
So now inside this for loop, we can start doing our divisions. So we could take the number and we can
use the modulo operator to divide it by i.
So it's exactly the same as each of these lines of division. If number divided by i is equal to zero,
so if it divides cleanly, well, then in this case, it's clearly not a prime,
right? Because if that number that we get passed in can be divided by any of the numbers between two
and number minus one cleanly with no remainder, then that means it's not a prime number.
However, if we get to the very end of our for loop and this if statement was never triggered, well,
then that means this is a prime number.
So how can we represent this with our code?
Well, we could create a variable called is_prime and set it to true.
If this if statement gets triggered, then we switch
this is_prime to false.
And finally, once we get to the end of the for loop, we can go ahead and check
well, is is_prime true or is it false?
And this expression is basically the same as just typing this because this is going to be true or false.
And if it's true, then we get to step into this block and we're going to print from this example output
and say that it is a prime number. But else or otherwise, then we're going to print the opposite
where  we say it's not a prime number.
There you have it.
This is the simplest way of checking whether if a number is a prime number. And all it does is it checks
through all of the numbers between two and the number.
And if it's divisible by any of those numbers, well, then it's not a prime.
Now, out there in the real world, there's a lot of other ways that you could implement this function.
And there's more efficient ways, there's faster ways and there's lots of algorithms that mathematicians
have come up with in the past. Now for our case,
what I'm really interested in is that you understand how inputs work and how you can use the argument
that's passed in to the parameter inside your function in order to do something with it.
As long as that's clear to you, then that means we can continue in the course and I can rely on the
fact that this code or this code will not throw you off and you'll know exactly what's going on when
it's being used inside the block of code and when it's being passed over into a block of code.
In the next lesson, we're going to be putting all of our knowledge that we learned into practice and
we're going to get started building our final project, the Caesar cipher.
So for all of that and more,
I'll see you there.
All right. It's finally time to tackle our final project,
the Caesar Cipher. As I mentioned before,
Caesar Cipher is this way of encoding text that,
um, was seen as early as during the times of Julius Caesar.
So when he had these top secret military messages,
what he would do is he would shift each letter of the alphabet by a certain
predetermined amount. I want to show you quickly how this works.
So we've got the alphabet here and let's say we wanted to encode the letter E. So
now we can line up the alphabet with a new set of alphabet.
And at the moment,
the shift is zero because the top alphabet and the bottom alphabet are lined up
with a zero difference. Now, let's say that we had a shift of one. Well,
then the alphabet moves to the left and A becomes B, B become C et cetera.
And we can keep going until we get to the amount of shift that we wanted.
So let's say we're going to encode all of our text with the shift of three.
Well, then E becomes H, F becomes I, G becomes J et cetera,
and so on and so forth.
And they've actually discovered these artifacts from ages ago
where people have created these sort of dials.
And by simply rotating the dial to a certain amount of shift,
then you can line up the letters with each other.
So A becomes N and Z becomes O and so on and so forth.
And this is a way that people actually encoded top secret messages.
By the end of this day,
you will have also built a digital form of the Caesar cipher.
And all you have to do is to type encode to start encoding a message.
Let's say something like Hello World.
And once we hit enter, we get to type the shift number,
which I'm just gonna choose a random one,
and it gives us the encoded result.
So now if I take this encoded results and I go ahead and type yes,
to restart my program,
and I'm going to use the decode function to decode my message.
Now, when I use the same shift number,
then I should be able to get back the decoded result.
So if there's people monitoring your phone, or you're trying to throw a message to
your friend in a paper ball,
then this is an easy way to ensure that if your message was intercepted then it
won't be understood by the other person. Once you're ready,
let's get started by heading over to repl.it/@appbrewery/caesar
-cipher-1-start. And this contains the starting code for this project
and this is part one of four.
So here I've already saved you the laborious task of typing out all the letters
in the alphabet and they're stores in a single list.
Now I've also got three inputs.
So this is what the user is going to type in.
They're gonna type in encode or decode,
and that's gonna be saved to the direction. Tey're going to type them message
which is going to be changed to lower case
and this is going to be saved in text, and finally,
they're going to input a shift number
which is going to be converted to an integer and saved inside this variable
called shift. So if you want to, have a run of the program as it is right now,
so that you fully understand what's actually going on before you get started.
And remember, don't change any of the code above,
but instead tackle the to-dos one by one.
The first step is to create a function called encrypt
that's going to take this text that the user typed in and the shift that they
typed in as inputs.
And this is going to use what you learned about functions with inputs,
from today's lessons.
And then once you're done with that, step 2 is to go inside the encrypt
function that you just created and shift each letter of the text forwards by the
shift amount. So, again, as we saw before a shift of one,
a shifter of two, a shift of three,
basically just moves the characters forward
so that each letter of the alphabet becomes a letter of the alphabet much
further down the line. Let's say that the user entered the text
Hello and if we tried a shift of five,
then the end result should be mjqqt
and the printed output from this function should say something like the encoded
text is this. And finally,
you're going to call the encrypt function and then pass in the user inputs from
over here
and you should be able to test the code and encrypt a message and see something
like this happen. Pause the video now, have a look through the starting code,
and once you're ready,
go ahead and tackle it and then come back and we'll go through the solution
together. Good luck. All right.
So I'm gonna fork a copy of the starting file and tackle to-do number one,
which is to create a function which is done using Def and it's called encrypt.
And this function is going to take two inputs. So inside the parentheses,
I'm going to put two parameters. Now you can,
of course use the same word as the inputs that you're going to put into it.
But in an ideal world,
you try to not confuse yourself between the arguments and the parameters.
So I'm going to call this plain_text,
this first parameter and the second parameter
I'm going to call it shift_amount. Now, of course, at a later date,
when we're sending the input to this function,
we're going to be sending the text to plain_text and shift to shift_amount.
Keeping the names of the argument and the parameter different will help us
later on to see which one is which. The next step is to go inside the encrypt
function, which of course means indenting by one,
we're going to shift each letter of the text forwards in the alphabet by the
shift amount, and then print the encrypted text.
This is going to be the challenging part of this whole exercise.
But essentially if we think about the problem,
what we want to do is we want to take each letter in the plain text.
So let's say all plain text is equal to hello.
Then we're going to take each of these letters in turn and then shift it up in
the alphabet by the shift amount. So let's say for example,
our shift amount was five and our plain text was hello,
the first thing we're going to do is we're going to take the H which is over
here, and then we're going to shift it up by five. So one, two, three, four,
five,
and we're going to turn it into an M. We can start off by writing a for loop that
loops through each of the letters in the plain text input.
And then we can take each of these letters and work out its position in the
alphabet list here.
And we can do that by using the index method.
So we can tap into a list, write .index,
and then put in the value that we want to get the index for
and we should be able to get that as the result. So back over here,
we're going to say,
alphabet, is the list, .index
and then inside the parentheses, we can put in our letter.
So we want to find out the index of the letter that we're looping through in
this alphabet up here. And once we've gotten a hold of that,
we're gonna save it into a variable called position.
Now, once we've got that, then we're going to calculate the new position.
Now the new position is just going to be the previous position,
which is going to be a number, and then plus the shift amount.
So while we're going through this code, let's look at this word
H. So the first time the loop runs letter's going to be equal to H, position is
going to be equal to zero one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
And then the shift amount is five,
so seven plus five is going to be 12.
So now the new position is going to be 12,
and we can tap into the alphabet list at position 12,
so seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve,
and get hold of the value at that position.
So we can say that new_letter is equal to the alphabet at the new_position.
And now once we've got this new_letter,
we can create a empty string here which we'll call the ciphertext
which is going to be the encoded text. And it starts out being an empty string
and then once we've gotten each of the new letters,
we're going to add it to the cipher text. Now,
the final thing we have to do inside this encrypt function is once the
for loop has run its course,
and we've added all of the new letters into the cipher text,
then at this point, it's a good idea to print out the output.
And it tells us that we should say something like this,
where we replace this final thing with the actual encoded text,
which has of course, called a cipher text in our case.
Now let's just make that into an fstring
so that it'll insert it when it runs and we're ready to tackle the last to-do. So
here,
we're going to call the encrypt function and we're going to pass in all of the
user inputs.
So it remember that our parameter names are plain text and shift amount.
So I'm actually going to use the keyword arguments, so I'm going to say
plain text is equal to the text that the user has typed in.
And then on the next argument,
I'm going to say the shift amount is equal to the shift that the user has typed
in.
So now we're ready to test our code and let's take a look at what happens.
So I'm going to use this example that we've done here by trying to encode hello
with the shift of five. Now the first thing that we type, the direction,
doesn't actually matter because it's not being used anywhere in our code,
at least not yet. So you can type anything you want,
I'm just going to type encode. And then the message is going to be hello.
And the shift number is going to be five.
And now it tells us that the encoded text is mjqqt,
which matches with the expected output.
You might think that we're done, right? This is perfect. This is great
and we've completed this entire exercise.
But lets consider a different scenario.
What happens if we tried to encode a word that had letters that were really
close to the end of the alphabet?
Let's say that we wanted to encode the message zulu.
Now I'm only doing that because if there's a z in that word, of course.
And we wanted to shift it by five.
Now let's think of what's going to happen right? In our code,
we're going to take each of the letters, we're going to take z first
and then we're going to get its position in the alphabet and add the shift
amount to the position to get the new position.
Now, this is already at the end of the alphabet. So if this number
which is going to be 25,
because there's 26 letters in the alphabet and we start the position at zero.
So this plus five is going to be 30.
And what happens when we try to get the 30th item from the alphabet? Well,
you'll find out when I hit enter.
We get an index error and it tells us that list index out of range, and it
occurred on line 15.
So just as we predicted, this does not exist.
We have to try and tackle this right? So if you haven't thought about this,
this is the time to think about how can you solve this problem.
I want you to pause for a moment and try to see if you can fix it.
All right.
So we know that this has a fixed length and what we want to happen when we have
a letter towards the end that we need to encode is to loop back to the beginning
of the alphabet. So to solve this,
all we have to do is just to copy the existing letters in the alphabet and then
just duplicate it once more.
So this means that if we find a letter that's z and it needs to be shifted up
by five letters, it's going to continue until it gets to e.
Now,
the really wonderful thing about this index function is it's going to give you the
first index that it finds.
So if we're looking for the letter a, it's going to give you the index zero
and then it's going to stop.
It's not going to look for all the indices and find this one at position 26.
So it means the our code will now work
even if we have a word that have a lot of letters towards the end of the
alphabet. Let's go ahead and give it a spin,
Right?
Let's type encode. And our message is again,
zulu. And we hit enter.
And then we have a shift number of five and we get our encoded text.
z becomes one, two, three, four,
five, it becomes e, and u, one, two, three, four,
five, becomes z. So now we've solved that small bug.
Now there's a lot of other ways that you could have solved this bug,
but I think this is the easiest way without disturbing our logic here and not
making our function even longer.
If you had any problems with your code, then this is the time to go back and fix
it and make sure that you really understand everything that's going on here
before you move on to the next lesson. But once you're ready,
I'll see you on the next lesson where we're going to decrypt our code.
All right. So now that we've managed to get our program to encode some text,
it's time to do the opposite direction,
which is how do we get our program to be able to decode a piece of text based on
a shift number.
So let's say that we try to decode the letter G and we had a shift number of
three. Well, in this case,
we actually have to work backward and shift backward in the alphabet in order
to get the letter that's three spaces previously.
So in this case,
that would be D. Go ahead and head over to caesar-
cipher-2-start and fork your own copy of it.
Alright, so we've got all the code that we had at the end of part one,
but now we have to create the decrypt function.
And the decrypt function is again
going to take the text that the user inputted and the shift number,
and both of these are going to go into the function as inputs.
And then inside the function,
we're going to shift each letter of the text backward in the alphabet
by the shift amount. For example,
if we started out with this code and we needed to shift each letter by five,
then we end up with the plain text, hello. And finally,
our function needs to print
the decoded text is, depending on what it is that we actually got. Finally,
in to-do part three,
we're going to use that direction
variable that we ignored previously, where we ask the user to type encode
if they want to encrypt and decode if they want to decrypt.
And then we're going to use an if statement here to check which one they chose,
and then we're going to call the corresponding function based on that direction.
And once you've completed all three to-dos,
you should be able to run your program and encode a message
as well as decode a message when you hit run again,
like that.
Have a think about how you might tackle each of the three to-dos and then pause
the video and give it a go.
All right. So how did that go? The first part should be quite easy.
All we have to do is define a new function called decrypt
and this decrypt is going to take the same inputs as our encrypt,
which is the text and the shift that the user entered.
But again,
I'm going to use some different parameter names to be able to differentiate the
arguments and the parameter. So in this case,
because the text that I'm getting is going to be scrambled,
I'm going to call the first parameter cipher_text,
and the second parameter I'll call it again, the shift amount.
Now, after a colon, I'm done with to-do 1. Now let's move on to
to-do 2.
So here I have to be inside the decrypt function,
so indented inside of the function,
and then I'm going to shift each letter of the ciphertext backward in the
alphabet by the shift amount
and then print out the decrypted text. To  do that I'm again
going to need a for loop,
and I'm going to loop through each letter in the cipher text.
And for each of those letters,
what I want to do is I want to get hold of the position that they are in the
alphabet. So I'm gonna check the alphabet and then use again,
that index function
and then tap into the position of the letter.
Once I've got the position, I'm going to define the new position
which is going to be the current position. Now,
remember, we're moving backwards in the alphabet now.
So I'm going to subtract the shift amount from the position.
Once that's done,
I can define a blank variable called plain text,
which is just going to be an empty string.
And once I've gotten hold of each of the new positions,
I can add to that plain text by tapping into the alphabet and then getting hold
of the letter at the new position. So now finally,
once that for loop's completed,
then I can print out the results and I'm going to use the same sort of output
structure as I've got in the example.
And we're going to replace that hardcoded text with the plain text that we've
decrypted. And finally,
I just have to turn this into an fstring so that it actually gets inserted.
Now, the last thing I have to do is the to-do number three.
So here we're actually gonna check the direction variable.
And we're going to see that if it's equal to encode, well
then we're going to call that encrypt method that we had previously,
so indented inside the if statement. But else
if the direction was actually equal to decode, well
in this case, we're going to call our newly created decrypt function.
And we're going to pass in the cipher text as the text and the shift amount is
going to be equal to the shift. So once again,
these arguments come from up here
when we ask the user to input those values.
And now it should go over to the decrypt function and do everything that's
inside to decrypt the text.
So now let's give our program a run and just make sure that it works as
expected. So I'm going to encode our message hello,
shift it by five, and then I'm going to run it again.
And I'm going to try and decode this message now.
So I'm going to type decode and I'm going to paste in that message we had before
and type the same shift number
and now we've got our text decoded.
So that's how you solve step 2 of our project.
Have a review of the code here and once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and we're going to cover part 3 of the Caeser
cipher. So for all of that, and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right. So now that we can encrypt and decrypt our messages, well,
you might be asking, well, what else is there? We've completed the project,
right? Well, let's think about how we can improve our code.
Because if you take a look at the encrypt and decrypt functions,
you'll notice that a lot of the things that they're doing in it are very
similar, right? We've got some piece of empty string to begin with,
we loop through each of the letters in the text that we get passed over and we
get the position from the alphabet, get a new position,
and then add the new letter to that empty string.
Your challenge in this part of the Caesar cipher project is to combine the
encrypt and decrypt functions into a single function called Cesar.
And we're going to get rid of these if and elif statements,
and we're going to get rid of two functions that are overlapping.
And instead, we're just going to have a single function and we're going to call
it just once passing over text, shift, and direction.
So it's going to have three inputs and it's going to save us a lot of repetition
in our code.
Have a think about what you learned about functions with inputs and see if you
can complete this challenge. So pause the video now and give it a go.
Okay.
All right.
So, let's first create a new function and we're going to call it caesar.
This function is going to take three inputs this time.
Not only is it going to get the text, the shift,
but it's also going to get the direction.
So I'm going to call the first parameter start_text because we could be passed
the plain text or the cipher text. So let's just set it as the start text.
The next one I'm going to call the same
so I'm going to call it shift_amount. And then the last one
which is the direction, in order to differentiate it from this direction,
I'm going to make it a little bit longer.
So I'm going to call it the cipher_direction.
And now after a colon,
we're done with defining our function and we can start figuring out how we can
combine these two functions together. We know in both of them,
we need some sort of way of storing a piece of text
which starts out as empty
and then it ends up being the entire encrypted or decrypted text.
Let's create a new variable called end_text to contrast with a start_text.
And we started out as a empty string.
Now, the next thing we have to do is identical.
We have to loop through this text that we get passed over.
So let's create a for loop; for each letter in the start_text,
we're going to do something with each those letters. Namely,
we're going to get hold of the position of the letter in the alphabet.
So this line of code is actually identical across the two functions; position
equals alphabet using the index function to get hold of the index of the letter
that we're currently looping through.
The next part is a little bit tricky because on one hand when we're encrypting text,
we're shifting that position upwards by adding the shift amount.
But on the other hand, when we're decrypting,
we're subtracting the shift amount from the position.
So one way of doing this is, of course, by using an if statement. So you could
check if the cipher_direction was equal to encode. Well then in this case,
the new position is going to be equal to position plus the shift_amount.
And then you could do the else statement.
But there's actually an even easier way of doing this.
We can just check for if the cipher direction was decode.
And in this case, we take the shift amount and we multiply it by minus one.
So remember this line of code is exactly the same as
this, but it's just way more succinct.
And now outside the if statement,
we can define our new position and set it to equal the previous position plus
the shift amount.
And the reason why this works is because let's say that we had a shift amount of
five and we wanted to encode our text, well the new position is obviously going
to be previous position plus five. Now on the other hand,
if we were decoding, well this
if statement is going to trip and our five multiplied by minus one becomes minus
five. So now when we add -5 to
the previous position,
so let's say the previous position was 12 plus -5,
then a quick check with a calculator should get you a 7.
It's exactly the same as subtraction.
So now that we've gotten over that hurdle,
all we have to do is to tap into our end_text and to add to it by getting hold
of the letter at the new position
in the alphabet. And finally, once all of that's done,
we of course need to print the results.
Notice how previously we said the encoded text is and the decoded text is,
well, let's copy this string and paste it in here.
How can we change this part to be dynamic,
so depending on the cipher direction,
and then this part is easy because we can just replace it with the end_
text.
So one way is, remember that when the user is typing in the direction,
they're typing in either encode or decode. So we can delete everything other than
that 'd' and then dynamically insert the cipher direction that we get passed.
And now if we make that an fstring,
it should be able to insert encoded text is whatever the end text is, or
decoded
text is whatever it may be. Now we can go ahead and delete both of these
functions
and also this if statement and we can tackle to-do number two
and we can simply just call the Caesar function
passing over the start_text as the text the user inputted,
the shift_amount as the shift that they inputted,
and finally, the cypher direction as the direction that they inputted.
Now, we've cut down our code by a lot
and we've gotten rid of all the repeated bits of code and we've used what we've
learned about functions with inputs to vastly simplify our code.
We're getting the same function to do repeated actions,
but depending on the different inputs,
it does something completely different.
So now let's give our code a run and let's just make sure that everything works.
Encoding.
Okay.
And decoding.
So there's a bit of an issue there because when we get our decoded result back,
it says holvo instead of hello. So what's going on here?
Well, in my code that I wrote for the Caesar function,
I've accidentally introduced a bug. And as programmers,
none of us are free from this fault. We create bugs, but then we fix them.
So why don't you use this as a good debugging opportunity?
If you've been typing along with me,
I want you to take a look at the code or take a look at the screen and see if
you can figure out what is causing this aberrant decoded result.
Why are we getting holvo back instead of hello?
Where is the problem in our logic in our code?
See if you can solve this and fix the code so that we get back the decoded
results of hello. Pause the video and give that a go.
All right.
So this bug,
if we think about the logic, is caused because our
if statement where we check the cipher_direction and change the shift_amount
by multiplying it by minus one,
this line of code lives inside the for loop.
And we know about for loops that it's going to keep going again and again.
So for every letter in the start_text of which there are five,
every single time, this code is going to get executed and the cipher direction
is always decode so we keep multiplying that shift amount by minus one.
So the first one becomes decode,
the next one becomes encode, decode, encode, decode.
And that's why we're getting some parts of our hello back, but the 'o'
and the 'v' are the parts that are not right.
So in order to fix this, all we have to do is take our
if statement out of the for loop, put it before
the for loop right here.
And now if we run this again and we try to decode the same message,
so that was mjqqt, and we use the same shift number,
but now we get back the correct decoded results. Brilliant.
So did you manage to get that right? Don't worry
if you use a slightly different way of coding this logic up.
It really doesn't matter
as long as you managed to get it to work in the end and combine the two functions
into one. Once you're happy with step three,
head over to the next lesson and we'll tackle the final part
part four of the Caesar cipher
where we complete our project. For all of that, and more,
I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right, we're about to cross the finish line. We're onto the last part of our Caesar cipher
and we're going to complete it in this lesson. First
go ahead and fork your own copy of part four of the Caesar cipher starting code.
And notice, firstly, we've got an extra file here called art.
And this, if you expand it fully, you should see an ASCII art of our logo.
Now, what we want to be able to do in this lesson is just to tidy up some of the loose ends, improve
the user experience and fix some of the bugs that you may or may not be aware of. To-do
#1 tells us to import and print the logo from art.py and this is going to show up when we first
load up our program like this.
Next, we're going to tackle this one. One of the things we haven't really thought about is if the
user enters a shift number that's actually really, really large like 100, then we're actually going
to run out of letters in our alphabet.
And so we're going to use what you've learnt before
and it might take a little bit of thinking around this to fix this particular bug right here.
And once you've done that, then we move on to over here and we think about what to do if the user wanted
to type a number, a symbol or a space.
So we want to preserve the symbols, space, or number that they typed in
and we're only going to use our cipher on the rest of the message,
so only the alphabetical letters. And everything else we're going to leave the same.
So, for example, if we had the text meet me at 3, then the end_text will keep the spaces where
they were, keep the numbers where they were.
And also if there were any symbols, we would also keep that in our final end_text.
And it's only the letters which will get scrambled.
And then finally, to-do #4, we're going to figure out how to ask the user if they want to
restart the cipher program.
So notice how in the final version, when we run this once, we can actually type yes
to go again.
This way we can keep encoding and decoding as much as we want until we're actually done when we can
type no
and it says goodbye
and that's the end of the code.
What we want to be able to do is instead of having to run our code again and again, we're going to
figure out a way of getting our code to be rerun
if the user typed yes to this question. And if they typed no, then and only then do we actually end
the program.
It might take a little bit of thinking to figure out how to solve all of these to-dos.
But once you're ready, if you're up for the challenge, then pause the video now and give it a go.
All right, so let's tackle them one by one. The first one you've already done before.
All it needs is to import the art file.
And if we want to be able to use the logo variable inside the art file, this one, then we can also
simply just write from art import logo.
So now we can print this logo right here.
So that's to-do #1 completed, now let's do the next one. This one requires us to figure out some
sort of clever solution so that when a user enters a shift that's greater than the number of letters
in the alphabet
over here, we have some sort of way of getting it back within the range of 0 to 25.
And I want you to see what happens when I type a message and I put a shift that's really large. You
can see we get an index out of range error because there is no letter at position 77 from the alphabet.
So that's why this line 14 over here actually breaks down.
If you have trouble with this, I gave you a hint where I wanted you to think about how you can use
the modulus.
So if we take 45 and we use the modulus operator to divide 45 by 26, which is the total number of letters
in the alphabet, then we should end up with the remainder.
Now, if you imagine we're dividing 45 by 26, then 26 goes into 45 once,
so we will get one, but we will have a remainder of 19.
So this is what we get from the modulus.
We would get the result to be 19, which is just the remainder.
And effectively, what this code does is it's going to divide a number by 26 as many times as needed
until we get to the final point where it can no longer be divided fully and we end up with a remainder.
And that remainder allows us to shift the shift number that's entered into something that fits in with
the number of letters of the alphabet that we have in here.
So then our code that we would have here is to modify the shift by taking the shift that the user entered
up here and then using the modulus to divide it by 26 as many times as needed until we get the remainder.
So now if we test this out, you can see that no matter how long my shift number is, let's try 87, we're
always going to get a result back because it's shifting that number down to fit within our alphabet.
And once you're done, let's move on to to-do #3.
So here we want to be able to allow any number, symbol or space, basically anything that's not within
the alphabet to go through and end up in the end_text.
But if it is one of the letters inside this list alphabet, then and only then do we actually want to
do the shifting and encoding.
In order to achieve this, we should probably use an if statement to say if the char...
So notice how I've changed the for loop to instead of writing for letter in start_text which kind
of assumes that everything in the start_text is a letter, to char which stands for character instead
because a character could be a number, could be a symbol, could be a letter, could be space.
And then once we get hold of the char or the character, we're going to check to see if the char is
in the alphabet.
So if it is indeed one of these letters and not some other random character, well then and only then
do we actually want this code to be executed.
So let me just make sure all the indentation is correct. And if it's not inside the alphabet, so else,
well then, in this case, we actually want to make the end_text append the actual character,
so without any modification.
Now, if we test this code by running it, so let's go ahead and encode. And I'm going to encode something
like Hello123%^ 321.
And now when I hit enter and I give it a shift, then you can see that the encoded result has all the
letters, all the things are in that list, the alphabet encoded.
But everything else, the numbers and the symbols are all left as they are, because more often than
not, your user might want to write a message like meet me at five or something, something exclamation
mark.
And this is just a very simple way of making it work.
Now, of course, there's a lot of other ways that you could have solved this.
So you could have, in fact, added a whole bunch of symbols and numbers and space and other characters
to this list
And instead of calling it alphabet, it could have been the characters list and then you could have
encoded all of that.
But that's actually not what the toO-do asks for. It wants us to let through the numbers, symbols, space
and only encode the letters.
So now all we have left is the last to-do, and this is probably going to be the most difficult one out
of the lot. What we want to do here is we want to be able to ask the user whether if they want to go
again, so whether if they want to encode or decode another message. And what happens in the final version,
the completed version of the app, is if we encode a message
and we get the result back, it doesn't just end, it doesn't exit because otherwise you would see that
message down here run again.
Instead it continues and it asks us, well, do you want to go again? So we could write
yes.
And it lets us again encode or decode a message.
We can basically go on and on and on and repeating this program until we want to exit.
And it's at that point when we can no longer type anything into our program and our code ends and we'd
have to run the whole thing again in order to use it again.
So at the moment, the part of our code that actually needs to be repeated if the user wanted to restart
it is actually just this part.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm actually going to shrink it down a bit.
And now all we're left with is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 lines of code which needs repeat if
we're going to get the user to reuse the Caesar cipher.
What if we go ahead and indent this and put it inside a while loop?
What are we going to check to make sure that our loop continues?
Well, we could create a flag called should_continue and we start this out to be true.
And then while this is still true, we continue to keep looping through this so that the user gets to
input a new direction, new text, new shift and call the Caesar cipher on that again.
When should we stop it though?
Well, if at the end of deciphering or encoding their message, we ask them a question, something like
type
yes
if you want to go again or type no
if you don't want to, we could put that inside an input.
Like so. And we can save their answer inside a variable. Let's just call that result. So now we can
use an if statement to check
well, if the results is equal to no,
so when they actually want to stop and they want to exit the while loop, well, at this point we can
switch
that should_continue to false.
And once that's done, then this means that this while loop, when it checks it, this is going to be
false and it will no longer continue.
Just as a final touch, we can even tell the user goodbye
so that they know that the program has ended.
Now let's go ahead and run our code and see if it works.
All right, so let's first encode something. And now I can type yes to go again, and you can see it's
allowing me to type encode or decode.
So let's encode something else.
Now, finally, if I decided I've had enough, I'm done with encoding and decoding, I'm going to type
no.
It tells me goodbye and I can now see my prompt, which means it's actually exited out of the program
and I would need to run it again in order to restart it.
Did you manage to get that right?
If you want to take a look at the completed code, then you can head over to caesar-cipher-4-end and
you will find the same code as I've got here.
And of course, feel free to play around with the code, modify it and make this program your own.
So if you wanted to add some extra features, if you wanted to make sure that the numbers and symbols
are all being encrypted and any sort of bells and whistles and anything else that you can think of,
this is the time to do it now.
But once you're done, be sure to get some rest, because tomorrow is yet another packed session where
we're going to talk more about Python dictionaries.
For all of that and more, I bid you good night and I'll see you tomorrow.
Hey, welcome back. It's Day 9 of 100 Days of Code.
And today we're going to be learning more about Python dictionaries
and nesting. And by the end of today,
you will have built a silent auction program.
We all know that there are auctions where everybody bids and you can see
everybody else's bid and the auctioneer gets you to bid higher and higher
values. Now there's also a type of auction called
a silent auction where everybody bids silently and no one knows the other
person's bids until at the very end of the auction where the highest bid is
revealed. That's what we're going to be building.
And if you wanna check out the final program,
then you can go to blind-auction-completed
.appbrewery.repl.run.
And here you'll not only see this amazing gavel built out of ASCII,
but also the secret auction program. So here's how it works:
let's say that I'm going to be the first person logging onto the program.
I'm going to give my name and my bid. Let's say
I'm going to bid a $53 for this item.
And once I'm done with my bid, it asked me whether
if there are any other bidders.
So if I type a yes then the screen clears and I can handover the laptop to
the next person who's going to make their bid. So let's say there's James
who's going to bid, um, even less than I did.
And then he's gonna make way for the final bidder who is going to bid $121.
So now at this stage, if everybody is done, then we type no,
and it's going to now tally up all the bids and figure out who bid the highest
and give us a winner, printing out 'The winner is Jenny
with a bid of $121.' There's a number of places that you could use this
if you are auctioning some piece of art or if you're trying to outbid your
brothers and sisters on who gets to go on the trampoline,
or if you're trying to start an auction with your friends or coworkers.
The silent auction has many, many uses. All right, in today's lessons,
we're going to be focusing mostly on the Python dictionary. But in addition,
we're also going to look at how we can nest say lists inside lists or
dictionaries inside dictionaries and also mixing lists and dictionaries as well.
Once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and let's get started with the day.
All right.
So the first thing I want to talk about is dictionaries in Python. Now,
dictionaries in Python work kind of similarly to dictionaries in real life,
right? So if you were to look up a word in the dictionary
say the word code, then you might find the definition as something along the
lines of program instructions for the computer. And dictionaries are really
useful because they allow us to group together and tag related pieces of
information.
The way I like to think about dictionaries is in the form of a table.
Every dictionary has two parts to it.
On the left hand side is the key,
and that is the equivalent of the word in the dictionary,
and then it's also got an associated value. That would be the equivalent
of the actual definition of the word.
Now let's say that we took this variation simple table of definitions of
programming words that we've come across so far
and we go ahead and we try to convert it right into a dictionary,
how would we do that? Let me firstly
drop the last two rows and let's just start with the first one.
The first thing we want to do is we want them to create a dictionary. And to do
that in Python, this is what the syntax looks like.
We have a set of curly braces and everything that's inside
the curly brace is the content of our dictionary.
The key goes first followed by a colon and then followed by the value. In our
table we've got this word bug, which is the first key,
so we can replace that over here in our dictionary. And the value that's
associated with this key is the definition for a bug.
So an error in a program that prevents the program from running as expected,
that becomes the value and can be replaced here after the colon.
So now, we've created an actual dictionary using Python code.
What if you wanted to have more than one entry in your dictionary? Well,
you would separate each of the key value pairs using a comma,
and then you can continue adding key and value pairs until you get to the end of
your dictionary. All right,
let's take a look at dictionaries in action.
If you head over to the day nine start code file and go ahead and fork your own
copy to work alongside me, then you can see that in here
I've already added the dictionary that we were defining earlier on,
and I've stored it inside of a variable called programming dictionary. Now,
currently I've only got two entries in this dictionary,
the definition for a bug and the definition for function. Now,
the first thing I want to highlight is when you create a dictionary that has
more than one element such as in this case,
then you want to take care to format it properly so that it's more easily
readable.
So what you'll see Python programmers do by convention is they will start off
the dictionary with the open curly brace at the top
and then every subsequent entry is indented by one indent.
And then at the very end of that entry, there's a comma
and then we hit enter so that the next item goes onto the next line
and finally,
the last curly brace should go at the very beginning in line with the start of
the dictionary.
And another thing that's quite nice to do is to cap off all entries in your
dictionary or list with a comma.
This means that if you needed to add more items into the dictionary
you can simply just hit enter and continue typing the next thing.
And if we wanted to add another entry,
it's a simple as adding in the key, a colon and then the value and to cap it
off again with a comma.
So now our dictionary represents exactly the same data as we saw in our table
over here with a bunch of key value pairs and a total of three entries.
Now,
the next thing I want to do is what if I wanted to retrieve an item from the
dictionary, because we know that if we had a list
what we would do is we would use a set of square brackets
and then we would give the index of the item that we wanted.
So the item at index zero or one or two and so on and so forth. Now for
dictionaries, it's kind of similar in terms of syntax
but the only difference is that dictionaries have elements which are identified
by their key. If we wanted this piece of information, for example,
then all we have to do is tap into the dictionary and then add a set of square
brackets and inside the square brackets, we're going to provide the key.
So here the key is a string and it's the string bug.
So let's go ahead and put bug in here.
And now if I go ahead and print this,
then you can see that it is going to give me the value,
which is 'An error in a program that prevents the program from running as
expected.' Now it's really,
really important that you make sure that when you're fetching something out of a
dictionary by it's key that you actually spell the key correctly.
A really
really common error is when you're trying to retrieve something out of a
dictionary and you've just made a very simple typo. So instead of 'u'
I'm typing 'o' here and you'll see
we get an error. And the error tells us that it's a key error referring to this
particular key and it highlights this line 7 where we're trying to retrieve
something out of this dictionary by this key.
Basically it's telling you that this key doesn't actually exist and it can't be
found. So it doesn't know what it is that you want. Remember how
when we had lists and when we try to retrieve something that was not inside the
list. So for example, this particular list at index 4
doesn't actually exist because this is zero one, two, three,
and four is actually not a piece of data inside of this list.
Similarly with dictionaries, if we try to put in a key that doesn't exist,
then we get this key error.
Now another common pitfall that students fall down into is they don't actually
use the correct data type. So for example,
if we defined this dictionary without putting a string around each of these
keys, then it's going to error out and it won't even let us run.
It's going to tell us undefined named bug because it thinks that this is a
variable that you've declared somewhere,
but it's not. In fact, what you wanted are these strings for keys.
And so when you have a key that is a string,
when you're trying to retrieve the data from that key,
you also have to make sure that you provide the key in its actual data type.
So for example, if this was just a number, say one, two, three,
then, of course, all you have to write in here is just one, two, three,
and it would know that this piece of data is what you wanted.
So that's how you retrieve items from a dictionary by adding a square bracket
and then giving it the key.
And it will look for the key inside the dictionary and give you back the
value. Now,
what if you wanted to add a piece of data such as that loop that we had earlier
on, but you want to do it programmatically.
So instead of doing it
when you were defining the dictionary at the beginning,
what if at some later stage in your program you needed to add a new entry?
Well, to do this, it's also really simple.
All you have to do is to tap into the dictionary,
which is called programming dictionary in our case and again,
using square brackets, we define the key.
The key I'm going to add is our loop.
And then after a equal sign, I get to assign the value.
So in my case, the value is going to be the definition for a loop.
And now when this line of code is executed and we go ahead and just print the
programming dictionary after this has happened,
then we'll see that it's actually different from what we had before.
So let's hit run and you can see that previously we had a programming dictionary
that had only two items, bug and function.
And after this line 10, where we print our programming dictionary again,
you can see it's now got three items, bug, function, and loop.
Now very often when you're writing code,
it can be really helpful to start out with a empty dictionary. Just as you saw
previously,
you create an empty list by simply having a set of square brackets with nothing
inside.
You can also create an empty dictionary by simply creating a set of curly braces
with nothing inside. And then at a later stage,
you can add to your dictionary by using this method that you saw here.
Now, on the other hand,
you might actually want to wipe an entire dictionary. Here,
I'm creating a new empty dictionary by creating this pair of curly braces with
nothing inside.
But I can also wipe an existing dictionary by simply doing the same thing.
We know that this dictionary, programming_dictionary, has three items in it.
But on line 17,
I'm going to say programming dictionary equals empty dictionary.
And now if I move this print statement down here,
then you can see that when it prints out,
it's actually going to be completely empty.
That can be really useful if you wanted to clear out a user's progress
or for example, if a game restarts,
then all the scores and stats will probably have to be wiped empty.
So this is one way that you could do that.
Now this method of tapping into a dictionary,
using the key to fetch the relevant item from it
and then doing something with it goes beyond just adding.
You can also use this to edit an item in a dictionary.
For example, let me go ahead and comment out these two lines of code
so we don't wipe our programming dictionary and instead I'm going to tap into
the programming dictionary and I'm going to fetch the item that has a key of bug
and I'm going to redefine its value.
So currently it should be an error in a program that prevents the program from
running as expected.
And I can prove that if I just wrap this around a print statement.
If instead I wanted this to be a different value,
then I can simply use the same syntax as I did for adding new items
but in this case
I'm actually editing this entry because it's going to look through the
dictionary,
find a value with this key and then assign it to whatever I put on the right
hand side of the equal sign. Now, on the other hand,
if it finds nothing with that key,
then it's going to create a new entry with the value again
on the right hand side of the equal sign.
Now let's say that a bug is instead 'A moth in your computer.'
Now, if I go and print my programming dictionary once more,
then you can see that the definition for our bug has now just been changed.
The final thing with regards to dictionaries that I think is really,
really useful is how you loop through a dictionary. And using your knowledge from
lists you might think that to loop through a dictionary, you would,
let's say we are using a for loop. And we say for, um,
thing in programming dictionary,
let's go ahead and print this thing each time.
Here's a good moment to play computer and think,
what do you expect to be printed?
So let's comment out all of the other print statements
so we don't get confused. And when I click run,
what do you think will be printed?
Right?
All right. Is that what you expected? Because it certainly
wasn't what I expected when I first learned Python.
I thought it would give me each of the items in the dictionary with this key and
its value.
But instead this code actually just gives you the keys.
Now, of course, once you do have access to the key, instead of thing,
I should actually really say for key in programming_dictionary.
If I wanted to print the key, then of course I could just write print key.
But if I wanted to get hold of the value,
I could equally just as easily tap into my dictionary,
use the square brackets and pass in that key.
So now when I hit run, you can see it's giving me first
the key from this line and then secondly
the value based on this line.
I'm using that retrieval code in order to get the value.
Of course,
remember that you can get access to all the code that I'm writing here by
looking at the end code of the day
that you'll find on the course resources list.
And if you want to, have a quick review of everything that we've gone through so
far,
because a lot of this knowledge is going to be tested in the next lesson where
we do a coding exercise that will really solidify everything you've learned in
this lesson so far. So for all of that, and more, I'll see on the next lesson.
All right. So hopefully everything we've learned in the last lesson made sense,
and you're ready to put your knowledge to the test by completing the first
coding challenge today.
And what you're going to be building is a grading program.
So if you take a look at the day 9.1 grading program
Repl.it coding exercise, you'll see that to begin,
I've already created a dictionary with a bunch of student names and their test
scores. Now,
without changing any of the code above here or below here,
I want you to write a program that will be able to convert these scores into a
grade. So the grading criteria is over here in the instructions.
So if the student's scores above 91,
then they'll get the grade outstanding. If they score above 81,
they get exceeds expectations and then acceptable.
And then finally everybody's scoring 70 or a lower gets the fail grade.
Essentially,
what you're going to be doing is creating an empty dictionary from scratch
which is going to be called student_grades.
And you're going to write some code so that each of the students are represented
inside this new dictionary.
And instead of having scores as the value's in that dictionary,
you are going to have the grades that correspond to the scores that they got.
Have a read through the instructions and the hints if you need some help,
but once you're ready, go ahead and pause the video and give this a go.
[inaudible]
All right. So to begin, let's first tackle this to-do 1.
Let's create a new empty dictionary called student_grades.
And the student_grades has to be spelled exactly the same as you see here,
because otherwise this print statement will not work.
The student_grades is gonna be an empty dictionary,
which if you remember from the last lesson, we said
it looks like this with two curly braces and nothing inside.
Now let's move on to todo number 2.
So we're going to write some code below so that we actually add the grades to
this student grades dictionary.
And we of course can get those grades by looking at each of the student's
scores. How can we do this? Well,
we're probably going to need a for loop because there's lots of items in this
dictionary. Let's go ahead and loop through this student_scores dictionary,
and I'm going to call each of the items the student,
because remember when we have a for loop looping through a dictionary like we
are doing here,
each of the items that gets picked out is actually the key rather than the whole
item. So again, we talked about this in the last lesson,
but hopefully, this should really make it clear. But even if you didn't know,
you could always of course just print it, right?
So if we go ahead and use the for loop and print it,
you can see we get all of the keys from this dictionary when we're looping
through it. So for each of the students,
we want to get hold of their score.
We can calculate the score by getting hold of the value
using this key from this dictionary. And to do that,
if you remember, is tapping in to the dictionary,
adding a set of square brackets and then giving it the key. So in this case,
it's going to be each of the student names. And once we've got a hold of the
score, well then we can use our if statement to check well
if the score is greater than 90,
so anything above 90,
then that means they're going to end up with outstanding.
Now, this is the part where we add a new entry to this student_grades dictionary.
So let's tap into the dictionary, use a set of square brackets again
to give it a key. And the key,
of course, should still be the student name which comes from here,
which is going to be the same as this.
Then we can add a equal sign and followed by the value
which is going to be outstanding.
So now we can repeat this process for the rest of these grades.
Yeah.
Everybody who scored above 80 but not above 90, so remember that this
if statement once triggered, will skip all of the rest of the elif statements.
And then if they scored above 70, they would get acceptable. And finally,
for everybody else, which means they scored lower than 70,
then they're going to end up with a fail grade.
Now it's really important that if you want the test to pass that each of these
strings has to match what you see over here exactly.
Now that we've done all of this hard work, manipulating our dictionary,
it's time to actually go ahead and run our code and see what we get.
So now our code has converted
each of these scores to the corresponding grade.
Harry gets exceeds expectations because his score is between 81 and 90, Ron gets
acceptable because it's between 70 and 80, and so on and so forth.
Now, did you manage to get it right,
or did you have any problems working with dictionaries? Now,
if you go beyond this lesson
I'm going to assume that you are comfortable with editing dictionaries,
adding to it, creating new ones.
So if you are not yet fully there, then I recommend just going back to the last
lesson, just reviewing it once more.
Once you've done that, head over to the next lesson
and we're going to talk more about nesting in dictionaries and lists. For all of that
and more, I'll see you there.
Now that we've seen lists as well as dictionaries
I want to talk about a concept that you often see in both of these collection
types and that's something called nesting. Now,
if we imagine a list or a dictionary
being something like a folder where lots of things can be stored inside it,
then nesting lists and dictionaries is just a matter of putting one inside the
other. For example,
here;s a dictionary that is very simple,
it's only got one key-value pair.
Now we know that we can add multiple key-value pairs into the same dictionary by
just adding a bunch of commas to separate them. Now, what if
instead of having a simple value like a string or a number,
I could also put a list as a value as well.
Similarly,
I could also use a dictionary as a value. In this case
we've got a list as the value for key, this first one,
and we've got a dictionary as the value for key2. Notice how this is a list and
a dictionary nested inside another dictionary.
The structure gets a little bit more complex,
but it gives us more flexibility when we're trying to store more complex pieces
of data. Coming back to our code,
let's go ahead and create some sample dictionaries to see what this actually
looks like in real life. For example,
this could be a dictionary that contains the country as the key and the city,
that is the capital, as the value. So for France,
that's Paris, for Germany that's Berlin.
This is a very simple dictionary that you've seen already. Now,
if I wanted to nest a list in a dictionary,
then I would be able to represent even more complex data. For example,
if I had a travel log where I was going to collect a dictionary of all the
cities I had been for each of the countries I've traveled to. So for example,
if I had traveled to France and I wanted to say that I've been to multiple
cities, I can't simply just say Paris,
and then Lille, Dijon, that doesn't really work because each key can only have one
value. The only way that we can make these three pieces of data
one value is by turning it into a list, like so.
So now in our travel log dictionary
as represented by the curly braces,
we have one key value pair and it just so happens that
the value in this case is a list.
And of course you can go on and add as many entries as you would like,
and still preserving this kind of structure of key being a string and the value
being a list. Now,
this idea of nesting isn't limited dictionaries by the way.
You could also just nest a list in a list.
So you could have a list which is A
and then B, and then the third item just happens to be another list which has C and D.
This is perfectly valid Python code
but it's not quite as useful as nesting a list in a dictionary or a dictionary
in a dictionary, because the way that data is structured. Now,
what if you wanted to nest a dictionary in a dictionary?
Let's say that we wanted to expand our travel log.
And instead of just storing the cities that I visited in each country,
what if I wanted to also keep track of how many visits I've made to that
country?
Or what if I wanted to actually label what this piece of data is?
Because at the moment it's kind of like here's
a bunch of cities that's associated with the country,
but it doesn't really describe this list.
And I'd like to give this to you as a challenge,
have a go at changing the France entry so that it contains another dictionary.
For the nested dictionary use the key cities_visited,
and for the value you can keep the list of Paris, Lille and Dijon.
Pause the video now and see if you can get that to work.
Yeah.
All right, so here's the solution. By nesting a dictionary
we can label the Paris, Lille and Dijon lists as cities visited.
All I need to do is create the string,
"cities_visited" and add a colon after it. But there's one more step.
We have to add a pair of curly braces so that France is associated with a single
value, namely our nested dictionary.
Now that we have a dictionary of the travel log,
all the countries I've been to, and each country has a value that is a dictionary
in itself and it can store multiple pieces of data
including the cities I've visited in that country
as well as things such as the total number of visits,
which in this case would have a string as the key and a
number of as the value. Now
have a go at creating your own travel log or modifying the second part of the
travel log so that you also have a dictionary nested in a dictionary and you're
able to represent something like this,
the number of cities you visited in a list and another additional piece of data,
if you wanted to.
Right,
And hopefully would have done something similar to this.
And so now our data structure is such that we've got a list nested inside a
dictionary, which is in itself nested in another dictionary.
Now that we've seen nesting lists inside dictionaries, dictionaries inside
dictionaries,
the last thing I want to show you is nesting a dictionary inside a list.
So we could basically have multiple dictionaries inside a single list.
So remember that lists are ordered and they're accessed by the positions inside the
list. So this dictionary would be the item at index zero,
this one at index one and so on and so forth.
Whereas inside a dictionary,
the items are accessed by their keys like this France or Germany.
Now I want to do the last type which is nesting a dictionary
in a list.
And I'm going to be working with the same travel log that we had previously,
but I want to change it so that instead of having this being one giant
dictionary with key-value pairs,
I want to change it so that each of these entries are a dictionary in itself.
Instead of having France be the key of this dictionary here,
I want the turn it into its own key-value pair. Going inside this dictionary,
I'm going to create a new key
which is called country and then put France as the value for that key.
So now I have an entire dictionary that has three pieces of data.
The country visited, the cities visited,
and the total number of visits. Let's do the same for Germany as well.
So now you can see we've got two dictionaries and instead of holding these two
dictionaries inside a dictionary,
I'm going to change it so that it's now a list. I'm going to turn these curly
braces into square brackets
and this way we can add as many of these dictionaries inside the list and
iterate through them if we need to.
When we've been creating dictionaries that only have one or two key-value pairs,
we've kind of just kept it all on one line.
But once you've got more and more key-value pairs in the dictionary,
it's usually a good idea to go ahead and separate out each of the entries,
Right?
Like what I'm doing here.
Now it's a little bit easier to see that we have a list which contains two
items, and each item is a dictionary.
Each dictionary has three key-value pairs and they all contain different types
of data. The first one has a value which is a string,
the second one holds a list and the third one holds a number.
The data types inside a dictionary can be completely mixed up if you want it to.
But what can't change is you still need a key and a value separated by a colon.
Now the only downside to this is you want to make sure that you're actually
aware that later on when you try to pull out the number of visits,
it's actually a number that you're working with rather than a string or when
you're trying to get hold of the cities visited
it's a list rather than a dictionary, for example.
So now that we've the various different types of nesting,
it's time for you to actually really understand this and get to grips with this
concept by completing a challenge yourself. In the next lesson,
I've got a coding challenge for you based on this travel log and you'll need to
use what you've learned so far to be able to complete it.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now,
if you head over to Repl.it, click on day 9.2 dictionary in list,
this coding exercise should appear.
And you'll see that we actually have the same list that we created at the end of the
last lesson.
This is a list called travel_log and it logs the countries that we've been
to, how many times we've visited it,
and the cities that we visited while we were there.
This is a list of dictionaries
which contain a list of cities.
There's some heavy nesting going on here.
Now your job is to make sure that this line of code on line 20 and 21 actually
work. In order to make it work, you are going to have to write a program.
So it's going to be a function
that's going to go somewhere in here. And you're going to get it to be able to add
new countries, the name,
the number of visits and the cities that you've been to so that it gets
populated in the travel log. And when we print travel log at the end,
it should show us all three of these entries.
So remember, the goal is not to modify this directly. In fact,
I don't want you to touch this part at all. Instead,
it should be your function
that's going to somehow go through this travel log and add these new pieces of
data.
Have a think about how are you going to achieve this and then pause the
video and give it a go. All right.
So, because we've already defined the name of the function here, in order for our
code to actually work and for the tests to go through,
we also have to create the function using exactly the same name.
So it's called add_new_country.
And then the inputs that it's going to take are the country_visited, the times_
visited,
and finally the cities_visited.
So now that we've created our new function,
the next job is to figure out, well,
how do we add these pieces of data
that's going to be passed in to these parameters and get that into this travel
log?
So the first thing you need to notice is each of the entries inside  the
travel_log is a dictionary.
In order to add to that list,
we should probably start off by creating a new dictionary that has all of these
pieces of data in it. For example,
we could create a new dictionary called new_country, which is an empty dictionary.
And then we can add each of these pieces of data to the dictionary. So we
could say new_country[]
and then we give the key that we want to add. So in this case,
it would be the key country as a string,
and the data or the value that's going to go in that is going to be whatever
gets passed into country_visited.
So now all we have to do is repeat the process for the other keys in the
dictionary. So visits is the next one,
and that's going to be set equal to the times_visited. And finally,
we're also going to populate the final key which is cities,
and that is going to be equal to the cities_visited.
Now, at this point, if you were to print out new_country,
you should see a dictionary with the three key-value pairs and the keys will
always be the same,
but the values will depend on which arguments were passed in when this function
was called. So once we have that new country,
then we can actually take our travel log,
and remember that the travel log is actually at its base, a list.
So instead of adding to it like we have been doing
when we're using a dictionary, in order to add to lists if you remember,
you should probably use the function append. And inside here,
we can add a new item to our list.
And that new item is, of course, going to be this dictionary called new_country.
So now if we go ahead and click run,
then you can see when travel_log gets printed on now line 27,
it's now got three entries.
The first entry is the dictionary for France,
the second is the dictionary for Germany,
and the last one is the dictionary for Russia.
We have now a list with three items,
each being a dictionary, each with a nested list inside as
well. So if
you wanted to,
you now have a way of keeping track of all the places you visited.
And later on,
as we start building out more complex apps and web applications,
then you can easily see how logic like this might be really useful
if we were building a real-life website for tracking our travels.
Have a play around with nesting, dictionaries, and lists.
And once you're happy that you've understood everything that's going on,
then head over to the next lesson and we're going to start tackling our final
project.
All right. So now that you've learned all about dictionaries,
we're going to put all of that knowledge to test and to use by building a blind
auction program. So here's the program. When you first run it,
it's just going to show you the logo art and maybe a line that tells you what
program you're in. And then it's going to ask you for your name.
So let's say we have three bidders, right? So first go,
I go to the computer. I type in my name, I type in my bid and I hit enter.
It asked me if there are any other bidders, I look around the room,
I see two other colleagues. So I type yes.
And now it clears the entire screen.
So the other people can't see what my bid was.
So now I leave the computer and my colleague comes over.
They type in their name and also their bid.
And again,
they look around the room and they see this one other person who wants to bid.
So they hit yes, again, it clears their bid. And finally,
the last person makes their bid. At this point, everybody has bid
so she's going to type no.
And it's at this moment when our program is going to work out
who has made the highest bid and print out who the winner is and what their bid
was. This way, instead of competing with each other on bids,
we actually all just give the highest price we're willing to pay
and this is known as quite an efficient way of making a bid.
And you see that a lot in say the construction industry and government,
et cetera.
The important thing in this program is you're going to start out using the blind
auction start replit.
And the first thing you'll notice is that I've already imported this function
called clear from the replit module.
And you can basically call this function, clear, whenever you want to clear the
output just as you saw here. Whenever we typed yes after being asked
if there are any other bidders,
that just calls the clear
and then it gets rid of everything that's in the console. In addition,
we've also got the starting art of the gavel logo
which you're going to put into the program.
And the most important thing of all is that I want you to create a dictionary so
that each person's name will be the key and their bid will be the value.
And this dictionary is going to contain many of these key-value pairs
and at the very end of the program when everybody's done with bidding,
then we're going to loop through that dictionary and figure out who has made the
highest bid. If you want,
this is a good time to analyze this completed project and see if you can
create your own flowchart using something like draw.io that I've shown you
before, or just take a piece of paper and a pen and draw out flowchart.
Now, if you want a hint,
then you can head over to the course resources and you'll get taken to the flow
chart that I've created for this program. So spoiler alert,
I'm about to show you that flow chart. So if you don't want to see it
and you want to create your own because it's a relatively simple program,
then pause the video now and complete the challenge by yourself.
Now for everybody else, who's still here, I want to show you,
this is the flow chart I've created to represent this program.
So we start at the beginning. We first show the logo from that file, art.py,
and then we ask for a name input, we ask for their price.
Now we're gonna add the name and the bid into a dictionary with the name as the
key and the bid as the value. Now, once we're done with that,
then we get to ask the user for another input and see if there are any other
users who want to bid. So if they answer yes,
then we're going to clear the screen and we're going to go back to here,
ask for another name, another price, and so on and so forth. But if they say, no,
everybody's done with bidding,
then we're going to call some sort of function that we have,
which is going to loop through our dictionary that was created here and find the
person who had the highest bid value and then declare them as the winner and
print out their bid. So it's a relatively simple program,
at least compared to other things that you've built so far.
So this is the time to pause the video and give it a go.
I'll see you on the next lesson where we'll go through the solution together.
All right, so how did you get on with today's project?
Hopefully it went really well and you're just here to see how I did it.
As I mentioned before, it's really useful when you're trying to create a large project to break it
down into smaller pieces so that you can tackle each of the pieces one by one.
And a great way of doing that is by creating your own flowchart.
So as I've shown you before in the end of the last lesson, this is the flowchart that I've created
for this particular program, and I'm going to follow it step by step to create this final blind auction
program.
The first thing we're going to do is we're going to show the logo from this file art.py, and notice
how this logo is stored inside a variable called logo.
The first thing we have to do is to fork our own copy of the starting project, and then we're going
to look inside the art.py module and then we're going to import that logo.
So now I can go ahead and print my logo.
So that's the first step done. Next we're going to ask for a name.
So that's going to be in the form of an input.
So let's go ahead and create a variable called name and we're going to set it to be an input.
And the input is going to say, what is your name?
So they're going to type in their name and that's going to be stored inside this variable.
Now, the next thing we're going to do is ask them for their bidding price. We'll say that inside a variable
called price and we'll create another input to ask them what is your bid?
And at the end of this, I'm going to add a dollar sign just so that when they are typing their bids,
they'll see this line.
And when they start typing, the cursor should be about here so they can see the dollar symbol before
their price.
So now we're down to here and we have to add our name and our bidding price into a dictionary.
Let's go ahead and create it up here and we'll call it bids and it's going to start out as an empty dictionary.
And then later on, once we've got the name and the price, we said that the name was going to be the
key and the price was going to be the corresponding value. To add a new entry to our bids dictionary,
we specify the dictionary, we add a set of square brackets, and then we add the key.
The key is going to be the name and the value is going to be the price.
So we would write it like this.
Now, we get down to the slightly trickier part. We're going to ask if there are any other users who
want to bid. And if the answer is yes, then we're going to clear the screen and we're going to loop
back to where we ask for the next name and the next bid price.
How do we achieve this?
Well, we can put this into a while loop. Let's go ahead and indent this.
So I just typed command and then the right-sided square bracket. Or on Windows, it will be control and the right
side of the square bracket.
And then we can wrap this into a while loop.
If we had some sort of variable that would keep track whether if the bidding is finished.
So let's call it bidding_finished.
And of course, it starts out being False.
Now, while bidding is not finished, so while not bidding_finished, so basically while this is still
false, then we're going to keep running this until forever.
But of course, we need a way to stop this.
So we're going to create a new input where we ask the user, "are there any other bidders?"
Type "yes" or
"no". This way we get to get an input which is going to be either the word yes or the word no, and
we can save this inside a variable called maybe should_continue.
So this way we can check this variable and we can see, well, if should_continue is equal to "no",
well, in that case, that's when we're going to flip the switch and change this bidding_finished variable
to true.
So this means that when we get to the end of this block in the while loop, then when it checks this
bidding_finished, it's not going to continue to loop anymore.
Now, on the other hand, if should_continue was yes or in fact any other value, then we can keep continuing
and we don't actually have to change this variable because it's already false.
Now we have our code looping, which means that unless the user types in a 'no' at the very end and bidding
becomes finished, this is this path.
Otherwise then we're going to keep going through all of these lines of code which is basically all
of this until we get to the point where this switch actually gets flipped.
So if you notice that if the user actually answers yes, then we want to clear the screen before we
repeat the loop.
That means we can check to see
well, elif should continue is equal to.
yes,
well, in this case, we're going to call that clear() function that I showed you in the hint at the very
beginning.
So this function comes from the replit module and it allows us to clear the output in the console so
that the previous name and bid gets cleared on off the screen and it leaves a fresh start for the next
user.
The last thing we have to do is to actually address this right? So when they answered no, they get taken
out of the while loop, but we still have to find the highest bidder from our dictionary and to declare
them as the winner.
How do we do this?
Well, let's put this in a separate function. So we could create a new function called find_highest_bidder.
And this is going to get the bidding_record as the inputs, so this will be the dictionary that represents
all the bids, the names and the values. I think it's easier if we can visualize what this bidding_
record might look like.
So we know it's a dictionary of key-value pairs where each key is a name and each value is a number.
So let's say we had only two bidders, Angela and James.
Angela bid $123.
James bid $321.
So we can see who's clearly going to be the winner here.
But how do we get our code to figure that out?
We need to somehow loop through this dictionary, right? which is called bidding_record.
We know that we can use a for loop to do this so we can say for each bidder in the bidding_record,
and this is a good point to remember that when you use a for loop on a dictionary, instead of looping
through each item in the dictionary, like each of these key-value pairs, it actually loops through
each of the keys.
And we covered this in the very first lesson of today where we talked about how the for loop works
when we're looping through a dictionary. Now, we're going to get hold of each of the bidders inside
this dictionary.
So what do we do with it?
Well, we want to use the key to get the value.
Let's take the bidding_record and pass in the key,
and this should give us the value.
So now we can actually save this inside a variable which I'm going to call bid_amount.
So the first time this for loop runs, the bid_amount is going to equal 123
and the next time the for loop runs, the bid amount is going to be equal to 321. If we had some sort
of way outside of the for loop
that keeps track of the highest bid, well then we could use this number to check against the current
bidding amount.
We can use an if statement to check
well, if the bid amount is greater than the highest bid, well, in that case, then the highest bid
becomes the bid amount.
So what this means is that we start out with a zero. The first time the for loop is run, the bidder
is going to be equal to Angela,
the bid amount is going to be equal to Angela as the key passed into this dictionary, which is going
to get us the value 123. If 123 is greater than zero,
well, then this highest bid is now going to become 123. The next time the for loop runs
the bidder is now James and the bid amount is now 321.
Now we're checking if 321 is greater than the highest bid.
Remember this, in the last round, got set to 123.
So this is going to be true.
And this means James' bid, 321, is now going to be the highest bid.
In addition to keeping track of the highest bid, we can keep track of the winner. If this is indeed
true, if the current bidder has the highest bid, well then at the same time as setting the highest
bid,
we should also set the winner to the key,
so the current bidder.
And once we've gone through this for loop and we've looped through all of the records in the bidding record,
well then finally we can actually print
"The winner is..."
the winner that's stored in this variable. And we're going to say they won with a bid of... and let's add
a dollar sign and then we're going to pass in the highest_bid.
Now, we can turn this into an fstring and it will use both of these variables, which is storying
the highest bid and the winner's name to print out who the winner is.
So down here, when should_continue is no going down this path,
we can now print and declare the winner. In addition to saying that bidding finished is true,
we're also going to call that function, find_highest_bidder, and pass in all of the bids that we
have been keeping track of over here.
Now, just before we run our code, let's go through each line and make sure that everything looks all
right.
Firstly here, where it says, 'what is your name?'
maybe we can add a colon and then a space
so the user starts typing here.
Then it asks, 'what is your bid?'
We can add a colon as well and the user will start typing after the dollar sign.
Now, I can already see a problem that's actually going to happen because of this line 23.
I wonder if you can spot the issue here, especially if you think about what we're going to do with
this price later on.
But I'm going to add one more new line here and then I'm going to run the code and we'll see what actually
happens.
So now let's go ahead and run the code.
And you can see our gavel printed and then it asks us for our name, so I'm just going to put my name and
then 123. And then one other bidder who's going to be James, 321.
And now if I say no, there are no more bidders,
see what happens when I hit enter.
I get a type error
and it tells us that the greater sign is not supported between instances of a string and an int
and this happened on line 16.
If we take a look at line 16, basically we're comparing the bid amount, which is the value that came
out of the bidding record, which is what's being passed in here,
and that, of course, is a dictionary where the keys are the names of the bidders and the value is
the price.
So what's actually happening here?
Well, it's because when I took this price input in, I kept it as a normal input.
Instead, it should be turned into an integer.
So that way we can work with it as a number so that when we're comparing it against, say, zero or
whatever other number later on, it can actually do the comparison.
It doesn't actually make sense to the computer when you're comparing a string versus a number. That doesn't
actually work.
And this was covered when we talked about data types in Python.
Now, if we hit run again
and we do the same thing, and when I say no, you can see that it tells me the winner is James with
a bid of 321.
Essentially, the hardest part of this challenge is figuring out how to loop through a dictionary and
get hold of each of the bidders and each of their values and compare them historically against previous
values inside this dictionary.
If this function is confusing to you, then I really recommend either going over to Thonny, pasting
the code in and exploring it by going through it step by step.
Alternatively, if you can't install Thonny or you don't have access to your normal computer, then you
can also go to a website called pythontutor.com.
And this also lets you visualize your code, although in a slightly more simplified way. If I go ahead
and paste in my function, find_highest_bidder, passing in the bid record, let's go ahead and create
a new dictionary of bids.
So now we have a dictionary of bids with two key-value pairs just as we entered before,
and then I'm going to call this function, find_highest_bidder, and pass in these bids.
Now, if we go ahead and click visualize execution, you can see it's going to go line by line, and we
can click next to see how it's jumping through this.
Firstly, it's bypassing this function, creating this next dictionary.
So now it's got a function stored somewhere, which is this one,
it's got a dictionary called bids stored somewhere else.
And now we actually get to the line, which is going to execute that function and it's going to pass
over this dictionary of bids to this function.
And if you step through this line by line, you can see it creating these new variables and populating
them. The first time we run it
the highest bidder is zero, the winner is an empty string, and the bidder in the for loop is now Angela.
It's the first key from the dictionary as it points to here.
Now if we keep clicking
next, it works out the bid amount which is the value corresponding to that key, and then it works
out the highest bid by comparing whether if the current bid amount is greater than the current highest
bid.
So 123 is greater than zero
so when I click next, you'll see highest bid gets replaced with the bid amount and the winner is now
going to be set as Angela. The next time the loop runs the bidder is
now James, and if I keep going through this, you can see that James actually ends up with the highest
bid and becomes the winner.
So now the for loop is done because it's looped through all items in the dictionary and it's now going
to print the output, which is 'The winner is James with a bid of $321.'
This is another way that's really, really helpful to visualize your code.
And the other great thing is that even if while you're visualizing there's still something you don't
understand, you can actually click on this button to get live help from users across the Internet.
And if you want to practice your own debugging, just as we did in today's lesson, you can also click
to help some of these users who are looking for help with their code.
And you can practice reading code, understanding code and helping other people with their bugs and
their issues.
Finally, if you want to take a look at the completed code for today's project, then as always, you
can head over tor repl.it/@appbrewery/blind-auction-completed.
And it's important to remember that this is just one way of completing this project.
There are lots and lots of other ways. But as long as you test your program thoroughly and it works
in the same way, then it doesn't matter too much how you've done it.
But it's important that you've absorbed the knowledge in today's lessons, and the most important of
which is this concept of dictionaries, adding to dictionaries, and also looping through dictionaries.
So have a look through the completed code and also have a play around with Python Tutor, which is
a really great resource for your learning.
And I'll see you tomorrow for more lessons on Python.
Hey there! Welcome to Day 10 of a 100 Days of Code
and today we're gonna learn about functions with
outputs. Previously
we've already seen the other two flavors of functions; a plain function and
also functions with inputs. But in today's lessons,
we're going to be using the skills that we've learned
and we're going to be extending our knowledge of functions to build a
calculator app. I think at some point in every program has lives
they will have built a calculator app.
So if that hasn't already happened to you, then today is your lucky day,
because that's exactly what we're going to be making.
So it's a simple text base calculator,
and we can start off by writing a number and then picking one of the operations:
plus, minus, multiply or divide. So I'm going to divide this by two,
and then it shows us the full calculation, 5 / 2 = 2.5.
And now we can continue calculating with the answer from the previous step,
or we can type 'n' to start a new calculation. Let me type a 'y'
and maybe I'll do 2.5 + 6
and now I get 8.5. By the end of the lessons today,
you'll have understood how functions really work,
how you can use them to reduce redundant code and how you can provide inputs to
functions as well as providing outputs. Once you're ready, head over to the next
lesson and let's get started.
To begin
the first thing I want to talk about is more on functions.
So we've already seen a couple of things that we can do with functions.
The first thing I showed you was how to create a very simple bog-standard
function using the def, the name, the empty parentheses,
and then the colon. And then within the body of the function,
you can do a bunch of things which will be carried out every single time you
trigger or call the function like this.
And the first type of function basically just helps you reduce the amount of
code you have to write
when you have instructions that you want to execute repeatedly. Now,
the next type of function we saw actually had something inside the parentheses
and this something is an input which can be passed over when we call the
function. So in this case, 123
is the argument which gets passed into this parameter called something
and then it gets used within the body of the function.
The second type of function, the functions
which allow for inputs, gives us the ability to modify the code in the function
and to get it to do something different each time
depending on what input was passed in.
We're now onto the final sort of flavor functions
and these are functions
which allow you to have an output
once the function is completed.
We start off with a simple function, and in this case
you'll notice that even though I could, I'm actually not giving it any inputs.
The inputs and the outputs are completely separate from each other.
So this is a normal function that you've seen many times now. And within the
body of the function, I'm going to do some piece of calculation. Let's say
I'm going to calculate what is three times two,
and then save it to a variable called result. Now, once that's done,
I can use the output keyword, which is return.
And then after that keyword, I can put whatever it is
I want to be the output of this function. So in this case,
the output is the result.
And what that means is when I call this function later on and it runs,
then it will go ahead and output this result
and it replaces this line of code where this function was called.
Now that result is held in the code where the function was called and I could
save it to another variable. Result, of course, equals
3 * 2 and that means this output now equal 6.
So this is what the code might look like. Somewhere I would define my function
which has an output, which you can tell by the return keyword. Now,
at some other point in my code, I decide to call that function
and once that function executes, that return or whatever is outputted replaces
the function call. And at the very end,
it means this variable output will store whatever the output is.
So in this case, output would be equal to 6.
The way that I like to think about functions with outputs is almost kind of like
a machine, right?
If you had a machine where in goes some empty bottles and after some processing
or some inputs, outcomes a bottle filled with milk.
So in this case, this function has an input, the empty glass bottle.
It has an output, the glass bottle filled with milk and in the middle,
there's some processes or some code that's being executed to create this change.
This ties together all the things that we've learned about functions.
So now head over to the Day 10 starting replit,
and go ahead and fork your own copy of it. Now,
once you have your own copy of it,
we're going to create some functions with outputs of our own.
Let's start off by creating a new function
which I'm going to call format_name
and the reason is because this function is going to take a first name and a last
name, and it's going to change those inputs,
even if it was lowercase or if it was all caps,
it's going to change it into title case, something like this
where the first letter is capitalized in each word. To begin,
I want you to create this function and then go ahead and add two inputs to it.
One could f_name, so first name and another code l_name,
which is the last name. Pause the video and give that a go.
All right.
So all we have to do to add inputs to our function is just to put the names of
these parameters inside the parentheses.
So now our function is able to take these parameters as inputs
whenever this function gets called.
The next step is we're going to convert these strings that gets passed in,
so it could be something like this, all lower case.
It could be all capitalized, or it could be kind of random, right?
Like some are capitalized, some are not.
But we're going to make it all uniform,
so all of these are going to end up like this. And to do this,
we can search around in Google and you might come across a similar question in
Stack Overflow: How do you convert a string to title case in Python?
They have an example and it's trying to do exactly what we're trying to do.
If we take a look at the answers,
you can see that somebody is helpfully pointing to this title function.
So you take a string and then you write .title and then afterwards,
the string gets transformed and every word now starts off with a capital letter.
And if you want to know more about how this title case works,
then you can click on that link in title and then have a read through the Python
documentation. Once you've read through that,
go ahead and modify this Fname and Lname so that they end up being both in
title case. Pause the video and give that a go.
Right?
All right.
So we want to go ahead and take this Fname and then write a dot and then write
title to convert it to title case.
Once we've done that, then we're going to do the same with the l_name.
And if we go ahead and actually print these out,
and of course, in order for the function to actually execute,
we'll have to call the function. So I'm going to put two inputs in here,
one which is going to be, um, just angela, all in lowercase
and then the second one is going to be ANGELA all in up a case.
And now when I run this code,
you'll see that the result is they both get converted to title case.
In essence,
this part of the code becomes whatever the previous value of f_name is converted
to title case. You might have spotted already that this title function actually
has an output.
It returns a version of the string where each word is title cased.
Instead of simply just printing this,
we can also capture it inside a variable.
Let's create a new variable called formatted_f_name and also
formatted_l_name.
Now what's happening here is we are transforming this input f_name,
turning it into title case.
And then once this function executes,
it has an output and that output replaces this part of the code
and then it gets stored inside this variable.
Now we can go ahead and print the final version of our function
which is going to use an fstring to take the formatted Fname and then add a
space and then print out the formatted Lname, like this.
Now, if I start out with my first name
but all in strange sort of casing,
and then my last name in all caps,
let's go ahead and hit run and see what happens.
You can see that my first name gets converted to title the case,
my last name gets converted to title case
and then that result is stored in formatted Fname
and this result becomes stored in this Lname,
and then they get printed and formatted, like so. Now
instead of printing this result out,
we could also return it as well. In the same way that this title function
returns the output, replaces this part of the code,
we can also do the same with our format_name function.
So let's delete the print function and go ahead and use return
instead.
Now this formatted string becomes the output
and as we mentioned before,
what happens with functions with outputs is this output replaces the part of the
code where the function was called. Now,
if this is the string that we want to print,
then all we have to do is just to save the output
which replaces this part of the code inside a variable like this.
And then all we have to do is just go ahead and print that formatted string.
As you can see, when I run the code, the same thing happens. Now you can,
and you might've alternatively,
just taken this function call and put it straight inside the print statement.
That works exactly the same way.
And we can visualize this using Thonny.
If I go ahead and paste everything we have inside the editor and go ahead and
run debug,
then we can step into and see what are the steps that happen.
So the first thing
when this line 6 gets executed is it tries to call this function, format_name.
So it passes in these two inputs.
And we're now within the function where we have access to these two inputs,
Fname and Lname.
Now the formated_f_name becomes the title-cased
version of the first name and the same thing happens with the last name.
So we now have a formatted_f_name and a formatted_l_name
and that is what's going to be returned as the output.
Now, once that's completed, that output replaces
whatever was in between the print statement,
which is where we called this format name function
and this is what gets printed into the console. As I mentioned before,
we've actually already been using functions that we didn't create that have all
of these functionalities, right? For example,
the Len function takes an input and has an output.
The input is going to be a string,
my name again, seemed to be really obsessed with my own name.
So now this line of code is going to run this built in len function,
calculating the number of letters inside this input that we've given it.
And then it's going to return the result as an output,
which we can now capture inside a variable.
This is the inputs, this is the function
and once this is completed,
the return or whatever it is after the return statement is going to replace this
part of the code.
Then that result or output then gets stored inside of this variable.
So this return keyword is really the most important thing in order to create a
function that has an output,
because everything that comes after it is going to replace where the function
was called. In the next lesson
we'll take a quick look at the return keyword in more detail. Specifically,
let's see what happens
when we have more than one return statement in the same function. All right.
For all of that and more, I'll see you there.
In the last lesson, we looked at functions that return some sort of value.
We created a function called format_name that returned a string. In this
lesson
let's see what happens when a function has more than one return statement.
When the computer encounters a line that has the word return on it,
then it knows that this line is the end of the function.
If I add a line of code after the return keyword, notice what happens when I run
this code. It doesn't ever get executed.
And this has because the return tells the computer that this is the end of the
function and you should now exit the function.
You can actually have multiple return keywords within the same function,
and you can even have a empty return keyword.
So just the return keyword without anything afterwards.
So for example,
we could check whether if the fname is equal to an empty string or the lname
is equal to an empty string. So this case,
it means that when we called it format name, maybe we didn't give it any inputs.
For example, let's say that instead of just calling the function as it is,
we actually used the input function.
So what is your first name and what is your last name?
Now
what happens is it'll ask us for a input and it will take these two inputs
and then call that function and return the formatted version to be printed.
So now in this case, it's possible that we might have just not given it
a first name or not given it a last name and it probably shouldn't go through
these lines of code. But at the moment, it's still running this function
trying to get the title case from the empty string and then printing it.
And I can prove this to you by just adding an extra word in here.
So again, empty first name, empty, last name,
and then it's print result and then of course nothing.
How can we get it to bypass the rest of the code if the user typed in an empty
first name or last name? Well,
we could use what I mentioned before, an early return.
So we could just write return without anything afterwards
and this is going to escape the function.
So it's basically going to terminate the function early.
Now this time, if I leave an empty first name and last name,
you'll see it prints none because there is no output from this to print.
Now, of course,
it's probably safer to actually return something that tells the developer what's
actually going on so we can give a meaningful message,
like return, something like this.
So this way we can catch the cases when something is not quite right and then
exit our function instead of wasting time for it to continue working on
something that we don't want it to do.
We've covered a number of things in today's lesson
and I want you to combine this with your existing knowledge to tackle the
challenge in the next lesson
to get to grips with this concept of functions with inputs and with outputs.
Head over to the Repl.it day 10.1 Days in Month
coding exercise. Here,
you'll notice that I've copied over the is_leap year function that we created
a while back in another coding exercise. Now,
the first thing I want you to do is to modify this function so that instead of
printing leap year or not leap year,
we're actually just going to return true if it is a leap year and false
if it is not a leap year,
because we're going to be using that function in the next function that you're
going to modify,
which is a function that's going to tell you how many days there are in the
month that you specify. So for example,
if I was to call days_in_month and passing in the year as
2022 in the month as 2,
then I should get an output of 28,
as in there's 28 days in February, 2022.
This is the reason why we need to know about leap years
'cause in a leap year, there's actually 29 days in February.
You're going to combine the output from this function
as well as this list of days_in_month
in order to modify this function to output the number of days in a month
when this line of code is called.
It's really important that you don't change any of the code below,
but you are going to modify this function and add more lines of code in it.
Take a look at the hints if you get stuck,
but otherwise, pause the video and give it a go.
All right.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to change each of these print
statements so that it returns a Boolean instead.
So this one should return true, and this one should return true. Now,
when it's not a leap year, I'm going to return false
instead. This way,
basically, when we call this function, is_leap, passing in a year,
then we'll get the output as either true or false.
So we can now use that inside our function days_in_month.
But before we do that, we need to get some inputs.
We need to know what is the year and what is the month the user is interested
in. So that is going to be passed in using these positional arguments.
We're going to ask the user to input a year and input a month,
and then each of these pieces of data gets passed into here and here,
which will end up inside our function ready for use.
The first thing I'm going to check is if the year is a leap year.
How are we going to do that? Well,
we're going to use our function here, is_leap, passing in that year,
and then the output will be checked using the if statement.
Remember that the way that if statements work is that if something is evaluated to true,
then it's gonna carry out the line of code below.
But if it was evaluated and it turned out to be false,
then it's going to skip this line of code.
So instead of using true or false, or if a three is bigger than two,
we're going to use the function, is_leap, and pass in the year that we got as an
input. So this way,
when a year is tested in this function,
then it's going to output either true or false
which is going to replace this part of the code because it's the output from
this function. So now if that output is true,
namely it is a leap year,
then we're going to check if the month they were interested in was the month of
February. So if the is_leap year
is true and the month is equal to 2, well,
in that case,
then we're going to return 29 because there's 29 days in February in a leap year.
If this is the case,
then this function is going to end right here when it returns 29.
But if this is not the case,
then it's going to bypass this line of code and we can output the number of days
in a month for any other condition, so when it's not a leap year.
We can go ahead and simply just use the return statement to tap into that list
called month_days
and we're gonna pull out the value at the current month
that's being requested.
But remember that because lists start counting from zero and the month that the
user's going to be interested in doesn't start from zero,
so if they're interested in January then this month,
instead of being 1, should actually be 0 to pull out this 31.
So then we actually have to subtract one from it.
So now if we test the code and we enter the year
2022 and the month of February,
then we'll get the correct output, which is 28.
That solves the challenge. Now, some of you, I know,
might have gone even further because we talked about using the return statement to
catch out any situations where there might be invalid inputs.
So you could,
if you wanted to, also add an if statement that checks
whether if the month is greater than 12 or if the month is less than one. In
these cases,
then it's actually an invalid input and you could just return invalid month. And
you could of course do the same thing for the year.
And this way it ensures that our function doesn't progress unless we have clean
data.
But this, of course, is not necessary to complete the challenge because we're now able
to figure out the days in the month using this leap year function's output,
and the output from our days_in_month function. In the next lesson,
I'm going to address something that a lot of students are thinking at this
point. And the question is why return at all?
Why not just simply print the outputs instead,
because this way it seems to end up doing the same thing, right?
It's still going to print this down here.
And if we just added a print to this return and a print here and got rid of this
one, then it would still behave exactly the same.
This is exactly what I want to talk about in the next lessons.
So, see you there.
Hey guys,
I want to quickly spend a few minutes talking about a concept in Python known as
Docstrings.
Docstrings are basically a way for us to create little bits of documentation as
we're coding along in our functions or in our other blocks of code.
Now, previously, we've seen that when we use other functions
like the ones that were ready to find by Python, like the length function,
you can see that as soon as I open up my parentheses,
I can see this little piece of documentation that tells me what this function is
actually going to do, namely return the number of items in a container.
So how can we create the same kind of documentation for the functions that we
write? Well, we would do that using docstrings.
The docstring has to go as the first line after the declaration.
So here we've defined the name of our function, the inputs,
and then after the colon, the first indented line will be the docstring.
But that's not it.
You also have to use three of these quotation marks and it's in between these
three quotation marks that you can write your documentation.
We could write something like, well, what is this format_
name function going to do?
What would we want our future selves or another user who's using this function
to know about it? Well,
it's going to take a first and last name and format,
it.
Notice how with docstrings
you can actually write strings that are multi-line. Normally,
if I was to create a normal string, let's say, I dunno,
a = "A String".
If I hit the enter key,
I'm going to get a warning because it's going to interpret this as the end of
this line.
And it won't see this closing quotation mark as being a part of this string.
But when we use a docstring, we can write as many lines as we want
and it will be interpreted all as the same thing altogether,
as if it was fitted onto the same line like this.
Now that we've added our docstring, it's time to see what it looks like. Now,
if I call this function format_name, and I open up the parentheses,
you can see that the text we wrote here now gets populated in the documentation.
It takes the first and last name and formats it to return the title
case version of the name.
So this is a way for you to be able to start documenting your functions and
giving each function a little bit of an explainer.
Now you can also use this as a multiline comment.
So notice how when we write a comment and we go to the next line
it becomes code again.
Now you can in fact use something like this
where you just comment as many lines as you like
and this will be interpreted as a comment
as long as it's not assigned to anything. So for example,
if I create a variable
then this is now a piece of code. Because it's a little bit confusing
the official Python guidance is actually to avoid multiline comments like this.
What is actually much easier is to just write your multiline comment and then to
highlight all of it and then to hit command + forward slash or control + forward
slash on Windows.
That's a much better way of differentiating the comment from actual pieces of
code.
Have a go at adding docstrings to the other functions that you've created and
see it show up when you call your functions.
So we're now ready to tackle our final project of the day
and that's building up a calculator program.
If you head over to calculator-final.appbrewery.repl.run,
you'll see how the final project works.
We get to enter a number and then pick an operation and then pick the next
number and it will calculate the result. Now,
at this point,
we can either continue to calculate with the result from the previous step.
So let's multiply it by two, alternatively,
I can type N and that clears the screen and lets me start out a new
calculation,
like so. Now,
because a lot of the concepts that are covered in this project are actually
quite difficult,
I want to go through this project together and while we're building it up,
there's also a lot of small challenges along the way that I want you to tackle.
Once you're ready, head over to the calculator starting file and fork
your own copy to get started.
Right?
This calculator is going to have some different functions that it can do.
So for example, it will start out with a add function,
which takes two inputs and n1 and n2,
and then it's simply just returns n1 + n2.
This is pretty simple. This is all that there is to
the functionality of adding, takes one number and adds it to the other one.
And I want you to go ahead to create the functions in the same format for these
other mathematical operations. So subtract,
multiply, and divide. Pause the video and complete this challenge.
Right?
All right. So subtract is as simple as add.
So we'll just call it subtract. We pass in again
two numbers, n1 and n2,
and we'll return the outcome as n1 - n2.
And for time sake, I'm just going to copy and paste these for the last two
and I'm going to rename them multiply and divide.
And then when numbers are multiplied,
we use the asterisk sign and the number of divided we use the forward slash.
So now we have four functions; add, subtract, multiply, and divide.
And what we want to do is we want to somehow store these functions inside a
dictionary. Here's another challenge for you.
Can you create a dictionary where the keys are
each of these symbols that we've used to add or subtract or multiply,
and the values are just the names of the functions.
So pause the video and try that now.
Alright, let's go ahead and create this dictionary. Now we start out of course,
with a set of curly braces and as I mentioned,
each of the keys are going to be the symbols for the operations and the values
are going to be the names of the functions. So we've got plus,
and then we've got subtract, multiply,
and divide. So now we have this dictionary,
let's go ahead and save it inside a variable called operations.
Now this dictionary is going to act as the means in which we're going to call
these functions. At some point down here,
we want to be able to tap into the operations and then pass in the key that we
want, so for example multiply,
and then store this as the function that we want.
That means we can then call this function and then pass in one number and a
second number
and this function is currently going to act as the multiply function. Now,
if we change this to plus,
then this function is now going to act as the add function.
So now the next thing we're going to do is we're going to create a variable
called num1
where we ask the user for an input to say
what's the first number.
And there's number of course has to be converted into an integer.
Now, the next thing to do is to ask them for the second number,
so this is going to be pretty much the same as this line of code,
other than the word second. Now,
the next thing is we want to ask them which of these operations they want to do.
Firstly,
we want to be able to loop through this dictionary and print out each of these
keys.
And then we're going to ask the user to type out one of them so that we can
figure out which operation they actually want to do.
Go ahead and try to use a for loop
to loop through this dictionary of operations and print out each of these
symbols. All right,
now we're going to use a for loop
and we know that when we use a four loop with a dictionary,
it will loop through all the keys rather than the values or the actual entries.
We can say for each symbol in the dictionary operations,
go ahead and print out the symbol. And of the moment
if I run this code, you'll see that it'll ask us for the first number,
the second number,
and then it's gonna loop through that list and then print out all the
operations.
So now we're ready to go ahead and ask them for a operation symbol. Pick and
operation from the line above.
So they're going to see all of these keys and then they get to pick an operation
like so. And that symbol is now going to be saved within this variable.
So now we can go ahead and take that operation symbol to pick out the value
that's associated with it. For example, if in this case
the user chose the plus symbol,
then we're gonna pick out the add function.
And then just as I shown you before,
we want to use that add function to add these two numbers together.
But of course,
if they picked a different symbol then we want to be able to carry out the
different operation. See if you can get this calculator to work so we can print out
the num1 and then the operation symbol,
and then num2, and finally the equal sign
and then the answer. See if you can make this line of code work and make sure that
it works whenever you choose any of these operations,
and it will calculate it using these numbers that you input.
Pause the video now.
All right.
The first thing we need to do is to get hold of the calculation function
and this is going to be done using the operation symbol.
So we're going to tap into our dictionary of operations here,
and then we're going to use the square brackets to pass in
the operation symbol.
Now we can use this calculation function as if it were any of these functions.
And that's of course, based on the choice the user made here.
So we can now say calculation function and we can pass in the num1 as the
first input, num2 as the second input.
And of course our function all have a return value.
And so this part is going to be replaced when the code runs with the actual
answer. So we can now save that inside a variable called answer,
and then that will get sent over here and we can now test it out.
So let's try adding three plus five.
So I'm going to use the add symbol and we end up with three plus five equals
eight. Now what about something a little bit more complicated?
Uhm, 45, 78 and we'll choose multiply.
Now, I think in reality that it actually makes more sense to put num2
after the user's enter the operation symbol so that you actually end up with a
better user experience like this. You can pick the first number,
pick the operation, and then pick the second number.
We've managed to get our calculator to work. But in this lesson, I want to talk about something else.
I want to talk about the difference between printing something to the console over here versus returning
something as an output from a function, because a lot of students get very confused at this stage and
they think, well, why don't I just print this results instead of returning it?
What's the actual difference and why would I use return?
That's what I want to address in this lesson.
At the moment, we've got these four functions, and when we call it, we pass over some inputs and
then once we get a hold of the output, we go ahead and print it out into the console.
Now, in the current state of the calculator, it's hard to see the difference between the print and
the return.
But here's a question.
What if we wanted to take the output that comes from calling this function and instead of just storing
it inside a variable and then printing it out, what if we want to pass it as an input to another function?
Let's say that at this point we decided, you know what, we're going to ask them to pick another operation.
And then let's ask them to pick another number.
And finally, let's go ahead and get the calculation function again based on this new operation symbol
that they picked. And then we're going to calculate the new answer
but this time, instead of passing over the calculation function, we're going to pass over the answer
that we got back from this step.
So num1 is now the previous answer
and the second number that's going to be the input is going to be num3.
At this point, when we're calling this calculation function, we're passing over the results or outputs
of this calculation function, and that is going in right here,
and then the third number goes in as the second input.
What basically has happened here is I've taken the output from this function,
so in fact, I could replace this answer with this output,
and I've taken that as the first input into the calculation function and then num3 as the second
input
and then using all of this in order to get the answer.
Let's call this first_answer,
and let's call this second_answer just to differentiate the two answers.
And now I'm going to write a slightly different print statement. In this case, the calculation is done
using the first_answer and then the operation symbol and then the num3 that was inserted at
this point in order to obtain the second_answer.
So now if we give this a run.
Let's do 3 + 2. Now, in this first step of the calculation, we get 5 as the result.
So now if I want to pick another operation, let's I want to multiply 5 by 3.
Then I'm going to take this 5, which is the previous answer,
I'm going to say multiply, and then I'm going to provide the next number, which we'll call 3.
And now it takes the previous answer from the last step and puts that in as the first number in the
calculation, multiplies it by 3 in order to get the final answer.
In this case, what I'm able to do because I have an output from my calculation function up here because
each of these all return their answer, I'm able to take the result from that calculation and plug it
right back into another calculation function using the result of that function call as the input to
another function call.
And I'm only able to do this because I'm using the return statement and because I have outputs from
my functions.
This would not be possible if I was using a print statement.
In the next lesson, we're going to reorganize our code and introduce a while loop so that we can continue
making as many calculations as we want to.
In the last lesson we made it possible to reuse the result of the first
calculation.
The answer for the first calculation became our input for the next calculation,
allowing us to chain the calculations together. However,
this created quite a bit of repetition in our code
and it limits our user to just two calculations.
Let's allow the user to chain as many calculations as they want to.
And I want to throw this over to you as a challenge,
so can you use a while loop and the input function to achieve this?
Ask the user
this question, type 'y' to continue calculating with the previous result or type 'n'
to exit.
If the user types y then your calculator should allow them to continue chaining
together calculations with the previous answer.
If they type anything else the program should exit for now.
I'll give you a few seconds to pause the video before I show you the result.
All right. So the easiest way to solve this is through the use of a while loop.
So let's say that after we've asked for the first number and we've shown them
all of the different symbols that they could possibly pick from,
lets set a flag called should_continue.
And we'll set that to start out as true.
Then we can create a while loop and while it should continue as true,
then we're going to perform these things.
Now we want to change some of this text so that it's a little bit more reusable.
Let's say pick an operation,
and what's the next number instead of the second number.
So now we have a first number, we have a operation,
we have a second number and then we pick out the function from that dictionary
of operations and we get our answer.
So I'm going to change this back to answer and we're passing in num1
and num2 into the calculation function. Now,
once this line has been printed,
everything that occurs afterwards is pretty much repetition.
And instead we're going to ask the user to type y-- type y to continue calculating
with the answer from the previous step.
Let's make that an fstring and let's check what this is actually equal to.
So remember that the input function is also a function that has an output,
which is a little bit then zen,
but the output of this function is whatever the user typed in.
So if they typed in y then this part is going to become y. That's where we're
going to check.
So we're going to check if the result of the input from the user is equal to y,
then in that case that means we should continue and it should repeat back.
But when it loops back,
we want to make sure that num1 is equal to the answer from the previous step.
So we can say if this is true,
then num1 is going to be set to equal the answer.
But on the other hand, else, if they typed anything else,
so we could say maybe type y to continue calculating with answer or type n to
exit.
So now if they type y then the answer is going to be set as the num1 back at
the start of this while loop
so that this num1 becomes the answer from the previous step.
But if they typed n then we want this while loop to the end.
So we're going to change the flag should_continue to false.
So now let's give that a run.
Right?
Let's say the first number is five.
Then we're going to add three to five and then we're going to type y to
continue. So now we get to pick another operation,
so let's multiply, um,
eight by two and we get the result from the next step and we can actually keep
going until we're basically done, right?
So we can take the 16 and we can divide it by four.
But if we type 'n' on the other hand,
then our program ends and we see the prompt once more.
And that's the solution to the challenge,
but it's a little bit sad to just exit, right?
Because with a calculator more often than not,
what you want to do is to start a fresh calculation where you get to determine
the first number and the second number once more.
If the user didn't want to exit
but if they wanted to start a new calculation,
then how can we get them to go back all the way up here so that they provide the
num1 as a fresh input? This is a little bit tricky
and in programming, this concept is known as recursion.
It's basically the idea that you could have a function that calls itself.
So let's define a new function called calculator and this function takes no
inputs and has no outputs.
But all of this code that we've got here so far is inside the calculator
function. To begin when we start,
we have to call the calculator function in order for it to find the place where
this function was defined and to actually carry out all of these instructions.
Now,
the next thing we get to do is a little bit interesting because when the user
types no,
and says that they don't want to continue calculating with the previous answer
but instead they want to start a new calculation,
what we want to do instead of just exiting the while loop,
we want to call the calculator function because what this is going to do is it's
basically going to take us all the way back up to the beginning where we get to
enter a new input again.
And remember that once you reach the end of a function,
everything gets reset to the beginning. So should_continue becomes true again
and this while loop will continue working.
So let's try running this new version.
We've performed a calculation and now we want to start a new calculation,
so I'm going to type n. And now I get to again define the first number again.
This recursion basically happens because we're calling this calculator function
within the calculator function.
Essentially the code runs and runs and runs until it reaches here
and if these conditions are met and this calculator function is called,
then it goes and finds the calculator function in order to call it once more.
But now you have to be quite careful with while loops and with these recursive
functions
because let's say that instead of having all of this code and some checking code
to determine when I should call calculator,
if I actually just called calculator within calculator,
then this is going to be a infinite loop.
It's just going to keep going back and forth.
The calculator function calls the calculator function,
which goes back up and calls and it goes around and round around until forever.
Again,
be careful and make sure that there is some sort of condition that needs to be
met in order for this function to call itself. In the next lesson,
we're gonna add the finishing touches to our program and also fix a bug that you
may have already spotted at this point.
Now that we've pretty much completed all of the logic and functionality of this
calculator, it's time to add in the bells and the whistles,
including adding in the calculator logo and also checking for any bugs.
Adding the calculator logo is pretty simple.
You've done this loads of times before.
All we have to do is import it from the art module,
and then we're going to print it at the beginning of our calculator function.
So this way
when we get to the end and the user wants to start a fresh calculation,
we'll also show them a logo again. Now the next thing to notice,
this is a bit of a bug that you might've seen or not.
But what happens if we try to enter a number with a decimal point?
Let's say we want to calculate 4.5 multiplied by 2.
Our program has already crashed
as soon as I've entered 4.5 and hit enter. As a challenge,
can you diagnose what went wrong and fix this bug? I'll give you a few seconds
to pause the video before I give you the
solution.
Alright. Here's the solution.
The bug goes back to our lesson on datatypes.Notice how it's giving us an error
and it's pointing to this line
number 26. Line number 26 takes this input
which is a string and converts it into an integer. But of course,
a number with the decimal place shouldn't be converted into an integer.
We should actually hold it as a floating point number instead. This way
we're able to perform more accurate calculations.
So instead of just 4 times 5,
we can do 4.5 times 5.5, for example.
So instead of using int here, I'm going to change that to float
and I'm going to do the same here for num2. Now, when we hit run,
I can actually perform calculations using numbers with decimal places,
but I can also use numbers which are whole.
So let's multiply 2.5 by 2, the answer is 5,
and you can see that all the numbers are being reported to a greater level of
accuracy, meaning we have numbers after the decimal point.
And this is all because we converted that int to a float.
Now that there's a lot more features that you could add to your calculator.
You could add a square root capability, you could add exponent capability,
but the important thing here was really for you to see how functions that
provide outputs are really useful
when you come to a more complex program where you can take the output from one
function call and pass it into the next function
call as an input.
So this output can be reused in different parts of the code.
And this not only allows us to reduce repetition and also make our more reusable
and more modular,
but also it gives us the flexibility of performing more actions after a function
has completed. Now,
we're going to be using a lot of the concepts that we've learned here today in
tomorrow's capstone project. A lot of things I've explained,
including things like the recursion
where we're calling a function within its own definition or things like setting a
flag using a wall loop to continue
some piece of code execution is all going to come in really,
really handy tomorrow.
So make sure that if there's anything that you don't understand here
that you review it and you're comfortable with what the code is doing before you
proceed. That's all for today and I'll see you tomorrow.
Hey, it's Angela here. Congratulations on making it through the
first 10 days. Today, I've got something very special lined up for you,
our first capstone project. Today
we'll challenge you to apply everything you've learned so far into one big
project.
You're going to need to dig deep and apply all your Python skills for this
capstone project. But by the end of the day,
you'll have built an awesome blackjack game to enjoy.
This is probably going to be one of the hardest things you'll build yet,
but at the same time, the end result is also going to be the most fun.
The final project you're going to be building is blackjack.
And if you had over to
247blackjack.com or search for any other free online blackjack game,
you can hit play and you can click deal for the dealer to give you some cards.
The game is really simple. Essentially
you're trying to get as close to 21 as possible and all of the cards which have
a Jack, a Queen, or a King count as 10.
So you're adding these two cards up 5 + 10 equals 15.
And you're trying to figure out if you can risk getting another card.
So I'm going to click hit, and I'm going to get one other card
but that takes me over 21 and so the dealer wins.
So this is the game that we're trying to create.
This is what your version of Blackjack is going to look like.
Now the user interface is a little bit simpler,
but it's just as fun to play with.
So our first two cards are a 9 and a 10,
and it also shows us one of the computers cards.
Now I'm already on 19,10 + 9.
I'm close to going over 21.
So I'm going to type 'n' and end the game right there.
I end on 19,
the computer ends on 18 and because 19 is greater than 18,
that means I win.
Have a go at playing the final game by going to black-jack-final.appbrewery.repl.run.
But once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson so that we can actually build this game ourselves.
For all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson. Have fun.
All right.
Let's talk about the mechanics and the program requirements for the Blackjack
game that you'll create. For those of you who are not familiar with the game of
Blackjack  also known as 21,
I'm just going to spend a few minutes to go through the rules with you.
Blackjack is a game that's played using cards.
And the goal of the game is to add up your cards to the largest number without
going over 21. If the cards in your hand
add up two more than 21, then it's called a bust
and it means that you lose immediately.
And it doesn't matter how much you've gone over 21, as long as it's over 21,
then you lose. Now the way that the cause are counted
is that all the cards from 2 to 10 count as their face value.
So a six is a six and a nine is a nine, et cetera.
But the Jack, Queen and King each count as 10 and the other special card is the
Ace.
Now the Ace can either count as a one towards your total,
or it can count as an 11. And depending on whether,
if you've gone over 21 or whether if you're under 21,
you can decide which value you want your Ace to represent.
Let's play a sample game. Let's say that the dealer over here got
a 10 to begin with and you got a queen which also counts as a 10 to begin with.
So these
are the first cars that are dealt and both of these cards are revealed.
And then the dealer deals another card to each of you. Now the dealer's
second hand is concealed so you can't work out what their total is,
but you can see your own card.
So the moment we don't know what the dealer has,
it might be 10 plus anything,
but we know that our score is 13, 10 + 3.
At this point you might ask the dealer for another card.
So now you have three cards and luckily it adds up to 20 without going over 21.
But there is also a possibility that you might've gotten a card that would have
pushed your total over 21 at which point you now lose.
And it doesn't matter what the dealer has in their hand,
you've already lost because you've gone over 21.
Now let's say that we got lucky and our total adds up to 20.
Now at this point we say we don't want any more cards
and the dealer reveals their hand. If. like in this case,
they end up with 20 and we have 20,
then we end up in a draw.
So whenever your score equals the dealer score,
then you will draw rather than win or lose. Now,
if on the other hand, the dealer ended up with an Ace,
which we know can count as an 11 and they actually scored higher than us.
They have 21 and we have 20, well, in this case, we would lose.
Now the rules also state that if the dealer ends up with a hand that's smaller
than 17, so 16 or under,
then they must take another card.
Those are the basic rules of blackjack,
but I'd recommend that before you get started head over to the link that's in
the Blackjack starting file and have a few games of Blackjack
just so that you can see for yourself how it actually works and how you win and
how you lose.
And then head over to the final version of the completed project and play our
simplified version of Blackjack. This way
you'll see what the end result is that you're trying to create
and it will be easier when you're creating the code yourself. Now,
as I mentioned,
we're going to try and keep our version of Blackjack a little bit simpler,
and we're going to assume a couple of things.
The first thing is that the card's that we're starting with comes from this
list. You'll notice that I've got 2 through to 10,
all represented in the list.
And then I've got Jack, Queen and King represented as tens as well.
So this means that the 10 has four times the probability of occurring compared
to the other cards.
Now the Ace is going to start off being represented as 11,
and it's going to count as 11 until the user goes over 21.
Now finally, we're going to assume that we have an infinite deck.
So it means that when a card is drawn from the deck,
it's not removed from the deck. Whereas in a real casino,
they have maybe six or eight decks of cards. When a card is drawn,
then there's less probability of that same card occurring again.
And this is how professional card counters,
the people that the casinos hate the most,
actually go about trying to optimize and improve their chances.
But in order to keep things simple in our game,
we're not going to deal with things regarding probability or removing cards from
the deck.
We're going to assume that each of these cards in the list have equal chance of
occurring. If you head over to the App Brewery Blackjack
starting project,
you'll see each of these rules written out in more detail.
Take a look at it so that you're aware what our house rules dictate.
Now, if you scroll to the very top of the Blackjack project,
I've given you four tracks. So just as when you start a video game
you have the choice of normal, hard, extra hard or expert,
it's the same in this project. You can limit yourself to using only one
hint if you are at expert level in Python.
You can only use hint 1 and 2
if you want an extra hard challenge and maybe a little bit of a cry at the end,
there's also hard and normal. So I'll leave the choice up to you.
And if you scroll down, you'll find all the hints listed in here.
Now I recommend everybody, no matter your experience,
everybody should try out the Blackjack game and also look at how the final
project is supposed to work.
But then I've got other things such as a list where I've broken down the program
requirements. You know how we always say, when you have a big problem,
always try to break it down into smaller pieces.
Now you can of course create this list yourself by exploring the game,
exploring the final project,
and then writing your own to do list of things that need to be coded up.
Or alternatively,
you can look at the one that I've created inside hint 2. Inside hint 3
I've created a flowchart for you
which takes the to-do list and breaks it down into a flowchart where you can
look at the logic in more detail. Now, of course, as always,
it's a good idea to create your own flowchart
using a tool like draw.io or using a piece of pen and paper.
But if you need help,
it's there for you and you can download the PDF and read through it.
Now the rest of the hints
will go through how to solve this project in even smaller
bite-size chunks. Depending on your own level of Python at the moment,
choose your own difficulty level.
But I just want to say before you get started that this project is difficult and
I wanted to give you a bit of a challenge and to push yourself so that you get
stronger.
But it will inevitably be moments where you will have doubt and you will be
wondering, what am I doing? I don't understand anything. And in this moment,
I want you to look yourself in the mirror and tell yourself that you got this.
You can do it. And that remember that I'm here rooting for you.
I believe you can do it.
You've got everything that you've learned so far will enable you to do it.
There's nothing new in this challenge.
You just have to put all the pieces together.
You have to push through the difficult parts and maybe sleep on a problem and
think about it and then come back to it. But I believe you can do it. Once
you're ready, pause the video,
head over to the starting project and give it a go.
And once you're satisfied,
then head over to the next lesson and I'll walk through the solution with you.
Right. So how did that go?
I hope it went really well and you've managed to complete it all by yourself.
If you got stuck, I really recommend just having a sandwich, have a cup of tea,
take a break, and then come back to it.
You'd be surprised what your brain can do when it just has a little bit of rest.
But I want you to make sure that you've really given it a proper go before you
come here and watch the solution.
Cause I'm going to walk you through the solution step by step in case there are
little bits or something that you didn't understand or something that you want
to check. But I really,
really hope that you've managed to tackle most of this yourself. All right.
So without further ado, let's get started coding up our Blackjack project.
Hopefully you've already used hints 1, 2 or 3,
and I'm going to get started with hint 4 and build up our Blackjack project
step-by-step. Now the idea of the hints 1, 2,
and 3 is to get you to create these small to-dos of your own so that you
can have practice breaking down the problem into a list and then breaking it
down into a flowchart and then breaking it down into smaller bite-size to-dos.
So let's start out with the first one,
we have to create a deal_card function that uses the list below to return a
random card and 11 is going to be the Ace in this deck.
So let's get started by forking a copy of this repl and we're going to go and
create our deal_card function.
Now this function is going to contain these cards,
so I'm going to go ahead and paste it in, make sure it's indented
so it's inside the function. And now I'm going to use these cards to randomly
pick one out of this list. So to do that,
we can of course import our random module.
And then I'm going to use random.choice to pick a random card from my list
of cards. And then this of course has an output,
this random.choice
so I'm gonna save that output, namely the random card, inside a variable called
card.
And then finally we're going to return this chosen card as the output.
So that's step 4 done.
Now let's move on to step 5.
So we're going to deal the user and computer two cards each using the deal card
function, and very helpfully
the hint tells us that we can start out with a blank
user_card and a blank computer_card list.
So we basically just have to add two cards to
each of these lists. To do this,
I'm going to use a for loop and I'm going to use the range operator to run this
for-loop twice.
So you've seen this syntax before when we talked about for loops and I've got an
underscore here because we don't actually need this particular variable.
All we need is for this loop to run twice
and this code is going to achieve that. Every single time this loop runs
we're going to get a new card by calling deal_card.
Now remember that deal_card has an output,
it outputs a random card. So if you want,
it's actually quite helpful to add some documentation to this.
So we could say returns a random card from the deck.
And now when I write deal_card
you can see that the doc tells me that this function is going to return a random
card from the deck. So that random card is going to replace this function call
so we can capture that data by storing it inside of a variable.
So we'll call that new_card and set it equal to the output from the function
deal_card. Now,
the next thing we're going to do is we're going to add this new_card to the
user's cards.
So at the moment, it's an empty list and all we have to do is say user_cards
.append
and then the object that we want to add to that list is going to be the new_
card.
Now some of you might be tempted to instead use the plus equals.
You might want to write something like this; user_cards += new_card.
And I want to show you what actually happens when yourun this.
cause this is a really common error.
We get a trace back and we get a type error.
It tells us that the int object is not iterable and it highlights this line 49
as the reason for the error. So what's going on here?
Well,
this += is actually shorthand for writing the extend function.
Now you can see that the extend function is something that extends a list
by appending elements from the iterable. So what does this mean? Well,
it means that whatever you put inside this parentheses,
it has to be a list itself. For example,
if this new_card was a list of cards,
so maybe just the first dealt card and another card
or even just it by itself inside a set of square brackets
which turns it into a list, well then if we run this code right now
we no longer have any errors and if I convert this back to what you saw before,
which is using the plus equals, we also have no errors.
But when you only want to add a single item, not a list, to an existing list
then you have to use append. So hopefully you didn't have this issue,
but if you did,
this is the reason. Now that we've created these two lines,
you can see that it's a little bit redundant because we're creating this new
card variable just to hold the output from this function.
And then we're immediately putting it into this list using the append.
So instead we can actually just get rid of the middleman and put deal_card
directly inside the append.
And this does exactly the same thing in a single line of code.
Once we've done this for user_cards,
we'd probably want to do the same thing for the computers cards.
So it computer_cards.append, and then we call deal_card again,
remembering the parentheses.
So we've got a total of three parentheses at the end and this way we deal a new
card and that new card gets appended to the end of this
list.
All right. So now let's tackle hint number 6.
We're going to create a function called calculate_score
that's going to take a list of cards as an input,
and then it returns the score after calculation.
And it tells us that if we get stuck,
we can look up the sum function to help us.
So let's create a function called calculate_score
and this calculate_score is going to take some cards as an input,
and then inside the body
it's going to calculate the total of all the cards in this list.
So if we take a look at the sum function in Python,
the way that it works is you can put a iterable,
so like a list inside the parentheses as an input
and then it's going to add up all of the items in the list
and it's going to return the total. Back in our code
we can simply write sum, and then inside these parentheses
we can pass over the cards and we can return this value as the output.
Basically
if we had cards equal to a list with 1, 5,
3,
4, then the sum function is going to end up being equal to 1 + 5 +
3 + 4, which is going to be equal to 13.
And then that will become the output of this function.
So now let's move on to hint 7.
A Blackjack only happens when
we have a hand with only two cards and those cards have to be an Ace and a 10
value card. In our deck
we know that an Ace is represented by 11 and we have a number of 10 value cards.
So there's a number of ways that we can check for this Blackjack.
One of the ways is by checking to see if the 11 is in our deck of cards,
and then we can combine that with an and to check if the 10 is also in our deck
of cards. And finally,
we can check to make sure that we've got a hand size of two.
So we can check that the length of our cards is equal to two,
and this would represent this logic: a hand with only two cards, an Ace
which is represented by 11 and a 10. Now, on the other hand
we could actually also simplify this because a hand with only two cards that
must contain an 11 and a 10, we can
instead of checking for both 11 and 10, we can check to
see if the total,
so that if we summed the cards and if this was equal to 21,
then it would be exactly the same thing, right? 10 + 11 is 21
and we've still only got a deck of two. In this case
what we want to happen is we want to return zero instead of the actual score.
So this way we can indicate that the user or the computer has got a score of
Blackjack. That's hint number 7 sorted,
let's move onto a hint number 8. It tells us that inside calculate_score,
we should check also for an 11, which is an Ace.
If the score is already over 21,
then we should remove the 11 from the cards and we could replace it with a one,
because remember that an Ace can count as an 11 or 1.
So in the beginning, when the user's score is very small,
then we probably want to count it as an 11.
But once the user goes over 21,
then we probably want to change it and count it as a 1 instead
so they don't go over and they don't lose. Let's first write
the if statement.
So if there is the 11 inside our deck of cards and the
sum of the cards, so the total_score, is already over 21,
then we want to do something about it.
And the hint tells us to look up the append and remove functions.
So we've already seen the append function many times,
and we know that it just adds a single element to the end of the list.
Now the one that we haven't used a lot of is the remove function
and this we'll search for the first instance of the given element and removes it
out of the list. This is kind of what we need to do.
We need to go ahead and remove the 11 from the list of cards. So we can write
cards.remove, and inside the parentheses,
we use the 11 and then we do cards.append,
so that we end up adding a 1 instead of the 11.
This way we remove the 11 and replace it with a 1.
And hopefully our cards will now take the user to below 21.
Now let's move on to a hint 9. So we want to call
calculate_score at some point in our code
and if the computer or the user has a Blackjack
or if the user's score is over 21, then the game is going to end.
This might be a good time to start tidying up our code a little bit,
because we've got our function over here,
the calculate score function.
And remember that you can only call a function after it's been declared.
So for example, if I wanted to call this function over here,
then I actually can't.
I can't say calculate_score because it hasn't yet been declared.
So instead,
what I'm going to do is I'm going to take this function and I'm going to move it
to where we dealt our cards and I'm going to collapse some of these functions so
I can see my hints and my code a little bit easier.
So now that I've moved my function to above the line where I want to call it,
it's now become valid code.
And this is the place where I want to call it because it's only after I've dealt
the user and the computer some cards can I actually calculate their scores.
Firstly, I want to calculate the score using the user's cards.
So this list of cards from the user gets passed into this function and uses
all of the logic to output some sort of score.
And then I'm going to store that score in a variable
which I'll call user_score.
And I'm going to do the same thing for the computer,
so computer_score equals calculate_score. And remember,
it's always helpful to add a little bit of a docstring to tell ourselves and
other programmers what this function does. Let's quickly summarize it.
So this function is going to take a list of cards and return the score
calculated from the cards.
So now when I open that parentheses,
I know that I probably have to pass in my list of cards in order to get back the
score.
So let's put in the computer_cards in as the inputs,
and now we've got the user_score and the computer_score.
So this score could equal zero
if they got a Blackjack or it could just simply be the value of the cards that
they hold all added up together.
Now that we've called calculate_score
we also want to make sure that if the computer or the user has a Blackjack
or if the user's score is over 21, then we have to end the game.
Let's write our if statements. If the user_score is equal to zero,
or the computer_score is equal to zero,
or the user_score is greater than 21, then in this case
we're going to tell the game to end.
So we could create a new variable called is_game_over
and we start out with false, of course. But then when this happens,
we're going to change that variable to true instead.
Our is_game_over variable is just a simple boolean.
It starts out as false and when certain conditions are met,
then we change it to true. Now at the moment, our program is not finished.
So it was not really obvious how we're going to be using this is_game_over
variable. But we're setting ourselves up for the next steps.
Now that we're tracking if the game should end,
we can look at this value to determine what to do next.
So that's hint 9 completed. Let's test our code and see how everything works so
far.
I'm going to add some print statements here so that I can see what the user's
cards are and what the user's score is. Using an fstring
I'm going to show your cards, so the user's cards, and the current score.
And I'm also going to print the computers first card.
Remember when I first explained the rules of Blackjack,
the dealer will reveal their first card
so you get a little bit of a clue as to what kind of hand they might have.
So in here, we're going to insert the computer's cards
and we're only gonna pick out the first item, so that the one at index zero,
and we do that using a square bracket after the name of the list.
Now let's give our program a run and see if it actually works.
The first thing that prints is a list of our cards.
So in our hand,
we have a 2 and we have a 6 and 2 + 6 added together
of course makes the score of 8.
And then it reveals to us the computer's first card, which is a 10.
Now we can be reasonably assured that our code is working.
And it's a good idea to regularly test your code so that you don't wait until
the end when they're a lot of problems
and you don't know which part of the code is responsible.
Now let's move on to hint number 10.
It says that if the game has not ended ask the user
if they want to draw another card. If yes
then use the deal card function to add another card to the user's card list.
If no, then the game has again
ended. Over here in the if statement
we can add an else because if the game hasn't ended, as in
they haven't gone over 21 or nobody's got a Blackjack,
then we're going to ask the user if they want to get another card.
I'm going to use a input
and I'm going to ask the user to type 'y' to get another card,
otherwise type 'n' to pass.
And I'm going to save this input inside a variable, which I'll
call user_should_deal.
Now we can check to see if this variable is equal to 'y'. Well in that case,
we're going to add another card to
the user's card list by doing the same thing that we did in the beginning
where we dealt two cards to each player by saying
user_cards.append and inside the parentheses
the thing that we want to append is the output from deal_card.
So just a quick check to make sure you've got all the parentheses there and then
we're ready to address the else. If they didn't type 'y',
then that means they don't want another card. Well, then in this case,
the game has again ended.
So we can say is_game_over equals true.
Let's test this out as well.
We got 7 and 11 with the current score of 18.
If we type 'y' hopefully we'll get another card.
And we did see that prompt and we saw something happen,
but our program then promptly ended. Let's take a look at the next step.
How can we get our game to repeat itself?
So hint number 11 tells us that the score will need to be rechecked with
every new card drawn
and the checks in hint 9 needs to be repeated until the game ends.
Notice how we've got this flag, is_game_over, which is set to true
whenever the game ends. It starts off being false
and what this means is we can actually create a while loop
which basically keeps on calculating the user_score
and the computer_score, makes all of these checks
which are in hint 9,
and then repeats itself until the game ends.
Let's go ahead and do that. After all the initial setup,
we're going to create a while loop and the while loop is going to be active
until the game is over. So we can say
while not is_game_over,
then go ahead and carry out all of these instructions.
So calculate the user_score, calculate the computer_score,
check that nobody's gone over 21 and nobody's gotten a Blackjack.
And if the user wants more cards than they should, if they don't then the
the game is over. So let's run this and try it again.
Our cards are 10 and 10 which probably means we shouldn't get another card
cause we're already so close to 21, but I'm going to be daring and press
'y' anyways. And it tells us that our cords are now 10,
10 plus two.
So we got an extra card and that takes up our score to 22.
That worked perfectly.
So now let's go back and tackle the next part. Hint
number 12 says once the user is done, it's time to let the computer play.
The computer should keep drawing cards as long as it has a score less than 17.
So the while loop is responsible for dealing with when the user wants to keep
drawing cards. But once that's done,
then we can tackle hint number 12,
which is how does the computer actually play? What is its strategy?
Well, we know that the computer has to keep drawing cards
as long as it has a score of less than 17. But, of course,
0 which represents a Blackjack is also less than 17,
but we don't want it to draw a card if it has a Blackjack.
We can represent this logic using a while loop; while the computer_score is not
equal to zero and the computer_score is less than 17,
then in this case we want to keep drawing cards.
We're going to take the computers cards
and we're going to use the append to add a card by dealing another card to the
computer.
And then we're going to recalculate the computer_score so that it updates
and this while loop is evaluated on the latest score.
So the computer_score is going to equal calculate_score using the computer's
cards.
And that means that the updated computer_score is equal to the return value from
calculate_score. So that's hint 12 complete. In the next step
we're going to start comparing our player's hand with the dealer's hand.
See you in the next lesson.
At this point, we've created two while loops.
The first while loop is for the user so that they can continue taking cards
and the second while loop is for the computer so that the dealer can follow
their strategy. Now it's time to tackle hint 13
where we create a function called compare.
We pass in the final user_score and computer_score,
and then we compare the scores to see who has won, who has lost,
or if they have a draw.
So remember that in order to call a function,
it has to be declared before the line we want to use it.
So let's go back up and after hint number six
where we had the last function,
let's add this hint here and create our compare function here.
This compare function is going to take the user_score and also the computer_
score and it's going to compare these two scores.
If the user_score is equal to the computer_score,
then we said this should mean that it's a draw.
So we'll return some sort of message that represents this.
But elif or else if the computer has a Blackjack,
so the computer_score is equal to zero, well in this case
we should return that the user has lost and the opponent has a Blackjack.
And then we go through this list and we add in all of these other conditions.
So I'm gonna speed it up a bit.
Now for the final condition,
it says that the player with the highest score should win.
So we can write an elif that compares the user_score against the computer score
and we're basically saying if the user_score is greater than the computer score,
well, then that means that the user wins.
But if that's not true and because we've covered everything else,
we now have the final return, which is you lose.
Now,
remember that if, elif, else statements are evaluated from top to bottom.
Even though if the computer score is a zero which is a Blackjack
which is obviously much less than whatever score the user might have,
because it's going to return at this point and it's going to exit the function,
it will never get to this comparison if this is already true.
If you get confused about how if elif and else works
especially the order in which you add the conditions,
have a look back at the lesson where we talked about this in more detail.
This might be a good time to revise that concept.
But now that we've completed our compare function,
we're going to use it at the end of our code here
because this is a time that the user is done drawing cards,
the computer's done drawing cards
and now we can call that compare function
and pass in the user_score and also the computer_score.
So this should hopefully give us the final result
as a piece of text. Let's run the code as it is and see what happens.
We started out with a 3 and a 6 making a 9.
Now we know the computer at least got a 10, so let's add another card.
So now we have a score of 11 with 3, 6, and 2,
so we can still keep going. And luckily we've managed to get a total of 21.
Now we're pretty much invincible I think. So if I go ahead and hit no
cause I don't want to take any more cards, then let's see what the result is.
So it tells us we win and a big smiley face.
So we can probably give the user a little bit more information,
like revealing the final deck; what the computer got, and what we got.
I'm going to go ahead and create some other print statements above this one.
Maybe I'll tell the user that your final hand is this,
and the final score was...
And then let's reveal to them the computer_score,
and then finally we can print the user_score and the computer_score to
tell them who won, who lost, or whether if its a draw.
In this deck, we've got 14, so let's add another card to it.
Unfortunately we went over because we've got another 10.
So our final hand is 10, 4, 10
and the final score was 24. The computer's final hand was 21,
lucky them.
So we went over and we lost. If we wanted to play another game because we are
Blackjack addicts,
then we want to give the user some sort of means of doing this right?
And that's what the last hint addresses.
So we're going to ask the user if they want to restart the game.
If the answer is yes,
then we're going to clear the console and start a new game of Blackjack and also
show the logo from art.py while we're at it.
Let's go ahead and add a input and we can ask them,
do you wanna play a game of Blackjack? Type yes or no.
So remember that this entire function is going to be evaluated and the result or
the output is going to replace this part of the code.
So we can say that while the input is equal to y
then we're going to keep playing the game.
The game is all the code between hint 5 and the end where we compare.
So if we actually put this inside a function by
indenting it over and then creating a function here called play_game,
well then we can actually call this function,
play_game, every time the user types 'y'.
Now we don't want to clutter up our screen with all the previous games.
So before we call play_game,
we also want to clear the console. And to do that
we obviously have to import the clear function from the replit module.
So from replit
import clear, and now we can call this clear function to clear the console in
here after each game.
And then we can call play_game so that the code in this function gets repeated.
And we also said that at the beginning when we play game
we're going to show the user the logo from art.py.
So let's go back and import that as well.
So from art import logo,
and then at the beginning of every game, we're going to print our logo.
That's all there is to this project
and now let's run it one final time and see the whole thing in action.
Do you wanna play a game of Blackjack? Yes.
And it reveals our beautiful Blackjack logo.
It tells us the cards that we have, so current score of 11.
I'm going to take another card. I'm on 21, which is perfect.
So I'm going to pass now. And it tells me that my final hand was 21,
the computer's final hand was 17 and I win. And now I can play another game just
by typing 'y' again.
And I can keep going on and on playing my game of Blackjack.
So I hope you had fun at building this game with me.
I know this was a really difficult project and I know that some of you would
have probably had some issues,
but I really hope that you persevered and you got through it in the end. And
through the process
you've managed to apply a lot of the things that we've learned in the last 10
days.
This is a good time to review the concepts you've learned and have a think about
what you might need to revise or revisit so that you're really,
really strong on all the concepts
and you're comfortable to continue on to the next 10 days. Now,
if you want to take a look at the final code that I've got here,
then just head over to repl.it/@appbrewery/blackjack-final
and you'll see all the code that I went through with you just now.
The first thing I want to talk about is a concept known in programming as Scope.
And this scope is something that we've actually come across already in our
programming, but I wanted to leave it until we've seen functions,
we've seen if and while loops, different types and blocks of code,
before we start talking about this really important concept. Now,
if you want to visualize this concept,
imagine you have a house with a fence around it and you plant an apple tree
inside your garden. Think about who can access those apples.
Just you and your family right? But what if instead,
you had an apple tree in the neighborhood by the sidewalk, for example.
Well, this is kind of free for all. Anybody can go and access those apples.
This is a starting point for how to understand scope.
Head over to the App Brewery Day 12 start Repl.it and go ahead and fork your own
copy of it.
Take a look at the code that's in the starting file in the main.py and try to
understand what it's doing. First
I create a variable called enemies and I set it to equal 1.
Then I create a function called increase_enemies,
and I try to set that variable to 2. Finally,
I call my function triggering all the lines of code inside,
and now I want you to predict what will this print statement print in the
console and what will this print statement print?
And it might not be what you expect it to be.
So I would expect that here I've got a variable which is equal to one.
When this function is called,
this variable enemies should now be equal to two.
So when it's printed down here from outside my function,
this should be equal to two, and this should also be equal to two.
But look at what happens instead.
I get enemies from inside the function equal to 2,
but from outside the function, it's equal to 1.
So what's going on here? To really understand this
we have to understand the concept of scope. And scope is a really,
really important thing in programing.
You see it in every programming language and although its a little bit different
between the programming languages,
it all goes back to that concept of the apple tree being within a fence or
outside a fence.
So let's take a look at some other examples before we come back to solve this
problem.
The first thing to think about is a concept called local scope.
Local scope exists within functions. So for example,
if I was creating a game and I had a function called drink_potion
which is somehow going to strengthen my player,
well, maybe it would have a variable that's created inside the function.
So it could be something like potion_strength
and I could set that to start off where the value of two.
Now in this case
if I was to go and print this variable potion strength from within the function,
notice I'm indented here,
and of course I need to call this function for that to happen.
Notice what happens when I run the code. It's equal to two.
That's what we would expect, right?
But notice what happens if I try to print the potion_strength from outside the
function here. This firstly gives me an error
right when I'm writing it inside the editor. And when I tried to run it,
it gives me an error inside the console. And the error is a name error
and it tells me that the name potion strength is not defined. Clearly I've
defined it here, but why can't I access it outside the function?
Well, this goes back to the concept of local scope.
When you create a new variable or indeed a new function inside another function,
it's only accessible,
you can only use it when you're inside that function because it has local scope.
It's only valid within the walls of this drink_
potion function.
What if we wanted it to be accessible outside the function? Well,
now we need to think about something called global scope.
The only difference between global scope and local scope is where you define or
where you create your variables or your functions.
So let's say we have a different variable.
Let's say that I created a variable called a player_health and it starts off
being equal to 10. Now let's say later on I have the same drink_
potion function, and this potion has strength of 2.
So now inside my function drink_potion,
if I wanted to print my player_health
even though it wasn't defined within the function, this is perfectly possible.
And if I call my function
drink_potion and then run the code as it is,
you will see 10 being printed.
So this has a global scope. It's available anywhere within our file because it
was defined at the top level of the file. Now, when I say top-level,
I don't mean physically at the very top of the file.
I mean that it's not within another function, like potion strength here because
this is defined indented inside a function.
So this is a local variable
whereas this is a global variable. And global variables are available within
functions, no matter how deep it gets nested
and it's also available outside of functions.
This concept of global and local scope doesn't just apply to variables.
As I alluded to before, it also applies to functions and basically anything else
you name. This is a concept called the Namespace.
So we defined this variable player_health, we define this function
drink_potion.
Anything that you give a name to has a namespace and that namespace is valid in
certain scopes.
This concept of scope applies to basically anything you name.
If I was to nest this function drink_potion inside another function,
let's call it game. Well,
this drink_potion now has local scope within the function game.
So this is why this line is now erroring out because it can't actually see inside
this function. So now in order to call this drink_potion,
I have to be within the four walls of the game function.
So whenever you give name to anything, a function or a variable,
you have to be aware of where you created it.
Now it's easy to notice where you've created functions, we have the def keyword,
right? But when you create a variable
that's the first time that you give it a name and you set it equal to something.
And where you write that line of code defines the scope of that particular
variable. Here it's outside of every other function,
whereas here it's inside a function actually nested two levels deep.
So it has a local scope to this function.
Now, unlike some other programming languages,
if you've come from say C++ or Java,
there is no such thing as block scope in Python.
What this means is that if you were to create an if statement,
say if 3 > 2,
and if you were to create a new variable inside an if block or a while loop or a
for loop, basically any sort of block of code that's indented,
this does not count as offence.
It still has the same scope as its enclosing function,
or if there is no enclosing function then it has global scope.
So let me show you a full example. Let's say we had a list of enemies,
so the enemies could be skeletons, zombies, or aliens. So now,
if I was to define a game level, right?
Like the level that the user is currently playing at,
let's say they're on level 3.
And I create an if statement and I check if the game_level is less than level
5, well, in that case, I want to create a new enemy,
but I don't want the enemy to be too difficult to beat.
So I'm going to pick from the list of enemies and I'm going to pick the first
one. Notice how,
even though this new enemy is a variable that's created within this
if block, if I go outside the if block
so I'm not indented at all anymore, and I try to print this new enemy,
this is perfectly valid code. And if I run the code,
you'll see skeleton being printed.
But notice how as soon as I embed this within a function,
so let's define a new function.
And now this line error is out because within the function there is local scope.
So now this new enemy is available anywhere within this function,
because blocks like if, while, for, all of these blocks of code with colons and
indentation, they don't count as creating a local scope.
So in order to print this new enemy,
I actually have to be within the boundary of this function,
which means my code has to be here.
The most important thing to remember from this is if you create a variable
within a function, then it's only available within that function.
But if you create a variable within an if block or a while loop or a for loop or
anything that has the indentation and the colon,
then that does not count as creating a separate local scope.
Coming back to our original example.
I want to talk more about the global scope and the concept of modifying
something within the global scope. Here we have enemies,
which is a variable that has global scope,
and here we have a function which creates a local scope.
Now we think that we're tapping into this variable and setting it to two.
But in fact, we're actually creating a completely new variable
that's entirely separate from this one.
And this is why when we printed it here,
it showed it was equal to 2. But when we printed it here, it showed
it was actually equal to 1. If you want to make this a little more obvious,
I can call this a skeleton and I can set this to be a zombie.
And when I hit run, you can see again, this prints zombie,
this prints skeleton,
because these two variables are actually entirely different things.
And we're not changing this right here at all,
we're just creating a new variable that has a local scope.
Now it's usually a terrible idea to call your local variables and your global
variables the same name. But in this case,
what we actually wanted to do was we wanted to modify this variable,
we wanted to do something like maybe += 1. And notice how
as soon as I write += 1,
that my editor starts going crazy and tells me that this local variable enemies
is defined in an enclosing scope is referenced before assignment.
What does that mean?
It means that the editor thinks you're trying to tap into a local variable that
you defined somewhere around here.
And then you tried to modify it by adding one to the previous value,
but you actually haven't defined it. What we wanted to do though,
is we wanted to tap into this variable and change it here.
In order to do this,
we actually have to explicitly say that we have a global variable
which is called enemies that's defined somewhere outside of this function.
And that is the enemies that we want to use inside this function.
So it basically takes that global enemies into the function and allows you to
modify it. Without this line of code
we cannot modify something that is global within a local scope.
Now there's a reason why it's so difficult to modify something that has global
scope.
You probably don't actually want to do this very often, because it's confusing and
it's prone to creating bugs and errors. Because this variable with global scope
could have been created anywhere in your code, right?
And you would be modifying it completely independent of when you created it.
So it might've been days between when you wrote this code and when you wrote
this code and it just makes everything more fallible,
more easy to fail.
This is why very often people will tell you when they're teaching you Python to
avoid modifying global scope. You can read it,
that's not a problem. You can use it within your code, like we are here.
But don't try to modify it within a function that has local scope.
But what can you do instead?
What if you wanted to have this functionality like a function that changes the
number of enemies?
How can you achieve this without modifying the global scope within the function?
Well, you could use what we learned about return statements instead,
right? What if instead of modifying the enemies,
you actually just simply returned it as the output.
So return the current value of enemies + 1.
Now once you call this function,
you'll get hold of the output and you can save it to the global variable enemies.
So this now means that this function can be taken away and placed anywhere in
your code and you don't actually need to know how it works.
As long as you know that this is how you increase enemies,
then all you have to do is just call it.
Remember, you should be careful with variables that have global scope,
but don't believe the people who tell you that you should never use global
scope. Global scope can be incredibly useful
especially when you're defining constants. Global constants
are variables which you define
and you're never planning on changing it ever again. It's just something like,
for example, the value of pi, right?
You want to look it up once and you want to put it into your code and you never
want to look it up ever again.
And every other time you want to use it, say inside of a function, then all you
want to do is just tap into that value of pi.
So usually, in order to differentiate these constants
which you're pretty much never going to change from the variables
which you are likely to change,
the naming convention in Python is to turn it into all uppercase.
For example,
if you had PI or you had a URL that you needed to use,
or you have some sort of Twitter handle,
then these are all going to be uppercased, separated with underscores.
What this means is that later on in your function and you want to use one of
these global constants, as soon as you type it,
you can see it's the uppercase and you know
to remind yourself to not modify this inside your code.
Now that we've talked a little bit about scope,
it's time to put your knowledge into action. Head over to the next lesson
and I've got a quiz that will test your understanding.
So, for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Now that you've completed some of the scoping problems, it's time to tackle
the final project.
This final project is a little bit special because now I think you've got enough
experience and enough skills under your belt to actually create this project
entirely from scratch by yourself. So you're flying solo now.
Now the first thing I want you to do is head over to guess-the-number-
final.appbrewery.repl.run
and I want you to play this game quite a few times actually,
just so that you get a good idea of how it works. Now,
the first thing it tells us is Welcome.
And then it tells us it's thinking of a number between 1 and 100,
and then we get to choose a difficulty. So I'm going to choose hard.
Now it tells me that I have five attempts to guess the number,
and I'm going to make a guess.
Now it tells me that 50 is too high, it's not the number that it was thinking,
and I have to guess again. And notice how I started out with five attempts,
I'm now down to four attempts. So let's try 25.
So 25 is too low, but 50 is too high.
So that means the number is somewhere in between them.
Let's try 30. Again, too low. Let's try
4o. Too high. Maybe it's 45.
But I only have one attempt left
cause I went for the hard level. And as expected,
I didn't manage to get the right number and I've now run out of guesses.
So I've lost. If we run again,
we can try playing this on an easy level.
On an easy level, we get 10 attempts instead of 5.
That gives us a little bit of extra opportunity.
So let's try 50. 50 is too high. 25 is too high. 10,
10 is too low. So it's between 10 and 25. So let's try 15.
Now, if 15 is too high, but 10 is too low,
then we're pretty close to the answer.
It's now between 12 and 15, let's try 13, 14.
There we go. The actual answer that it had in mind was 14.
And I had four attempts remaining to get the final answer and I managed to get
it at the end. Play through this game at least three,
four times on the different levels
and remember that the easy level has 10 gos,
the hard level, the user gets 5 gos
at guessing the number. And look at how the code works and how it's functioning.
And then I want you to break down this problem. Write a to-do list,
create your own list of tasks that you need to solve and start with the simplest
one. And once you've tackled that, start putting in some comments into your code.
Write down the functionality your program needs,
and then write the code and then test out your code and keep going until you've
tested it and made sure that it works in all situations.
So this final project has no starting code.
I'm not going to give you any comments or to-dos to start off with.
I want you to try and tackle this entire project by yourself.
And the only thing I'm going to give you is this link so that you can try out the
final project. And I know that there's a lot of ways that you can cheat,
but don't do it. Have faith in yourself. If you tackle this for an hour,
I'm pretty sure you're going to get there in the end.
You have free reign on the styling or the wording,
whatever it is you want it to say.
But it has the have the same functionality. Now
this also means that if you want to get some ASCII art of your own,
then you can head over to this website
which I'll link to in the course resources and just type the name of your game.
So maybe it will be Guess
The Number.
And you can change the font that you want for it.
Maybe something a little bit isometric or maybe ogre,
or maybe train, whatever it is you want.
And then once you're happy with the font,
you can select and copy everything that's on there,
and then inside your project
you can create a new file called art.py and then create a new variable and set
it equal to the design that you've got in mind. Now,
in order for it to look right, you actually have to create this as a docstring,
so three quotation marks to begin with and then three quotation marks to end.
And then just make sure you have enough horizontal space to display the whole
thing in one go instead of it being truncated
when you have a little bit of space and you should be able to see the actual
design.
Pause the video now and create this number guessing game by yourself
as the final project.
How did you get on?
Hopefully you managed to complete the project and you're just here
to check through the solution. Now,
if you haven't given it a proper go and I mean,
at least an hour at tackling this, then go back, keep going.
It's only when you struggle that you actually get better.
You can watch me type code all day long,
and it's not going to make you a better programmer.
So I know you're going to try really hard and I want you to try really,
really extra hard and make sure that you can complete each of these projects by
yourself. I mentioned that this one doesn't have a starting repl,
so we're gonna start out with our own and you can call it anything you want,
but I'm going to call it guess-the-number game.
Now, when you're creating a new project from scratch
like we're doing right now,
it can seem a little bit intimidating staring at a blank screen.
The first thing to do is to just divide the project into the individual
components. So while you're playing this game,
you can see that there are different bits of it that we need to complete right?
The first one is printing all the starting parts of the game,
the next one is trying to figure out how to set this difficulty level,
getting the user to type in a word easy or hard,
and then changing the number of attempts based on that. We can already start
thinking about maybe we need to make a function to set difficulty,
and then we need to let the user make a guess, right?
So they're gonna guess a number. So let's say I'm going to type in 50,
and then we have to somehow check that guess against the number that was
originally selected and then check to see if it's too low or too high.
So now we have some additional parts of our program, right?
We need some sort of way of choosing a random number between 1 and 100.
So that's the first thing that's probably going to happen in our code.
We need to have a function to set difficulty,
we probably need some sort of functionality to, um,
let the user guess a number.
And we'll also want to check that number that they've guessed against the number
that we originally had to see if it's too high or too low.
So probably a function to check user's
guess against the actual answer.
Now notice how every single time I make a guess,
my number of attempts go down.
So we also need to track that right? Track the number of turns and reduce by one
if they get it wrong.
Now it's looping back again to this stage where we're making another guess.
So if 50 was too high, then maybe we'll guess 25.
We have to have some sort of way of repeating this part of the code, right?
We're going to repeat it as long as they have attempts left and they are wrong.
Now, if however they get it right,
so I think I have a good chance of getting it right. So if 25 is still too high,
let's try 12. And there we go. When I get the answer right,
it tells me, you got it. The answer was 12.
So now we've got some of the basic parts of our code down in comments,
and we can start thinking about how to write it out, right?
Let's start by tackling the easiest one,
which is choosing a random number between one and a hundred.
All you have to do for this one is just to import the random module, or even
better yet from the random module, import the randint function.
Now inside our code,
we can simply just use randint. We can say the answer is equal to a randint
that is between 1 and 100. And of course remember that rand
int includes a and b,
so both 1 and 100 can show up.
In addition to this, we probably have to give the user some of these messages.
So I'm just going to copy some of these messages.
So I'm going to print 'Welcome to the guessing game.'
And also I'm going to print that
I'm thinking of a number between 1 and 100, like that.
So now we've got an answer that they need to guess,
and we've got a little bit of starting text for them.
The next easiest thing in this is to figure out a way of letting the user
guess a number. So we know that we'll need an input to
ask them to make a guess, so we can copy this part.
And we can use that as the prompt,
and then we're going to have to save their guess and convert it to an integer.
So they're going to be typing a number here, right? And we'll call this guess.
Now the user is able to guess a number and we now have to figure out some sort of
way of checking the user's guess against the actual answer.
This is probably a good time to create a function.
So why don't we go up to the very top and create our function here.
We'll call this check_answer,
and we're gonna pass in the user's guess and the actual answer in order to
achieve this checking functionality. So in this case,
we're going to check to see if the guess is greater than the answer,
well, in this case, it's too high, right? So we'll just print too high.
Now, what if the guess was actually less than the answer,
still not equal to the answer, but in this case it's too low.
So now the final condition is they actually got it right.
So you could write elif guess is equal to answer,
but you could also just use else because there's no other possibilities.
This else statement catches the moment when they actually get it right.
So in this case, we're going to print what we have here,
and then we'll get to print out the answer. Of course,
we're going to replace that with whatever the actual answer is and turn this
into an fstring. So now that's that step done.
And let's think about what else is easy that we can knock off the list.
Let's think of function to set the difficulty. So up here,
in addition to our check_answer function,
I'm going to create this other function, some way of setting the difficulty.
So let's call this set_difficulty,
and it's probably not going to take any inputs.
It's just going to do some sort of action. So when we first start off the game,
it already asks us to choose a difficulty.
So I'm going to copy this text and I'm going to put that into an input,
choose a difficulty easy or hard.
And then we're going to save this probably into a variable,
which I'll call level, so the level of difficulty that they want. Now,
if this level that they chose was equal to easy,
well, in this case,
we want to set the number of attempts that they have to 10.
So they have 10 attempts. But on the other hand,
if they chose hard, then they only have 5 attempts.
So this is probably a really good time for creating a global constant.
So we already saw this in the previous lesson on scope,
but this is a really nice thing because it means if we create this global
constant at the very top, then if we want to switch around how our game works,
we can really easily access these constant by just scrolling through the top of
the page. Let's call the first one, um,
EASY_LEVEL_TURNS, so the number of terms you get on easy,
which is going to be 10.
And then we'll have HARD_LEVEL_TURNS
and this is going to be equal to 5.
Now I've got these two constants which is global
and I can use it inside any of my functions or basically anywhere on this
page. If the level is easy,
I'm going to set the number of turns to equal the EASY_LEVEL_TURNS.
So this is going to be a number right? Else,
so if they chose hard instead,
then turns should probably be the HARD_LEVEL_TURNS. Now,
setting it here is no use. I actually need it inside my game.
So now going back in my game,
I need to let the user know how many number of attempts,
how many turns they actually get. To start off
I'm going to use a print statement that just prints the number attempts they
have remaining. And it's not always going to be 5.
Sometimes it's going to be 5, sometimes it's going to be 10.
So what I'll need is some sort of way of tracking this number of turns,
right? But how do we know how many turns they get? Well,
it depends on what they chose here, right? If they had chosen hard,
then turns should be equal to the HARD_LEVEL_TURNS. If they chose easy,
it should be equal to the EASY_LEVEL_TURNS.
So instead of using this as some sort of global variable
which I have to change inside here, which would require me saying global,
and then turns so that
I can access this particular variable and change it inside
these steps, it'd would be much,
much better if I just returned these values as an output from this function.
If this is set as return,
then I can simply call this function set_difficulty,
which is going to trigger this input. And then once the user has set it,
then the output is going to be the actual number of turns they have.
And I can now use it inside this print statement to show them how many turns
they have. Now.
I've already written quite a bit of code actually,
and it's probably a good time to run the code. While I'm testing my code,
it's probably a good idea to actually see what the answer is.
So we can add a bit of testing code that just prints out what the actual answer
was selected as. And if we run the code
now you can see we've got the starting part pretty much down.
Welcome to the Number Guessing Game.
I'm thinking have a number between 1 and 100,
and then we've got our little hint here. The actual answer is 63.
So we have to make a guess.
And I've really noticed that that input needs a space here so that I'm not
writing right next to the colon. So let's say I guessed 50.
Now it's asking us to choose a difficulty.
So I've already got a little bit of a problem here.
I should actually have this before the other part.
So I should choose the difficulty and then make a guess.
So now let's stop and run and see if we fix that bug. And you can see
yep, indeed it asks us for a difficulty first.
So I'm going to choose easy
and it tells me that I've got 10 attempts remaining and then to make a guess.
And if I choose hard instead, then it tells me I've got 5 attempts.
Now, if while you are play testing this game
and you realize that actually 5 is not enough, then all you have to do is
scroll to the very top of the game,
change this one global variable here,
and all your changes, you know, will be reflected in the code below.
Now let's get back to our game. Let's say I make a guess and our code ends,
right? Even though I've got my check_answer,
it's not actually being called anywhere.
So it lets go ahead and call that function, check_answer
and then we can pass in the user's guess that they made at this step,
and we can also pass in the correct answer which comes from here.
So let's run our code again.
So I'm going to choose the easy mode and I'm going to make a guess.
Now 50 is too high because I can actually see the answer,
it's meant to be 32. So that works. But I can't guess again.
It's not letting me. It's actually ended the program.
So we probably have to tackle this particular todo
if we actually want to get the right functionality.
How do we get the guessing functionality to repeat if they get it wrong? So that
as you might've guessed is probably gonna require some sort of while loop. While
they've gotten it wrong, we probably should go and let them make a guess
again. These parts will definitely need to be repeated.
So let's create a while loop.
What are we going to check in our while loop to make sure that it keeps on going?
Well,
the thing that we're trying to aim for is to get the user to guess the actual
answer.
If we set the while condition as while guess is not equal to answer,
then that pretty much guarantees that these lines of code will keep going until
the user actually gets the right answer. Now however,
when we do this, we get an error, undefined name guess.
Well because guess hasn't been declared yet.
So why don't we declare it outside of the while loop and simply just create it as
a variable? So we'll set that to equal zero. Now at the moment,
this is a global variable. This is a global variable. This is a global variable.
So it's probably a good idea to put our game functionality inside its own
function. So we can create a new function here, which I'll call game,
and now we'll need to call and trigger this game inside the global scope
if we actually want this to be carried out.
Now that we've done all of this hard work,
let's run our code and let's try it out.
Lets go for easy.
And I'm going to start off by guessing 50 as always. 50 is too low and I can see
the answer is actually 90. So I'm going to go for the next number.
Lets try a number that is a bit too high. 95, too high.
Now, what if I actually get it right? What if I actually guessed 90? Well,
it tells me you got it. The answer was 90.
So the only thing that we're not really doing is tracking the number of turns so
that we tell them you have 10 attempts, you have 9 attempts,
you have zero attempts. And if they get zero,
then they're going to lose right? Here
we have this print statement that runs only once because it's not inside the
while loop. So let's tackle our final to-do
to track the number of turns and reduce it by one
if they get it wrong. Now, where do we know that the user got it wrong?
Well inside the check answer function. If it's too high or if it's too low,
then we have to deduct the number of turns they have. But if they got it,
then we don't. One way of tackling
this is again creating a global variable called turns,
set it to start off at zero,
and then inside this function,
we simply just say turns -= 1 and also turns -= 1 when
it's too low or too high. Now because this is a global variable
we again would need to say global turns in order to use it inside our function.
But as I mentioned,
this is not a good idea because it means that you're modifying the global
function within a local scope.
How can we achieve the same functionality without having to use a global
variable? Well,
we could instead just pass in the number of turns that we currently have and
then inside our function,
we can return the number of turns minus one. And we can do the same down here.
So now when we call this function check_answer,
we can pass in the current number of turns
which remember it got set by the set_difficulty function,
and we can pass that in into here.
Because it's not immediately obvious that this function actually has an output,
it's probably a good idea to add a docstring to this function.
Remember the three quotes,
and then in between we're going to say checks
answer against guess. Returns
the number of turns remaining.
Now when we actually call check_answer
you can see that this is what actually happens and that we have a return that we
can be aware of.
If this is going to be the number of turns remaining,
then we can save that to this variable turns so that we update this local
variable every time we check the answer.
Now this part is a little bit mind blowing,
so you might actually want to put this through Python
Tutor and step through it
step by step to see what's actually going on and how this turns variable is
being updated by the output from this function.
If you're totally happy with what's going on, then feel free to keep going.
So now let's check out our code.
50 is too high and 20 is too low, and 38 is just right. Now
what if I actually ran my number of turns down to zero?
So let's try hard because this is only going to give us five attempts.
So let's say I guess 50 and then 70,
and I'm just going to put in some random numbers so that I end up with no
remaining guesses. You can see it's actually not stopping me right?
And also for some reason we have a bug where the number of attempts we have
remaining is not actually being printed. So let's address that issue.
Well, if we want it to happen every time and repeat,
it's going to need to go into the while loop. Instead of printing our number of
turns here, why don't we print it here inside the while loop instead?
So let's make sure the indentation is correct and now let's try it again.
So I have 5 attempts remaining. Let's make a guess.
I have 4 attempts remaining. And notice how it's counting it down;
3, 2, 1. This should be my last guest,
but notice how it actually keeps on going. It doesn't stop the game.
I can keep going and it's going into negatives now.
How can we fix this? We need some sort of way of tracking
when this number of turns goes down to zero. When that happens,
we have to stop the game and tell them that they've lost.
Why don't we create an if statement, check
if the number of tons is equal to zero and print something.
Let's check the actual final version. Let's see what happens in this case.
When I run out of gos,
I make a guess, it's two low and it tells me you've run out of guesses.
You lose. We can print that here as well.
But notice how if we run the code as it is,
so let's just keep guessing the same number until I run it down to 1.
So now I make a guess, it tells me you run out of guesses. You lose.
But it's still letting me keep going even though I've lost.
How can we make our game end? Well,
luckily we've got our game inside a function
which is being called at the very beginning.
Now remember that with functions you have the return keyword.
You can return with an output or you can just write return for it to exit and end
the function. So now with that return keyword in place,
once I run out of turns, see what happens.
It stops and it doesn't let me guess any more.
Perfect. We've managed to get that
right. The thing that we're still missing is this prompt for the user to guess
again. Now this is kind of optional.
It depends on your own feel for the user experience.
I think it makes sense to say, 'It's too low. Guess again.' because it's kind of
telling them to do something. Although there's make a guess,
also prompts them to make a guess. So you can have, you don't have to.
If you wanted to have that,
then you probably actually have to check that they still have turns remaining.
And if they do, then make sure that the guess is not equal to the answer,
so they haven't got it right within this turn, and then to print that 'Guess
again'. So now every time they get it wrong,
but they still have remaining guesses
it should say 'Too low. Guess again.' or 'Too high. Guess again.'
But if they actually get it right,
so the answer should be 83, then it says 'You got it.
The answer was 83' without asking them to guess again.
Now we've pretty much completed this code.
Of course you could have added additional art.
So you could have created an art.py and then used the text to in the ASCII
generator to create a ASCII art.
Yeah.
And then back in here we could have imported it.
And we could put that at the very beginning of the game.
But the rest of the customization is basically your own, right?
You're free to do whatever it is that you want to and to change the wording, to
change the text.
The really important part was that you were able to play this game,
understand how it worked and then break down the problem into smaller pieces
that you could tackle one by one.
And if you had trouble actually completing this program by yourself,
then you should have noticed when we were walking through it
when I just broke down that big a problem into smaller chunks
how much easier it became tackling each of the smaller things, right?
Letting the user guess a number or choosing a random number between 1 and 100,
you can definitely do parts of this.
And as you built up the game, towards the end you realized, ah,
this was missing or that might be nice.
Then you could start adding more and more bits to it.
So if you wanted to review the final code that you see here,
you can, of course, head over to the guess-the-number-final Repl.it at this
particular link in the course resources.
But hopefully, you've actually managed to build out your own version and it's
even better than what I've done. And if you're particularly proud of it,
be sure to share it so that the rest of us can take a look and have a play with
it as well.
So I hope you enjoyed the project today and I'll see you tomorrow.
Hey guys! Welcome back to a 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to look at debugging,
the process of removing bugs from your code.
If you manage to get to this point,
you've probably written quite a bit of code already,
and I will bet that you've probably made some mistakes, some typos,
some errors and some bugs. So in this lesson,
I want to talk about some techniques and tips for how to find bugs and how to
get rid of them from your code. Now,
the first documented bug was actually found by this lady, Grace Hopper.
She was probably one of the first programmers and one of the pioneers of the job
that we're undertaking right now. Now in her notes,
you'll find a moth that's been taped to the notebook,
and this was found in a relay that was preventing her code from running
properly. And this was pretty much the first
actual case of a bug that's been found in a computer.
Even though we're not dealing with moths these days anymore,
we're still going to end up finding bits of things in our code that prevent the
code from doing the things that we want it to.
The important thing to remember is don't feel down when you've created a bug
because everyone gets bugs. And when I say gets bugs,
I mean, we create them, right? So once you've gotten over this, next,
I want to talk about some of the tips and techniques that you should follow on
how to quickly be able to identify and remove these bugs.
So the first step is to describe the problem.
If the problem is messy and it's not well understood in your head,
then it's almost impossible to debug it.
So untangled the problem and try to make sense of what's going on. To begin,
go ahead and fork the starting repl for today's code.
Now, the first thing to notice here is that I've written a bunch of code in the
starting repl
and we're going to be uncommenting these blocks one by one and eventually
solving all of the debugging problems.
So the first thing you're going to do is to uncomment the first block of code.
Now in this block of code,
we're going to practice describing the problem to help us solve this debugging
problem. Now if you take a look at this function
you can see that at some point in the function,
we're supposed to print this line out into the console.
But if we go ahead and hit run, you can see that nothing gets printed.
So what's going on here?
I want you to take a look at this function and describe the actual problem.
What is the for-loop doing? When is the function meant to print "You got it"?
What assumptions are you making about the value of i? So pause the video,
read the function and have a go at describing the problem.
All right.
So what we've got here is we've got a function that loops through all the
numbers between 1 and 20,
and then once that number reaches 20, it's supposed to print "You got it".
But the problem is that when i reaches 20,
it doesn't print this line into the console.
So now that we've described the problem and we understand what's going on,
let's see if we can solve it. If we think about this problem,
when i reaches 20, it doesn't print out this line.
There's an assumption in there, right?
The assumption is that i will definitely reach 20.
But if you think back to how the range function works,
the stop or the upper bound is actually omitted.
So when you write range(4),
it actually produces a number from 0 up to 3.
And in our case, when we write (1, 20),
it actually goes from 1 all the way up to 19
but not including 20.
The problem here is that i actually never reaches 20.
So this assumption is completely false. Pause the video
and see if you can fix the code so that this line actually gets printed.
All right. So all we need to do is change this to 21 instead of 20
and now when we hit run, you can see it actually works
and we managed to debug this problem. Always when you come across a problem
in your code,
try to describe it so that you really understand what the issue is,
and then test your assumptions and see which of those assumptions is actually
false.
Now the next step is to think about reproducing the bug that you've encountered,
because when you encounter it once but you don't encounter it the next time
that becomes a really difficult bug to fix. Go ahead
and uncomment the next block of code.
And we're going to comment out the previous section because we're done with it
now. So this is the only part that should be active in your main.py.
In this section, we're going to try and reproduce the bug.
So when we run the code,
sometimes it will work and it will print out one of the dice images from this
list, but occasionally you will get an error.
These types of bugs are really difficult because you might test your code only
once or twice, and it looks all fine. It works.
But then occasionally you get an error.
And the important thing is to reproduce that error.
When does that error actually happen?
And based on that knowledge, we can fix our code.
Try to reproduce the bug yourself and try to notice when it happens and see if
you can change the code so that it always produces this error.
[inaudible],
We've got a list of dice images, which are just emojis.
And we've also got this random number, dice number between 1 and 6.
Now, when we try to pick out of our list,
occasionally we get an error.
Now we have to notice when the error occurs, and to reproduce the bug
we have to figure out which of these numbers is actually causing the problem.
So we know that this is a random number between 1 and 6
and if we check the documentation, it tells us that randint
works a little bit differently from range.
It will return a random integer in the range of a and b,
including both end points. So in our case,
both 1 and 6 could be generated and it could be any number.
So if that was equal to 1, well, does it generate an error?
No, it just picks out this particular item.
But what if it was 2 or 3 or 4?
Or what if we tested 6? Well,
now every time we hit run, you can see we get an error.
And now that we've got our error to show up consistently,
it's a lot easier to debug because we know that the index error list index out of
range happens when this dice number is 6.
So when we go back to our previous code, well,
we can't use 6 in this list because lists start counting from 0.
So to get this dice 1, we need dice_num to be 0.
And then this is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
and 6 is somewhere out here and it doesn't exist. Now,
go ahead and fix this code so that all the dice images are represented and we
never see this error again. Alright.
So that is as simple as shifting down these numbers.
So instead of making a random number between 1 and 6,
we actually want a random number between 0 and 5. And now,
no matter how many times we run our code,
we're never going to get that error show up again.
Very often I've asked you in the quizzes
especially to play computer.
And the reason is because this skill of pretending to be a computer reading
through your code and imagining what you going to do each time is really,
really useful, especially when you're debugging.
So let's comment out the previous block and try the next block.
Take a look at this code.
It takes an input
in the form of an integer and it ask the user for their year of birth.
And then it uses an if statement to check if they were born between 1980 and
1994, in which case they're classified as a millennial.
But if there were born later than 1994, then they're classified as a Gen Z.
So depending on which country you're from,
there's different classifications for your particular generation.
This is just the typical words that you hear on the internet.
You're a millennial, you're a Gen Z, you're a baby boomer,
and this comes from a lot of the history of the US. But nonetheless,
I want you to run the code and I want you to see what happens when I put in
1994. Absolutely nothing,
so we have our bug right there. Run through the code line-by-line and evaluate
each statement. For example, if year is equal to 1990,
will line 77 evaluate to true or to false?
What if year is equal to 1994?
Look at each line of code and follow the logic and check what it will evaluate
to.
So I want you to play computer and figure out what is the problem,
and then go ahead and fix the bug. Pause the video now.
All right. So
let's pretend that we got 1994 as the input.
So now I'm the computer
and I know that this year is equal to 1994.
Now with this year being equal to 1994,
I go into this if statement so is 1994,
greater than 1980? Yes it is.
So this actually becomes true.
Now I have to check the second condition and it also has to be true for this if
block to be triggered. So is 1994,
less than 1994? No, it's not.
It's actually less than equal to 1994,
or it's equal to 1994. So in this case,
this condition becomes false.
And we know that if we try to combine a true and a false then it actually just
becomes a false.
So this gets skipped.
Now, next, we look at the next statement, right?
If 1994 is greater than 1994,
well, that's also not true. It be greater or equal to,
or it could just be equal to.
So this condition is also false.
So that means it's also going to skip this next line and there's no more lines
of code left, which is why the computer doesn't print anything.
So let's restore our code to before we started playing computer
and we can identify that this problem occurs because there is no bucket that
actually catches the 1994.
We could simply fix this code by changing one of these conditions to be greater
than or equal to either here or here.
And that means that the year 1994 is not skipped over in our conditions.
And when we hit run, it will actually tell us that we are in fact,
a Gen Z.
Now the next step
and the next tip is pretty obvious. When the editor's giving you an error or when
the console is giving you an error, fix the errors before you continue.
Now, this is a little bit easier when you're dealing with errors in the editor,
because it will actually highlight to you the line that's broken.
So here we've got a print statement and when we hover over it,
it tells us that it expected an indented block. So that should be a good enough
clue to tell us what's actually wrong.
So if we go ahead and indent this block, then that error goes away.
But that's not the only error, no. When you run this code,
you still get another error. So let's say that I am a 12-year-old girl,
we get another error.
And this error does not show up when we write the code,
but it only shows up depending on what input we gave to this age variable.
So now we have a different type of error. We have an error that's in the console.
How do we solve this error? Well,
the easiest way is just to select the parts of the error
that's not specific to your code like this age greater than 18 or line 84,
but the part that is pretty much common to whenever anybody gets this error.
And now if we copy it and we paste it into Google,
then you can see there's a lot of other people who've had this issue.
And if we read what the problem is,
it tells us that you're getting the input from the console as a string
and you must cast that input as an int
before you try to do these numerical operations like comparisons. Back over here,
that's exactly what we're trying to do on line 84 right here.
This age comes out of this input function and it returns a string.
And so in order to turn this into a number,
we of course have to cast it or type convert it into an integer.
And now when we run our code and we give it our age,
it no longer errors out.
And if I tell it that I am in fact 21,
which is still not my real age,
then we actually get the print statement working.
But remember that the errors don't always solve all of your bugs, like this.
In this case there are no errors with my code whatsoever,
it's just not doing what I want it to do.
And these are the most frustrating bugs to debug because nobody is helping you
here. There is no errors that you can Google,
there's no underlines that you can check.
You actually have to rely on your skills as a programmer to fix this.
Now we, of course, know that this needs to be an fstring in order to insert that
variable into this position in the curly braces.
But if you didn't, then this would be a lot harder to debug.
Experience comes in really handy with debugging and the more bugs that you
solve, the better you get at it. So go onto the internet,
try to help people in Stack Overflow. Go on to the discord channel for the course,
try to solve other people's bugs and you will find yourself getting stronger
and better day by day.
Now the next tip has been the thing that you've probably been screaming out for.
Why don't we use print? And indeed you are correct.
Print is basically your best friend. Now as developers
I know we don't have a lot of friends,
but at least we can rely on print to be our trusty friend.
Do you have heartbreak? Use print. Now print probably can't help you with your
relationship issues or family issues,
but it can help you debug your code,
which is a pretty decent thing for it to do.
So let's go ahead and comment out the previous block and let's uncomment this
one. And now I'm sure you're pretty much dying to use print to solve these
debugging issues. Why Angela? Why haven't you been using it before? Well,
I've been saving it for this perfect moment.
Take a look at the code and see if you can use print as your friend to help you
solve the issue. Pause the video now and give that a go.
So here, we've got
a very simple program that figures out the number of words in a book. Pages
starts out zero, words starts out at zero,
and we have to input the number of pages in our book and the number of words in
our book.
And then we multiply the pages by the words to calculate the total number of
words in the book and then we print it out. But if we have a go,
you can see that let's say we have, um,
45 pages making a booklet and we have 250 words per page and we get 0.
So the output that's supposed to tell us the total number of words in the book
ends up being 0. So what's going on here?
How can we debug this? Let's go ahead and use print.
What are our assumptions? Well,
we're actually getting the number of pages and the number of words correct
so that we can calculate this.
Why don't we add some print statements before the final one? Let's print
what's the actual value of some of our variables that we're getting from the
user. For example, I could say, um,
the pages equals and then insert the pages variable in here in an fstring.
And I can also print my other variable in an fstring,
which is the word per page variable.
And this is equal to let's insert that variable as well.
And now when I run my code,
I've got my print statements going and I can test it out.
So we still got 45 pages and then 250 words per page.
Now you can see that my variables are logged. So this one,
this pages variable does equal 45. So it captured my data correctly.
But the word per page equals 0,
which is not what I entered at all. I entered 250
so I was expecting this to be 250.
So now using print, my best friend,
I've managed to narrow down the problem.
It's something to do with this variable.
So let's take a look at what's going on here. Well,
I've spotted the problem,
have you? Pause the video and see if you can fix this code
so the final total number of words actually gets printed when you run the code.
Pause the video now. All right,
we've narrowed down to this one line of code that's probably broken.
And if you look closely, you'll see that instead of a single equal sign
which means assignment,
this variable should be equal to this value.
We had two equal signs.
This means does this variable equal this value?
And this actually gets evaluated and becomes either true or false.
Now, in this case, it's actually false. Words per page starts out being equal to
zero, and then it becomes equal to 250.
So if this line of code is false, then that's just left as it is,
it doesn't actually affect anything.
And this total word is still using zero, which is why it's printing out zero.
So now that we've identified the issue, all we have to do to fix it is that.
And if we run our code again,
you can see it works exactly as it should do.
Now before you start getting really committed to print and start making
friendship bracelets for this print statements,
there's another tool that I really want to talk about
and it's a tool that's bigger, it's fancier, it's more complex.
So what is it?
It's a debugger and we've already seen debuggers a little bit.
So I've already shown you pythontutor.com
and you've also seen us use the debugger in the Thonny editor right here.
Now, in this example, I'm going to stick with the web version of Python Tutor
just so that you don't have to install anything extra.
But if we go ahead and comment out the previous block and uncomment
the last one, you can see that we have yet another problem to solve
and yet another piece of code, that's not doing what it's supposed to do.
So in this case,
we've got a function that's supposed to mutate a list so that it takes a list as
an input
and then it's supposed to multiply each of the items in the list
so the final output should be something like 2, 4,
6, 10, and so on and so forth.
Basically taking each of these numbers and multiplying them by 2,
which happens on this line of code. But unfortunately when we run it,
we just get a list with a single value, 26. So what's going on?
Let's try and debug it.
So I want you to copy these lines of code and then paste it into Python Tutor
and then go ahead and click Visualize Execution.
Now that it's inside the debugger, we can do a lot of things with it.
We can step through the code to see it line by line. So for example,
the first thing that happens is we create a function called mutate and this
mutate gets past a input called a_list.
So now inside this function, mutate,
we've got a variable called a_list and it's this list with these values.
Now, as we keep going, we can see we create a b_list, which is an empty list
and then we use the for-loop to loop through each of the items in the list.
So the first time this item is equal to the first item in the list,
which is 1,
and then we multiply it by 2 to create this new_item variable,
which is now equal to 2.
And now the loop goes back to the beginning and we keep doing this with each of
the numbers in the list. We multiply 2 to each of the numbers.
Now, once we're done with that loop, the next line that happens is this one.
This b_list gets appended with the new item and finally,
we print out the b_list. Now this is where the problem occurs.
Notice how b_list is just a list with one value.
And that is in fact what gets printed. So with this debugger,
we've managed to see line line what the computer is doing,
which is really helpful in itself.
But we can actually make this process even simpler. Inside
most debuggers, you can put a breakpoint
which tells the computer to stop what you're doing at this particular line.
And then at that moment in time,
I want to examine what all the variables and all the functions are doing.
So in our line, the key problem happens right here.
If I click on this line, you can see it becomes red
and this is where it happens, this is the break point basically.
So now I can scroll over to that point in time I can examine the values of all of
my variables. a_list is still what I expect it to be,
but b_list is completely empty. And this item happens to be on the last item
number 13 and the new item is doing what it needs to do,
multiplying it by 2,
but none of them are being added to my list because if I click next,
you can see this b_list is equal to just one value.
And it happens to be the last value that new_item was equal to.
So by using this debugger,
you should now have a good idea of what the problem is.
Pause the video and try to fix this code so that the mutated list with all of
its six values gets printed. Pause the video now.
All right.
So the simple problem is that when we are adding the new item to this b_list,
we're doing it outside the loop.
It's when this loop has completed and at the very end
do we actually call this line.
So what we needed to do to fix this code is just to indent that line over.
And now when we run the code,
you can see that the proper output gets printed
and if we change this code in there, the debugger, if we edited it right here,
then when we visualize it, you can see if I put a breakpoint here
that right line of code gets executed six times
and if we go to that line of code and we hit next,
you can see that the b_list is now getting new values added each time as we
would expect it to. And when we examine all of our variables
especially this b_list variable,
it's exactly what we expect it to equal each step of the code.
So a debugger can be really useful.
It's almost like you've put a print statement on all the variables in your
code,
and you can isolate a particular time point to see what each of the values are.
And as we become even more experienced,
we're going to be using the debugger more and more.
Now, I've got some final tips for debugging,
and these are not so much techniques, but there are just really,
really important tips from somebody who's done quite a lot of coding and created
a massive amount of bugs in my lifetime.
So tip number 7 is take a break. It's really,
really important when you're just staring at the code and you keep looking at
it, it's not going to tell you the solution.
Just have a cup of tea or have a nap,
or just go to sleep and try to tackle it tomorrow.
You will be surprised just how much easier things are when your brains had some
downtime and then you come back to it. Everything seems so much more obvious.
And if you really, really get stuck and you just can't see it, ask a friend,
not your friend print, but your actual friend,
a real human. Preferably a developer, but they don't have to be.
It could be somebody who's taking the course with you.
You could go onto discord and find other students to help you because after all,
you're all just leveling up your own programming skills
right? The really good thing about asking a friend to look through your code is
they won't make the same assumptions that you've made.
So they have some fresh eyes that they can look at the code with,
and it might be incredibly obvious what's actually happening.
And it's really not embarrassing at all.
If somebody managed to help you with your code,
you can offer to help them the next time when they get stuck. And for the person
who's helping you,
they're also just working out their programming muscles, right? Now
the next tip is to run often. No,
you don't have to go exercising to be a good programmer.
But what I mean is run your code often.
Don't wait until you've written loads and loads of code to hit run
and then find out you've got loads of snags and loads of bugs.
But run it after every little execution.
Once you feel like you've changed the program ever so slightly, run it. Confirm
that it's actually doing what you want it to do,
because if you leave it all to the end,
then you end up with a pile of bugs and you don't know where to start. Now,
if you do end up in that situation and you can see multiple bugs at the same
time, try to tackle them one at a time
instead of trying to do bits and bobs of each. It will really, really help.
And the final tip is, of course, Stack Overflow. I've saved this the last
because you really don't want to take every single small bug of yours to Stack
Overflow, that's not what it's designed for. Instead,
it's really designed as a way of asking other developers
when you think that you've come across a bug or an issue that should be unique.
Now, if you think that you issue isn't unique and other people should have
encountered this, then just search Stack Overflow.
If you really think that nobody in the world has had this issue that you are
having right now, then that's the moment to ask the oracle, I mean Stack
Overflow.
I've worked in a lot of companies where everybody just goes to the part when
Stack Overflow is down, because there's just no point. As programmers
we use it and we search it so much and it's become a really vital tool in the tool
belt.
But you only wanna ask a question when you've pretty sure that you've exhausted
all other avenues of debugging and you've searched all of Stack Overflow and you
finally end up with something very strange and very weird that you want others
to help you figure out. So don't worry about creating bugs.
And hopefully at this point, you're creating friendly bugs,
like this little Caterpillar right now.
And as you scale up and become even more advanced,
you're going to be creating bigger and more scary bugs.
So at some point in the future, when you're creating bugs like these,
then you really know that you've become a professional.
You will wish to come back to today when you can tackle bugs like these
instead. So don't worry about
about creating them. It doesn't mean that you are bad programmer. In fact,
it's an important part of every programmer's journey. Just as a sort of personal
note,
there was a point in time where I've really thought that I was not a programmer of
code, that I was just a programmer of bugs.
It seemed like every line of code I wrote was a bug.
So these are my 10 top tips for debugging.
And I hope that any time when your code is not doing what you expect it to do to
come back to this lesson, review these 10 steps, go through them one by one
and I bet 99% of the time, once you've gone through all of these stages,
you will have solved your bug and you will have made your code a lot better.
And remember that every bug that you catch in your code and that you fix is like
lifting a dumbbell in the gym. It's just one rep.
And the more reps you do the better you'll get at programing. In the next
lesson, I've got some coding challenges for you to debug.
Are you ready to flex your programming muscles?
I hope so. Head over to the next lesson and get started.
To begin, go ahead and select the Debug Odd or Even exercise.
All right. So now that you
have learned all about the tips and tricks and the steps to go through
to debug your code,
it's time to put some of that into action. In the upcoming three lessons,
I've got a bunch of code that you've already written before.
The first one, for example,
is the Odd or Even code challenge that you did a long time ago.
Now, the important thing is for you to not just go back to the old code,
copy it, paste it in, submit, done. That isn't going to teach you anything.
There's no point doing this if you're not going to learn. But instead,
what I want you to do is to look at the code, see what it meant to do.
So for example, in this case,
we're trying to input a number and then we're trying to get our code to check
to see if it's an odd number or an even number, and then print it out. Now,
in most of these upcoming code exercises, they're going to be broken,
but it's your job to try and fix it
to make sure that it does what it's supposed to. In this case,
you should be able to type in a number and it should print,
"This is an even number." if it's even, "This is an odd number." if it's odd.
Once you've spotted the problem and debugged and fixed your code,
then I'll go through the solution with you. So pause the video now.
All right. So,
as always, let's first hit run to see if it actually works or not.
And in this case, it doesn't even run. It gives us a syntax error straightaway,
and it tells us that on line three, we've got some invalid syntax. Now,
on line three, that's actually not all that specific.
But notice how sometimes when you get errors,
it's actually nice enough to have a little arrow pointing towards the bit of the
code in that line that it thinks is problematic.
So let's try and fix this error before we proceed.
So why does it have an issue with this equal sign? Well,
remember that two equal signs is checking and one equal sign is assignment.
So in this case,
we're actually saying number % 2 should be equal to zero,
which is nonsense. It doesn't actually make any sense. Instead,
what we wanted was two equal signs so that we can check that the left-hand side
is equal to the right-hand side.
And now if we hit run and we enter a number, it should now work.
Did you manage to get it right?
If not, be sure to review some of the lessons on debugging and try to apply it in
the next exercise. So once you're ready, head over to the next lesson.
All right. So in this lesson, we're going to be debugging our leap year
coding exercise. You've done this coding exercise before, you wrote this code
which checks to see if a year is a leap year.
It prints leap year if it's true, and not leap year
if it's not a leap year.
All you have to do is to fix this code.
So use what you learned about debugging and try to fix this coding exercise.
So pause the video now.
Okay.
All right. So first off,
let's go ahead and just run our code and see if it works.
And then we're going to enter a known leap year.
So a quick Google away lets see when is a leap year.
Well, 2020 seems to be a leap year. So let's try that.
Let's check 2020. And we get an error.
So errors are good. They're much easier to fix than the Programming problems
which have no errors.
And it tells us that there's a problem on line three and it's a type error,
not all arguments converted during string formatting.
What does that mean? Well, what's a type error anyways?
A type error is when you're trying to do something with the wrong data type. In
our case, it's pointing at line three. So if we take a look at line three,
what's happening here?
Well, currently we're trying to take the year that the user inputted, so 2020, and
divide it by four to see if the remainder is equal to zero.
Now, this is a little bit harder to solve than the previous one.
But what you should realize is that it's pointing towards a type error,
so what data types have we got going on? Well,
if we go ahead and print the type of our year,
then you can see that it's of class string.
But if we print the type of this 4 that
we're trying to divide it by, that is of class int.
So this is the problem. These two types are not matched.
So when you try to divide a string by an integer,
this is what ends up giving you this problem.
So why is this a string when we entered a number?
Well it's because the input function, remember, gives the user a prompt and then
takes whatever they type in the console and turns it into a string.
So in order to turn this into an int which is what we want,
we have to wrap it around a set of parentheses and then type
convert it into an integer. And now when we run it again,
we can see that it actually works. And we're happy that we fixed our code.
Once you're done with this challenge,
head over to the next one and complete the final debugging exercise.
So we're onto our final debugging exercise.
This is debugging Fizzbuzz. Fizzbuzz, if you remember,
is a program that will print Fzzbuzz
if a number is divisible by both three and five.
It will print fizz
if it's only divisible by three, and it will print buzz
if it's only divisible by five.
If it's not divisible by three or five,
then it's just going to print the number.
And our code is going to do this all the way from 1 to 100.
So what should happen by the end of this is in our console when we hit run,
it should start typing one and then it should type two and then three,
it will type fizz. And four, it will type four. Five,
it will type buzz and so on and so forth.
You should remember this from the previous exercise where you actually had to
write all this code. Now, as always,
don't just paste the solution code in. That won't do anything.
You need to work for it to gain knowledge.
So now that you know what the program is supposed to do,
what you are going to do is try to figure out all of the bugs in here and try to
fix all the bugs so that the program runs as it should do.
Pause the video, think about the 10 steps and try to apply it here.
Now, just as a quick note, unlike the previous debugging exercises,
there's more than one bug in this code. So, good luck
and I'll see you on the other side.
All right.
So, as I mentioned,
there's quite a few bugs in here and we're going to fix them one by one.
As always,
the first thing we're gonna do is we're just gonna run the code and see what
happens.
So the first thing you'll notice that's a little bit odd is it's printing
instead of just one, two, three, four,
it's printing it as if it's a list with the square bracket around it.
So let's see if we can identify why. Well in our code,
if none of these if statements are true, then it prints the number.
But in this case it's not just the number.
There seems to be some square brackets around the number,
in which case it's printing a list with that number as the single item inside.
So let's get rid of that and let's run our code again.
That looks a little bit better, a bit cleaner. Now let's take a look at the code.
So we know that when the number is only divisible by three then it should print
fizz,
but three, in this case, is actually printing Fizzbuzz, and five is printing Fizzbuzz
and then three and four, it seems a bit of a mumbo-jumbo.
So, what's actually happening here?
It seems like instead of just printing fizz,
it's printing Fizzbuzz and the number.
So there must be a problem in our checking code.
So let's think about what our code needs to do. When the number is divisible by
both three and five, then instead of the number, it should print Fizzbuzz.
So Fizzbuzz should only be printed
if the number that we're currently checking is divisible by both three and five.
Let's use the print statement to help us.
If we use an f-string and we say that we are currently on number and then we
put the number in here. This way
we'll actually print out the current number we're looping through
and then we can see what's being printed each time. So let's run the code.
And if we scroll to the top, currently on number one it prints one,
currently on number two it prints two, currently on number three
it prints Fizzbuzz, Fizz and three. So that is very,
very strange behavior indeed.
It seems like lots of things are true in our if statement. What's happening? Well,
if number is equal to three,
then it seems to be printing Fizzbuzz,
which means if we walk backwards, this if statement must have been true.
Now three divided by three should have zero as the remainder,
so this should be true. But this can't be true,
so this must be false. And it should only print Fizzbuzz if it's divisible by
both three and five. So instead of an or,
this really needs to be an 'and'.
So let's hit run again and see what happens this time. Currently on number three,
it prints Fizz and three. So that's again,
a bit of a problem. So we fixed the Fizzbuzz parts.
It is now printing Fizzbuzz correctly. Namely,
when it's on number 15. But why is it still printing the number?
The number should only be printed if none of the others are true.
But instead, it seems to be printing Fizz and then also printing the number.
What's the reason here? Well,
notice how we've got an else statement here that triggers the printing of the
number. Now, an else is paired with an if. So in this case,
what's happening is it's checking if the number is not divisible by five,
then print the number. That's not what we want. And in fact,
if you look at the print statements,
you can see that only when the number is divisible by five
does it not print the number. When it's divisible by three,
it's still printing the number. This is not what we want.
What we want is for this to be checked, and if that's not true,
then check the next thing. And if that is not true, then the next thing.
And finally, if all three of these are not true, then print the number.
So what we actually need instead of a whole bunch of ifs is actually some else
ifs.
So let's replace those two ifs with some elifs and now let's run our code.
So currently on number one, two, three,
so three now prints Fizz, five prints Buzz, nine prints
Fizz, 10 prints Buzz and 15 prints Fizzbuzz.
So I think we've actually managed to fix all of our code.
So I think we should be able to remove our print statement now.
And indeed we've managed to successfully solve all of the debugging problems
here. Now did you manage to get all that right? Don't worry
if you have to struggle a little bit. In the future,
you're going to be making a lot more bugs and you're going to be repeating this
process of using the 10 steps
to try and identify the problems and fix the code and make it free of bugs.
So hope you had a fun and jam packed day.
Now this might be a good time to revisit some code that you've given up on a
long time ago or projects that you've started
but you've stopped because you ran into bugs. And then review them,
use what you learned today and try to fix the bugs and get your code working.
Now tomorrow, I've got a big day for you coming up.
We're going to spend the whole day creating a big project and we're going to be
making the Higher-Lower game. So I'm looking forward to it,
I hope you are too. So get a good night's rest and I'll see you tomorrow.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 14 of 100 Days of Code. Today
you are going to spend building an exciting game called Higher or Lower.
And if you want to have a go at it, just go over to higher
lowergame.com and click on classic.
So the classic version of higher lower is you compare one search term,
The Grand Budapest hotel
which is a movie, against another search term AFL,
which is the American Football League.
And you have to say if the second one has higher or lower searches
than the Grand Budapest hotel. So I think this probably has higher.
And indeed I'm right. And then now it gives you a new term to compare.
So Six Nations Rugby versus AFL who has lower.
I think this probably has lower and I'm right.
And you keep going until you get it wrong.
And it's a weirdly addictive game for some reason. Okay.
So now I've gotten it wrong and it tells me how many I got right as my score
and I can play again if I wish to. Have a play around with that game
because the final version we have looks a lot simpler,
but it's still just as fun to play.
Instead of comparing average monthly searches on Google,
we're comparing who has more followers on Instagram.
So we're bringing this game up to date. In this case, it's comparing Neymar,
a footballer from Brazil against Chloe Kardashian, a reality TV
personality and businesswoman from the US who has more followers.
So I think it's 'B', I could be wrong and I'm wrong.
So here we're comparing
Rihanna a musician and businesswoman from Barbados against Shakira
a musician from Columbia.
So I'm going to guess probably Rihanna and I get it right,
so I get to score one point. And this game continues on and on until you get to
the point where you get it wrong, same as the one that you saw before.
And there we go. So I got three as my final score,
and that's the end of the game.
The aim of the game is to try and stay alive for as long as possible and score
as high as possible by thinking about who might be more popular than the other.
Now here comes the interesting part.
You are going to be coding up this game entirely by yourself.
You're going to apply everything you've learned so far to understand how this
game works by playing it quite a few times,
going to this URL and looking at all the specific nuances;
what happens if you get it wrong, what happens if you get it right,
and you're gonna write the code all yourself,
and you're probably going to need your skills of debugging to fix some problems
as you go along as well.
So the approach I want you to take is first think about the problem and then
break down a large problem into smaller problems.
This way you can tackle them one by one, and it won't be so intimidating.
Now, step 2 is to look at those problems and make a
to-do list. Given the items on the to-do list,
you're going to pick the one that you think is the easiest to begin.
Let's say that, uhm, maybe generating a random number.
That's pretty simple, right? Well, in this to-do list,
that's the first one we're going to tackle. So in this case,
we're building a very simple dice game, right?
The game that you were going to be building is a lot more complex,
it won't just have three to-dos. But the idea is the same.
Once you pick the task that you think is the easiest, generating a random number,
then you gotta take that problem
and you're going to break it down into comments in your code.
So just as you've seen me do it for our previous project,
you are going to do the same thing.
You're going to take that problem of generating a random number and then split
it into different pieces, right?
First, you probably have to import the random module and then you probably have
to use a function like randint to generate
a random integer. So now that you've taken a big problem and broken it apart into
smaller problems, taking the easier smaller problem
and break it down into comments in your code,
then you are ready to start writing some code.
So write code beneath the comments, run your code,
make sure that it does what you want it to do. And if it doesn't, then fix the code.
And once you've done that, then it's back to the beginning,
write more code under the comments, run more code,
fix more code until you've managed to cross out that task.
And then its a case of tackling the next one that you think you can attempt.
So this is the real skill of programmers; taking something that's immensely
complex and difficult, breaking it down into smaller problems,
breaking it down further,
and then tackling them from the easiest to the hardest and doing this one by
one. Eventually by the end, you end up with your final product.
This is what I want you to do.
So the first thing you have to do is the head over to the final version of the
game,
play it at least 10 times just so you understand exactly how it works and then
pull up the starting code for the day, which is the higher-lower-start,
and go ahead and fork your own copy of it.
Now you'll notice that there's three files in the starting code. One is the art
.py that contains the logo and the versus symbol that shows up when it asks you
to compare.
So compare A, Christiano Ronaldo versus B, Vin Diesel.
And these are the art that you're going to display. And finally,
and probably most importantly, there is a file called game data. Now game data
only a single variable.
It's a list of dictionary entries.
Each of these dictionaries have four keys and the keys are the same for
all of the entries. They've got a name, the name of the account,
the follower count,
so how many followers in millions does that account have.
So for example, Christiano Ronaldo has 215 million followers,
at least at the time when I compiled the data. And then it has a description,
he's a footballer or this is a social media platform,
she's a musician and actress. And finally the country that they're from.
You're going to use all of these pieces of information to construct a comparison
line like this, compare A: Cristiano Ronaldo
a football from Portugal. We have B.
And you're going to ask the user to guess who has more followers. And if they get
it right, they get to keep playing, where A now becomes the previous B,
so Vin Diesel who you used to be B now becomes A,
and then you get to compare against a new person and it keeps on going until they
get it wrong. That is the task ahead of you
and it's not going to be easy, but I think you can do it.
So give this project at least an hour. You'll need to write the code,
you will need to fix problems, you'll need to debug,
you will need to test it quite a few times. But by the end of it,
you will emerge a stronger programmer
I promise. So good luck and make sure you have lots of struggle and I'll see you
on the other side.
All right, so I really hope you've given this challenge a good go and you've spent at least an hour
toiling over it and struggling, and you should be wiping sweat off your brows before you come and look
at the solution.
The struggle is so important and I can't stress it enough.
But in this lesson, I want to run through how I would tackle this problem.
Now, it doesn't mean that you have to do the same thing.
There isn't one solution.
There's probably thousands of different solutions for a project like this.
And as long as your program runs exactly the same way, then you've succeeded.
It doesn't matter at this stage how you've done it necessarily.
As long as you manage to organize your thoughts, break down the problem and write the solution code
and get it to run, then you are victorious.
The real challenge in today's project was for you to break down a big problem into smaller, solvable
chunks.
It isn't even so much the code that matters.
It's this skill that you really need to develop to become a really good programmer.
And so far I've been breaking down the problem for you, showing you the steps that would take you to
the solution.
But now you're really wearing the big-programmer pants and you're doing it all by yourself.
So let's think about this problem and how we would break it down.
There's some easy problems here, right?
We need the art to display.
So let's add a comment for each problem we identify.
We've got the ASCII art showing up here and we've got the versus showing up here.
Now, the next one is we've got these randomly generated accounts right from the data.
So we've got Camila  Cabello and Emma Watson.
How do we get these random accounts to show up?
That's another problem, right?
So we know that we've got all of this game data here in the format of a dictionary that's nested inside
a list.
And we need to figure out a way of pulling out a random account from this list.
So that's another problem I've identified.
Now, the next thing you'll notice is that the data contains many key value pairs, the name of the
account, the description, etc. But when we display it, it's all nicely formatted; the name and then
what they do and then where they're from. We'll have to add that as probably another problem to solve.
How do we format the account data into a printable format?
OK, so let's say we solve that and we've got A and B, now we have to ask the user for a guess.
Guess who has more followers.
So that's another problem to solve.
And when they do type an answer, let's say we think maybe A has more followers, then it's going to
have to check that answer and see if it's correct or if it's wrong.
So that's going to be a big problem.
Check if user is correct, because that's going to require a couple of things,
right?
We're going to probably have to break down this problem into smaller problems if we want to solve it.
So, for example, we probably need to figure out the follower count of each account, and then we'll
probably need to use an if statement to check if user is correct.
Now, if we get it right or if we get it wrong, the game is always going to give us some feedback.
"Sorry, that's wrong" or "You're right."
So let's add to our problem list. Now,
in addition to giving them feedback whether if they got it right or whether if they got it wrong, it
also has a way of tracking score,
right?
Every time they get the answer right, the score goes up by one.
In addition to all of that, the game repeats itself when the user gets it right.
So let's say in this case, I guess Dwayne Johnson, then you see how the game repeats itself, right?
It goes back and it takes Dwayne Johnson puts it in position A and generates a new account in position
B for me to go again.
So I get another round because I got it right.
So we'll need to address that in our code as well.
Have some sort of way of make the game repeatable.
And it's not just repeatable, actually, because we also have to move the previous B up to the A position
if they do get it right for the next round.
So I think Khloe Kardashian maybe has less.
Oh. So let's say, I guess Dwayne Johnson again in this case.
Now, if I get it right, Taylor Swift, who used to be at position B now gets moved to position A,
ready for the next round.
So this is another problem we have to tackle.
So not only does the game have to be repeatable, we also have to have some sort of way of making the
accounts at Position B become the next account at position A.
And finally, notice that in between the rounds, if I get it right or if I get it wrong, the whole
game actually clears the previous progress other than letting me know that I got it right and my current
score
and it displays everything afresh.
It doesn't clutter up the screen and I have to scroll down.
So that's probably the last problem we'll need to tackle.
So clear the screen.
That's it, I think for now. I've broken down this large problem, which is build this game, into a bunch
of smaller problems and as we code along, we're probably going to break them down even further.
This really was the key skill that I wanted to test you on, being able to take a big project, turn
it into smaller problems, and then tackle them one by one.
So if you manage to get this far and you've managed to identify all the problems that you need to solve,
you're ready should consider yourself successful.
Now, the next stage, we're going to try and tackle each of these one by one and be able to create
the final version of the game.
Let's get started. Now, the first thing is probably the easiest, so I'm going to start from there and
I'm actually going to go in the order that I've written the problems rather than picking them off from
the easiest.
I think this just makes it easier for you to understand what's going on when I'm writing the code.
But in your case, you can pick off the problems in whichever order you want as long as the final version
works as you expect it to. To display the art which is going to be the logo to begin with,
I'm going to have to import that art file. And I'm going to use the from art import logo.
This way, I don't have to write art.logo every time I want to use it. Now I can simply just write print
logo.
So that's the first one tackled.
That was pretty easy.
Some of them are going to be a lot harder than that.
The next one is to generate a random account from the game data.
And remember, the game data is here in a separate file and the data is held inside a variable called
data.
So let's go to the top and let's do the same thing. So from game_data import data. And now we can
use that data to generate a random account.
In order to generate a random item from that list, we have to use the random module,
so I'm going to import the random module. And I can use that random module to tap into the choice function
and pass in my data, which is a list.
So this function is going to take this list and then find a random entry in there which will give
me a random account.
Let's call this account maybe account A and set that equal to the output from this random choice function.
Now, I'm probably going to need more than one random account because I need to compare A against B.
By calling random choice on data
again, I make sure that I get a different random account.
So at this point, we've got account A and account B, which hopefully are different from each other.
But if you wanted to, you could in fact check and just make sure.
So if account A equals account B, then in this case you make sure that account B is regenerated.
Often, as you're coding along, tackling the problems, smaller problems arise and you start thinking
about what could happen and you start addressing that with code as well.
So I think we're now done with this second problem and we're ready to move on to the next one.
Let's format the account data so that we can print it out in this format.
So the account name and then A and then whatever it is that they do,
and finally from and where they're from.
So we know that the data of each of these accounts is basically a dictionary.
And we know that we access dictionaries using the key-value pair. So we could, for example, access
the account name
by tapping into the random account, let's say, account A, and then we use that square brackets and
then we put in the key in here, which let me just check, is the name.
So let's put that right here.
And this will go into that dictionary and pull out the value under the key name and save it to this
variable.
And we can do the same thing for the other two pieces of data we need.
And just make sure that you don't have any typos in your keys here, because remember, they need to
match these precisely in order for it to not error out.
Now that we've got all of these pieces of data, we can now print the final version. So we're probably
going to use an fstring to insert all of these pieces of information, and we'll probably start off
with the account_name and then a comma. We can write a and then put in the account_desc, and finally
put from and the account_country.
That's pretty much it.
But notice how I've done this just for account A and I actually have to do it for both Account A and
account B. So instead of repeating all of this code, it might be a lot easier if I actually pulled
this out into a separate function.
So let's create that here.
Let's create a function that does this.
I'm going to turn this into a docstring to explain the function, and I'm going to call the function
format_data and it's going to take an input which is the account.
And now using this account, we can make this more reusable by deleting the _a part of it.
And of course, we need to indent everything over so that it's actually within this function. And instead
of printing the final outcome, I'm going to return it as the output.
So now we can call that function down here and we can pass in each account in turn. For example, we
could say print "Compare A: " which is going to be first_account.
So we're going to use our fstring to insert the data that we get back from our function call.
And I'm going to call it within the print statement.
You can, of course, take it out and create a separate variable,
but I think this should be clear enough to see what's going on.
So we're going to call format_data and we're going to pass in the account A for this first line, and
then I'm going to do the same for B.
So in this case, I'm going to pass an account B and it's going to format the data and then print it
out.
So as I always say, it's a good idea to run your code frequently.
Probably any time you solve a problem, you should probably run it and see if it works the way you expect
it to.
So the first one, the logo gets printed. The second one, we've managed to get some random accounts
because every time I run it, the accounts should be different.
And finally, we format the account into this format with their name, their description and their country
all written out from the print statement using this lovely format_data function we've created.
We've already done really well
so let's keep going. Now,
at the moment it just says compare A, compare B. But instead, it'd be much nicer if we can put in that
art, the versus ASCII art in between the A and B.
Now you could write the line again from art import versus, but instead you could also just add a comma
here and write versus.
So now it's going to import both the logo and that versus art and we're going to put it right here.
So we're going to use a print statement.
And instead of using a string inside double quotes, we're just going to write the name of the variable
which is called versus.
And if we take a look at the final version, you can see it also says compare A against B, so we'll
change the second word to against.
And now when we run the code, it should look pretty much identical to the starting point of our final
game.
Let's tackle the next problem. We need to ask the user for a guess to see who has more followers, right?
So I'm actually just going to copy this string right here and I'm going to put that into an input.
So who has more followers, A or B, and this input is going to come back as a string and I'm going
to save it inside a new variable called guess. Now because it asks them for A or B, they might type
A like this 'a' or they might type A like this 'A.'
Ideally, we should make it so that it doesn't matter what they typed.
It'll still be valid as long as they typed an A. So we can turn this all into a lowercase format.
So if they typed it capital like this, it'll become lower. If they typed it lowercase then it's already
lower and it will be fine as well.
So that way it's more consistent.
So now our final product actually looks pretty much exactly identical, but it doesn't really have much
gaming functionality yet.
To do that, we have to move on to the next problem and check if the user got it right. In order to check
if they got it right,
the first thing we'll need is to know how many followers they each have,
right?
Each of the accounts, A and B. Let's get a a_follower_count
and that is going to be using the account_a and then pulling out the data under the key follower_
count. So I'm actually just going to copy it to make sure I definitely don't make a typo and I'm going
to tap into account_a and then pass in that key follower_count remember as a string because our
key is a string.
So when we use it also has to be a string inside double quotes.
And I'm going to do the same for the b_follower_count from account_b.
Now I've tackled that mini-step inside the problem.
The next step is use an if statement to check if the user is correct.
Now, again, I think this piece of functionality would be really nice if it was reusable.
So I'm actually going to pull out of this main sort of flow of the game and define a separate function
at the top.
And this function is going to be called check_answer and it's going to get the guess,
the a_followers
and the b_followers.
And I'm going to add some docstrings.
So the docstrings are really important, especially when your function returns something. For example,
in this case, it should actually say takes the account data and returns the printable format.
That makes it so much clearer what this function actually does,
what are its inputs and what are its outputs. In our check answer
then it's going to take the user's guess and the follower counts of A and B and then returns if they
got it right.
So how might we write this?
Because the logic is actually a little bit difficult.
We need to check which account has more followers and then we need to check if the user actually got
it right.
So it's almost a two step process.
And I think in these cases it's actually really worth sort of sketching it out.
You can use a pen and a piece of paper.
I'm just using Skitch right here so I can show it to you more easily.
So let's just construct a simple sort of two by two matrix.
And at the top, we've got the-- let's say the user guess is A and an alternative is they guess B.
Now, these are the user's guesses, but then it's going to be compared against the actual reality or
the answer, which is that A has more followers than B, and the alternative is that B has more followers
than A. If the user guessed A and A indeed has more followers than B, then they got it right.
And similarly, if they guess B and B did indeed have more followers than A, then they would have
also gotten it right.
But if it was the opposite case, as in they guessed A but actually B had more followers, then they would
be wrong.
And also if they guessed B and A has more followers, then they would be wrong as well.
Now, using this table, we can now construct our if statement.
There is a very, very long version of it, and there is a much shorter version of it. So the very
long version would check for something like if the a_followers is greater than the b_followers,
so A has more followers than B, and the guess is equal to A.
Now you can go through this kind of way and create four of these if and elif, else statements.
But it's very easy to get lost in some of the logic.
And also it means you have to type a lot of this out instead of using the else as the alternative.
So I think a much easier way would be to first check if A has more followers than B, and in this case
you can then check
well, if the guess is equal to A, well then that means they got it right
so I should return
true. But if this was not right, then I should return false.
An alternative and a much easier way of expressing this is to simply return
guess == a because when this is evaluated, is guess equal to a, then it's going to return
true. But if guess is not A, if it's B, then it's going to return false.
So that's a little bit mind bending,
but if you actually go through it enough times, especially using a debugger like Python Tutor to
just see how it works, then it should become pretty clear pretty quickly.
In my case, all I need to do to express my table of possibilities is to first check if A is greater
than B. Now else, namely, if the opposite was true, B was greater than A, then I'm going to return
if guess is equal to B.
So now basically the code says if A has more followers and they guessed A then return
true. If B has more followers and they guessed B then return true.
And if the opposite happens, then return false.
Basically, it's going to return whether if the user got the answer right.
Now, we can basically check that in here and we could create a new variable could is_correct
and set that to equal the output of our check_answer function.
So we're going to call it and pass in all the necessary things, the guess, the followers from A and
B. So guess and then the a_follower count and the b_follower count.
Now, once we know whether if they got it right or not, we can tackle the next step, which is give
user some feedback on their guesses. So we can check,
well, if is_correct--
well, in this case, we should probably print something like "You're right."
But if they didn't get it right, then we're going to print sorry, that's wrong.
Now, in addition to giving them feedback, we should probably also keep track of the score. So we can
start off our game with a score of zero.
But as they play on and if they get it correct, then the score should be incremented by one each time.
And in addition to printing out, "You're right,"
we should also give them some feedback on the current score.
And if sorry they got it wrong, then we should also give them the final score,
because at this point the game is going to end and they should know how well they did.
So now let's go ahead and play our game and see if it works.
So compare Cardi B against Kourtney Kardashian.
I think it's probably going to be B, and it tells me you're right and current score happens to be inside
curly braces.
So there's going to be a lot of debugging that you're going to need to do while you're writing this
code,
and you're probably going to make a lot of mistakes.
But everybody does them, including me.
If we get it right, we get the feedback, you're right and the current score. If we get it wrong,
then we get the answer
Sorry, that's wrong.
And the final score as well.
That's all working so far.
Now we have to figure out some sort of way of making the game repeatable. And, as you might remember,
that's usually going to require some sort of while loop.
But it's important to think about which parts of our game actually repeat themselves,
right? Because when we play the game, it looks like everything's kind of static.
But if we think about it, the score is set to zero probably can't be repeated, but the accounts
probably do need to be generated and they do need to be randomized again.
And then we need to ask the user again, compare A against B and then ask them for an input and then check
the answer.
So all the rest of this probably needs to be repeated.
So I would say everything from here probably should be within our while loop.
So what is our while loop going to check?
Well, maybe we could create a flag like game_should_continue and start out as true.
And then while that's still true, then we'll repeat all of this code below.
So let's indent that into the while loop. Now, at which point should this become false?
Well, they get to keep going as long as they get the answer right,
but the game ends as soon as they get it wrong.
This is the point where we're going to change
game_should_continue to false so that once it prints "Sorry,
that's wrong."
It's going to end the game.
Now let's try and run the game and see if we can get our loop to repeat itself.
I'm going to choose A, and you can see you're right, current score is one. And now it's telling me to compare
A which is a new random person against B, a new random person.
As long as I get it right, it will allow me to keep playing the game. But as soon as I get it wrong,
so I'm pretty sure that National Geographic sadly doesn't have as many followers as Kim Kardashian.
So I think this is going to get me to exit the game.
Sorry, that's wrong.
Your final score is three, and as you can see, my game has now ended.
But notice how in the final version of the game, the count at position B actually becomes the one at
position A in the next round.
So the game kind of continues like this.
And then once I guess this, Kim Kardashian is now going to become the one at position A and it keeps
on going as long as I got it right.
So we now need to code this functionality into our program.
At the very beginning,
we generate a random account A and a random account B. But instead, what we want to happen is we want
to make sure that the account at position B becomes the next account at position A.
So once this game has run its course and we're looping back to the beginning again, the account A
should become the previous version of account B. But this obviously will give us an error because there
is no previous account B. So what we could do is we could actually take this out of the loop and say
account B is equal to a random choice of data and account A becomes that account B. But then the actual
account B is going to be a new random account.
Let's play this through in our heads as a computer.
The first thing that happens when the game starts for the very first time is we generate a random account
B. Now that account becomes the account A and then account B becomes a new random account.
Now when the game loops back, it's not going to touch these parts of the code.
It's going to start from here.
So now the account A is going to be replaced by the previous account B, and this new account B is going
to be a new random account.
But what if the new random account is still the same account?
How can we get the code to continue checking until it has found a different account?
Well, we could replace the if statement with a while loop, then the code will keep checking until
they are no longer equal.
And this way, when we run our code, you can see that as long as I get the answer correct,
then the previous B becomes the new A and B now becomes a new random account.
That's pretty much all of the functionality sorted, right? But we've got a couple of things to tidy
up.
One is we need to clear the screen in between the rounds of our game so we know that we can import the
clear function from the replit module.
But here's a question, where do you call it? Because if you call it at the very beginning of the loop,
like here, then what's going to happen is that your logo is never going to be displayed.
And also, when you actually get the answer correct, like we will here,
the result isn't shown because the result is shown at the very end of this while loop. And once that's
done, it's going to loop right the way back here and it's going to clear everything in the console.
And that's all going to happen in a fraction of a second.
So the user won't actually see it.
So we need to move this clear function.
The ideal time, I think, to actually show it is just before they're about to see the outcome of their
action.
So somewhere here.
So now, once we've asked the user what we need to ask and we've got their answer, we clear the screen
and then we show them the outcome.
Now we get to see the logo,
we get to see all the versus and A and B, let's select B and we got it right.
So we get to see that feedback as well.
It clears the screen and we have a new comparison to make.
Now, the only thing you'll notice is that the logo disappears in each successive round.
It might be nice to see it even if we're going to the next round.
So to do that, we have to print the logo just after we clear the screen right here.
So now, even though we've cleared the screen, we still get to see the logo again as long as we get
the answer correct.
That's all there is to it.
We've now completed all of the functionality that's in the final version of the game, and it took quite
a bit of code at the end.
But as long as you broke it down into these smaller components, each of the components and each of
the problems are much, much easier to tackle.
I hope you enjoyed building this game and you have fun playing with it.
I hope you enjoyed building this game.
And I'll see you on the next lesson.
Hey, welcome back to 100 Days of Code.
This is Angela from the App Brewery, and today is day 15 where we're going to set up our local development
environment for Python and we're going to be building a Coffee Machine project.
So when we designed the course,
we really wanted you to get up and running as fast as possible and start coding straight away.
But as our project gets more and more complex, then it's really important to start thinking about setting
up a proper development environment.
Now, if you were a chef, then you need really sharp knives. And as a programmer, you need a good development
environment.
In today's lesson, I'm going to show you how to set up my favorite IDE,
and the IDE stands for Integrated Development Environment.
This is a piece of software that will help you as you're creating your code,
and it's going to do a whole bunch of things for you including things like linting your code, finding
errors in it, giving you guidance on your coding style, helping you debug issues, just making life
easier for you as you start writing more and more code.
This is the moment where you're graduating from a newbie developer.
It's like as if you've gone into the mountains, you've fetched water for this old sensei for like 20
years and finally he's going to show you how to use a sword.
This is going to be the equivalent of our sword.
Now, in terms of development environment, there's actually a whole bunch to choose from.
And you might have heard of some of these like Jupiter or Spider,
VS
Code and some of them we've already used like Thonny.
But the one that we're going to use is something called PyCharm.
And this is an Intelligent Development Environment, an IDE, that is specialized for Python.
The tool has been sharpened especially for python coding, and it's what the professionals use. In
the coming lessons,
we're going to get really familiar with this tool.
And gradually, I want to show you how it can help you become a better and more productive developer.
But before we can get started installing PyCharm, we first have to get the latest version of Python
installed on your computer.
In the course resources, you can go ahead and find the download link for Python. Then once you're
there, it should automatically detect your current operating system.
So here I am on Windows and it says download the latest version for Windows. And then if you click on
the big download button, it'll ensure that you get the latest version of Python.
Now, it's actually a very small file, so it shouldn't take very long to download.
And once it's complete, go ahead and open up that .exe file.
Now, go ahead and make sure that the checkbox for Add Python 3.8 to Path is checked and
then leave everything else as it is
and click on Install now. And make sure that you have admin privileges while you're installing
so you have to be logged on as the administrator. And say yes to any of the prompts.
Now, installation should only take a few minutes. And once it's done, you might get a hint here saying
"Disable path length limit."
If you see that, then go ahead and click on it.
And again, say yes for allow. And then you're done and you can close off the wizard. If you're on a Mac,
the process is virtually identical.
Once you head over to the link from the course resources, you should see it automatically, let's you download
the latest version for Mac.
And once the download is complete, you can go through the wizard clicking
continue agreeing to everything that they ask you to agree and click install.
And again, you'll need to be on the administrator account and type in your password to allow Python
to be installed on your computer. Once installation is completed, it should open up this folder and
you should see Python 3.8 or a later version like 3.9 or 3.10.
But as long as you see this, then you've been successful and you can delete the installer from your
computer.
So now you should have successfully installed Python onto your computer, and we're ready to proceed to
the next step. Head over to the next lesson
and we're going to download and install PyCharm.
So you should have now successfully installed Python onto your computer,
and we're ready to proceed to the next step,
which is to download PyCharm. Again, in the course resources,
you'll find a link to the home page to download PyCharm.
And once you get to this page,
you should click on the download button and this takes you to the options page.
Now, here, it should automatically select your system.
So currently I'm on a Windows computer,
and it's automatically selected the Windows tab.
And you can click on the system requirements to make sure that your computer is
compatible. And you can also take a look at the installation instructions,
which is pretty simple. It's basically download and run.
So there's two versions of PyCharm;
the professional and the community version.
You're going to select the community version because it's completely free and
open source to use.
The professional version has a free trial and after that you'll have to pay for
it, but the community version already has all of the features that we need
and more. Once you click on download, that will take a little while,
anywhere between 5 to 10 minutes. So while you're waiting for that to run,
you can head over to the next lesson
and I'll talk about some of the features of PyCharm that we can look forward
to. Now, if you are on a Mac, the process is pretty much the same.
So head over to the link that's in the course resources,
click on download and download the community version of PyCharm.
Now, if you're a Linux user, you can also toggle to the Linux tab.
And while your here,
you can look at the system requirements and the installation instructions.
Once you are ready, go ahead and click on the download button for the community
edition, which is free and open-source, and then download will begin.
And again, it'll take anywhere between 5 to 10 minutes.
So let it download and head over to the next lesson where I want to show you
some of the great features of PyCharm.
Up until now we've been using Repl.it as our code editor and Repl.it has a
number of great features like how easy it is to share code and to fork copies of
the same code so that you can always get the starting code and the final code.
But Repl.it does have its limitations.
And as you're becoming more and more advanced and you start building more
complex projects, you'll start to feel the constraints of a simple text editor
like Repl.it. Now PyCharm is a tool that's used by professionals.
And I want to show you a couple of features so that you can see firsthand why
PyCharm is so popular with Python developers.
And the first thing I really like about it is also a very, very basic thing,
it's spellcheck for the English words that you use in your code.
This just means that while you're writing code,
you are creating names for your variables, creating your keys, your values,
or your print statements, that it makes sure that the English that you write,
the parts that's not actually code, is actually spell-checked
and you won't believe how many times this will save your skin.
Here's an example, something that's really,
really sensitive to spelling is a dictionary.
We all know that when we're using a dictionary and let's say we wanted to print
one of the values from our dictionary. We're taking our contacts and getting hold
of James's details, and then we're trying to get hold of his phone number.
Now, if you type this wrong, for example,
if I wrote phone number without an 'e', and I try to run this,
then you'll see, I get an error.
But the spell check should already alert you to the issue before you even hit
run. See how this is underlined with a squiggle
and it tells you that there's a typo in the word phon,
and you can click change to phone maybe.
And it's just a subtle hint to say, 'Hey,
I think maybe you got that wrong. Just DoubleCheck.' And indeed,
once we fix that,
then we get rid of all our issues and everything works perfectly.
The next feature that I really like is having more space to develop.
What do I mean by this? Well,
very often we actually tend to have more than one code file, right?
For example,
let's say that we moved our contacts into this data file and we imported it
instead.
So it will say from data import contacts.
And now when I want to code things up and I want to get hold of certain things,
for example I want to get Jenny's email,
then ideally I would want to see this side by side,
right? In PyCharm
all you have to do to split the screen is just right
click on the file and then say split and move right.
And now all of a sudden you can see both sides at once.
This means it so much easier to refer to some other piece of code when you're
developing.
So here I can now easily see that the key for Jenny has a capital J,
so I have to tap into my contacts,
tap into the key Jenny and then get hold of her email.
This split-screen comes in really handy as your code gets more complex and
there's more and more files.
And now another advanced feature of an IDE compared to a simple text editor like
Repl.it is a built-in linter.
So what is a linter? Well, a linter in real life, is something that picks off a
little bits of dust,
bits of lint from your clothing, and in Programming it's something that picks out
bits of code that you've written that might not be in accordance to the style
guide. When we're writing code and we're trying to decide, well,
how many spaces do I leave between things, do I use tabs or spaces,
what is the maximum line length,
all of these sort of things that maybe won't break your program per se,
but it will mean that your program might look different from somebody else's
and you just want to know what is the convention so that you can keep your code
consistent with other Python developers. Well,
this is what a style guide is for.
And the style guide that most Python developers will abide by is something
called PEP 8.
And we've already seen this when we were talking about tabs versus spaces.
For example,
the guidance is that an indentation should have four spaces, and indeed it should
be spaces over tabs.
And then there are other things like what's the maximum line length
so that your lines of code don't become really,
really long and difficult to read, or things like how many blank lines should
there between functions and variables in your code and all sorts of things.
This is a very long document and it's actually very difficult to read all of it
and remember all of it while you're in the middle of coding.
But luckily for us, if we're using PyCharm,
it automatically applies those rules and guidance to our code
and lints our code. For example,
if I was to create a function called my_function,
and inside here
I've just got two inputs, n1 and n2,
and then it calculates the total by adding n1 to n2,
and it returns the total as an output. Now,
at a later point, I decide to call my function, passing in some numbers,
maybe say 4 and 5. Now firstly,
notice how I've got some light yellow squiggly lines under both of these lines.
And when I hover over it, so I don't have to click on it.
I just keep my cursor on top of the line which has the squiggles,
you can see
it tells me that PEP 8 guidance specifies that there should be two blank lines
after a class or function definition,
but instead it only found one.
So basically what it's trying to say is that the style guide says that there
should be two lines after and before each of your functions so that everything
is more spaced out and easier to read. And here, when I hover over it,
you can see it says there's missing white space after the comma.
So the style guide says that every time you use a comma in your code,
you should always have a space. This way again
it's easier to read and it keeps your code consistent with other Python
developers so that when people look at your code,
they can see that you're following the standard conventions.
But remember that this does not affect how your code runs.
Even with all of these suggestions and these style guide rule breaks,
it doesn't actually mean my code won't work. If I run it,
you can see that it works perfectly without any errors.
And it's only a matter of keeping your code tidy and keeping it in line with the
conventions that Python developers have set out. Now,
another advanced feature of an IDE compared to a text editor is the ability to
view your local history.
What that means is I can go to show history
and just as if you were in a browser, you can see your browsing history,
well here you can see all of your coding history.
So you can scroll back all the way in the last 12 hours and see the edits that
you've made. For example, at thirteen past four today,
I created this brand new function. So this is the current file
and this is what it looked like at that moment in time.
Now scrolling forward into the future,
the next thing I did was I added a new function call here and I added some space
here.
So if you've had some sort of catastrophic events and you realize that you've
really messed up, you've deleted everything,
you can always scroll back to previous time points and simply just copy and
paste the code.
Or you can revert back to that particular time point.
Can you imagine if you are writing your essay and the number of times I have
lost my essay because my computer is crashed.
Imagine if you had this ability to just scroll back in time and find one
snapshot that you liked and then revert everything back to that moment in time,
how powerful could that be? Well,
you now have that in your hands with local history in PyCharm.
Now another really handy feature is the ability to view the structure of your
code. Instead of going to the project navigation,
if I click on this structure pane here
you can see that it breaks down my code into all of the variables and all of the
functions. That means that my function could be declared, you know,
many hundreds of lines somewhere else,
and I'm scrolling around and I'm trying to find it.
All I have to do is look at well, here's my function,
and if I click on it
it takes me straight there and I can now edit it if I wish.
And if I needed the variable jenny_email, well
it takes me straight there as well.
Once you start having lots and lots of variables and lots of lots of functions,
this is a lifesaver.
Now there's a lot of other features that I'm going to show you that PyCharm
can do, but I want to do it gradually. For now
here's the last tip on PyCharm.
Whenever you create a variable or a function name and you end up using it in
lots of places, so for example
you might call my_function here and then you might call my_function again
passing in some different parameters at some later point in time.
And then you decide that actually,
I really don't like the way that I've named that function.
It would make so much more sense if it was called add instead because it returns
the total right? If I was to do this manually in a code editor,
I would have to go add,
and then all of these lines will break and I have to find all of them and then
change them manually. And that's very painful.
So instead, what you can do in PyCharm is you can
right-click on the name of your function or your variable, go to refactor -> rename.
And now it will find all of the places where this function is created,
where it's called, and you can now change it everywhere.
So click refactor,
and it's now found the function that needs to be renamed and also all the places
where it's used. So it's used in two places, here
on line 11 and here on line 14.
So now I click do refactor and what'll happen is it'll change all the places where
it occurs. And it's much,
much safer than say just using find and replace.
Let's say that I had a print statement here that said, um,
my_function is a function.
And if I used find and replace where I just say, well,
my_function now equals add and I click on replace all,
it's going to now change it in all the places. But on the other hand,
if I use refactor -> rename,
then it's going to be intelligent enough to know that this print statement is
just
text whereas the places
where my function is used and the places where my function is declared,
that is what I want to refactor and rename.
And it leaves all of the innocent bystanders alone.
There's a lot of really exciting things yet to come as we start getting used to
using PyCharm. But as with any new tool,
you'll spend a little bit of time getting up and running with it and getting
used to using it. Now, when I was in primary school,
I still remember the moment when I got to graduate from writing with pencils
to writing with a Berol handwriting pen.
And it was a really significant moment in my life when I was allowed to write
with the adult tools. So this is kind of what's happening right here.
We're graduating to PyCharm.
It's going to take a little bit of getting used to and learning our ropes,
but it's going to take us closer to our goals.
Hopefully by now, PyCharm should have now downloaded and you're ready to head
over to the next lesson where we're going to install it.
Now that you've downloaded PyCharm,
we're ready to go ahead and install it onto your computer. Now this video,
I'm going to go through all the steps for installing and setting up PyCharm on
Windows. If you're on a Mac system,
then go ahead and skip this lesson and you'll find the walkthrough on the next
lesson. Once you download has completed,
go ahead and click on the exe file
if you're running on Windows. And then you're just going to go ahead and follow
the wizard. And if you want to have an icon on your desktop, check the checkbox
to add the launcher, and then go ahead and click next.
Now leave everything as the default and click install. Installation should only
take a couple of minutes. And once it's done,
you can go ahead and click finish.
Now, you can double click on the icon to open up the program and the first time
you do so you'll need to agree to the privacy policy and choose whether if you
want to share data with them. Now you get to pick your UI style,
either dark mode or light mode,
and then you can skip all the rest of the setup.
Now to test it out, go ahead and create a new project and name it
whatever you want. But the really important thing is to click the Project
Interpreter drop-down and under base interpreter that you select the latest
version of Python that you just installed,
which in my case is Python 38, which stands for 3.8.
It will take a few moments before your project gets set up.
And once it does, you might see
a little popup that says something about Windows Defender.
If you see this,
then go ahead and click fix and click configure automatically.
If you don't see this pop up, then don't worry about it.
Now you can go ahead and right-click on your project folder and select new,
and then new file. Now we're going to create a new file,
which is going to be called main.py. And in this file,
we're going to test it out just by writing a hello world that will get printed
to the console. And once you're done,
then go ahead and click on Run and then select the main.py file to run.
And the console should now popup and you should see hello world printed.
That's it.
You're ready to start working with PyCharm and you should be able to use it in
the same way that you used Repl.it.
In this video,
I'm going to walk through the process to install PyCharm on Mac. Now,
if you're on a Windows computer and you've already installed PyCharm,
then you can skip this video.
So you should have now downloaded the PyCharm installer.
So go ahead and open up the DMG file. Now,
when you see this window, drag the icon for PyCharm into the applications
folder. And now you can go to spotlight and search for PyCharm.
Then go ahead and click on it to open it up. Now,
make sure that you have admin privileges and go ahead and say open. And then
agree to the privacy policy and decide if you want to share data with them or
not. Now you can select never used
PyCharm and click next.
Then you can pick between dark theme or light theme and click next.
And then go ahead and click on skip remaining and set defaults.
Now we can go ahead and create our first project in PyCharm.
Name your project whatever you want,
but it's really important that you click on this drop-down to check that your
project interpreter, and especially the base interpreter, is set to the latest
version of Python that you installed, which in my case is Python 3.8.
Now, if you're running on a Mac or a Linux,
you might see several versions of Python in that dropdown list.
So make sure that you select the latest version that you installed and then
click next. Once it has configured and created your new project,
this is what you should see.
And now you're going to go into your project folder, right-click on it,
and then go to new -> file. Now on a Mac, right
click is also the same as control clicking.
So you could hold down the control key and then click on the project folder.
And again, choose new, and then file.
And the file we're going to create is going to be our main.py. Now,
inside here, all that we're going to do is just print hello world.
And we're going to run this code and make sure that it works.
So go to run and then click on this run button and select the main Python file
as the one you want to run and then down here, you should see the run tab
pop up all of a sudden,
and you should see your hello world printed in the console.
And then it'll say process finished with exit code zero,
zero is a success,
and that means you're now all set up and you're ready to start using PyCharm
as if it were any other Python editor.
So anything that you've done in Repl.it you can now do in PyCharm.
You can create new files, you can write the files and you can run those files.
Now you should have PyCharm up and running,
and we're finally ready to tackle today's project,
which we're going to write in PyCharm. You've just been hired.
Congratulations, but first there's the matter of coffee.
We all know that programmers can't work unless they're loaded up on coffee.
So your company has asked you to create the code for a coffee machine.
Now you, very cleverly, go online and look at the other coffee machines.
And you notice that it only costs $230 to buy a coffee machine,
but you're not going to cheat. You're going to create everything from scratch.
And luckily we don't actually have to build the hardware because we're programmers,
right?
But we're going to use this real-life coffee machine as the inspiration for our
virtual coffee machine, noting the features and the capabilities.
So what does it say? I found some wonderful graphics on here
which tells me that they're three hot flavors
which I'm guessing are these three buttons, it's coins operate
which I think they mean it's coin operated, and there's not much else that it can
do.
Let's take this example and we're going to make a digital version of it.
We're going to create our own coffee machine.
And the first step we need to replicate is the ability to make three hot
flavors. So the flavors we're going to make are 1. espresso,
2. latte, and 3. cappuccino. Here
are the recipes for these three types of drinks.
Each of them requires a different quantity of water,
a different quantity of coffee and a different quantity of milk.
And they also each half a different price.
We're going to be modeling all this data in our coffee machine program as well.
But luckily for you in the starting code,
I've already included all of this data inside a dictionary.
So you don't have to remember this,
although it might help if you're at home and you decided that you really wanted
a latte instead of your usual black coffee. Now, in addition,
the coffee machine has some resources that it has to manage.
So it starts out with 300ml of water in the tank,
200ml of milk and 100 grams of coffee.
The second feature of our coffee machine is that it's coin operated.
So we're going to be using American coins and they have four types of coins:
the penny, the nickel, the dime, and the quarter.
They used to also have the dollar as a coin
but a few years ago they stopped minting that. So we're not going to count it
and it probably means one less if statement for us.
Notice what each of these coins are worth. The penny is worth a cent,
the nickel worth 5 cents and the dime 10 cents,
and the quarter is a quarter of a dollar.
These represented in decimal values would look something like this.
Now here's the important part. Let's think about what our program requirements are
if we break it down one.
1. We need our coffee machine to be able to print a report.
It needs to be able to tell us what resources it has left,
how much water has left, how much milk, et cetera.
If you head over to the completed version of the coffee machine,
the link is in the course resources,
and you can go ahead and try out the final version of the coffee machine.
So let's say that we wanted a report on all the resources that the machine has.
All we have to do is type report, and we can see all the resources we have.
Now, in addition to being able to print a report,
we also want to be able to check that the resources are sufficient when the user
orders a drink. Now let's say that the user decided to order a latte.
It asks me to insert some coins and then it gives me the change and it gives me
the latte. But now if I check the report,
I can see that I've only got a hundred mils of water left.
And I know from the previous slide that a latte and a cappuccino is going to
need more than that amount of water. So let's see what happens
if I go ahead and order a cappuccino. It says, sorry,
there's not enough water.
So our program is able to look through all the resources that the machine has,
checks it against the recipe of the drink that we're trying to make, and tells the
user if there is insufficient water or if there's insufficient milk,
and as long as one of the resources is insufficient,
then it can't make the drink and it gives the feedback to the user. Now,
as you saw before,
our program also needs to be able to process coins because our machine is coin
operated.
So no fancy contactless payments or pay with your Apple watch, none of that.
We've only got coins. When we order something,
it should ask us to insert coins.
And it's going to ask for the quantity of each type of coin.
So let's say that I insert one of each, then in this case,
there's actually not enough money to cover my drink and it refunds the money and
doesn't give me a drink. But on the other hand, if I do insert enough money,
then it should be able to calculate how much money all of these coins are worth
and then calculate the amount of change based on the cost of my drink.
And then it should hand me my drink and tell me to enjoy. So,
in addition to being able to process the four types of coins,
calculating the actual monetary value based on the number of points,
it should also check that the transaction is successful.
That the user didn't try to hoodwink us by not giving enough coins and asking
for a drink. So if they haven't inserted enough coins,
then we're just going to refund them and tell them, sorry
that's not enough money, and not give them their drink.
But if the transaction was successful,
then we're going to make the coffee. And in the process of making the coffee,
we're going to have to deduct the resources.
Notice how every time we make a drink,
say in this time we made a latte and previous to the latte,
we have 300 mills of milk. But after the latte,
when we asked for the report, you can see that the water has been reduced,
the milk has been reduced,
the coffee has been reduced and the money has been put into the coffer.
This program, even though it seems simple,
just a simple digital version of a coffee machine,
it actually has quite a few requirements.
So I recommend that you look at the screen and try to see how each of the
requirements work by having a play around with the final version of the code. Now
I've created a detailed program specification for you as a PDF file
which you can download in the course resources.
And this goes into a lot more details on each of those points. For example,
what should the prompt print in the beginning of the program,
and then how to turn the machine off,
how to print the reports and how each of those points should work in detail.
Go ahead and download this and make sure you read each of the sections and test
it out in the final working version of the project.
Once you're ready,
you can go ahead and head over to the starting version of the code. And again,
I'm sharing this using Repl.it,
but I want you to copy everything that's in here,
there's only one file the main.py file,
and I want you to create a new project using PyCharm and call it coffee
machine,
Right?
And then create a new file inside your project called main.py,
and then paste all of the starting code into your main.py.
And now you are going to code inside this file. And once you're ready,
you're going to click run and you'll be able to run this main.py down here
and this will act as your console. Now,
one really handy feature of
PyCharm is something called to-do tracking.
Whereas previously in Repl.it I've been creating to-dos and you've been able to
view them. But if I have lots of to-dos in different places,
you can't actually see all of them at once.
You have to scroll through the file looking for them.
But in a professional tool,
we actually have something called to-do tracking and its a tab that's down here.
So if I go ahead and take some of these program requirements,
I can put them in as to-dos. To create a
to-do you have to follow the syntax. First is a pound sign
and then we write TODO in all caps, and notice how that's just changed color just
now, and now you can see in the todo tab,
it's found one todo item.
Now we can write todo number one
and this is to print a report of all the coffee machine resources.
Now let's say that I created a todo somewhere else, right?
Like all the way up here,
check that the resources are sufficient to make the drink order. And notice how
they're completely in different places in a different order.
But every time I create one of these todos using this format,
it will get picked up in the
todo tab. And you can go ahead and see where they live.
So it's found two items inside our main.py
and you can see that this one is todo one, this one is todo two.
And when you click on them,
they'll take you to the correct places in your code.
Use this to break down the problem into smaller problems that you can solve one
by one,
just as you've done before and try to see if you can complete this project.
Just the word of warning: this project is quite ambitious.
But you've now got professional tools to help you,
and you've got a lot more skill under your belt.
So give this problem at least an hour to work on it and make sure that you
satisfy all the criteria that's set out in the program requirements
and also that your program works exactly the same as the final version of the
coffee machine.
Now,
there are so many possible solutions to create this coffee machine program
satisfying all the requirements. And the way that you code it up is essentially
your choice, right?
Whether if you decide to use a while loop or use a for loop or create a
different data structure, there are endless possibilities.
What I'm going to show you now is just one of those possibilities.
And what's really important is you don't feel like you've done it wrong
just because it's different to mine. As long as it works
the way that you expect it to, then consider yourself successful.
The first thing I'm going to do is create a new project in PyCharm,
and I'm going to call my project coffee machine. Again,
making sure that I've got the latest version of Python as the interpreter I'll
click
create.
Now that the first thing I'm going to do here is right-click on this and create
a new file, which is going to be my main.py.
And then I'm going to go to my starting project in Repl.it and I'm just going to
copy everything there is over here and paste it into this main.py.
Now you might find the font of your code or of PyCharm a little bit too big or
too small. If that's the case,
you can just go into preferences and change the appearance and the font to a
different size. And this is for the user interface.
And if you want to change the font of the editor, then you can go here,
go to font and then change that size here.
I've tried to make it as large as possible so that when you were looking at this
video on an iPad or an iPhone, all the code still be readable.
But of course, normally when you're coding,
you'd probably want to fit more lines into the same screen,
but it's not good to strain your eyes. So try to strike a balance there.
Now I'm going to collapse that sidebar because I'm going to be coding entirely
in this one file.
Now notice that the beginning we get given a menu,
and this is a dictionary which contains three entries.
And each of those entries have a name of a drink,
espresso, latte and cappuccino.
And then each of them have a value that holds a bunch of data,
including the ingredients that are required to make that drink
and also the price of the drink. Now there's also a resources dictionary,
which holds the resources of the coffee machine.
Now that we've got all of that, then we're ready to go.
I'm going to tackle these requirements one by one.
And the first one says to prompt the user by asking,
what would you like? Espresso, latte or cappuccino.
So I'm actually gonna just straight up copy this line and put that into an
input. This is going to be saved into some sort of variable,
which I'll name choice.
Now it tells me that the prompt should show every time action has completed.
For example,
once the drink is dispensed and it should show again and again and again.
So that means we probably going to have to embed this input in some sort of while
loop. So I'm just gonna say for now while something is true,
then keep asking for this prompt. Right now
if we decide to go and run this code where we go to run and then click on this
button and then select the main.py to run,
then you can see that it asks me what would you like? And if I've put an input,
it'll keep asking me until eternity, basically,
because that there's currently no way of turning that true into a false.
So let's take a look at the next requirement.
We should be able to turn off the coffee machine by entering off into the prompt.
For maintainers of the coffee machine,
they can use off as the secret word to turn off the machine and your code should
end execution when this happens. So when somebody wants to buy coffee,
this is the line that they see. But when a maintenance guy comes along,
then they should be able to enter something.
And if this choice happens to equal the secret code,
which is off, then in this case we should stop the while loop and exit.
So that gives us a way of changing this true into some other form of variable,
right? So we could create a new variable code is_on,
start it off as true and while the machine is on,
then it should continue to loop through and ask the user for their choice.
But if the choice happens to be off, then we're going to turn
that is_on into false. Now,
if we run our code again,
so now that you've run it once you can either stop it or you can rerun it,
and now it's going to stop your existing code and rerun the code.
So if you don't want to see this dialogue every time,
then just check this box and then click stop and rerun.
So now if we make a selection or we say something basically anything other than
the key word, which is off,
it's going to loop back and forth and keep prompting us.
But if I say off, then the machine turns off and you can see that I've now exited
the program. Now we've tackled 1 and 2.
Let's go on to number 3. When the user enters the keyword report to
the prompt, another secret word, a report
should be generated that shows the current resource values. For example,
water, milk, coffee, and money. So how can we do that? Well, firstly,
we don't actually have a variable that holds the amount of money.
So let's create something,
let's call it profit maybe and set it to equal zero to begin with.
Our machine has an empty money box in the beginning.
So now we have to check to see, well, elif
the choice was equal to report. Well, in this case,
we have to generate a report and the report is basically going to print all the
values of these resources.
So I'm simply going to copy the expected output and I'm going to paste it here.
And then we can try and turn that into print statements,
making it a dynamic instead of hard-coded. In my case,
I want to add print in front of all of these lines.
And previously we've been doing this just by writing it one by one,
and then maybe we could copy and paste it.
But let me show you a quick tip that you can do in PyCharm. If you're on Windows,
hold down the alt and the shift key on your keyboard. If you are on a Mac,
hold down the option and the shift key.
Now click at the beginning and hold and drag down.
So if that doesn't work, try out a few times,
you'll get the hang of it eventually. But notice how I've now got four cursors
and that means when I write print, check this out.
Isn't that cool?
I've managed to write on four lines at once because I need that repeat
functionality and this is a way of doing multiline editing.
Remember that shortcut and use it in the future if you find it useful.
So I'm actually going to change this all into fstrings because I want to change
these numbers instead of being hard-coded,
I want to insert them into here using the curly braces.
The water is stored under resources,
and then it's in the key called water.
And now notice how I've got a outer double quote,
so I can't have an inner double quote.
So I'm going to change this into single quotes instead,
like, so. And I'm going to do the same for milk and coffee.
So now I've added the water, milk, and coffee into my print statement.
All I have left is the money.
So let's delete the value and let's insert that profit into here.
Now let's run our code again and let's check it out.
If I type report it should now give me a report of all the current values and
money is equal to $0 because that's what we start off with.
We're now ready to tackle number 4. Here
we have to check that when the user chooses a drink, we're going to check
if there are enough resources to make that particular drink they chose.
For example, if a latte requires 200 ml of water
but there's only 100ml left in the machine,
it should not make the drink because it actually can't make the drink
and it's going to print out, 'Sorry, there's not enough water' or not enough milk,
not enough coffee, whatever it may be.
So let's tackle this particular checkpoint.
Now that I've got the if choices equal off, if choice equals report.
Now, if it's not either of those,
then they're probably going to be entering the name of a drink.
So let's catch that using an else statement.
And then inside this else statement
I'm going to get hold of the particular drink that they ordered by tapping into
our menu dictionary and then using that choice they typed in as the key.
Let's say that the particular drink that they chose is equal to menu
and then the key is of course going to be the choice.
So now if I just print this drink and I run my code..
So the shortcut for running is actually holding down the control and R and now
it can go down here and you can see it's asking me for what I would like,
so I'm going to choose latte. And what's going to be printed
is the latte entry in my recipes dictionary up here, so this particular
value.
Now that I've got this value stored inside a variable called drink,
well then I can tap into its ingredients and loop through each of the ingredients
comparing it against the resources and seeing if there's enough.
Now this is a little bit of functionality that should probably be self-
contained. So instead of just printing the drink,
I'm actually going to create a new function. So up here,
I'm going to create a new function with our def and I'm going to call it is_
resource_sufficient.
And this is_resource_efficient is going to take the order ingredients as a
input and then it's going to work on that.
So if we want to call that function and pass in the order ingredients we'll have
to call is_resource_efficient
and then the other ingredients will be from the drink and then getting hold of
the values under the key ingredients.
All right.
So under this particular key, it will fetch this particular dictionary.
And this is the dictionary that's going to be passed over to this function as
the input.
So now that we have a hold of a dictionary with all the ingredients that are
required and the amount of each ingredient,
we can now compare it against our resources
which is a very similar dictionary with the resources and the amount that's left
in the machine.
We can loop through the order ingredients and for each of the items in the
ingredients,
we're going to check to see if the order ingredients at that particular key,
so this is getting hold of the value, is greater than or equal to the resources
using the same particular key. For example,
if we were looking at the first example,
the item would be equal to water.
So if we fetch the value from order ingredients
with the key of water, we should get of 200.
And we would now test to see if 200 is greater than or equal to the 300 that
we have under the resources. Well, in this case,
then we should probably tell the user that we actually can't make it.
So let's put an if statement there and I'm going to use this same string here to
print it out.
Now notice when I pasted that string in and
it has the double quotes from the PDF file here that it's actually not being
recognized and I'm getting an error here.
And the important thing to know is that there's a difference between decorative
double quotes, like these,
which looked different for the beginning quote and the end quote.
And then there are Programming double quotes which look like this,
so I'm going to select this whole line
and I'm going to add a double quote and notice how they look identical from the
front and the back. So now it's going to print, Sorry
there is not enough.
And the enough of what? It's going to be
the item that we're currently looping through.
So let's change that to an fstring
which makes that an active piece of code that's going to be inserted.
And in this case,
we're going to return false because there is not enough resources.
But otherwise,
if we managed to get to the end of the for loop and we still haven't returned or
exited the function by returning false, then in this case
we can return true.
So if this particular logic is a little bit confusing for you,
you could have something like, like this.
So you have is_enough = true, and you could change is_enough
to false.
If any of the order ingredients are greater than the resources.
And finally at the end, you could return is_enough.
So basically it stays true unless one of these if statements gets activated.
But for simplicity sake, I'm actually just going to keep it simple like this.
And we're now ready to receive that result here
so we can put an if statement here.
If the resources are sufficient for the drink,
then we can proceed to continue to the next step.
The next step is to process coins.
The user's going to be asked for the number of quarters
they have, the number of dimes, nickels, and pennies,
and you have to remember their values.
So if you're from the US this shouldn't be a problem. But if you're like me
somebody who's not from the US, um,
I actually find it really confusing when I go to the States.
I always think that the larger coin, that the nickel, should be worth more than
the dime, but I think it was just me being silly.
So we're going to ask the user to insert some coins, we're going to process it
and then we're going to calculate the total value of the coins
they inserted. That, to me,
sounds like it should be a separate function as well.
So let's create another function here, which I'm going to call process_coins.
And this is not going to take any input,
but it is going to return the total value of the coins inserted.
Now, how do we process coins? Well,
first we can print to ask them to please insert coins.
And then afterwards, we're going to somehow calculate a total, right?
This is the variable that we're going to keep track of
and we're going to return as the output of this function.
The total is going to be calculated based on the four types of coins.
So the first question we're going to ask them is how many quarters?
And this of course is going to be a whole number,
so we're going to turn it from a string into an integer.
And we know that each quarter is worth 0.25
of a dollar,
so we can multiply the number of quarters by 0.25
and then we'll get the monetary value.
Now we'll need to do the same thing for a bunch of other coins.
So instead of quarters, this is going to be dimes,
and then it's going to be nickels and finally,
it's going to be pennies. Dimes are worth 10 cents,
nickels are worth 5 cents,
and pennies are worth 1 cent. Now,
instead of just setting the totals of each of these values, every subsequent one
other than the first one
which remember creates this variable and sets its value,
every other one is just going to be added to the current value like this.
So now at the very end of all of this,
we're going to return the total as the output.
And whenever you have something that returns like both of these functions,
you should probably be adding a docstring. So in this case,
this returns
the total calculated from coins
inserted. And in this case,
what happens is it returns true when order can be made and false
if ingredients are insufficient.
Now let's call this function that we created, process_coins.
If there's enough resources to make the drink,
then the next step is to actually ask them for the money.
So here is where we're going to call process coins.
And notice when I write this and I hover over it, you can see that docstring
we just wrote, returns the total from coins inserted.
That means this is going to return
and we need to capture the user's payment in this variable.
So this returns the output replaces this function call,
and then it gets saved inside this variable called payment. Now,
what are we going to do with this payment? Well, that goes onto the next step,
which is to check that the transaction was successful.
So we have to make sure that the user has inserted enough money to actually
purchase the drink they wanted. But each drink of course has a different price.
So if the user inserts enough money, then we're going to give them some change.
But if they haven't inserted enough money, then we're going to say, sorry,
that's not enough money. And the money is refunded.
But if they have inserted enough money then the cost of the drink is going to be
added to the machine as the profit. So the next time when we trigger the report,
then we're going to get to see the increase in the monetary value.
Again,
let's create a new function and let's get rid of some of these squiggly lines by
adding enough spaces in between the functions.
This one I'm going to call is_transaction_successful,
because that's basically what we're going to be checking.
And it's going to take two inputs.
It's going to take a input in terms of the amount of money that was received,
and it's also going to have another input, which is cost of the drink.
This function's goal is to return true when the payment is accepted or it's
going to return false
if the money is insufficient.
Uhm
Notice how there's this line to the right here of your editor.
Basically what happens is if you have a line of code that's a little bit too
long past the recommendation from PEP 8,
you can see that PEP 8 recommends that a line should not be longer than 120
characters
because it's very hard to read for somebody scrolling around like this.
So in this case,
they would want you to put it onto a new line so that you don't have to scroll
and you can see it all on the same screen. But in our case,
this is not a problem because we have not exceeded the line length
recommendation.
So how are you going to check if the transaction is successful?
Well,
if the money received is greater or equal to the cost of the drink, well in this case
that means we should return true, right? The transaction is successful.
And if it's not the case, if it's the opposite case,
then we're going to print, Sorry that's not enough money.
And the money is refunded to them.
Right.
So let's print that here. And we're also going to return false.
Remember that the return has to be the last thing in your function.
If you put this above the print statement then the print statement will never
get called, and that's why you have this highlight. And if you click on it,
you can see that it tells you this code is unreachable.
So there's a lot of these little hints and tips that really help you when you're
developing.
But if the user has inserted enough money then the cost of the drink should be
added to the machine as the profit so that we can see it in the next time report
is triggered.
So this means that if this money_received is greater or equal to the drink cost,
then we're going to add to this variable called profit that we have up here,
which starts out at zero,
but we're going to add the drinks cost to profit.
So we're going to say profit += drink_cost.
And now you'll see an error under the profit
because this is acting inside
a local scope and profit is outside in the global scope.
So in order to reach it, we have to say global profit.
And the final part of checking the transaction is seeing if the user has
inserted too much money then the machine is going to offer change. For example,
here is however many dollars in change and the change should be rounded to two
decimal places. Again, it's going to be inside this if statement.
So the change is going to be equal to the amount of money received,
subtracting the drink cost.
And this of course could be any number of decimal places.
So we can use the round function
which you've seen a long time ago to round this number
and the second input is the number of decimal places.
So if you just hover over the function name, then you can see the docs come up
and this function is basically going to around a number to a given precision in
decimal digits. So the first is the number you want to round,
and the second is the number of digits that you want after the dot
basically. Now that we've gotten hold of the change,
we're going to print and tell the user,
basically, here is this many dollars in change.
And of course I have to add an F to activate that fstring.
So now we're ready to call is_transaction_successful
and we're going to pass in the money_received and the drink_cost.
So the money_received is, of course, going to be the payment from the previous step
that was calculated from all the coins and the drink_cost is going to be based
on the drink and it's under the key cost,
which we can confirm up here. So the drink is this dictionary,
and then there's the ingredients and the cost.
Right.
Let's rerun our code and let's test it out with something. Let's say
I want a latte. Please insert coins.
Let's say we tried to insert insufficient coins.
It tells us, sorry, that's not enough money. Money is refunded.
But let's try giving it enough coins this time.
And in this case,
it accepts it and it tells us here's $2.42 in change rounded to two decimal places,
and we're ready to take another drink. So now if we hit report,
you can see that we've now earned some money in our machine and all our code is
working as expected.
So we're now ready to tackle the final part, which is to make coffee.
If the transaction is successful and there are enough resources to make the
drinks
the user selected, then the ingredients to make the drink should be deducted from
the coffee machine's resources. For example, before I purchased a latte
I have 300ml of water.
After I purchased the latte that gets reduced by 200 to 100,
and the same happens to the other ingredient values.
But of course the money goes up because I've already taken payment in the
previous step. Let's take this into an if statement
because remember this function returns true when the payment is accepted or false
if their money is insufficient.
So this is where we're going to call on next function
which is to make coffee. So let's create
make_coffee. In order to make coffee
we need to know the drink name so that we can tell the user here's your
particular drink.
And it will also need to have the order ingredients.
The goal of this function is to deduct the required ingredients from the
resources. In order to do that,
we're going to get hold of the order ingredients and we're going to loop
through them. So for each of the items in the order_ingredients,
we're going to look inside the resources for that particular item
and we're going to subtract the amount that's in the order_ingredients.
And once all of that is done, so the for loop
ends, then we can print and we can even add an emoji to this.
Right.
On a Mac
you can insert an emoji by going to edit, emoji, and symbols. On Windows
the easiest thing to do is to just search Google for a coffee emoji
and then copy and paste it into your code.
So now let's call make_coffee here and notice how
if we are here the machine is on
and it's not any of these other previous choices,
and then the resource is sufficient and the transaction is successful.
These are all the steps that it took us to get to this particular stage in our
code.
So now we're going to make the coffee and we're going to pass in two things.
So let's just see the prompt again. We need to give the drink name
which is going to be the choice that the user entered, and the order ingredients
which is going to come from the drink and it's under the key ingredients.
So now we're ready to test and run our code once more.
Let's say, I want a latte and I'm going to insert lots of money.
And now I have my latte. If I hit report,
you should be able to see that a bunch of resources were subtracted and the
money is increased. If I try to order another latte,
it should fail because there is not enough water and there's not enough milk.
You can see that it's not going to let me go through as long as one of the
ingredients is not enough.
So we've now managed to fulfill all of the requirements of our coffee machine
program. Now,
this probably a lot more complexity that you could add to your coffee machine,
but basically what I wanted to show you today is how you would program something
that exists in real life,
like a coffee machine and even something that seems as simple as a coffee
machine. It can lead to a lot of errors,
a lot of bugs and a lot of anguish, but its good.
The more that you struggle,
the closer you get towards your goals. And the clearer the role of the function,
the easier it will be for you to untangle the logic.
If you want to take a look at the completed code that I've written in this
lesson,
then simply head over to the link that's in the resources and you'll be able to
see it in
Repl.it. Make sure that you've managed to fix any issues in your code
and that it runs exactly the same way as expected in the program requirements.
Hey! Welcome to Day 16 of 100 Days of Code. Now
today,
we're going to be pulling out the big guns, we're going to be learning about
Object Oriented Programming otherwise known as OOP.
Why are we learning about it? Well, if you think back to yesterday's project,
some of you I'm sure at some point during the project, would have had this
feeling of what on earth is going on with my code?
And the reason is because our code is getting more complex,
it's trying to do a lot of things,
and it's trying to manage a whole bunch of relationships.
So one function is changing a variable,
and then that same function is doing something else to another variable.
And at some point, the logic of our code starts looking very, very spaghetti-
like.
And it's at this point where it's really hard to track and remember what's
actually going on in our code.
So this style of programming is called Procedural
Programming where we set up procedures or functions that do particular things.
And then one procedure leads to another procedure, and all in all, the computer's
mostly working from top to bottom and then jumping out into a function as
needed.
Procedural programming is one of the earliest paradigms of Programming.
In fact, back in the days when we had older languages like Fortran and COBOL,
they rely pretty much exclusively on procedural
programming like what we've been doing.
But the increase in complexity,
the increase in the number of relationships that we need to remember and manage
starts making it look a bit like the dating history of the Kardashians.
And it gets very,
very confusing because everybody has been in touch with somebody else. Now,
the kind of relationships I prefer are one to one, me and my couch.
So how can we maintain a simple relationship in our code while being able to
write more and more complex projects? Well,
this is where the Object-Oriented paradigm comes in really handy.
Now let's imagine that you're tasked with creating the program for a self-
driving car. Now, as you can imagine,
this is a pretty complex project and it's many,
many notches above the coffee machine that we've been struggling with so far.
But what if you broke it down? What is a self-driving car?
What are the different components that make up a self-driving car? Well,
it probably needs some sort of camera module to keep track of what's on the road
and to recognize what's on the road,
it will probably need a form of lane detection to know if we're actually within
the lane or if we need to turn off or if we need to park, and it will need some
way of navigating so that when the user says, I want to go to the bank,
they identify the branch they want to go to,
and then the navigation gets set up and the car knows how to get there.
And finally, you'll probably need some form of fuel management, right?
What should happen when the fuel gets low?
Should it go and automatically recharge at a specified point?
Now I'm obviously simplifying this task. There's a lot,
a lot more that goes into making an automated car.
But we've already managed to break it down into several modules that we can
think about tackling, right?
But imagine if you have a whole team who are all working on this project and
within that team,
there's sub-teams who are working on each of these different modules.
Well then by splitting up this big complex task into separate modules,
then we can all work on this car simultaneously,
massively improving our productivity,
making it much quicker to eventually build all the software for this car.
Plus on top of that, a lot of these modules are reusable.
So if it just so happens that the next year we're tasked with building a drone,
well, a lot of those programming modules that we built, like the camera module,
the fuel management, the navigation,
that's all going to be incredibly useful in our drone delivery software as well.
And because we've taken out these individual chunks of code and modularized them
using Object Oriented Programming,
we won't have to code them up again in the same way that we might need to
if we were using procedural programming.
So what exactly is all Object Oriented Programming? We've seen that we can split
a larger task into that smaller pieces.
And each of those pieces can be worked on by separate teams, separate people,
and also each of those pieces become reusable if we need the same
functionality in the future. But Object Oriented
Programming actually takes that concept even further.
And I think the best way to explain it
is to imagine that you are tasked with running a restaurant.
So you take over this restaurant from your long lost uncle
and you realize that it's actually really hard running a restaurant.
So, first off, you have to be the receptionist and you reserve seats for your
restaurant visitor's and then when they order something,
you have to be the waitress and bring them their order.
And then of course the order needs to be cooked up, right?
So you're also gonna run into the kitchen and be the chef, create the thing that
they ordered and finally,
you're also going to be the cleaner tidying up after everybody
once they've left. As you can imagine,
if you were one person having to do all of these tasks,
that's going to be a pretty rough day. There are in fact one-man restaurants,
and I've seen some work really in well Japan,
where you have one person who's taking the order,
who's making the food, who's tidying up after you.
But the limitation here though, is that look at how many seats he has.
You can't have a large restaurant running everything by yourself. In the same
way we can't create a very complex and really large software project
if we are using a procedural style of programming where we're sort of running a
one man band. It gets very,
very complex and very hard to manage very quickly.
So lets consider the alternative.
What if we had just hired a bunch of people where they each have their own
individual roles. They're trained for it, they know what to do.
The waiter knows how to wait and the chef knows how to cook. Well,
in this case,
you could just be the manager and you can manage all of your staff and tell them
what it is that they need to do.
But then you won't have to worry about the nitty-gritty details of exactly how
they need to go about doing their jobs. So for example,
you don't need to tell the waiter
how to wait on customers and you don't need to tell the chef how to cook an egg
because they already know how to do that.
And we can use the same concept to simplify the relationships in our code and
make it scalable for a larger and more complex project.
We've seen a little bit of why Object Oriented Programming is really useful,
but now let's take a look at how you would actually go about implementing Object
Oriented Programming.
So in the last lesson we talked of this example of the restaurant,
where we hired three types of staff,
and we had a manager who would then manage all of these three different types of
staff. Now,
the reason why Object Oriented Programming is called that is because it's trying
to model a real world object.
So let's say that we are creating a virtual restaurant. Well, in this case,
we probably have to model a virtual chef, waiter,
cleaner, and manager.
So let's say that we were going to model a waiter. In order to model our waiter,
there's probably two things we need to think about: what it has and what it does.
In terms of what it has, well, it might have variables like,
is it holding a plate, true or false?
Or which tables is it responsible for? Maybe table 4, 5 and 6.
Now it also has things that it does.
Maybe they're able to take an order to the chef and maybe they also need to take
payments and add money to the restaurant. So these two different things,
what the waiter has and what the waiter does are
the two most important things that make up an object: its attributes and its
methods. By looking at the code,
you can pretty much see that the attributes is basically a variable.
An attribute is just a fancy word for a variable that's associated with a
modeled object like our waiter here.
Because it's not just a free floating bit of a variable, right?
It's not just somewhere in our main.py.
It's actually a variable that's attached to a particular object.
It's the waiter's tables responsible.
Now the method goes along the same vein. These,
as you can clearly see, are just functions
but we call it a method because it's a function that a particular modeled
object can do.
We need a waiter object to take the order and we need a waiter object to take
payment. Again, these are not just free-floating functions.
Now, there's a lot of new words that are part of Object Oriented Programming and
programming in general, we're going to see them again and again,
and eventually it's going to become a word that's going to be in your
dictionary. But for now, just remember that in Object Oriented
Programming,
we're trying to model real-life objects and those objects have things
and they also can do things.
The things that they have are their attributes
and these are usually modeled with variables, and the things that they can do
are called methods and they are modeled by functions.
So essentially, an object is just a way of combining some piece of data and some
functionality altogether in the same thing.
But we can actually have multiple objects generated from the same type.
So when we've modeled a particular job in our virtual restaurant
like the waiter's job,
and we figured out what are the things that the waiter have and what are the
things that it can do, well,
we can actually generate multiple versions of the same object. So we could have
Henry who's a waiter and we can also have Betty who's a waiter,
and we can generate as many of these as we want from the same blueprint.
And in OOP we call this blueprint, or this type, a class.
And we call these individual objects that are generated from the blueprint
an object.
So now let's take a look at how you use these class blueprints to create an actual
object.
[inaudible]
So here's a blueprint for a car.
And that blueprint that specifies what the color of the car is,
how many wheels it should have, what its mileage is, how much fuel it has,
all of those bits of data combined with all of its functionality
like the ability to drive, the ability to stop and break.
And that blueprint which models a real-life car is known as the class.
And it's from this blueprint,
this class, that we can generate as many objects as we want. Now,
the object is the actual thing that we're going to be using in our code.
The code equivalent of what just happened,
creating a new object from a blueprint,
looks like this in Python. You have the class
which is normally written with the first letter of each word capitalized,
which is known as Pascal case.
This is to differentiate it from all the variable and function names that we
give in Python, where each word is separated by underscores.
So in this case,
the car is the object and it gets created from this car blueprint.
All we have to do to create the object from the class is to give the object a
name, it can be anything you want, set it equal to the name of the class,
and then the parentheses, which in the same way as it activates the function,
it activates the construction of this object from the blueprint.
Now, in order for us to practice this and to see it in action,
we're going to using a library of code that somebody else has created.
And what it allows us to do is to finally start putting graphics onto the
screen. The premise is really simple.
Let's say that somebody somewhere has created a blueprint for a turtle.
Now this turtle has a paintbrush on its back,
and you can tell the turtle to dip the paintbrush in different colors,
pick a different of size paint brushes and most importantly,
you can tell it to draw onto the screen.
This library is called turtle graphics and it's preloaded with every download of
Python so we can get started with it straight away.
So go ahead and open up PyCharm and create a new project.
Now I'm going to call mine, buy the old convention day 16 start
and making sure that I'm on the latest version of Python in my base interpreter,
I'm going to click create. Now, once you've created the new project,
go ahead and create the main.py as we have always done.
In our case,
we're going to be creating an object from a blueprint that somebody else has
already created,
and the blueprint lives in another module called turtle.
So we'll have to import that module.
And we know that from previously,
we can import other modules and use the things that are declared inside the
module by importing it, and then tapping into various things in there.
So for example, if I was to go and create another new file
which I'll call another_module.
Now inside another_module, let's say I create another variable.
And now I can go back to my main.py,
I can import my another_module I just created
and I can tap into that variable
that's inside another module by saying another module dot another variable.
Now let's go ahead and run this code as it is.
And you can see the value of that variable from the other module being used
inside our main.py.
Now I want to do the same thing using turtle, but in this case,
I want to tap into the class called turtle
that's declared inside this turtle module. The wording's a little bit confusing,
but let me show you what I mean.
So I'm going to tap into the turtle module and I'm going to get hold of a
turtle class. So notice how it's got the C here
denoting that this is a blueprint for creating a new turtle
object. Now, remember that to actually construct the object
we need to add the parentheses at the end,
and now we can save all of this into an actual object, which we get to name.
So I'm going to call my turtle timmy
and now I've got a new turtle object. Essentially,
we've done the same thing as we have done up here.
We've imported a module called turtle,
we've tapped into that turtle module here,
and then we've fetched something from that module. In this case,
it's a variable. And in this case,
it's a class which is denoted by the capital T, the Pascal case here.
And then we've used the parentheses to initialize
or basically construct an object from that blueprint
and we've saved it into an object called Timmy.
Now I can simplify this code to make it look more like what we had in the slides
by saying, instead of import turtle, I can say from,
from the turtle module import the turtle class.
So now, instead of writing all of this,
I can simply just write Timmy
equals a new object created from the turtle class and it's constructed.
This is how we would construct our new object.
So now I have this brand new object called Timmy
and if I go ahead and print timmy
you can see that when I run this code what gets printed is a new turtle object
from the turtle module
and it's saved at this location in the computer's memory.
So this is very different from say
if we just printed a string or a number.
It works completely differently. In this case,
it's actually a object that's being printed. Now,
what can we do with this object?
[inaudible]
Now, as we saw before with our car
object it has certain attributes, right?
Like speed and fuel, data that it could keep track of that are really important
to the modeling of an actual car object. Now,
when it comes to accessing these attributes,
the syntax or the code looks like this. Car in this case is the object
and then we use a dot or a full stop to separate the object from the actual
attribute that we want to get hold of, which in this case is speed.
What this code does is it essentially identifies the object
and then it says, from this object get the speed attribute.
This is actually gonna represent the speed of this particular car
object. Coming back to our turtle.
One of the other classes that is inside this turtle module is something called
screen.
And the screen represents the window in which this turtle is going to show up.
So let's go ahead and create this screen
object. I'm going to call my object my_screen
and then I'm going to create it from this blueprint of a screen that we
imported. Now we can tap into one of the screens properties
which is called the canvas height and canvas width.
So let's see what the height is, and notice how we're using that dot notation.
So this is the object and then separated by a dot we've got the attributes that
we want to access from this object.
So I'm going to print that into the console. Now,
when I go ahead and run this code,
you'll see a window pop up very briefly
and that was the screen on which our turtle is going to show up.
Now, if you take a look in the console,
you can see that not only have we printed the turtle object,
but we've also printed the height of the canvas for this particular screen that
we've created.
So the screen here is the object and that canvas height is an attribute that's
associated with that screen.
Now, in addition to the things that an object has,
so data that it holds like the speed or the fuel
which we've already seen, it also has things that it can do, right?
So functions that are associated with that particular object. And these functions
when it's tied to an object is known as a method.
But essentially we would use it the same way as we have done with any other
function that we've created so far.
The only difference is the syntax. Firstly,
we would tap into the car object and then using that same dot notation that
we saw with the attributes, we're saying car.stop.
So essentially what we're doing is we're getting hold of the object and then
we're calling this function that's associated with that object,
which is known as a method. So coming back to our code here,
one of the things that we can do with this screen object that we've created here
called my_screen is we can tap into one of its functions.
And because it's a function that's tied to an object,
it's actually called a method.
So the method name is called exitonclick.
And what this will allow us to do is instead of having our screen show up and
then quickly disappear when our code ends,
this exitonclick will allow our program to continue running until we click on
the screen and then it exits our code.
So let's try this again and notice how we've now got our screen show up
and this canvas has a height of 300 and a width of 300,
but now we can see our turtle in the form of the arrow. So this is our
a little Timmy shown up in the middle.
And our code is only going to exit when the screen detects a click
because we've called this function that's associated with the screen object.
So now if I click on the screen,
you can see process finished with exit code zero, our code is ended and the screen
has disappeared. Now there are other functions as well.
So if we take our little timmy object and we say, well, timmy,
why don't we change the shape of you on the screen
and we'll change you into an actual turtle?
So now when I run the code,
you can see that object in the center is now in the shape of a turtle.
Now,
if you want to know how I know about all these things I can do with the turtle
graphics library, then of course,
I'm getting all of this information from the documentation.
So in the course resources,
you'll see a link to this Turtle graphics documentation,
and it tells you all the things that you can do with your turtle.
So for example,
you can call all of these methods that are associated with your turtle object to
get your turtle to move and draw,
and you can also use it to change its position or change its coordinates,
as well as doing things like changing the color or resetting.
And you can browse through this list to see how you would use each of these
things. So for example,
if I wanted to change the color of my turtle,
I can do that by simply just calling this method, color,
and then inside the parentheses
I pass in the argument of the actual color string.
Now you can choose from a whole range of colors just by putting in the name as a
string into that method which is called color.
So go ahead and see if you can change our turtle timmy's color from the default
which is just black to one of the colors that you see in this link here,
and the link, of course, is in the course resources.
So let's say I want to change it to a coral color like this one.
All I have to do is tap into my object which is called timmy,
and then call the method which is called color onto it.
And you can see all the methods are
denoted by a little M here in the circle.
Now this color, of course, expects some sort of input.
So the input that it expects is a actual string of a color.
And my string is going to be coral, which I picked up from here.
So now let's run our code and see what it looks like now.
Once the screen refreshes,
you can see that our turtle is now a nice coral color,
and we've managed to do all of this to change the shape,
change the color, all because we were able to call these functions
which belong to this
object. Now see if you can use the documentation here and figure out how to get the
turtle to move forward by a hundred paces.
Pause the video and try to complete this challenge.
All right.
So we saw earlier that it has a whole bunch of move and draw methods.
So we can simply use this forward method to get it to move forward.
And in terms of the parameters that it takes,
it takes a number which is going to determine the distance that it's going to
move forward by.
So we said that we wanted our turtle to move forward by a hundred paces.
All I have to do is specify the object that I want to move which is timmy,
and then call that method forward and pass in the distance.
So I said a hundred paces. So now let's run our code again,
and you can see that little turtle just move forward by a hundred paces.
So now we've seen how to create a new Object from a blueprint,
we've seen how we can tap into its attributes by using the object name dot and
then the name of the attribute.
So this is the same as having a variable that's associated with that object.
And finally,
we've seen how we can call methods that are associated with the object.
For example, here
when we changed the shape or when we changed the color or when we told it to go
forwards. Now in the next lesson,
I'm going to show you how you can get hold of more external libraries
not just turtle, but a whole world of packages that you can tap into.
And you can start using these packages of code that other programmers have
already developed,
and simply by creating objects from the existing blueprints and reading the
documentation to get it to do various things that you want it to.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now I've mentioned a lot about using code that other developers have written and
the most common way to do this is through using packages of code.
In this lesson,
I'll show you how to integrate an existing package of code into our project so
that we can practice creating objects and working with attributes and methods.
Now we've seen modules of code where each file that we create in our project is
essentially a module in itself.
But a package differs from a module in the sense that it's actually a whole
bunch of code that other people have written, lots and lots of files all packaged
together to achieve some sort of goal or purpose. Now,
let's say that we wanted to create a table of Pokemon and their type.
So we wanted some way of documenting that Pikachu is an electric type and maybe
Squirtle is a water type. Now,
if we wanted to do that in ASCII so that we could print it in the console, well
then we would have to go about formatting it and it'll be quite painful.
So we might have to print some sort of pipe and then maybe we would have the
name of the field, so Pokemon name,
and then maybe another pipe. And then we would have the name of the next column,
which is their type.
And then finally we would close that off and then we would have to print some
sort of a horizontal line
maybe like this and so on and so forth just to create this table.
And it's quite difficult if you're not used to manipulating ASCII and
visualizing it. I certainly am not up to this task.
So what could we do instead? Well,
we could search for a package that other developers have created to achieve this
goal. And the place that we would do that is somewhere called PyPi,
which is the Python package index.
And this is a bunch of software for the Python programming language that is
developed and shared by the Python community. So we can see their source code,
but more importantly,
we can see how to implement the code and how to put it into our project.
In here, I'm going to search for something called prettytable.
And this is a very simple library that is going to help us to display tables in
a ASCII format.
We can click on the project links to find out more about it.
And this will take us to the Google code archive,
where the documentation is hosted.
If you go to Wikis and go to tutorial,
you'll see some documentation on how to use it.
Now, this particular package is not as extensive as the turtle graphics package.
So there's actually not a lot of things you can do with it,
but its got more than we need for our use case.
The first thing we have to do is to install this package into our project.
Now, unlike the turtle package
which is already preloaded with every copy of Python, in order to use the
packages that you find in the Python package index,
you actually have to install it.
So here's how we do it in PyCharm. First, go to the preferences,
so in Windows, I think it's under file and then preferences. On Mac is under
PyCharm and then preferences.
And then here you'll see a whole bunch of things you can change
including the editor or appearance which we've already messed around with.
But I want you to click on your project.
So my project is called day-16-start and then we're going to go into the project
interpreter. And here we can click on the plus button to install any package that
you find in the Python package index. Make a note of what it's called.
So ours is called PrettyTable and then we're going to search for it inside the
available packages. And once we found it,
we're going to select it and then click install.
If you are working with Repl.it,
you can also install packages just by going to the packages tab
and then again, searching for PrettyTable. Once you click on the package
that you want, click on the plus button to add it to your project.
Now Repl.it is a little bit weird because it says installing
but it never actually confirms the success. But once you click run,
everything will go through and it will work perfectly
as long as you see it in your list of packages here. Now,
if you want to remove the package, you can simply click on the minus button,
but now we're going to work with it.
So now it's installed successfully,
we can go ahead and close this down and click okay.
And we can now access this package called PrettyTable in our code.
Again,
I'm going to import it so I can say import prettytable.
And now I can use everything that's inside this package. Now,
if you want to see the source code,
you can actually right-click on it and select, go to, implementation.
And this will take you to the Python file where this entire prettytable is
implemented, so all of the code that they've written.
It's a little bit daunting and it's got a lot of code in it,
but we don't have to worry about how the code is created and how it works.
All we need to do is look at the documentation for this package and see how we
can implement it into our project. Now in the next lesson,
we're going to get some practice
constructing a prettytable object and using the documentation to explore this
object's attributes and methods. For all of that and more, I'll see you there.
In the last lesson, we added an external library to our project.
Now it's time to construct a prettytable object and practice using its methods
and attributes. Our starting point as always
is the documentation. Here
you can see how to construct an actual prettytable object.
So let's use what we've learned previously about constructing objects to go
ahead and create this object from the class. Now, firstly,
we're going to do the same thing as we did previously with turtle.
We're going to tap into the package prettytable,
and then we're going to import the prettytable class noted by the c here.
Now that we have access to this class inside our code,
I want you to go ahead and create an object from this pretty table class and the
object should be named table. So pause the video and give that a go.
All right. So we said I'll object is going to be called table,
and then we're going to construct it from this class called a prettytable.
So we're going to put it in with its casing.
So this is the Pascal case that we spoke about earlier on,
and then in order to actually give it the go-ahead and construct,
we have to add the parentheses at the end.
So now you've created a new object called table from this prettytable and we
can actually go ahead and print this table. And even at this stage,
it's ready going to start printing out a bare bones version all the table.
But of course this table has no datas
So it's actually kind of hard to visualize what all of these ASCII characters
are doing in an empty table.
But no matter, the next thing we can see in our documentation is how to go about
adding columns. So it's got this method, remember methods
are functions that are associated with an object and this method will add columns to
whatever table we specify. Now the method takes two inputs.
One is the name of the field,
so our field names are Pokemon name and type.
And then we've got a list of strings
which is going to be the data that's going to go into that column. Essentially,
every time we call that method, add column,
it's going to allow us to give a field name as a string,
and then a list of data in order that they're going to go into the table.
So we're going to add our table one column at a time. Using that documentation
see if you can add both of these columns to our table object and then once
you've done that, we're going to print the table object again
and we should be to see an ASCII table. This is what you're aiming for
when you run your code.
It should print out your table and nicely format it in this ASCII style.
Pause the video and complete the challenge.
Right?
All right.
So we've got our table object and remember that methods are functions that are
associated with the object. So we say table object dot,
and then we get to call that method,
add_column. And notice how it takes two inputs,
the field name and the data that's going to go into the column.
So the field name is going to be a string,
and this is going to be the name at the top of our column. So in our case,
it was called Pokemon name. And then after a comma,
we get to put in a list of all the data that's going to go into our column.
So just as a quick reminder, our first column contains Pikachu,
Squirtle and Charmander.
Now, we should have added a column to our table and you can safely ignore all
of these typos because of course, Pokemon names are not real words.
But if you wanted to check against the poke dex
you can actually go to this link in the course resources,
and you can see how each of these Pokemon are spelt. Now,
the next thing we want to add is the associated type with each of these
Pokemons. So for example, Charmander is a fire type of Pokemon,
Squirtle is a water type Pokemon,
but essentially we're going to add the data that's in the second column.
So the field name is called type, and then we've got three pieces of data
that's going to need to go into the list in the same order as the previous
Pokemon. That way we'll actually match them up properly.
So if you haven't already, go ahead and add the second column.
Right?
So again,
I'm going to call the same method on my table and this time I'm going to add the
field type and the data is going to go in the order of the data that I had from
the previous column. So the first one is the type of Pikachu which is electric.
And the second one is the type for Squirtle, which is Water. And finally,
we've got fire for Charmander.
So now this will be matched to this,
this will be matched this and so on and so forth.
If we go ahead and print our table now, so
if we run our code and take a look in here,
you can see how we've now got a nicely formatted table by creating an object
from this pre-made prettytable class and we've now called this method
add_column to add two columns. And when we print our table,
it's now nicely formatted in ASCII. Now,
remember that we can also change the object's attributes.
For example, if we wanted to change the appearance of our table,
that's probably controlled by an attribute. If you scroll down,
you can see that we can change the table style by tapping into each of these attributes.
For example, if I wanted to change the alignment of my data in the table,
I can change this align attribute to L for left-align, C for the center-align or
R for right-aligned.
Do you remember how to tap into an object's attribute? If you do,
go ahead and see if you can change our table from center-aligned by default to
left-aligned. Pause the video and try to complete that challenge.
Right?
So again,
we're going to tap into our table object and we're going to use the dot
notation, but this time
instead of accessing a method associated with the object
which is of course denoted by the M, we're going to access an attribute or in
this case, they've titled F which is a field.
And the one that we want is this align. So let's go ahead and type align,
and now we have access to this attribute. Let's see what happens
if I go ahead and print this align attribute.
You can see that for both of my columns, Pokemon name and type,
the align attribute is set to C, which is centered.
What I want to do is change the whole table to be left-aligned. Just as we would
with any other variable we can of course print it,
but we can also change it.
And we would change a variable by just using the equal sign, right?
So let's change the alignment to left-aligned,
and now let's run the code again.
And you can see now both of my columns are now aligning with the left hand
margin.
So we've seen how we can use attributes
like the ones here to change the styling of our table.
We've seen how we can use methods
like add_column or add_row to work with this table object and get it to
perform some sort of functionality, like adding pieces of data to it.
And we've seen how we can create new objects by simply constructing it from the
blueprint class. Feel free to mess around with prettytable
as much as you like change, other things about it,
or add different pieces of data.
But once you're happy with creating the object changing the attributes and
calling the methods,
then head over to the next lesson where I've got a quiz for you.
Now as we start using objects and their attributes and methods more and more,
we're going to start to see why it is that they are so useful and so loved by
programmers. Now,
I think one of the non-programmers that explained OOP the best is actually the late
Steve Jobs.
And he has this brilliant example that makes it really clear why objects are so
great. In his story
he talks about this concept where let's say you were traveling to Japan and
after a long flight,
you finally land and you go outside and there's beautiful cherry blossoms, Mt.
Fuji is looking wonderful. But unfortunately on the flight,
you had soiled your T-shirt.
You were overly eager with the tomato juice and you spilled everything upon
yourself. So what do we do? Well,
you're in this unfamiliar city and you have no idea
even whether the hell you are let alone where to find the nearest
dry cleaners or launderette. And plus on top of that,
you don't have the local currency. They take yen,
but you only have pounds and you don't even speak Japanese. So what do you do?
It's going to be a real struggle trying to solve this problem. Well,
you staying at a hotel, right? And the hotel staff probably speak English.
So you go the receptionist and you tell it the hotel that, Hey,
my t-shirt is soiled and they say, Hey, no problems. We'll take that from you.
And we'll go and handle all of that messy stuff.
We know how to find the dry cleaners,
we can pay them in the local currency and we speak the local language.
And what you get back is just a nice clean t-shirt.
So this is similar to the process of working with objects. Essentially,
if you have this hotel object
which has a blueprint for how to handle dry cleaning
some sort of clothing, then all you have to do is just get the object hotel and
then call its associated method dry clean,
and then it will do all of the messy stuff for you.
And you don't have to worry about the implementation of this function at all.
So now you can work with multiple objects
getting them to do different things and trust that they know how to manage their
data and how to perform the necessary functionality.
Coming back to a problem that we've already solved
creating that coffee machine with all of the program requirements. Well,
it's time to put our Object Oriented Programming knowledge to the test because
we're going to be making a OOP version of our coffee machine.
Now the program still has the same requirements
as before. You have to print reports for
all the resources, you have to check if the resources are sufficient,
process coins, check transaction is successful, and finally make coffee.
But in this case, you're going to be working with objects.
In the course resources,
you'll find a link to the starting project for the OOP coffee machine.
So if you head over to this link,
you can see that there's a whole bunch of code that we've already written for
you. Now,
the idea here is you're not going to touch any of these other files,
the money machine, the menu, or the coffee maker. All that code has already
been written for you
and it's almost like you're working with an external library.
You're just going to trust that they do what they say they do.
And you'll find a link to this coffee machine documentation that I've created
which describes in detail what each of these classes or blueprints allow you to
do. So once you construct an object from the menu item class,
then you have access to the name attribute, the cost attribute,
ingredient attributes, and there's also descriptions of what it should do
and what an example might be.
You have access to all of these classes and you can build objects from each of
these classes to solve this project.
In order to work with PyCharm, all you need to do is to download the zip
file it with all the starting code from our course resource website.
Alternatively,
if you are already logged in on Repl.it, simply fork the project and then click
on these three dots to download the zip file here. Now,
once you found that in your downloads folder,
all you have to do is uncompressed or unzip it.
And then you can go into PyCharm and open it here.
So click on the open button and then navigate to where you had that folder
downloaded. Remember it needs to be unzipped.
If you're on windows, right-click the zip file and choose extract all.
Then click extract.
You should see an unzipped folder popup next to your zip file.
If you're on Mac then all you need to do is just double-click on the .zip file.
Now, if we click open on that folder,
then it will open up this project. And when you open up the project folder,
you'll see all of the same files.
Now you're only going to be working from the main.py. In fact,
I don't even want you to care that much about the code that's in the other
files.
It has class definitions and a whole bunch of other things that we're going to
learn about in the next lesson.
But for now, I want you to treat it as if it is an external library
which you're just going to use. At the very beginning of the main.py file,
I've already imported all four classes that you are going to be using; menu,
menu item, coffee maker, and money machine.
Now all of these classes are documented in the coffee machine documentation
website.
All you have to do is head over to this website and read through what each of
the classes do. Some of them have attributes and methods,
others just have methods.
So each of these classes have already pre-written code that do a lot of the
heavy lifting and all of the code that we had to write when we wrote the coffee
machine code from scratch.
But this time you're only going to be using these four classes and the objects
created from them in order to achieve exactly the same goals as before.
So while the goals are fresh in your mind from the previous day,
you should review the code from the previous day and then have a read of the
documentation and see how you would implement exactly the same project
but this time using only the objects created from these classes.
You'll need to spend some time on this because you'll need to think through how
to create objects from these blueprint classes and then how to use the objects,
how to call the methods and the logic that's required to put everything
together. Pause the video
now, have a think about this problem, and try to make the coffee machine do
exactly the same and have all the same functionality as the coffee machine that
you created in yesterday's project.
If you got stuck or if you had any problems completing this project, the first port of call is to review
the lessons you learned today.
It might just be that you need to see some of the theory a few more times and listen to it a few more
times and practice it a few more times before you're ready to tackle this final challenge.
But if you have completed it and you just want to see the solution, then I'm going to go through it
with you right now.
Again, we're going to complete all of the program requirements step by step.
So the first thing is to print a report for all of the current resources in the coffee machine. Back
in PyCharm,
I'm actually going to collapse this entire project folder because I'm not going to be writing any code
other than inside main.py.
Now you can see up here, we've got access to four classes. And if we take a look inside the documentation,
you can see that both the coffeemaker class and the money machine class have a method called report.
And this is going to print a report of all of the resources like water, milk, coffee,
and this is going to print a report of the current profit.
So our final report is going to be both a report from the money machine as well as the coffee maker.
Let's go ahead and start off by creating some objects from these classes.
For example, the money machine is going to be just called money_machine
or you could call it my_money_machine.
You can actually name your objects anything you like.
But I'm just going to use the default Python snake case to create a new variable money_machine, which
is going to hold my object. And my object is going to be created, of course, from the money machine
class.
And the construction happens when I add the parentheses.
So now I have a object created and stored inside this variable money_machine.
Now, if I want this money machine to create a report, then all I have to do is tap into the object
and then write a dot and then call the method that I need, which is report.
So now if I go ahead and run my code,
you can see it prints out the current amount of money in the machine.
Now let's do the same thing for our coffee maker.
Again, I'm going to call it coffee_maker, and you see this frequently.
The object naming tends to be the lower case and snake case, so separated by underscores, version of the
name of the class.
So the name of the class is CoffeeMaker, and usually you'll see people name the object exactly the
same, but in lowercase.
And now that I have my coffee _maker, then I can go ahead and call the report method on that object
as well.
And now, if I run my code once more, you can see that I've got everything now being reported and printed
out.
So in this case, we don't actually have to care how report is implementing all of this functionality.
All we have to do is read the documentation, find the method that does the thing that we want, and
then trust that it will carry out the functionality as described.
Now that we've completed step 1, the next one is to check that resources are sufficient.
My first port of call is going to be going over to the documentation.
And you can see that the coffeemaker class actually has a method called is _resource_efficient.
And all we have to do is pass in the drink, which is a menu item, and then it's going to check and
give us true, if that drink order can be made, and false if the ingredients are insufficient.
So how do we get hold of this drink menu item to pass over to this method?
Well, if we take a look at the menu class, you can see it has a method called get_items and this is
where you really see reading the documentation properly,
actually absorbing everything that's in here becomes really, really helpful.
This menu class has two methods that are really useful.
One, It's able to get a hold of the names of all the items that are available on the menu.
And it returns it as a string separated by forward slashes.
It's also able to find a drink based on the order name.
So if we passed in one of these names to this function find_drink, then it's going to return a menu
item object if it actually exists.
Otherwise, it's going to return none.
We're going to need both of these in order to ask the user what they want.
Let's go ahead and set up our while loop. As we had previously
I'm going to create a new variable called is_on and it's going to start off being true.
And then while coffee machine is on, well then we're going to get hold of all the options that we
can offer the user. And we get that by calling that method get_items.
But of course, because this is a method, it's associated with an object.
So we have to create an object from this menu blueprint.
So let's do that next to all the other objects being created.
So let's create a menu object and it's going to be created from the menu class,
and then we add the parentheses.
And now we have access to that object by the name menu.
The options are going to be equal to the menu object and then we're going to call the get_items method.
And then when this method returns, it's going to save the string and all the options into this variable
called options.
Now we can get the user's choice by asking them for what would you like?
And then inside a set of parenthesis we'll offer them all the options. And then, of course, I need
to turn this into an fstring.
And the code highlighting immediately tells me that this is actually now working.
So once I've got the user's choice, then I can incorporate the reporting behaviour into this choice.
Remember, previously we said if the choice was equal to off, then that means the is_on is going
to be equal to false, and elif
the choice is equal to report,
well, in this case, we're going to get the coffeemaker and the money machine to make their reports
into the console.
Finally, we're ready to tackle the next problem, which is how do we check that we have enough resources?
And this is going to require us to find the drink given the order name that the user chose from the
choice and then get hold of the menu item which comes as the output from this method call.
So else, we're going to save our drink as a variable called drink, and then we're going to tap into
the menu.find_drink. And find_drink, you'll notice, takes a order name as the input.
So this is a string and this is going to be equal to whatever the user chose inside this choice.
So let's put the choice in here as the input.
And now, once we've got hold of this drink, let's go ahead and print it.
Remember, we're expecting a menu item object at this stage.
So let's click run, and let's make sure that we can hit report to get the report,
we can say off to switch off the machine and exit the code, and we can also get hold of a latte by
passing in latte as the drink that we want.
And we now get printed a menu item object at this particular location in the computer's memory.
Perfect.
Everything is working as expected.
Now, instead of printing the drink, I'm going to tackle this step 2, which is to check that the
resources are sufficient.
Again, that's going to require us to look through our documentation. And you'll see that the coffee
maker class has
that method is_resource _sufficient, and it expects a menu item object as the input.
And then it's going to return true when it can be made and false if it can't.
So let's get hold of our coffee maker object and then get it to check if the resources are sufficient
to make the current drink that we're interested in.
And let's go ahead and print the results here
and run our code.
Let's say that we wanted to make a latte. That's going to be resource sufficient, so true. Espresso,
also true, and a Cappuccino is also true.
So we can make all three drinks, basically.
Now, instead of printing this, what we want to do is we want to check if this is true and then proceed
to the next step if there are enough resources.
Now the next step is to take payment from the user and to process the coins and check the transaction
is successful.
Notice how in our coffee machine documentation for the money machine, we don't actually have a way
of processing the coins. But it what it does have is it allows us to make payments passing in the cost
of the drink and then it will return true when the payment is accepted or false, if insufficient.
So let's see what happens if we actually try to make payment.
Let's tap into our money machine object and then call the make_payment method and we have to pass in
the cost of the drink that the user ordered.
So we've got the drink object here, which remember is a menu item, and each of the menu items have
three attributes that we care about: the name of the drink, the cost of the drink and the ingredient
list.
So this is what we're interested in at the moment. So we can pass in the drink.cost which is the
attribute that's associated with the drink object,
and that cost is going to be processed by this make_payment method from the money machine.
And then finally, it's going to tell us whether if this was successful or not.
So let's see what happens when we run this code as it is.
Let's say I wanted a latte,
notice how it's asking me to insert coins:
how many quarters, how many dimes, how many nickels and how many pennies. A the coffee machine,
I don't actually need to care about how the money and the coins are processed.
All I had to do is call make_payment and it deals with all of this automatically.
Finally, it gives me the change and it returns true, telling me that this make_payment was indeed
successful.
If you actually look inside the money_machine code, then you can see that it has a method called process_
coins, but it's called when make payment is triggered.
This class is going to process coins, and then it's going to decide whether if it was successful
or not. And if it was successful, it's going to add the cost to the profit,
and if not, it's going to tell you that that was not enough money and your money is refunded.
Coming back over here, if this is successful, then that means the user has managed to pay and we fulfilled
step 3 and 4 just using one method.
The final thing we have to do is to actually make the coffee.
And that, of course, happens right at the end here.
And all we have to do to make the coffee is get hold of the coffee maker object and then call the make_
coffee method and we can pass in the order, which is our drink.
Because remember that the make_coffee method expects a menu item as the input parameter.
We can actually simplify this code even more by saying, well, if the coffee maker is_resource_sufficient
and the money machine was able to take payment, well then we can get the coffee_maker to make coffee.
So now let's go ahead and run our code.
And let's report to begin with, to see how much resources we have to begin with.
And then let's order a coffee.
Insert lots of money and we've got our coffee back.
So now let's go ahead and order a different coffee, latte, and let's go ahead and insert lots of money.
And you can see, here's my latte.
But now, if I hit report, you can see that the objects, the coffee maker has been managing our resources
and the money_machine has been managing our profit.
Now, if I decided to order another latte, then it should actually tell me, sorry, there's not enough
water and there's not enough milk. So it can't make me that drink.
And we've managed to achieve all of this functionality by writing very few lines of code, and the code
itself is actually very, very easy to understand.
Even if you came to this completely fresh, you've never seen how each of the methods are implemented,
you don't know how the coffee maker works,
you don't know how the money machine works,
you can see quite easily what it's trying to do.
And so if you only have to write this kind of code, then it would make it so much easier to create
even more complex functionality in your coffee machine, right?
So have a play around with these classes:
the coffeeMaker, the moneyMachine, the menu, the menu item, etc. And see what else it is that
you can do with this code
while not touching any of the blueprints for each of these classes.
Now, in the next lesson, I'm going to be showing you how to create your own classes so that you can
actually start structuring your code using full object-oriented programming.
And we're going to learn about these things like the initialization and how classes are declared and
why there's all this self all over the place.
That's all yet to come on tomorrow's lessons.
Hey guys, welcome to day 17 of 100 Days of Code. Now,
today
we're going to be focusing on how we actually create the classes that we've been
using in yesterday's lessons.
Today's final project that we're going to be building up towards is a quiz game.
So we're going to be able to create a true-false quiz,
and we'll be able to play the quiz,
answer the questions and keep track of score.
But we're gonna be building this completely using Object Oriented Programming. We're
going to be creating our classes ourselves and then using the objects created
from those classes in order to build this game. And once you're done,
this is what you'll be able to create. Question one, A slug's blood is green,
true or false. True. Now,
if you want to have a play around with the final project to get a feel for how
it works,
then you'll find a link to this final version of the quiz game in the course
resources. But once you're ready,
then head over to the next lesson and we're going to get started by learning how
to create our own custom classes. So, for all of that and more,
I'll see you there.
Throughout all of yesterday, we've been using other people's classes.
And we said that a class is simply just a blueprint for creating an eventual
object. In this lesson,
we're going to talk about how we can create our own classes,
so our own blueprints, which we can use to create our own objects.
Now let's go ahead and create our own custom classes in code.
Go ahead and create a new project either in PyCharm or Repl.it wherever you
prefer. And we're going to name it day-17-start,
and then hit create. And again, as always,
once you've created your project, it's time to create your first file
which we're going to name main.py.
And then we can collapse our project sidebar and focus on the code.
So how do we create a class? The syntax looks very simple.
You have the "class" keyword followed by the name of your class and then a colon
.
and then all of the code that's in your class will follow this and it will be
indented. Let's create our very first class in Python.
As I mentioned,
the way that we would create a class is first by using the class keyword.
And then we get to give our class a name.
Let's say that we're building a website and we need a class to model our website's
users.
So this class is basically going to be the blueprint to represent what our
users have and what they can do on our website.
Let's call our class User
and then we finished this declaration with a colon as usual. And everything
else that's going to go inside
this class is going to need to be indented after the colon.
Let's start out with a completely empty class.
Our user class is going to do absolutely nothing for now. However,
because I've created my blueprint
I can already use it to create my first user object.
So let's say I wanted to create a user_1
and I'm going to create it using that class,
which notice it's now being recognized by PyCharm,
and it's got the C symbol next to it. And of course,
to initialize an object from a class,
we have to add the parentheses at the end.
Now we get an error here because there's an indent expected.
So basically Python doesn't like it
when you create something like a class or when you create something like a
function and you have a colon,
but you don't have anything inside that function or class. For example,
if I just immediately wanted to print "hello" afterwards,
I get exactly the same error; indent expected.
It's expecting this function that you've created or this class
you've just created to have some sort of content before you go ahead and do something
else. So how can we fix this? Well,
if we actually really want to leave this function or this class empty,
we can use a keyword which is pass.
And all it does is it just passes. It says, I don't want to have a go right now.
Just continue to the next line of code. And this gets rid of our errors
both in the function declaration
as well as in our class declaration. We've now essentially completed the
first step towards creating our custom classes,
which is writing the declaration and then building an object called user_1 out
of that class. And we've also seen how to name classes in Python.
Now the name of the class should have the first letter of every word
capitalized.
And this particular style of naming in Programming is known as Pascal case.
So if you think of Blaise Pascal as a person,
then we know that everybody's name,
every person's name, has the first letter capitalized and also the first letter
of their surname or their middle name
and basically every subsequent name capitalized. Now,
this is different from another type of casing which you may have come across
which is called camel casing.
And camel casing is only different from Pascal case because the first word is
lowercase, but every subsequent word it has it's first letter capitalized in
exactly the same way as Pascal case. And finally,
we've also come across snake case where all the words are lowercase
but they're separated by
an underscore. In Python programming, you won't see a lot of camel casing.
You will see Pascal case being used for the class names,
snake case being used pretty much to name everything else.
Now that we've seen how we can create a new class.
Even if it's a class with nothing inside.
And we've seen how we can create a new object from that class
by using the same code that we used in yesterday's lessons.
The next question is: "Well, how do we create an attribute for that class?". Well,
one of the easiest ways of doing this is simply tapping into your object and
then adding an attribute.
So we could say user_1.id =
"001".
And we could add as many attributes as we want just by using this method of
using the dot notation after the name of the object,
and then just adding any piece of data we want. So now,
if I go ahead and print user_1.username,
you'll see that this attribute now exists in this object
[Inaudible]
And you can see the value that's held in that attribute being printed in the
console. So just a quick reminder,
an attribute is a variable that's associated with an object.
So it's almost as if we just created a new variable, but in this case,
we've attached it to an object. But here's a question though,
if we had lots and lots of attributes like this,
and every single time we create a new user,
let's say we created user_2 and we had to do the same thing,
create it from the class and then say,
user_2.id = "002",
and user_2.username
= "jack". And this is one,
a little bit prone to error because it's perfectly valid for me to make a typo
or change the name of an attribute where I end up with something like this.
So is there a way of making this simpler?
How can I specify all these starting pieces of information
when I create my object from the class? Now,
in order to do this, we have to understand something called a constructor,
which is a part of the blueprint that allows us to specify what should happen
when our object is being constructed.
And this is also known in programming as initializing
an object. When the object is being initialized,
we can set variables or counters to they're starting values. In Python,
the way that we would create the constructor is by using a special function,
which is the init function.
And you can tell it's special because it isn't just the Def keyword
and then the name of the function. It's got two underscores
either side of the name.
And this means that it's a method that the Python interpreter knows about and
knows that it has a special function. Now,
what is the special function? Well, it's normally used to initialize the attributes.
So if inside our class
we add this init function and you can see as soon as I write def and then
init, I've really got autofill helping me so I can just hit enter
once it's selected. Now,
inside this init function is where we initialize or create the starting
values for our attributes. Now,
the important thing to remember is that the init function is going to be called
every time you create a new object from this class.
For example, if I print,
then every time that this construction happens
when we create a new user,
then this print statement is going to be triggered.
So you can see here, this print statement gets triggered
and then we print the user_1's username, and then we've got
another user being created. Just as a quick reminder,
the attributes are the things that the object will have.
And they are basically just variables that are associated with the final
object. So for example, if you're constructing a car bject,
then one of those attributes could be the number of seats it has and
normally that's equal to five.
So how do we set these attributes in the constructor? Well,
this is what the code would look like.
We have our init function and inside the init function
in addition to this thing called self
which is the actual object that's being created or being initialized,
in addition, you can add as many parameters as you wish.
And that parameter is going to be passed in when an object gets constructed from
this class. And once you receive that data,
then you can use it to set the object's attributes.
This is what it would look like when we actually call our constructor.
We know that we can create an object by calling the name of the class and then
adding the parentheses. But if inside our init function
we have some additional parameters,
then we can also pass in data to those parameters
which will be used to set the attributes for that object.
So in this case, once this line of code has completed,
then my_car.seats is going to be equal to five.
And this is exactly the same as if we created our
my_car object first and then we said my_car.seats = 5.
It's completely the same.
But it does make it a lot quicker when you're creating a lot of objects that
need all the same attributes. Let's see how we would do it here.
We've got our init function already declared.
So if we wanted to pass over a user ID
when we construct our objects, we can add that as a parameter
and then inside the init we can say self.id,
so self.id is going to be the attribute that's associated with this class
and we can set it equal to the user_id that's passed in when any user gets
constructed. So now when we create our user,
instead of creating these attributes later on, at the time of construction
you can already see that we can add a user ID.
So let's give it the same ID.
And now let's add another attribute.
So we're going to pass in the username and I'm going to set the attribute
self.username equal the username that's past it.
Notice how in this case I've named my parameter user_id
and that value is going to become the self.id attribute.
So notice how these two actually have different names.
You can name either of these anything you want.
It's normally convention that you will see the name of the parameter be equal to
the name of the attribute, but you don't always have to stick to these rules.
Now let's go back to our constructor whereas previously it was empty,
now we have our user ID being passed in and I can now pass in the second
attribute, which is the username. So my username was going to be Angela.
And now we've created a new user,
which is user_1 from this user class
and we're initializing it with these starting values where the first value is
going to become the user ID which is going to be the self.id,
and the second value is going to become the self.username. So now,
if I wanted to print the user_1's username,
then I can simply write
user_1.username exactly the same way as before,
or if I wanted the ID, it would be user_1.id.
So now let's comment out the rest of the code and hit run,
and you can see we've got the user ID being printed here. Now,
remember that when you add parameters to the constructor
which is the init function,
you're now saying that whenever a new object is being constructed from this
class, it must provide these two pieces of data.
If we uncomment this and you try to run it, you'll see you get an error.
And it says that on line 12,
this user is being created from the user class.
But according to the init, we're actually missing two required arguments;
user ID and username.
So now when we create any object from this class,
we have to provide the user ID and the username.
But this is now much more convenient, right?
While we previously needed three lines of code, we now only have one.
Now sometimes when we're creating our attributes,
we might want a default value to start with.
And if at some later point in our program we want to modify it,
then we'll do it at that point.
But it doesn't make sense for all attributes to be initialized when we actually
create our object. So if, for example, in our case,
let's say that we were coding up the Instagram app, right? Well,
each of the Instagram users, they would have an ID,
they would have a username and they would probably have a follower count.
So they might have something like self.followers.
This is always going to start out as zero, right? You start a new account,
you're going to have zero followers. You might get some followers later on,
you might not.
But it doesn't make sense for followers to be something that we have to provide
whenever we construct a new object.
It seems very wasteful to have to always write zero
when you construct any object from this class. So in Python,
we can also provide a default value just as I've done here.
Instead of setting it equal to one of the parameters that's being passed in when
this class is being initialized, instead I'm just setting it to a value,
which is zero. Let's get rid of that from the initializer
because we now have a default value of zero.
And if I go ahead and print my, let's say,
user_1.followers attribute, and I hit run,
then you can see it's zero because all objects being created from this class will
have a followers attribute that set out to zero to begin with.
In addition to creating attributes, we know that we can also create methods.
The attributes are the things that the object has and the methods
are the things that the object does.
Let's say that we were creating the car class and we've really created the seats
attribute. Well, later on
we might decide that we want to call a method to change that seats attribute's
value. So for example, I've been watching a lot of truck racing recently.
Yeah.
[inaudible]
And one of the things that people do when they mod their cars for racing is they
take out some of the seats. This way it reduces the weight of the car,
and it means that you can go a bit faster. So in our car class,
we might, in fact,
have a method where the car can enter race mode,
where the seats are dropped from 5 to 2.
This is what the method would look like. Inside the class declaration,
we have a function, but remember when a function is attached to an object
then it's called a method.
This method looks exactly the same as how we've created other functions.
We have the Def keyword, we have the name of the method,
we have some parentheses which can take inputs, a colon,
and then the body of the method. So in this case,
all it does is it gets hold of the object and then the object seats attribute
and then changes it to 2. So now when you call that method,
all you need to do is get hold of the object and then you use the dot notation
to call that method enter_race_mode, and of course,
with the parentheses at the end.
So let's say that while we're modeling our Instagram user,
we want to have a way for the users to follow each other, right?
And when they follow each other, their follower counts obviously go up.
So let's define a new method. So we're going to use the def keyword
and then we're going to name our method follow. Now a method,
unlike a function, always needs to have a self parameter as the first parameter.
This means that when this method is called,
it knows the object that called it. Now,
in addition to that self parameter,
we're also going to pass in the user that we've decided to follow.
So now let's say that we actually had two attributes,
the followers and the following count, right?
So they both start from zero, so two default attributes.
But when a user decides to follow another user,
well in this case,
the user who we're following, their follower count goes up by one and our own,
so the self.following count goes up by one as well.
So the self keyword becomes quite important when we're working with classes and
objects. It's a way for us to refer to the object
that's going to be created from this class inside the class blueprint.
So you'll never see self when you're using objects
but you see it a lot when you're writing your code inside your class.
Now let's go ahead and call this.
And let's say that user_1 decided to follow
user_2. This is the user_1 object,
and this is the follow method from the user_1 object.
And then the user_2 is the person who we're going to follow.
So now let's go ahead and print the user_1's
follower count and the user_1's following count.
And let's do the same for user_2 as well.
You can see once this method has run,
then user_1's follow account is still zero,
but user_1 is now following one person.
User_2 has one followers and has zero people that it's following.
Right?
Now that we've seen how to create our own custom classes,
we're finally ready to build the quiz game.
Now this game is going to be a simple true/false game.
So a question will be asked to the user and they'll select true or false,
and then we'll tell them if they got it right or wrong and give them a score.
Now to begin, the first step you'll need to do is to download the zip
file it with all the starting code from our course resource website.
Alternatively,
if you are already logged in on Repl.it simply fork the project and then click
on these three dots to download the zip file here.
And once you've extracted the actual folder, quiz-game-
start from the.zip file, then we're ready to go ahead and open it
using PyCharm. In PyCharm
we're going to click open and then we're going to navigate to the place where we
have our quiz-game-start, which in my case is in the downloads folder.
PyCharm should automatically configure the latest version of Python you've got
installed as the interpreter.
So you can go ahead and close these popups.
And if we open up our quiz-game-start folder,
you can see we have four files, data,
main, question_model and quiz_brain.
And over the course of the next few lessons,
we're going to be writing the code in all of these files so that we end up
creating our final quiz project.
The first task that we have is to create a model for a question in our quiz.
If we had a question object, well what kind of attributes should it have?
It might have a text attribute for the question texts,
and it might also hold an answer attribute
which is going to be the correct answer to that question. Now,
these two attributes should be initialized with a value
when a new question object is created from this class.
For example, if our first question was 2 + 3 = 5,
which we know the correct answer should be true. Well,
then we might write the code like this to actually initialize a new question
object. And when this initialization goes through the constructor code inside the
question class
will take these two pieces of data and then add them to the corresponding
attributes, the text and the answer.
And so our new question object will have both of these attributes initialized
with a value
when a new question object is being created. Inside your project,
go over to the question_model.py file,
and go ahead and create a new class called question
and that question class should have an init method
which will initialize two attributes,
the text and the answer just as you've seen in the previous slides.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge by creating this
class.
Right.
All right. So we know that to create a class,
we first have to use the class keyword. And then in our case,
the name of the class is going to be called Question because we're modeling what
a question would be like in our game.
We know that each of these questions have two attributes;
a self.text and a self.answer.
And those two attributes are going to be initialized
when we create a new question object. So we need the init function in here.
And we're pretty much going to use the autofill.
So once you write Def and then you write init,
you can see it in the dropdown list and then just hit enter
and the code will be inserted automatically. This way
you don't have to remember the exact order of the parentheses or where to put
the colon, et cetera, et cetera. Now, inside the init function,
we're going to set up two attributes as we said.
One is going to be called text and one is going to be called answer.
And if we want to create an attribute, we have to use this syntax,
self. and then the name of the attribute,
because eventually when we create a new object from this class
say a new question object, then we're going to be passing in these two items,
a piece of text which is going to be the question,
and then either true or false as the answer. And then later on
if we wanted to access the text,
then we would say new_q.text.
Now of course at the moment,
these are all yellowed out because it seems to have no effect.
There's no way of receiving a value for each of these attributes.
And to do that, we have to add some inputs inside the init function.
So let's just call it q_text and a q_answer.
You can of course call these parameters anything you want.
But the important part is you set the self.text to that first value and the
self.answer to the second value.
So now when we actually go ahead and print this new_q.text
object like we have here,
then it will go ahead and actually fetch this value into the output.
If you go to run and then run and then select a question model,
you can see that is what gets printed in the console.
Let's delete those two lines and now we have completed our first task,
which is creating our question class from scratch.
Now in the last lesson,
we created our question class. In this lesson,
we're going to be creating a question bank of question objects.
Notice how we can create a question object by using the name of the class and
then giving it some inputs for the question and the answer. Now,
if we create a whole bunch of those and then put them into a list like this,
then we can create a question bank of questions to use in our quiz.
If you take a look inside the data.py file,
you'll see that I've already included a whole bunch of questions inside here,
and you can see it's got some text and it's got some answer.
So the exact structure of this file is that it's got a whole bunch of
dictionaries, 12 in total,
and all of these dictionaries are saved inside a list
and that list is called question_data. Now, when you first come onto this file
you'll see some warnings, these little yellow squiggly lines.
And the reason is because it would expect for proper formatting,
each of these dictionaries should be indented inside the list. Now,
in terms of actual functionality, this won't change anything.
The indentation of the items in a list are not as important as the indentation
in say a method or a for loop.
But it's still better to get rid of all of these warnings.
So what we're going to do is we're going to select everything inside this file,
we're going to go to code and then auto-indent lines.
And this you'll notice has now auto-indented
all of the dictionaries inside the list.
Now you'll still notice some red squiggly lines. So in this case,
the reason is because the line is too long, it's greater than 120 characters.
You can see that's where the cutoff is. So in PyCharm
it's really easy to separate lines.
If you just identify a good spot in that line, hit enter,
and it will automatically add some quotation marks around it so that it still
behaves the same way as before, but now it's on separate lines.
And I'm going to do the same to line 8 as well.
Now the final warning expect a new line at the end of the file,
so it let's give it that.
And the last thing that you'll notice here is that there's a squiggly line here
under Backrub because that is a unknown word in the dictionary.
So if you want to, you can actually save words into the dictionary
to you get rid of all of these squiggly lines.
This is actually a name of a company,
so it's probably not going to be in the dictionary.
But if you go ahead and put your cursor on it like this,
you'll see a little light-bulb light up and you can go ahead and select save
'Backrub' to project-level dictionary,
and that will get rid of all of your warnings and errors
and you'll see a nice green check mark in the right corner.
Now that we've done all of this formatting with the data,
let's really examine it. What we have here is a list of dictionaries.
Each of the dictionaries have the same key for the question text and the same
key for the question answer.
So what we need to do is we need to be able to bring this question data into the
main.py file. But instead of having a list of dictionaries,
we want a list of question objects.
We know already that we can create a new question object by simply constructing
one from the question and then giving it the required inputs.
But in order to do this inside the main.py file,
we, of course, have to import the question model and we'll also need to import the
data.py. So from the question model
I'm going to import the question class, and from the data file
I'm going to import the question data.
Now that you've got both the question data and the question class,
your goal is to create the question bank.
And once you're done,
it should contain a list of question objects
each being initialized with a question and an answer,
and the data is going to come from these dictionaries from the question data.
So you'll need to think about how you can loop through that question data in
order to create this list of question objects.
Pause the video and give that a go now.
All right. So we know that we need to create this question bank
which is going to be a list of question objects.
So I'm going to start out just by creating an empty list
and then I'm going to loop through each of the questions inside the question
data. And for each of these questions,
I'm going to create a variable, which we'll call a question_text
and the question_text is going to come from those question dictionaries from
here. And if we imagine
we have one of these dictionaries and we want to get hold of the question_text,
then we'll need to tap into the text key.
So I'm going to put text inside here and I'm going to do the same thing for the
answer.
So this is going to be using the answer key that we see right here.
So now if we're looping through the first one, we should have 'A slug's
blood is green.' and 'True' for these two variables.
So now I'm ready to create my new question,
which is going to be created from the question class.
And you can see that in the constructor, it's expecting two parameters;
one is the q_text and another is the q_answer.
We can set the q_text to this local variable called question_text,
and we can set the answer to the question_answer. And of course,
for simplicity sake,
we can also get rid of the named parameters and have them just as the parameters
like this.
So now that we've created this new question object and saved it in the variable
new_question, we're ready to add it into our question bank.
So we can say a question_bank.append,
and we'll append each of these new questions that we create in the for loop.
So now if I go ahead and print this question bank,
you'll see that when I hit run and select my main file,
then it prints out a list denoted by the square brackets and inside the list
you've got a whole bunch of question objects. And if you count,
there's actually 12 in total,
one for each of the dictionaries inside our question_data.
So very often when you're getting data from the
internet or from somewhere else, it'll likely be in a format
that's very similar to this. What we're doing is we're converting each of these
pieces of data which has a string key,
which means it's very easy to make typos
if we're using this in our code everywhere,
and we're converting it into a object
which now has all of that data in a very easy and foolproof way of accessing the
text and the answer. And you'll notice here,
if I actually write the wrong thing,
then it's actually going to highlight to me
this is not something that you can use. And if I start typing,
I've also got the help of the auto-insert.
Now that we've created our question bank of question objects, the next step is to
actually get our quiz up and running.
Now that we've managed to create a question bank
which consists of a list of question
objects, the next natural thing to do is to actually bring up one of those
questions and to ask the user to answer the question. Now,
for all of the questioning and quizzing functionality,
we're going to put that into the QuizBrain,
which is going to be a class in its own right.
And it's going to manage everything from asking the user for the next question,
checking whether if the answer was right and also checking to see if we're
actually at the end of the quiz.
You're going to be creating this QuizBrain and class
and this class is going to have two attributes to begin with; a question number
which is going to have a default value of zero
because all our quizzes will start from the first question.
And this is going to keep track of which question the user is currently on.
And we're going to use that number to go through the list of questions
which will be passed over to this QuizBrain object when it gets initialized.
And then you're going to have a method which is called next_question
which will pull up the question from that list
depending on which current question number we're on.
If you take a look at the final version of the quiz game,
you can see that it displays the question number, Q. and then that number.
And then it displays the question text,
and then it asks the user for an input, true or false.
This is what we're going to be focusing on in this lesson.
Inside your quiz-game-start,
go to the quiz_brain file and create the quiz brain class.
Add those two attributes; one is the question number
which starts out with a default value and the other is the question list
which is going to be initialized when you create a new quiz brain.
And we're going to be passing over this question bank here into this question
list when we initialize a new QuizBrain.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge.
Right?
All right. So let's start off by creating our new class
which is going to be called QuizBrain and inside this class, we'll need to
initialize some of those attributes,
so I'm going to create the init method. Inside the init method
I'm going to create that first attribute which was called question_number
and I said we would set it to have a default value of zero.
So this means every time we create a new QuizBrain
object from this class,
it's ready going to have an attribute called question_number that set to zero.
Now the next attribute is called question_list,
and this is not going to have a default value. Instead,
it's going to get it as a value passed over.
So lets put that as a q_list here and set it equal to question_list.
So what's going to happen is inside our main.py file,
we're going to be initializing that QuizBrain and the value that we're going to
put in there as the question list is going to be the question bank. This way
we'll receive the question bank and it will be inside this question list
attribute. Now I have another challenge for you.
Create a method called next_question inside the QuizBrain.
This method needs to retrieve the item at the current question number from the
question list. And once you have this item,
use the input function to show the user the question text and ask for the
user's answer. Pause the video and give this a go.
Alright, here's the solution.
First we're gonna define a new method called the next_question,
and this method is basically going to get hold of the current question and that
is of course going to be from the question list.
And then we're going to tap into that list and get hold of the item at the
current question_number. So for example,
question_number is going to start out being zero
and so it's going to go into this list
which is basically going to be our list of questions from our main.py,
so our question bank.
And remember, each of the items inside that list is a question object and
question objects have text attributes and answer attributes.
So in addition to getting hold of the current question,
we can then get hold of the current question text by taking the current question
and then just simply writing .text to get the value that's saved in that
attribute.
We're going to use an input to ask the user for
what their answer is to this question.
This is going to be an fstring because we're going to be inserting the current_
question.text. And at the very beginning
if you remember,
we also have the Q. and then the number and then the colon.
So that will be the self.question_number.
And then we've got our colon and then it's going to be the question text.
And then we're going to ask the user for a input; true or false.
And that's it. That completes the challenge.
Now all that's left is to show the very first question to the user and run our
code. Let's go back to the main.py and import the QuizBrain class.
So we're going to say from the quiz_brain file import the QuizBrain class.
And once we've created our question bank,
then the next thing to do is to create our new quiz.
So this is going to be a new QuizBrain object
and when we initialize it, we have to pass in a list of questions.
And that is of course going to be the question bank.
So now that we've got our quiz up and running,
then we can say quiz.next_question.
Let's go ahead and run this main.py file.
And you can see we get our question text being displayed, true or false being
asked, but our question number starts from zero.
And that is, of course,
because we need zero here in order to get hold of the first question from the
list and that's why this has a default value of zero.
But by the time we reach this input,
it would be really good if this actually read one instead of zero.
So one way we could do this is we could do this plus one,
but remembering that we actually need to increase the question number every
single time we call next_question anyways,
then once we've gotten hold of the current question,
we can actually tap into that self.question_number and increase it by one.
This will have the same effect,
and if you look at it now we've got the right question number being shown here,
the right text being shown, and then we can insert true or false.
Now at this stage,
our program is just going to exit. In the next lesson,
we're going to have to work out a way for our questions to keep being asked. And
we'll need to write some more code for that to work.
In the previous lesson,
we managed to get our QuizBrain up and running and to start asking the user for
their answer.
But currently, there's no way for our program to continue to the next question
once the user has typed an input. However,
if we take a look at the final version of the quiz game,
you can see once the user's typed an input, it
then goes to the next question and shows them the question number 2
and the question text for that second question.
How can we create that functionality to work with our QuizBrain?
Well,
if we could create another method called still_has_questions
well then inside our main.py we could probably create a while loop and
the while loop checks
if the quiz still has questions remaining.
Well, then in that case, we're going to keep going to the next question.
So how do we create this functionality and how do we create it inside the
QuizBrain? Your job is to create a new method here
which is going to be called still_has_questions.
And this is going to return a boolean, either true or false.
And depending on that boolean,
we can get our while loop to keep working and keep running and looping,
or we're going to get the loop to stop
once the quiz has run out of questions.
Here's the behavior that you're looking for by the end of the challenge.
The while loop should continue serving up the next question to the user until we
reach the end of the quiz.
Have a think about how the question number and the length of the question list
relate to each other and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right.
So we know that we can get the length of our question list by using the Len
function. Currently, in all the current version of the question bank,
we have 12 questions in total.
So the length is going to be 12.
Now we want our loop to keep going until we've reached the number of questions
in our list.
What we could do is we could check to see if the self.question_number is
less than the length of self.question_list. In that case, we'll return true,
but otherwise we'll return false.
Remember that this question number gets increased every time we show the user
the next question. It starts out being zero
and then it goes immediately to one.
And then we get to the end of the next question function
and we get to our while loop. So in our while loop,
we can check to see if the quiz still has questions.
And if this is true, then go to the next question. But if it's false,
then exit the loop and we're at the end of the game.
Back inside our QuizBrain
we can actually simplify this method even more because we know that this is
going to be evaluated by the computer
and it's going to be either that true or false. If it is it's true
then it goes into this block. And if it's false,
then it goes into the else block.
We can actually save ourselves all of this effort by
simply just returning this expression. Now,
what it's going to do is, let's say that a = 5 and b =
3.
And if we were to return five is
greater than three,
then this is basically the same as this expression
which gets evaluated by the computer. And when this code runs,
it's going to be either true or it's going to be false. So that
that value is then going to be straight away
returned by this method back into this while loop
to see if we should continue going to the next question or not.
So let's run this file and you can see it asks me the first question.
And then it's going to go to the next question.
And then it's going to basically keep going until it gets to the end of the list
of questions and then it
ends our entire program. In the next lesson
we're going to figure out how we can check the answer that the user has inputted
here and see if its actually the correct answer.
Currently when we run our code
you can see that while we can input our answer,
our code doesn't actually really care because it's not checking to see if it's
right or wrong. In this lesson
we're going to add one more method to our QuizBrain
and that's the ability to check the answer that the user inputted and see if it
was correct. And that means we need to keep track of the user's score.
So we'll add another attribute score
which has a default value of zero to begin with
and it'll increase every time they get a question right. So in this lesson,
we're going to create a new method called check_answer.
And this check_answer function is going to be used to see if the user's answer
which comes from this input is the same as the actual answer to the current
question.
What we need to do is we need to save this user's input inside a variable
which we'll call user_answer.
And then I'm going to call our check_answer method
and I want to pass over the user_answer. Now, in addition,
I also want to pass over the correct answer and the correct answer is going to
be the current_question.answer.
So let's replace that with current_question.answer
because we know that current_question is a question object
which has a text attribute and an answer attribute.
And once we've passed over the user's answer and the correct answer,
then we can receive it inside our check_answer function as a parameter.
So we'll call this user_answer
and the second one we'll call the correct_answer.
So now this input is going to be passed over here
and the correct answer is going to be under this variable name.
So now we can see if the user_answer is equal to the correct_answer.
And just for safety sake,
it's usually a good idea to drop both sides to
a lowercase so they are comparable. This way
just in case the user answers True or true,
it will be treated exactly the same.
If the user_answer matches the correct answer, well
then this means that they got it right, so let's print it.
But on the other hand, if that was false then that means they got it wrong.
So let's tell them that's wrong.
Now it might also be a good idea to tell the user what the actual correct answer
was. Now you have a choice depending on where you want to put that.
So you can either choose to only show them the correct answer if they got it
wrong like this.
But I think it's actually a good idea to show them the correct answer
even if they're got it right.
So I'm going to change the indentation so that it's actually outside of the
if/else block,
and it's just simply going to happen once the if/else block is complete.
Now, the next thing to do is to keep track of the user's score so that every
time they get a question right then it should increase the score by one.
Pause the video and add a new attribute called score to the QuizBrain class and
increment it by one every time the user gets it right. Now,
what you're aiming for is to be able to print out the score and the current
question so that you can tell the user 'Your current score is:' and printed out
after every single question.
Pause the video now and complete this challenge.
All right. So let's go ahead and create our new score attribute
which is again going to have a default starting value of zero.
And then whenever the user gets a question right,
then we're going to increase their score by one.
So let's tap into that score attribute and then increase it by one.
Now we've got our score being tracked,
then we want to be able to print out what the users' current score is.
So at the end of the check_answer, let's create another print statement
which gives the user their score.
So 'Your current score is:'
and then we'll insert the self.score.
And we'll also tell them out of a possible number of questions,
so we can insert the self.question_number.
So this means that they've completed five questions so far where they've had
five chances to get things right
then we can show them that they got however many right out of those five.
So maybe they got 3/5 right, or maybe they got 5/5
right. And now if we run our code,
we can see that print statement in action.
So it tells me that I got it right and then the--
and then the correct answer was true.
And that my current score is 1/1.
Right
Now, if I get one of these wrong,
then you can see that my current score is now 3/4.
And it tells the user that they've missed out on one point.
It'd be nice to add a little bit of space in between each of the questions.
I want to be able to see all the questions that I've done so far.
So I don't want to clear the screen,
but I want to be able to add a new line here.
So at the end of my print statement, I'm going to add a print
which is just going to print a new line.
So that in between each question
I have a little bit of space to tell each question apart from the other.
The final thing I need to do is to tell the user
their final score once the entire quiz is finished,
and we want to be able to print something like 'You've completed the quiz' and
then we'll print out, um,
something like 'Your final score was:'
and then we'll give them their final score so maybe they got 10/12
correct. And this way they can see what their final outcome was.
So have a think about how you might be able to print these two lines here
and how you can get hold of the question number and the user's score to print
inside our main.py. So pause the video and complete this challenge.
All right. So the first line is very easy to print.
All we need to do is wrap a print statement around it.
The second line is a little bit more tricky because it will need to have an
fstring.
So we want this second value to be the total number of questions in the question
bank,
or it could be the current question number that the user is on.
You can do either.
You can either say question bank and wrap a length function around it,
like this, which will give you the total number of questions
cause we're at the end of the quiz now. Alternatively,
you can also tap into the quiz object and get the question number when the quiz
ended. And similarly with the score,
you can say quiz.score.
So now once the quiz has completed,
you can see our print statements. You've completed the quiz and your final score
was 0/12 because I was just button mashing and it didn't get any
questions right.
So I'm sure you've had a few gos with your quiz now
and you've answered all the questions and you know all the correct answers.
It's a little bit dry if we only have one question bank, right?
Wouldn't it be nice to be able to switch out the question data with some new
questions? Now you could certainly write your own questions,
just change each of the texts and the answers to whatever question you want to
add. An alternative though, is to use the Open Trivia database,
which is a free-to-use user contributed trivia question database
and it has over 3000 verified questions to pick from. In the course resources
I've got a link to the open TDB, the open trivia database,
and we can go ahead and take a look at their API to see how we can generate some
questions. For example, if I wanted 10 questions on,
let's say computers and I want the difficulty to be easy
and I want to select the type to be true or false
And then I'm going to go and click generate API URL.
Now that I've got my URL,
I can open up a new tab and go to that location.
Now, we'll get some data generated in a JSON format
which is a JavaScript object notation
but it actually looks pretty much the same as a Python dictionary.
So let's go ahead and copy everything that's here and then go into our data.py
and I'm going to replace the entire question data with what I got just now.
Now once you paste it in, it's going to be very hard to read.
So we'll need to go to code and then reformat code in order to get it to look a
little bit more normal.
So you can see that we've got this dictionary and it has two key-value pairs.
One is a response code and another is a list which is under the key results.
If I go and reformat this again,
you can see that results is comprised of 10 dictionaries.
Now,
each of these dictionaries contain a whole bunch of key-value pairs and inside
each of these key-value pairs it has a bunch of things
including the category, that type, the difficulty,
the question, the correct answer, and the incorrect answers.
So what we can see here is we have a dictionary and then we have these two key
value pairs.
So you can simply just get rid of the enclosing dictionary and leave it so that
you have this as a list of dictionaries. Now,
if we go and reformat our code so that we can see each of these dictionary
objects,
you can see there's a total of five key value pairs and they each have the keys
category, type, question, which is the question text and the correct answer
which is a string that's true or false.
These are the two bits of information that we're interested in.
So can you figure out how you can modify the main.py in order to get our
quiz to start working again with this new data?
Pause the video and complete this challenge.
All right. So we've got our question data from the data file,
but now we have to change the names of these keys.
Whereas before it was called text and answer,
now it's called question and correct answer.
So the question_text is under the key question and correct answer is under
the key correct _answer.
So just by changing those two things and pasting all of that data in
we can already get started with this brand new quiz. And you can play with it and
mess around with different data from the open trivia database,
change the category, change the difficulty,
and you have endless number of questions to play with.
And this really brings about some of the advantages of Object Oriented
Programming. Notice how only our main.py file actually has knowledge of how each
of these classes work and behave. Our QuizBrain actually didn't need to be
touched at all
when we changed our data over. This is modularity at its best.
We're able to completely switch up the question data to a different language,
to a different topic, to a different format, and the quiz brain doesn't care.
All it has to concern itself with is how to track which question we're on,
how to get the next question, how to check the answer.
And as long as it's able to do that and perform the functionality of a quiz,
it's unconcerned by where the data comes from, how it's formatted,
and it will continue to work. So, as you can imagine,
if your colleague was working on quiz brain,
they don't actually need to know how the data looks or how it's structured.
And you, on the other hand, could be working on the data,
getting hold of each of these pieces of data or writing the quiz.
And you can already see how we've got a piece of program
that's able to be far more complex than what we used to be able to create with
simple procedural code.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 18 of 100 Days of Code. Now,
today, we're going to learn about some really exciting things.
We're going to look deeper into turtle graphics,
starting to do things with graphics, with the help of the turtle module.
And we're also going to be learning about Python tuples as well as looking
deeper into importing modules in Python.
By the end of today,
we will have written some code that is capable of generating million dollar
pieces of odd work. So we're looking at a Damien Hirst,
which sold for 1.275
million pounds a little while ago.
And we're going to be using Python turtle to create a similarly beautiful dot spot
painting,
which could be randomized and create beautiful pieces of art
like this one. Once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and let's get started.
As I mentioned, in this section
we're going to be working heavily with the Python turtle module.
And as we've seen before,
this turtle module is essentially a way for us to be able to draw graphics onto
the screen.
And you can imagine it as just this little wandering turtle with a pen on its
back and everywhere it goes, it leaves a trail of line.
So let's take a closer look at the turtle graphics module. Now here,
I've already created a brand new PyCharm project called day-18-start,
and I've created a blank main.py. Inside this project,
we're going to import our turtle. So as you saw from previous lessons,
we can import the turtle module and get hold of the turtle class
by simply saying from the turtle module,
import the Turtle class with the capital T. And now we can work with that class
and we're going to use it to create a new turtle object.
Let's call it timmy_the_turtle,
and this is going to be created from the turtle class.
So this is going to be a new turtle object saved inside this variable.
Now, when we actually run our project,
you'll see a brief flash of a window
and then it will disappear. In order for that window to stay where it is
and only exit when we actually click on the window,
we have to create another object, which we'll call our screen.
And this comes from the total module as well.
And it's a class called Screen.
We also have to import that if we want to use it.
So now that we've got hold of the screen,
we can use one of the functions called exitonclick.
So this way, when we run our code,
we can see our turtle show up in the middle as this little arrow and our window
won't disappear until we click on it. That's what exitonclick does.
So we need to keep this bit of the code at the very bottom.
It has to happen after we've done all this stuff with turtle.
So I'm going to move it to the bottom of the file. Now here's a question.
How do I know how to do that? Is it because I am super experienced
and I remember everything off the top of my head? No.
Is it because I'm super clever and I can just work things out? No,
that's definitely not the answer.
The way that programmers go about figuring out how to use these modules or
packages is through the use of documentation.
So let's take a look at the turtle graphics documentation.
And this is what the documentation looks like. It's a very,
very long document that goes through all of the things that you can do with this
module. Now, if we scroll down,
you've got a contents page here and you can see the various things you can do
with the turtle. Control it's motion or control the pen or change its visibility
or appearance. Now let's take a look at this shape function,
and you can see the documentation explains to us that this particular function
will set the turtles shape to one with a given name.
And we can choose from the various shapes, including arrow, turtle, circle,
square, triangle, and classic. So
let's use this knowledge and change timmy_the_turtle to have a different shape.
So inside here, we can put any of those strings.
So I'm going to change it to a turtle shape. This way when I run my code,
you can see an actual turtle appear on the screen.
It just makes it a little bit easier to visualize what's going on with this
module. Now, of course you can change it to any of the other ones,
test it out and see if it works. In an ideal world
you would read through the entire documentation of a module before you start
using it. But of course, in the real world,
we all know that that's not quite possible.
Very often you'll need the help of Stack Overflow. For example,
if we wanted to look at turtle graphics and we wanted to change the shape
of the turtle.
Then you can see that when you actually search for this inside the Stack
Overflow search bar, your results are not very relevant.
But if I put the same query into google.com and at the end I tag on the keyword
Stack Overflow, we get results that are a lot more relevant.
So if we take a look at this post,
you can see that it's starting to talk about this shape method.
And down here, this answer even links to the relevant part of the documentation
which we've already seen previously, this shape method.
The idea is that you might need to Google around to see how to achieve a certain
thing you want to do.
And then once you've seen some of the methods that they mentioned in the
answers,
then go to the documentation and read up on it in order to actually understand
what it does and how to use it. Coming back to our turtle,
what if we wanted to change the color of the turtle? Well,
this should be quite easy. We can see that in the color control section,
we can use this color method to set the pen color and fill color.
So for example, we could say timmy_the_turtle.color,
and we can put in a string here like red.
So now when I run my code,
you can see that my turtle timmy is now red instead of the previous default
color of black. Now,
how do I know which colors I can use other than the ones shown in the example,
red or green? Well,
it says that when we want to change the color using a color string or an RGB
color, then it accepts inputs as in pen color.
So it basically says it's using this method to set the color. And this method
gets the color from a Tk color specifications string.
So let's Google and see what that is.
If we click on the first link,
you can see it takes us to the strings and we've got a whole bunch of names and
their corresponding RGB values.
So what is this Tk exactly?
Tk is short for the module tkinter,
which is the Tk interface.
And this is one of the ways that you can use Python to create a graphical user
interface, which is also known as a GUI.
If you think back to the beginning of computer history,
if you think about the Apple Lisa one,
that was the first computer that had a graphical user interface,
where it had a mouse and you can point and click.
And this was huge back in the day.
But before then we had text interfaces like MS-
DOS or like our console when we're using Python.
The text interfaces accept text commands and the graphical user interfaces can
show images and allows you to click and drag and do all of those things by
looking instead of just typing commands. And tkinter is what the turtle module
actually relies on under the hood to create these graphics,
like our turtle showing up here.
So now that we've seen where these names come from,
a much easier way of using these colors is through a page where they have all
been rendered on screen. So in the course resources,
we link to this page where you can see all the colors next to their names,
and you can pick and choose whichever one you want.
Have a go at changing the color of the turtle by using one of these colors that
you see on screen.
Now that we've seen how we can create a new turtle and change its appearance,
it's time to look at how we can make it do certain things. In the documentation,
you can see there's a whole bunch of things you can do in terms of moving and
drawing. A very simple one would be to move it forward or to move it backwards.
So we can tell it to move forwards by a hundred paces.
And when we rerun the code, this is what we see.
So we can get it to move forwards, move backwards, and also move left
and right. So here, the input that it takes is an angle,
a number between zero and 360 to tell it what angle
to turn right or to turn left. For example,
currently our turtle is facing East. So if we wanted to face
South,
then we have to get it to turn right by 90 degrees. So we can say,
timmy_the_turtle.right and then we put 90 in here.
And that's what it looks like. In the upcoming lessons
we've got a whole bunch of turtle challenges for you
that's going to test not only your knowledge of programming that you've learned so
far, but also how well you can read and understand documentation.
This is a key skill to acquire as a seasoned developer because after all,
we can't always rely on other people telling us what to do.
We have to be able to get it from the source.
So make sure that you've got the documentation pulled up and have a glance
through it.
Then you can head over to the next lesson and start tackling some of these
challenges.
Now remember that some of these challenges can be quite a bit of a struggle,
but keep in mind that the struggle is good. The more that you struggle,
the stronger you get. I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right. Now,
the first turtle challenge I've got for you is pretty easy.
It's kind of like doing your stretches before we get started with the proper
workout. So in this challenge, you're going to be using turtle to draw a square.
It's going to be a simple 100 by 100 square,
and it doesn't matter where it is on the screen.
As long as you can get it to draw this, then consider yourself successful.
Pause the video, have a read through the documentation,
have a think about the challenge and go ahead and complete it.
All right.
So I'm going to comment out the previous lines of code other than the line where
we created our timmy_
the_turtle. Now to draw a square is pretty simple.
All we have to do is to get it to go forwards by a hundred paces,
and then we turn left or turn right by 90 degrees.
And then we get it to repeat this process one time for each of the sides.
And when we run the code,
now you can see it draws a simple square. Now,
of course, because we're programmers and we're lazy
and we don't like looking at repeated code, a much simpler way of doing this is
to simply create a for loop.
And we're going to use the range operator to say that this loop should run four
times and then let's indent these two lines of code.
And now it will do exactly the same as before
but this time we've only had to write three lines of code instead of a million.
This is probably the best solution,
but I will also take this solution because after all,
we're just doing the warmup right? Now, while doing that exercise
you might have realized that it's actually really painful to keep calling our
object timmy_the_turtle with such a long name.
But now that we've written it in so many lines
especially if you created this version of the code,
it's actually quite painful to go through each of them and change its name.
Remember in PyCharm
we have a really simple way of changing the name of a variable or a function,
basically anything that we've named ourselves. All we have to do is right-
click on the name, refactor and rename,
and we can change it to something really simple like how about Tim. Now
we've drastically made our code look a lot simpler just by doing that one thing.
I'll try to remind you of some of these shortcuts as we go along,
but once you're ready, head over to the next challenge.
So we're importing the turtle module in order to use it in our code.
So I want to spend a few minutes just quickly talking about all the ways that we
can import modules.
[inaudible]
You've already seen the basic import and it's very simple.
We have the keyword import,
and then we have the module name that we want to import.
So if we had just imported our turtle module with the simple import,
then in order to create a new turtle,
we would have to say the module name and then the name of the class.
And we would create a new turtle like this.
Now this is,
perfectly fine, but it would make it so much more convenient
if we were using that turtle class a lot to write our code like this.
This way, we don't have to keep writing turtle.Turtle or turtle.
whatever else it is that we want to import. And this code is again
pretty simple. We have the keyword from, we have the keyword import,
we have the module name,
and also the thing in the module that we want to import.
As you've seen with this kind of syntax, we can simply write...
And this means that if we were creating a lot of turtles, let's say
instead of just creating tim, we also created tom
and terry.
Then we don't have to keep writing turtle.Turtle,
turtle.Turtle every single time.
So this from import is really helpful
if you're going to use this thing that you're importing a lot and you don't want
to keep writing the name of the module in front of it.
Now you can actually go one step further. Instead of saying
just from turtle import whatever it is you want,
you can actually import everything by using the asterix.
Now you can use everything that's in that module as if it were in the current
file. And this has advantages as well as disadvantages
because it can make it really hard to see where each of these classes or methods
come from. So for example, if I just wrote forward, you can see, I can,
I can do this.
But it's really confusing to just see this method somewhere in isolation
because it's like, well, what is moving forward? What's actually happening,
where does this come from?
And it's more obvious when you import a module like random.
So from random import everything,
and then somewhere else in our code,
we might just write something like choice.
And this is a method from random where we can pick a random item from a
sequence, like a list. Now this code works
but it's really confusing. Like, how is this choice working?
Where does it come from? Which module enables this capability? Instead,
we just have the method whack right in our code
and it's very confusing as to its origins.
So well, amongst the Python community,
it's very unusual that you'll see good code written like this.
I want you to know what it does because you might come across it in the wild,
just so you understand what it's actually doing,
but I want you to try and avoid writing code like this.
Instead if you're using something from a module many times,
so more than three times, then you can think about using this from import.
But if you're only using it once or twice,
then just import the whole module and write out this turtle.Turtle so that
you can see that this module is the one that contains this class and that is
imported and we're using it to create this object.
It's just a lot more expressive in terms of the code.
Now, the final thing I want to show you which is quite a useful thing,
is how to alias modules. So for example,
we can import our turtle as t.
So what this does is we import from the turtle module and we give that module an
alias name, so a name that we define.
And what this means is that if you were to create your new object from the
module turtle, instead of writing out turtle every single time,
you can just write t and that it will represent the entire module.
So sometimes you'll have modules which are really, really long.
So it could have a really long name and you don't want to type it out every
single time.
So you give it an alias name and it will be exactly the same as referring to the
entire name of the module.
And you can create a turtle like this. Now,
even though we've been writing import,
there are some modules that you can't just import, right?
So for example, if I wanted to import the heroes module
which is something that I can use to generate hero names like Decepticon or
Leopardon, or Askew-Tronics,
then I can use one of the functions that's in that module,
heroes, called generate.
But if I just go into my code and I straight up try to import this module
which is called heroes, then you can see I get an error.
And the error says, there's no module named heroes.
Why is it that I can't do this but I can import turtle?
Well, the reason is because turtle is a module that's packaged with the Python
standard library. And this is a small library of code
which contains just the basics to get you started like a core set when you buy a
board game or like the basic track pieces when you buy a set of hot wheels.
So you can imagine this library of code as like a family library,
easily accessible, but very small. Now,
if we wanted to access the whole world of Python modules and packages,
then we need to go to a much bigger library. And that is,
of course, the Python packages,
which are hosted on the internet and we can install into our project as
and when we need them. So this way,
our final project doesn't become gigantic because we've got all of the modules
loaded into it from the internet.
Instead we only plug and play whatever it is we need.
So PyCharm is actually already smart enough to know that I probably want a module
that I haven't installed.
And you can see that as soon as I click on this error with the red underline,
I get a red light bulb over here. And if I click on it,
it gives me the prompt to install this package called heroes.
And once it's done,
then we can actually tap into this module and we can say heroes.gen.
And this is going to generate us a new hero name.
So let's go ahead and run our code.
And you can see we've got a name called Galvatron,
which is not bad actually.
So it's important to remember that when you try to import something that hasn't
been installed, like this villains package,
then when you try to run the code
you'll get an error that says no module named villains.
And this should prompt you to think, ah,
maybe that module is not a part of the Python standard library like turtle
and I actually have to install it.
Just remember that before you can import a module
sometimes if it's not bundled with the Python standard library,
then you might have to install it.
All right. Onwards to the next turtle challenge.
So this one is going to be a little bit more intensive,
but still a bit of a warmup.
So we're just going to go for a light jog and we're going to draw a dashed line.
You're going to get your turtle to draw a line like this
where it's going to draw a line for 10 paces and then a gap of 10 paces,
and then a solid line for 10 paces again
and it's going to repeat this until it does this 50 times.
The actual length of the line doesn't really matter,
the actual length of each of the sections doesn't really matter.
What's really important is you're able to get this alternating draw-
no-draw thing going on. To complete this challenge
you're going to need to look through the documentation and maybe also use the
help of Google or Stack Overflow and figure out how you can get this behavior to
happen. Have a think about it and pause the video and complete the challenge.
All right. So if we look through the table of contents here,
we can see that the thing that controls the pen is in this section.
We can control it's drawing, color, filling and more.
Now if we look at the drawing control you can see
we can get it to pen down and pen up. When we pull the pen down,
that means the pen is on the paper and it's going to make a mark.
But when the pen is pulled up, then there's going to be no drawing happening
when our turtle is moving.
That means we can write some sort of loop, right?
Where we get our turtle to move forwards by 10 paces
and then we can get this to pull the pen up.
And what this is going to do is allow us to move forwards without drawing.
So now, while the pen is held up we're going to go forwards. Once more
another 10 paces this is going to draw the blank. And then finally,
we're gonna go ahead and put the pen down again.
So now, all we need is for these four steps to repeat 15 times so we can write a
for loop and then create a range that goes from 0 to 15.
And then once we indent this block inside the for loop and run our code,
then you can see it draw our dashed line.
Did you manage to get this solution?
Did you manage to find the relevant part of the documentation to be able to pull
the pen up and put the pen down, or did you simply change your code so that it
drew black and then it drew white? All of these solutions would work,
but what I really wanted you to do is to dig through the documentation and find
the parts which will help you to achieve your goals.
Head over to the next lesson
and I've got another slightly harder challenge for you.
All right, so the next challenge gets a little bit harder.
It's like we're doing our sit ups now. In this challenge, you're going to be drawing a triangle, square,
pentagon, hexagon, heptagon, octagon, nonagon, and decagon.
So from three-sided shape to ten-sided shape and each of those shapes is going to be drawn with a random
color, and each of the sides are going to be 100 in terms of length,
and the final outcome should look something like this. All of these shapes overlaid on each other and
drawn out in sequence.
So you'll have to think a little bit about this because we know that a square has 90-degree angles.
So we could get our robot to go forwards and then turn right 90 degrees and then go forwards again.
But what about a Pentagon?
Well, a pentagon,
each of the corners has a 72 degree angle.
So what's the actual relationship?
How can we work this out?
Well, we know that to turn a full circle, it's 360 degrees.
So the way you work out the angle of each of these shapes is by dividing 360 by the number of sides.
So 360 divided by five is 72.
So each of the corners is 72 degrees.
Using this knowledge and what you've learned about Turtle, go ahead and see if you can complete this
challenge.
Pause video now and give it a go.
All right, so I'm going to delete the previous code and we're going to write the code that's going
to draw all of these shapes. The first thing I want to do is I want to put down that equation. So we
know that if we have 360 degrees divided by the number of sides, then we get the angle, right?
So let's save that into a variable called angle.
And then all we have to do is to get our robot to go forwards
by 100, we said. And then to get it to turn right and the angle that it's going to turn right by is
the one that we defined at the top there.
So then we just need this to be repeated for as many times as we have number of sides.
So we could create a for loop, for example.
And the range is going to take into account the number of sites.
So now if the number of sites is equal to let's say five, let's say we're trying to draw a pentagon,
then this would be the code.
So let's shift that along.
And now if we go ahead and run this code,
you can see it draws us a pentagon, a five-sided shape. So how can we get this loop to run for the
different sides?
How can we get it to go from a three-sided shape, a triangle, all the way to a ten-sided shape, a decagon?
To do this, instead of setting the number of sides statically like this,
why don't we create a function? Let's call it draw_shape.
And this function is going to take the number of sides that this shape has as an input.
And then the rest of this code can be indented inside the function.
And it probably makes sense to only calculate the angle once
when we need to draw the shape because for the given number of sides, that angle is going to be the
same across the entire shape.
For example, if it was a square then we're going to go from one to four drawing this four times.
So now later on, we can define another for loop and this for loop is going to go through all of the
different number of sides that we need.
Now, if we want a range of numbers between 3 and 10, we actually need to write the function 3,
11, because the stop number is excluded
so it'll stop at 10. As we loop through this range.
this shape_side_n is going to take on the value depending on where we are in the range.
So when we're first drawing this, we're going to draw a triangle with three sides so then we can pass
this shape_side_n into our draw_shape function and that should go from 3 to 10.
So let's run our code and see it draw our triangle first and then our square and then it just keeps
on going until it draws all of the shapes that we need.
Now, the very last part of the challenge is to make each of the lines a different random color.
So how can we do this?
So, of course, we're going to go to our good friend Google and we're going to search for the turtle
colors in Python.
I first tried to Google this without the python, and I got the different colors of various turtles,
which was really fascinating
but that's not what I wanted.
So if we take a look at the first link
this comes from a website called Trinket, and it has this interactive color palette where you can select
one of these colors that you like and then you'll get the turtle name, which then you can copy and
paste into maybe a list.
Let's call it colors.
And you can put as many colors into this palette as you want, and you can make it as extensive or as
short as you want it to be.
So here's a list that I created earlier.
And now, if we go ahead and set our turtle's color, so let's go ahead and get Tim and set his color to
a random color from this list which we know to be as simple as simply importing the random module
and then we can get hold of the random. choice
and then inside that method, we can pass in our list of colors so that it picks a random color from
that list.
So now let's run it again,
and you can see each time the shape is being drawn it's picking a random color from our list of colors.
So there you have it.
That's the solution to this challenge.
And this was a little bit more challenging I would say because we're doing functions and loops and
you have to get hold of some colors and you have to figure all of that out.
But hopefully you've managed just fine and you're ready to move on to the next challenge.
Now, our next challenge is our press up.
And this challenge is going to require you to draw a random walk.
Well, it's basically your turtle making random movements North, East,
South, or West, each time it progresses by the same distance,
but it can at any point choose which direction it wants to go out of the four.
And also you can see we've kept the color palette from the previous challenge,
and I've just applied it to the random walk so that each time it walks,
it's going to pick a different color.
Now this random walk is something that's used often in mathematics and other
disciplines.
So it's a way that can be used to model various real life situations.
Like for example
the financial status of a gambler or things like the path of a molecule in a
liquid or gas or the search path of a foraging animal,
and a whole bunch of other things. Take a look at this Wikipedia article
which I'll link to and take a look at all the applications
including sculpture making or Physics or brain research and a whole lot more.
So once you're ready,
go ahead and see if you can program your turtle to create a random walk using
random colors.
And I want you to think about how you can get the thickness of the drawing seen
here, so each of the lines is a lot thicker than before.
And also see if you can figure out how you can speed up the turtle so that it
draws much faster. And everything is of course
going to be in the documentation somewhere for you to find. Pause the video and
complete the challenge now.
Alright. So I'm going to delete all the code from our previous challenge,
but I'm going to keep my list of random colors,
which I'm going to use for my random walk here.
Now I'm going to keep the random import
even though it's currently unused because, as you guessed it, our random
walk is going to require some randomness.
So how do we actually get our robot to move in the four different directions?
Well, let's define another list called directions
and this is going to have all of the different directions
the turtle can face. So we'll start from 0
which will be facing East and then 90,
which will be facing North, 180 will be West and 270 will be South.
So now that we've got these random directions,
we can get Tim, our little turtle, to start moving.
So every time we're going to move forward by the same distance,
and it doesn't really matter how far you move your turtle
as long as you set a reasonable number.
So I'm just going to choose 30 and then I'm going to get my turtle to turn in a
random direction.
So I don't want to just use right all the time, so you can use left or right,
and pick a random direction from the list. But alternatively,
you can actually use this set heading. So for example,
we can set it to those four directions.
All we have to do is call setheading and then pass in one of those angles.
That's what we're going to do here.
We're going to use the random module and the random choice method to pick a
random direction.
So now this robot is going to move forwards and then it's going to turn a random
direction. But of course, we want this to loop a few times.
So let's say that we get it to loop 200 times.
I think that should be enough to draw a decent sized image.
Let's set the range to maybe 200 times for this loop to run.
I think that should get us a decent image. Now,
if you chose 300 or 500 or whatever the number, it doesn't matter.
As long as you can get a decent image on screen, then it's perfectly fine.
So we've now satisfied the basic constraints of a random walk
and you can see our turtle is now wandering around this alleyway,
completely aimlessly and modeling a real life process,
like an animal that's hunting for food.
Now let's implement the next part of this.
Let's go ahead and change our code so that it generates a random color for each
step.
That's pretty simple cause we did it before in the last lesson.
So we're going to get Tim to change his color and we're going to use the random
module
and the choice method to pick from all the colors that we've already got in this
list here. Now that it's pretty much random colors,
random walking, the next thing we want to do
if you saw my demo of it is we want to make each of the lines a bit thicker.
So how do we do that? Well, we have to head back to the documentation.
So it's probably going to be one of these methods.
And if we just read through the names of the methods,
they should give us a bit of an indication of which one might be the one that we
want.
If we take a look at the drawing control for our pen,
you can see there's a method called pen size and you can call this either pen
size or width, but it does the same thing. Essentially
it just sets the size of the pen which the turtle draws with.
If we set the pen size to something a little bit wider,
say maybe 15 in width,
then you can see when our turtle draws,
it's now a lot wider and it's a lot easier to
see what it's doing. Now,
the final trick I want to show you is how you can speed up the turtle's
animation. So if I was to wait for it to finish drawing here,
that's perfectly possible,
but I can also speed it up by tapping into the speed method for turtle.
And I can either specify this speed as an integer or as a string.
So the strings are fastest, fast, normal, slow, slowest,
and this determines the animation speed of the turtle as it draws.
So I'm going to go for fastest so we can say tim.
speed. And we'll put in that string, fastest.
And now when we run it, you can see it animates way faster
and it's drawing at the speed of light.
Our little turtle is completely going nuts,
but this means that it will take much less time to complete our 200 cycles as
we requested.
So I hope you enjoyed this lesson and you managed to get your turtle to do a random
walk. Now,
many of you would have done this challenge and you might've thought, wouldn't it
be nice if I could generate a completely random color rather than just selecting
a random one from this list? Well,
we can do that and I'll show you how in the next lesson.
So in the last lesson, we saw how to create a turtle that does a random walk.
Now in this lesson,
I want to show you how you can create a random color for your turtle drawing
rather than just using the named colors and then picking a random one out of the
list. When you take a look at the pen color of the turtle,
you can see that you can use a color string such as what we've been doing using
red, yellow, or a hex string that represents the color,
or we can use a RGB color.
And the RGB color is going to be represented by a tuple of different amounts of
red, green, and blue. So what exactly is a tuple?
Well,
a tuple is a data type in Python and it looks like this.
It has round brackets around it
and then each of the items inside are separated by a comma.
So does this remind you of another data type?
Does it not look a little bit like a list? Well,
indeed a tuple is very similar to a list. Each of the items that go into the
tuple are ordered.
So let's pull up my Python console here and let's create my tuple
which is denoted by a set of round parentheses
and then let's put in three items, 1, 3, and 8,
and there we have created a new tuple.
Now in order to get hold of any of those items in there,
I can write the name of the variable and then using square brackets
I can access the index.
So 1 is going to be at position zero, 3 is going to be at position one and
8 is going to be at position two. So if I hit enter on this,
then you can see that's going to be equal to 8.
And if you click this drop down on the right,
you can see the same representation; position 0, 1,  2,
and those pieces of data and the total length is three.
So at this point you might be asking yourself, well, I already know about lists,
so why do I need to know about tuples? What's the difference anyways? Well,
a tuple is going to be carved in stone
so you can't change the values like you can with lists.
For example, if I wanted to say
get hold of my tuple and instead of the 8 at position two,
I want to change it to 12. Now, if I go ahead and hit enter,
you can see I get a error and this is a type error.
This particular type, tuple, does not support item assignment.
So I can't just change it willingly like this.
And I also can't remove items from the tuple,
I can't change it in any way. Once you've created your tuple
you can consider it as carved in stone and it is what we call immutable.
It cannot be changed. So why would you use a tuple then?
Well, think about the times
like say if you're creating a color scheme for your website or are you creating
some sort of list that you want to stay constant and you don't want somebody to
accidentally change it or accidentally mess it up, well,
then you might want to consider using a tuple.
And if you find yourself creating a tuple and then realizing, Oh,
actually I need to change it well,
then you can simply put your tuple inside a list like this,
and you can actually convert it into a list.
Coming back to our documentation,
the color is represented by a tuple because if you define a color,
you're unlikely to change it.
And then we have a r, g, and b,
which is in the range between zero and the color mode.
So the mode can be between 0 and 1 or 0 and 255. In the course resources,
I've linked to this really handy RGB calculator tool,
which demonstrates how RGB colors work so perfectly.
You can see that if we have zero amount of red, zero amounts of green,
zero amounts of blue, we get black.
But if we mix different amounts of red and different amounts of green and
different amounts of blue, then we can get all of the colors in the rainbow.
The three primary colors can create any color that you dream of.
And each of these sliders,
you can see, goes from 0 all the way up to 255.
So more red, more green or more blue.
And this is what the RGB color ends up looking like.
I find it easier to think about the range between 0 and 255.
So in turtle,
we actually have to change the color mode to 255.
So to do this, it's a little bit tricky
which is why I didn't want to put this as part of the challenge.
But we have to tap into the actual turtle module and not the turtle object,
and then change the color mode for that module. Back in our code,
we can tap into our turtle module
which is known as 't' in our code.
And then we can tap into the color mode to make it go from 0 to 255.
So now that we've changed the color mode, we can now create a random color.
So let's get rid of this list of colors. Instead,
I'm going to create a new function called a random_color,
and this function is going to return a random color using RGB.
So let's first create a random red.
So we use the random module and then use the randint and then generate a number
between 0 and 255.
And then we can repeat this process for the other two color spaces,
so green and for blue.
Now we've got three random numbers,
one each representing each of the color spaces,
and then we can generate our tuple. Here's the challenge for you.
See if you can return from this function
a tuple that consists of the three random integers, r, g and b,
and then use that random color to color the turtle drawing instead of this broken
code which relied on that previous list of colors.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right. So we know that to create a tuple
we need a set of round brackets or parentheses,
and then we're going to put each of these in order,
so r, g and b. So here's our tuple created,
and this is basically our new random color.
And then this function is going to return that random color as the output.
So now instead of using random.choice and using that previous list,
all we have to do is get hold of a random color
that's going to be outputted from this function and then use it to color Tim's
drawing. So let's run this code again,
and you should be able to see that in this random walk,
the color is completely random.
Pretty much every single turn is going to draw something completely different in
terms of color.
And this is achieved by learning a little bit about how colors work and how we
can generate them using the random RGB colors.
Now the final challenge for today comes courtesy of a childhood toy that you
might've already seen. So this is going to be our training bike,
and it's going to be the last coding exercise before we tackle our final
project. So what are we doing? We're making a spirograph.
Do you remember those geometric gear shaped things
which you would draw and draw and it would make these funky circular shapes?
Well, that's what we're going to be doing, but with turtle.
We're going to get our turtle to draw a number of circles each with a radius of
a hundred in distance. And once it's done,
we should end up with something that looks like this.
So we're going to be using our random colors and we're going to be using the
documentation.
I want you to dig through the documentation and see if you can figure out how to
draw a circle and to determine how large the circle should be.
And then I want you to figure out how you can get it to repeatedly draw a circle
and change the tilt of the circle by a little bit each time,
so that you end up with that effect. Pause the video and give that a go now.
Alright. Again,
we're going to be scrolling through all of the available methods
looking for something that might help us.
I think it's going to be somewhere in the turtle motion's move and draw section.
And if you look down this list,
you can see there is a method that allows us to draw a circle with a given
radius.
So we can put in the radius as one of the inputs and draw our circle. Heading
back to our code,
I'm going to delete some of the previous parts where we've got the directions
and also changing the pen size.
I'm going to leave the speed as fastest because we're going to need it to go
pretty quick to draw all of those circles.
And I'm also going to delete the final for loop.
Now notice how I've got this warning here telling me that it doesn't really like
the idea of me calling a variable the same as the name of a function.
So why don't we just call this color instead
and then we can return that as the output and get rid of that warning.
Now we're ready to code up our spirograph.
So the first thing that we're going to try and do is to draw a circle.
Now the circle requires a radius,
so I'm going to give it a radius of a hundred. And when I hit run,
we can see briefly that it painted a circle.
So let's go ahead and create our screen from t.screen.
And then we can use that screen.exitonclick method so that when we run our
code, it doesn't actually remove the window until we click on it.
So I can see that I've painted my first circle
and I would like, if possible, to make my circle
have a different color each time.
So I'm going to change the color to use a random color that's produced by this
function. So now every time I run my code,
you'll see a different colored circle.
The turtle is basically gonna draw out this path and then go back to its
original position facing East.
If we wanted multiple circles to overlap with each other,
then we're going to have to change the heading or the pointing direction of our
turtle. If we look at this section,
the current state of our turtle,
you can see that you can get the current position,
the current Y coordinate and X coordinate,
but you can also get hold of the current heading,
so which direction it's pointing towards.
And all we have to do is just call this heading method.
So now if I print my tim.heading,
then you can see that when I run my code and I take a look inside the console,
it's pointing at 0.0.
What if we could change the heading to make it a little bit shifted?
Well,
there's actually a different method for changing the heading and getting the
heading. For example, if we want to set the heading,
then we have to use this method and give it a number.
So what if I get the current heading
and then maybe I add 5 or 10 degrees to it,
and then I change my turtle's heading using set
heading to the current heading plus 10.
And then we get a new circle drawn. So let's see what this looks like.
And you can see that I've drawn one circle and then I've tilted to the left a
little bit and then drawn a second circle. So extrapolating this,
you can imagine that if we had a loop that kept going,
then we could draw our final spirograph shape.
Let's create that loop.
So the parts that don't need to be in the loop is setting the speed.
But the color needs to change each time,
the circle needs to be drawn each time and the heading needs to be updated each
time.
Now I'm going to simplify this line of code to contract it into a single line.
So I'm setting Tim to a new heading
and that is from the current heading plus 10.
So now let's create our loop and let's say
we're going to loop a hundred times.
Now let's run our code and see what it looks like.
You can see it's drawing out our spirograph.
It's not as dense as it previously was,
but look at what it's doing.
It's drawing the same circle on top of a previous circle,
cause it doesn't know when to stop.
It's stopping only once it's gone through the hundred rotations.
So how can we figure out a way to get it to only draw as many circles as we
need?
Let's say that I created a new function called draw_spirograph,
and this function accepts a single parameter,
which is the size of the gap.
And that is going to be the size that's going to be in between each of these
circles that gets drawn.
And that's of course determined by the direction heading of my arrow.
So if I pass in this size of gap,
I'm going to use it here to change the tilt of my circle.
But I can also use that because it's a degree to determine how many times my
spirograph needs to be drawn.
So we know that there's 360 degrees in a full circle.
And for each circle that we're drawing,
we're basically giving it a different offset right? And
that's our size_of_gap.
So if we divide 360 by each offset,
then we'll repeat our code for as many times as we need to draw all the circles
and complete the final spirograph. Now,
the only problem is if I call this method,
dra, I think I meant to write draw.
So draw spirograph and I give it a size of five.
So a little bit smaller than last time,
tilting a little bit less each time. You can see that if I run this code,
we get an error.
And the error says that the float object can't be used as an integer
and it's telling us where we have that float object.
So remember that this number is going to go into here
and then 360 divided by five is actually going to give us a floating point
number, even though it divides cleanly
just because this is how division works in Python. Now,
unfortunately though our range function is going to need a whole number,
an integer.
It can't take a floating point number because then how many times are we
repeating it? 3.4 times? What does that even mean?
So this input has to be a whole number.
So let's turn it into an integer by creating an integer and then wrapping this
calculation inside the brackets. So now when we run our code,
you can see it paints our spirograph, shifting by five degrees each time.
And once it's gone through all of the iterations and the spirograph is
complete, then it actually stops.
Did you manage to get the solution for this challenge?
If not, be sure to review this lesson and fix your code as needed. Once you're
happy with everything that we've explained so far,
then it's time to head to the final challenge.
Let's go ahead and create a million dollar painting.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
This might seem a bit of an odd question,
but have you ever been to an art museum and looked at the exhibition and thought
to yourself,
I think I could probably do this and don't really understand why it's considered
art. Well, this is a piece of art
by Goldschmied and Chiari called 'Where should we go dancing tonight?'.
And it's meant to be a piece of concept art,
but when the museum cleaners came here at the end of the day and looked at this
mess of cigarette butts and shoes and random bottles,
they thought it was rubbish and they promptly cleaned everything up.
So this is what the exhibition looked like after the cleaners were done the next
day. So to the museum's horror,
their star exhibition gets cleared up and mistaken for rubbish.
So I was talking to a friend and I said, well, you know,
a lot of these modern art pieces, I could probably do it, right?
We could probably get together, put some bottles on the floor, make a mess,
call it art. And he told me, actually, no, you can't.
And you should read this book called the $12 million stuffed shark.
And it talks all about the economics of contemporary art.
And it's a fascinating read.
I've learned so much more about how contemporary art is priced and why they're
priced the way they are. But it also led me to discover some pretty big,
shocking discoveries. Like for example,
the art piece that's referred to on the cover of the page is this shark.
It's a shark that was fished off of the coast of Australia
and then it was preserved in formaldehyde. But it was preserved really badly
like they didn't use enough chemicals
and the shark started going a bit green and a bit of gray in other places
and it also started molding.
But this moldy green shark was bought for $12 million.
And this is not even the craziest piece. So for example,
this diamond encrusted skull was reportedly sold for $50 million.
And these butterfly wings
which have been dissected and stuck to a canvas was sold for 8.5 million.
So who exactly is this crazy man
who's creating all of these pieces of art that's fetching these insane
valuations? Well, it's a guy called Damien Hirst.
And I think out of all his paintings, the craziest ones are the spot paintings,
because it's literally spots of color that are organized randomly on a page. And
check this out.
This particular piece was sold for a whopping 1.275
million pounds.
So maybe like $1.5 million.
It's insane for a painting of dots.
But what I thought was even crazier is if you look at this painting,
at least it's got quite few dots, right?
You're getting your money's worth of dots. But look at this one!
This is the same artist, Damien Hirst, and this painting,
I counted only has 25 spots and this sold for half a million pounds.
It's not even about the number of spots. So I personally still,
as you can see, can't really work out contemporary art,
but what I can work out is how to get Python code to crack Damien Hirst's color
palette,
and use those colors to generate a random canvas of spot paintings that look
equally,
if not more appealing than some of the original Damien Hirst.
So this is what we're going to be making as our project.
And we're going to be using that package, colorgram, to get hold of the color
palette
and then we're going to use those colors to create our own spot painting
that's going to look like this. Firstly,
we're going to be using a package called colorgram and colorgram is a library
of code written in Python that lets you extract colors from images.
So for example, if you take a look at this picture,
once it was run through colorgram and 10 of the most common colors extracted,
you end up with a palette that pretty much looks the same as the colors in the
image.
This is the example of how you would use this colorgram package.
And in this case, they're extracting six colors from an image,
so it basically takes two inputs, an image, and the number of colors.
If we go into Google image search, and we search for a Hirst spot painting,
you can see that there's a lot of spot paintings that this guy created.
I want you to pick a painting with a color palette that you like, um,
maybe something like this, or maybe a bit brighter like this one.
But essentially,
pick one of these images and then go ahead and download it.
So save image.
And then you're going to save that image as image.jpg,
so jpg. And then go ahead and hit save.
Now go ahead and create a new PyCharm project.
I've called mine hirst-painting, you can call yours whatever you want.
Now we're going to drag our newly downloaded image,
image.jpeg into this project folder, hirst-painting.
And it's going to ask you whether if you want to move the file from,
in my case, the downloads folder to my hirst-painting project.
So then we're going to agree and click refactor.
So now this painting is inside my hirst-painting project,
and I'm ready to go ahead and create a new file called main.py
which is what I'm going to use to extract the colors from this image.
Here's a challenge for you.
See if you can figure out how to use this package,
colorgram, using their project description here and using the example code.
What you're aiming for is to be able to print out a list of all the colors
extracted from the image and each item in the list to be a tuple that you
create.
So remember previously we saw how the turtle module likes to work with color
tuples which are created with a amount of red,
the amount of green and the amount of blue, all contained inside a tuple.
This is the format that you're going to try and get your data into.
Might take a little bit of wrangling and a little bit of thought,
but just before you get started, here's a quick heads up.
I noticed that when I was testing this on repl.it and when I searched for color
gram in the packages,
I couldn't actually find the package to install into the project.
So this is another good reason for using PyCharm.
It just gives you all the professional tools and it has access to all the things
that you need. So pause the video and complete this challenge.
All right. So we know that in order to use external packages,
ones that weren't installed with the Python standard library,
we have to first install the package. To install a package
we go to our preferences and then we select our project
and then we go to our project interpreter.
Now we click the plus button and we search for colorgram.
And there it is. Now let's go ahead and install the package.
And once that's installed successfully, then we can close all of this and click
okay. Now that we've got our package,
we can actually import it. So we'll import colorgram,
and we can use the method that's described here called cologram.extract in
order to get ahold of six colors. Now, if we want more colors,
for example, in this image, that's probably a good 30 colors.
So let's go ahead and extract 30 colors from this image.
But of course our image is not called sweet_pic.jpg.
Ours is actually called image.jpg.
So let's go ahead and rename this image so that it matches with our file.
And remember that your image has to be at the same level as your main.py for
this kind of code to work.
So make sure that you've got it inside the hirst-painting project folder, on the
same indentation level as main.
Now let's go ahead and print out our colors that are generated.
And remember that when you hit run, this process might take a little while.
And the author of the library says that for a
512 by 512 image, it takes about 0.6 of a second.
Obviously, if the image is larger, it'll probably take a bit longer.
Let's go ahead and hit run and see what we get.
Once the process is finished,
you can see it's created some colors and these colors are in a list and it's got
some different formats for the color. To understand that we have to go back to
our documentation.
You can see that the color that's extracted can either be a RGB color
which is what we're interested in, or an HSL color
which is not quite what we want.
So let's go ahead and write a for loop that taps into each of those colors.
So for color in colors,
let's go ahead and create a new list called rgb_colors,
and we'll just leave it as an empty list. And then for each of these colors,
we're going to add to our rgb_colors by appending.
And the thing we're going to pend is each of these individual color objects,
and then we're going to get the RGB value.
And once this process is done,
then let's go ahead and print our RGB colors.
So now you can see we've got a whole bunch of RGB colors with r equals what, g
equals what and b equals what,
but this is not quite the format that we need it in order to use it inside the
turtle. We actually have to go one step further.
We have to create a r
which is from the color.rgb.r
and then we repeat this process for green
and blue.
And then we create our tuple by creating our new_color
which is going to be equal to a tuple with a parentheses
and then r, g and b. Finally,
we're going to add to our rgb_colors by appending this new color.
Now let's print our rgb_colors.
And you can see
we finally got it in the format that we need, a tuple with the r value, g value
and b value that we can use in our project.
Now we've managed to get the first part of the problem solved so we can go ahead
and copy this entire list and paste it into our main.py.
I recommend actually testing out these colors
using the w3schools RGB tool.
Go ahead and paste your color to replace this current tuple here.
Make sure that you still got that word rgb there, and then hit enter
and it will insert each of these values into the r, g and b.
So you can see the first color we got is actually a shade of white,
so probably one of the backgrounds.
So we can go ahead and delete that one because we're not going to be painting
the background in our own. It's just going to be white.
Now let's check the next one. As you can see, the closer the numbers are to
255, the more likely it is that it's a shade of white.
So this one is probably one of the other background colors in this image
so we can delete that one as well. And finally,
this last one is probably going to be also quite white-ish,
and we can probably delete that one too. This one because of the blue that's
109 I'm going to be pretty sure that this is actually a real color.
And there we go, we get this kind of sand color,
which looks very similar to some of these colors that we see on here.
So we can presume that the rest of these,
because they're sampled by the frequency of occurrence, are probably going to be
real colors that we can put into our painting.
Let's save this list as our color_list,
and we can comment out the rest of this code because we don't need to run this
computation every single time.
We just want to extract the colors and then you can delete or comment out the
colorgram related code. In the next lesson,
we're going to be using this color list to create our Hirst painting.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Now that we've used colorgram to extract all of the colors from our image
and we've created a list from that extraction and we've gotten rid of all the
white shades,
then we're now ready to go ahead and start using this color list to create our Hirst
painting.
So you can either delete the rest of the code or leave it commented out.
But the goal of the challenge is to use turtle and those colors that you've just
extracted to create a spot painting like this.
Here's the requirements of the program.
You're going to paint a painting with 10 by 10 rows of spots.
So that's going to be 10 along this side and 10 along this side.
Each of your dots should be around 20 in size and spaced apart by around 50
paces.
So you're going to need to look at the documentation for turtle to figure out
how to draw these dots.
You're going to have to figure out how to move your turtle so that it creates
this 10 by 10 pattern and paint our hundred dots using the color palette that
we generated. This is your chance to shine,
and it's time to pause the video and complete the final project.
So the first thing we're going to do is we're of course going to need to import
our turtle.
And I'm going to give it an alias just to make it more clear what it is that I'm
referring to. I'm going to create my turtle, which I'll call Tim again.
And it's going to be created from the turtle module and inside there,
there's a turtle class.
Now that we have our object created and saved inside Tim,
we're ready to go ahead and do some things with this turtle.
If you take a look at the documentation for turtle,
you can see that instead of just drawing circles or just moving forwards or left
or right, you can also draw a dot.
Now a dot takes two parameters,
its size and its color.
So we mentioned that we were going to draw a 20-size dot and then we're going to
pass in a random color. So let's create our dot.
Let's say tim.dot,
and then let's give it a size of 20 and then let's give it a random color. Now
because we're using the RGB color that has the r, g and b values between 0 and
255,
we first have to get the turtle module to change its color mode to
255. And we saw this in previous lessons already.
So now we can go into our color list and pick a random color using the random
module.
So let's tap the random module and get hold of the choice method and pass in our
color_list.
So now it's going to choose a random color from that list and then create a dot
hopefully. Now we don't want our painting to disappear once we hit run,
because right now if I run this code,
you can see it paints a dot and then it quickly flashes away.
So let's create a new screen object from the turtle module and the class is
called a screen.
And then we can get our screen to change its behavior by calling exitonclick.
This way when we run our code, you can see our dot painted,
and then only when we click does it disappear.
So we've managed to get our first dot onto the screen.
The next step is figuring out how we can get this process repeated.
What if we get our Tim to move forwards by say,
50 paces, and then we draw another dot.
So let's put this into a loop,
let's get it to run 10 times,
and then let's indent this block so that it goes inside the loop.
And now our turtle is going to draw 10 dots.
But notice how it goes off the screen and it kind of starts bang in the middle.
And there's also other problems like we're drawing the path as the turtle is
traveling. Let's address one thing at a time.
Let's try to move our starting dot so it starts somewhere down here.
Now there's quite a few ways of solving this. One way is simply by turning our
Tim, the turtle, before we go into the loop and setting its heading so that it
points in this direction.
You can have a play around with the heading and through my experimentation or
playing around with the code,
I've realized that I need to get this heading somewhere between 180 and
270.
So what's halfway between 270 and 180? Well,
it's going to be 225.
So let's change our heading and let's try again.
And you can see that our turtle is now moving roughly in the right direction.
So we know that each time the turtle moves by 50.
So if we want it to start about here, ish, then we need to move it one,
two, three, four, five times.
So 50 times five is 250.
So we'll set our heading for Tim and then we'll get him to move forward by 250
paces. So that way we get started right over here.
Now, at this point
it's still going to be pointing in that direction that we set over here.
So we'll have to set the heading back to zero
if we want it to continue in this direction.
Now at this stage,
you might realize you need to do a little bit of tweaking. So we could maybe move
our turtle forwards a little bit more so that it starts around here and we get
enough space for our dots.
But the next important thing we need to solve before we get rid of the lines
because we can still see the path of our turtle
which is really helpful, is we need to figure out how to get the turtle to
turn left, move up by 50, turn left again
and then start creating the second row.
That means we need to turn Tim so that it faces up
which is a heading of 90,
or you could also just turn it left by 90 degrees.
And then we're going to get it to move forwards by 50 paces.
And then we're going to get it to turn left again.
So we'll set the heading to 180, which is facing left.
It's through these step-wise changes to your code
that you can actually get a good sense of what it's doing
because you can see it drawing and then see if it's doing what you want it to
do. Now we know that we have our for loop
which is able to draw a line of dots going from left to right.
Why don't we move our turtle so that it starts out here again,
and then it can move along and create another line?
So after turning it to the left,
we're going to get it to go forwards by one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight, nine,
ten, by 10 times 50 paces.
So that's going to be 500.
So now the final thing we need to do is to change its heading so that it faces
right again. And now we're pretty close.
All we need to do is to get this
to repeat every single time we draw 10 dots.
How can we do that? Well, firstly,
this needs to go inside the for loop. Well,
let's say that we create a new variable called number_of_dots,
and we set it to a hundred. We're going to use that instead of the range
and we're going to create a range from 1 to the total number of dots we need
to create.
And then we can replace this underscore with an actual variable that we'll use
inside the for loop. So we'll call it
dot_count because this is going to represent the current number of dots that
have been painted. Now that we've got the dot count,
we can then go ahead and use an if statement to check and see if the dot_count
% 10 is equal to zero.
Then this means that the dot count is either 10 or it's 20, 30,
40, 50, 60, 70, 100.
And under those circumstances,
we want our tim to move so that it can go to a new line.
So now, if I run this,
you can see that Tim draws one row of dots and then swings back around,
start at the beginning and draws another row of dots. And then keeps on repeating
this until it gets to the point where it's drawn hundred dots.
But this is obviously very slow
so we could speed things up a little bit by changing the speed of Tim at the
very beginning to fastest.
So this way it'll animate a lot quicker and we can see our dots show up and it
takes a little bit less time to see it in action.
Once our painting is completed, you can see there's one other bug.
Our final dot is not painted. And this is of course
because our range operator goes from 1 to 100
and that means it's only going to run 99 times because 100 - 1 is equal to
99. So we can add one to this.
Yeah.
So once we've changed that, then we managed to get our hundredth dot,
which of course, again, triggers a new line. Now,
a lot of these lines were really useful when
we were trying to visualize how our turtle is moving.
But now that we've got our painting in place,
we need to try and get rid of these lines.
So we know that from the documentation we can use pen up and pen down. At the
very beginning and the moment where we've created Tim,
we can already get the pen to come up so that we don't draw those lines that you
see. By drawing dots we don't actually need the pen to go down.
It's just going to leave a dot and then move on.
So just by writing pen up and no pen down,
we already to get our dots being drawn.
Now the very last improvement that I can think of is once our painting is
completed, I'd really like to get rid of the shape of the turtle,
which in our case is a little arrow.
Now that's really helpful when we're trying to figure out which direction it's
facing or how it's moving. But at the very end, we don't really want this.
So again, back to the documentation, how can we get rid of our turtle?
Well, there's show turtle and hide turtle.
And this is how we make the turtle
invisible. It even tells us that you can do this while in the middle of a drawing because
hiding the turtle will speed up the drawing observably.
So let's go ahead and hide our turtle as well as moving the pen up.
And let's re-visualize this.
And you can see our dots being drawn without our turtle
and we end up with a beautiful Hirst painting that we've created completely
from scratch. Well,
maybe with a little bit of help from Damien Hirst's color palette.
So I hope you enjoyed this project. And I look forward to seeing you tomorrow.
Hey guys,
welcome to Day 19 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be learning more about turtle graphics,
but we're also going to look at event listeners, higher order functions, state,
and multiple instances of an object.
And we're going to be using this knowledge to build a whole bunch of games. We're
going to be making Etch-a-Sketch, one of my favorite childhood toys.
And this game is going to allow us to use the up and down arrows to move our
turtle forwards and back
and then we can turn our turtle clockwise and anticlockwise to continue
drawing.
So we can use this to create circles or to create lines.
And we can basically create drawings using our turtle program.
In addition,
we're also going to be making a turtle racing game where we will get to bet on
the color of a turtle who will win the race.
And then once we click okay to the popup,
then all of our turtles go to the starting line and they start moving at a
random pace.
And then once the first turtle hits the right edge of the screen,
it will be declared the winner and we will get to see if our turtle won or not.
So at the moment, the red turtle is not looking like it's going to make it.
I think the orange is probably-- Oh, the yellow's overtaking it.
And there we go. We lose. The purple turtle
was the winner of the race. So I hope you're
as excited as I am to build these projects together. Once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and let's learn about how we can listen to key
strokes on the keyboard.
Now in order to be able to create a lot of the games that we've spoken about,
we need a way of being able to listen to things the user does,
like when the user taps a specific key on the keyboard. And the code that allows
us to do this are called event listeners.
So if we look at the turtle documentation,
you can see that there's a whole section on screen events,
including listening to key presses or listening to a click or other things that
you can listen to. So the important thing is this listen method.
This allows the turtle screen to start listening and waiting for events that the
user might trigger, like tapping on a key.
I've gone ahead and created a new PyCharm project which I've called day-19
and I've created my main.py file inside the project. Now,
the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to import the turtle class and the
screen class from the turtle module.
And then I'm going to use them to create my Tim the turtle,
and also create a screen object.
This is basically going to control the window when we run our code.
So you saw it just flash just now.
Now in order to start listening for events,
we have to get hold of the screen object and then tell it to start listening.
And once it starts listening,
we have to bind a function that will be triggered when a particular key is
pressed on the keyboard. Now,
in order to bind a key stroke to an event in our code,
we have to use an event listener.
So the one that we're going to be using is this onkey method.
And you can see it expects a function with no arguments and also a key,
like the
'a' key on your keyboard or a key symbol, so the space or up or down.
So I'm going to say screen.onkey
and then I have to bind some sort of function to this method.
So let's create a function and we'll call it move_
forwards.
And all that this function is going to do is it's going to get Tim to go forward
by 10 paces. And let's not forget our colon here.
Now, coming back to my onkey method,
I'm going to say that when the space key, so the space bar, is pressed,
then trigger the function move_forwards.
Now here's a really important point; when we use a function as a argument,
so something that is going to be passed into another function,
we don't actually add the parentheses at the end.
The parentheses triggers the function to happen there and then.
But what we want is we want this method, onkey, to listen for when the space bar
is pressed and only when that happens to trigger this move_forwards function.
Now, the final thing I need to do is to add the exitonclick so that my screen
doesn't disappear when I run it.
And now what I'm going to try is when I hit the spacebar,
you should see my turtle move forwards by 10 paces each time.
So we're now controlling our turtle using a keystroke.
What we've essentially got here is a function that's being used as an input.
Let's say we have a function called function_a
that takes some sort of input.
And then we have a function called function_b, we can actually pass function_b
into function_a like this.
So notice that when we pass a function as an input,
we only pass the name without the parentheses at the end.
But how exactly does this function onkey work?
Because it's kind of crazy to use a function as the input to another function,
right?
So want to show you a quick example of passing a function into another function,
and I'm going to use the calculator example that we did many,
many moons ago. Um, when we created a calculator that could take two numbers,
add, subtract, multiply, or divide those numbers.
So we've got our four functions here. Now,
you don't actually have to write any of this out, cause it's quite tedious.
I just want you to watch and listen.
So let's say I create a final function, which I'll call calculator.
And this function is going to take a n1 and n2, two numbers,
but it's also going to take a function as an input.
Now, inside this calculator function,
I'm going to take the function name that was passed in
and then call that function by adding the parentheses and then passing in n1
and n2. So now I have my calculator function
which can take any function as an input.
And once that function has been passed in here,
then that function will get triggered passing in n1 and n2. Let's return
this result as the output,
and then let's call our calculator function,
let's pass in some numbers and let's pass in the name of a function.
So now let's go ahead and save this into a variable and then print that variable
result. So now when I run the code,
you can see I get five printed and that's because I've got add as the third
input here. But what happens if I change this to multiply? Well,
I get six instead of five.
And what happens if I put divide? Well, I get zero because,
because it's rounding up to a whole number.
But essentially what I'm trying to demonstrate to you is this concept
which is known in Python as Higher Order Functions.
And the idea of a higher order function is a function that can work with other
functions. So in this case,
our calculator is a higher order function because it's actually taking another
function as an input, and then working with it inside the body of the function.
Now there are certain programming languages where you can't do this at all.
But in Python, this is pretty commonly used.
And it's really useful when we need to listen for events and then trigger a
particular function. Now, while we're on the topic of functions,
I recommend that when you're using methods that you haven't created yourself
like for example onkey, to use keyword arguments
instead of positional arguments especially if like in this case,
the position doesn't actually have any meaning.
So now that you've seen how event listeners work,
we're going to be using event listeners to build out our Etch-A-Sketch program
in the next lesson. So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Now that you've seen how event listeners work, here's a challenge for you.
I want you to build a Etch-A-Sketch app.
This is what you're aiming for.
You should be able to create a turtle that will allow you to press the W key to
go forwards, the S key to go backwards,
the A key to go counterclockwise or leftwards and the D key to go right or
clockwise. And then be able to draw things like this,
or you could do up and right to draw curves like this.
We're kind of creating that childhood game which is Etch-A-Sketch.
When you press the C key,
it should clear all your drawings and put your turtle back in the center.
So think about what you've learned so far about how event listeners work,
and then use the turtle documentation,
read through the different methods that you have access to,
and then try to figure out how you can get this Etch-A-Sketch program to work in
the way that it's shown here. So pause the video and give this challenge a go.
This is the demo code from previously
and this is a really simplified version of how the event handlers work.
So for example, we've got our move_forwards function
which is going to be triggered when the space key is detected by the screen.
And the screen is able to detect it because it's listening for those keyboard
strokes and clicks. Now,
because the onkey function can only receive a function with no arguments,
at least this is what we see in the documentation,
then that means we have to create four separate functions, moveforwards,
move back, turn left, and turn right.
So now all I need is three more of these functions,
move backwards, turn left, and turn right. Now,
I'm going to change this binding from space to w which is going to be move
forwards.
And then I'm going to copy this and make three more of these so that I've got my
w as move_forwards,
and then I've got my S as move_backwards,
my a as turn_left and my d as turn_
right.
So now all we need to do is to actually create these functions.
So let's create our move_backwards
which is going to take Tim backwards by 10 paces.
And then the next function we're going to create is to turn_left.
And this is going to get the current heading of our turtle and add 10 degrees to
it.
So if you imagine that the turtle starts out pointing towards East
and this heading is going to be zero. And we know that to point North,
it becomes 90. So if we want this to turn leftwards,
then we have to add to the current heading value like this.
So this could be our new_heading,
and then we can get Tim to set
it's heading to that new heading so that we turn left by 10 degrees each time.
Now you could have also used simply just the left function.
So you could have said tim.left by 10 degrees. Both methods work
and it's totally up to you which one you choose. Now in order to turn right
it's basically the opposite. So instead of adding 10 degrees,
all we have to do is subtract 10 degrees or alternatively calling
tim.right, passing in 10 degrees.
Now we have all four functions defined and tied to a keystroke
let's go ahead and test it out.
So w should take us forwards, s should take us backwards,
a should turn left and D should turn right.
So perfect.
Now the last thing we wanted to code in was some sort of way of clearing the
screen. And we said we would bind that to the C key.
So I'm going to create a function called clear which I'll define here.
And this function is going to clear the screen wipe out all the drawing
and then take our turtle back to the beginning,
which was at the middle of the screen.
This is going to require a little bit of reading in the turtle documentation.
If you scroll through this list, you'll actually find two clear methods.
One is a method that is for the turtle
and another is a clear method for the screen,
which is the window basically. Now this clear is going to clear everything.
It's going to delete our turtle and everything else that's onscreen.
Whereas this clear,
which is tied to the turtle, is just going to delete this particular turtle's
drawings. So this is what we need to do.
We need to get hold of Tim and then call clear on him to get rid of all the
drawings he's made so far. Now,
the next thing we're going to do is we're going to bring our turtle back to the
center, to the starting point.
And this is going to be aided by one of the methods called home.
So I found this in the documentation and it says that it moves the turtle to the
origin, which is in the middle of the screen. Now,
all we need to do is to call home and notice what happens if I run this as it is.
So I can draw and basically make a mess.
And then when I hit C
you can see it goes back to the home,
but it's actually drawing its whole path back there as well. To prevent this from
happening we have to pull the pen up, which we've used before.
And then once Tim has reached home, then we're going to put the pen down
ready for the next drawing.
So now we can make a drawing, hit C, and then it goes back to the center.
Did you manage to complete this challenge? Don't beat yourself up
if you didn't manage to find some of the methods like home or clear.
It's a matter of getting practice with reading the documentation and having the
patience to go through it and look for the relevant methods.
And on top of that, it's just a matter of messing around with the code.
Try things out, see what happens. And each time you add something, run the code,
see if it does what you want it to do. And if not, fix it.
And that is the endless cycle of software development.
So don't get frustrated if you got stuck.
As long as you managed to make it work in the end
and you've learned some lessons from this process,
then you can congratulate yourself on completing the job.
And I find that I always learn more when I make more mistakes
and when I struggle more. Once you're done playing around with the code,
head over to the next lesson, and we're going to be learning about object
state and creating multiple instances of the same object.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
The objective is we want to be able to build a turtle race,
where we have multiple turtles to run along a line and then see who actually
reaches the finish line first. Now here's a question though.
We know how to build one turtle from the turtle blueprint,
but what if we need more turtles? How do we get hold of them?
Well,
we know that we can use a class or a blueprint to define what a turtle should
appear like and how it should behave.
So what it has and what it can do. Now,
we can then take this class and construct an actual turtle object from it
which is then doing all the drawing and walking around on the screen.
So this is what the code has looked like so far. We have Timmy
which is our turtle object, and turtle coming from the turtle module is the
class which is used to construct this object.
But that's not the end of the story because the whole reason why we can have
these blueprints is so we can make more objects.
So, we're not limited to just one turtle object.
We can create as many as we need in the same way that we have created Timmy.
We create Tommy, Johnny, Jenny, and Benny.
Even though both Timmy and Tommy are turtle objects,
they actually function completely independent of each other.
So in programming, we would say that they are each a separate instance.
So what does that mean? Well,
that means that they're each an example of the turtle object.
So just as you and I are both examples of human objects,
Timmy and Tommy are both examples of turtle objects.
And that means that at any moment in time,
they could have different attributes and they could be doing different things.
So that means, for example,
Timmy could have his color set to green while Tommy could have its color set to
something completely different, like purple.
Now the fact that each of these objects can have different attributes and can be
performing different methods at any one time in programming is known as their
state.
So the state of Timmy's color attribute is green and Tommy's color attribute is
purple. So in this case,
they have different state in terms of their attribute or their appearance.
But they can also have different state in terms of whether
if they are doing something. For example,
Timmy could be asked to move forwards while Tommy is staying completely
stationary. So Timmy is in the middle of a method call
whereas Tommy is not doing anything at all. Now in the next lesson,
we're going to be building out our turtle racing game
and we're going to see this in action.
The idea that you could have separate versions of the same object each with a
different state and acting completely independently from each other in order to
race against each other. So don't worry if this doesn't make sense
a hundred percent just yet. Head over to the next lesson
and we're going to start writing some real code to better understand this
concept.
All right guys. In this lesson, we're going to be building out our turtle race.
And through building this race,
we're going to get more familiar with these concepts of state and instances.
And that's because we need to create multiple turtles to join our race.
This is what we're aiming for. In the beginning,
there's going to be a little popup that will ask us to bet who will win the
race. And it asked me to choose a color.
Now the turtles are in the color of the rainbow,
so I'm just going to pick the red one. Once I hit okay,
we have all of our turtles lined up in the starting position and they will start
making random steps towards the right edge of the screen. Now,
the first hurdle that reaches past the right edge of the screen is going to be
the winner.
And at the moment it looks like the green turtle is probably going to get there
first. There we go. So as soon as a turtle crosses the finish line,
then it will print out a line telling us whether if we won or whether
if we lost our bets and which turtle won the game.
So this is the goal.
Now I'm going to get started by deleting all of the code inside our previous
Etch-A-Sketch project other than these few lines.
So I've got Tim my turtle, screen
which is a screen object that is going to hold the screen until I click on it so
that I can see what's going on. Now, because in this game
the dimensions of the screen or of the window is really crucial,
I'm not just going to get the default screen size show up. Instead
I'm actually going to use one of the methods that is in the screen object
which is called setup. And setup, as you can see,
allows me to set up the width and the height of this window
that's going to show up.
So I'm going to set the width of my screen to 500 and the height to 400.
So I should end up with a 500 pixel wide, 400 pixel high screen.
And once I hit run, you can see this is what it gets resized to.
Now, if you came across this code and it was somebody else's code,
then these numbers and their positions don't actually make a lot of sense,
which one's the height, which one's the width. So in these situations,
I recommend using keyword arguments rather than positional arguments. Oh,
let's write out the parameters explicitly. Our width
to be 500 and our height to be 400. This way
when somebody else comes along and reads your code,
it's a lot easier to understand rather than just 500 and 400,
cause it could be both ways.
So now that we've got our screen set up,
the next thing I want to do is to bring up that popup and ask the user to make a
bet. Now, if we take a look at the Python documentation,
um, where we've been spending a lot of time recently,
you can see that there is a method on the screen
which is called textinput.
And this is going to show up a popup window and it allow the user to look at the
prompt and the title and to enter a piece of text.
And if you want the user to enter a number, then you would use numinput.
So let's go ahead and add that here. So it will be a method from screen
which is called textinput and then it's got two parameters.
One is the title which in my case
I'm just going to say 'Make your bet'.
And then the second parameter is going to be the prompt. And in my case,
I will probably say, um,
which turtle win the race and tell them to enter a color.
Now, this works really similarly to our input
which we've been really used to because it will return the string and we can
catch that string inside a variable.
So we'll call it user_bet and we'll set it to equal the output from this
method.
Now let's give this a shot.
Let's run the code and then let's enter a color, hit okay.
And if we take a look in our console,
you can see that that bet string is printed in here.
So now the next thing we're going to do is we need to do something with our
turtle. I'm going to move it down a little bit.
And what I want my turtle to do is I want it to go to the start of the line.
So the very left edge of my screen. Now I could,
of course, just say tim.backward by, um,
however many paces,
but thinking forward and knowing that I'm going to have six or seven of these
turtles,
I can't just tell them all to go backwards because they're going to go to the
same position. Instead, we're going to use a method that the turtle has
which is called goto.
And this allows us to define an X value and a Y value.
But how do we know what X and Y values to give it? Well,
we first have to understand how the Python turtle coordinate system works.
So if you imagine your program window as a graph where the center of it is at
the coordinate (0, 0). Well
then if you have a window that has a height of 400,
then that graph will have a Y-axis that extends from the center at zero all the
way up to the top edge and then from the middle
it goes down to the very bottom edge, which is going to be -200.
So 200 plus 200 makes up 400 and the same happens with the X-axis.
So if the width of the screen is 500, then
the X-axis goes from the center 0 to positive 250,
so half of 500. And then from zero to -250.
So here's a question. Let's say we wanted to move our turtle here.
What do you think would be the X and Y coordinate of that point?
Okay. So let's say
that this is roughly halfway on the X-axis and about halfway on the Y-axis.
Then half of 250 is 125 and half of 200 is 100.
So at this point would have the coordinate of 125 by 100.
If we wanted our turtle to go all the way to the left side of the screen
say maybe starting over here or starting over here, well,
then we would have to use that
goto method and then specify a X-value and a Y-value. Following the logic of the
total coordinate system then in order to move our turtle to the very left edge,
then we should supply an X-value of minus 250
which is half of the width of 500.
Now the Y-value will determine where on the Y-axis our turtle moves to.
So if we had it at zero
then it would basically just go straight backwards and it would not go up or
down. But let's say that we put it at, um,
-100. So now if I run this code,
you can see that it goes in the right direction,
but it's actually gone off the screen.
So what's happened here is that -250 is on the very,
very edge of the window.
And once our turtle moves over there and the arrow is at the back,
then you can't actually see it at all.
So let's try changing that X-value and shifting our turtle a little bit more to
the right. Then you can see it moves to pretty much the start of the window.
So I recommend using this goto method and trying out some different numbers
just to see where it ends up on the screen.
And once you put in some different numbers in here,
you'll start to get the hang of how this coordinate system actually works.
But just remember that the X-axis is along the horizontal.
It goes from zero to positive and zero to negative.
And then the Y-axis is along the vertical,
going from zero to positive and zero to negative.
So we want to get rid of this line and we don't actually want our turtle to draw
at all. So to do that, we're going to do tim.penup,
and we're actually never going to put the pen down because we're going to be
moving the turtle itself.
And the other thing is that it would be really nice if instead of an arrow,
we actually got a turtle.
So we can of course say tim.shape and set it to a turtle shape,
but here's an even easier way. When we create a new turtle,
look at the prompt that it's giving us.
It's actually giving us a way to initialize a new turtle object already with a
shape set up.
Now this shape is set to have a default value
which is basically the arrow.
But we can also specify the shape and give it the turtle shape to begin with.
Now, when I run the code you can see that firstly,
I get a turtle shape and then the pen is up and I'm not drawing
and then it moves to this place on the graph; -230, -100.
So now the next thing we want to do is to be able to create lots of turtles,
right?
What if we had all of the colors in the rainbow and we create a turtle for each
color?
So there's six colors in this list and these of course,
correspond to the colors which turtle will recognize.
So here's a challenge for you.
I want you to create six turtles,
one for each of the colors in this list of colors.
You're aiming for the turtles to all go to the starting line in a distribution
that looks something like this. It doesn't have to be precise,
you don't have to get it perfectly right.
But just make sure that they're sort of evenly spaced out and they are at the
starting line. So this is what you're aiming for; six turtles, six colors,
all starting at the starting point along a different point on the Y axis.
Pause the video and give that a go.
So we know that in order to create lots of turtles,
we're going to need some sort of a loop.
So let's go ahead and use a for loop to say turtle_index
and we're going to create a range to specify how many turtles we need.
Our range function will go from 0 to 6.
And remember that the range function actually doesn't include the number six,
so it'll create a range from 0 to 5. And once we've done that,
then we can indent this block of code so that we create six turtles.
But at the moment, they're all going to the same position.
So how can we change this? Well,
we want the X-position to always be the same for all the turtles,
because the X-position is along the horizontal axis
and we want all the turtles to start at the starting point.
Nobody gets a headstart. But the Y-position is the thing that we want to change.
A really simple way of doing this is to simply create a list of Y-positions
and you can work out some sort of reasonable position that you want to take.
So let's say we start out at -70 and then we just increased by 30 each
time.
So then that becomes -40 and then -10 and then 20,
50 and 80.
So it's roughly distributed somewhere along the middle. Now,
instead of using this Y-position
which is hardcoded -100,
we're going to take the Y-positions and then pass in our turtle_index like
this. So now when we rerun this code,
you can see that for each of the turtles
they're all going to get an individual Y-position
and they're all separated by 30 in distance.
Now we've got our turtles neatly lined up at the starting point.
The next thing is to give them a different color.
So we're going to use the list of colors and then picking out the color using
the turtle_index.
So now we should get some multicolored turtles and it will be much easier to bet
on a turtle. So now that we have our turtle race
all set up and ready to go,
the next step is to actually get the turtles to start moving.
But before we can do that,
I really want you to get a good grasp of how the coordinate system works in
turtle. So in the next lesson,
I've got a quick quiz for you just to make sure that you really understand
what's going on here.
In the last lesson,
we figured out how we can get our turtle race up and running and get our turtles
at the starting positions. Now,
the next job we have is to figure out how we can get these turtles to start
moving. The movement is going to have to be randomized
and each step they take will have to be a random number. That way they don't go
straight to the end
and we end up with a terrible gaming experience.
So what we're going to do is we're going to create a random number,
let's say between 0 and 10,
and then we're going to tell the turtle to go forward by that random amount.
So it could be anywhere between 0 and 10.
And then we're going to get this to repeat itself many, many times.
As you might've guessed,
this is probably going to involve some sort of while loop.
So let's say we start out with a variable called is_race_on and it starts out as
false.
But then once the user has made their bet and we can check to see
user_bet exists, then in that case
we're going to switch that is_race_on to true.
And then we can use our is_race_on inside our while loop.
Now this way we prevent our while loop from starting up while the user is still
deciding on which turtle they're going to bet on.
So it doesn't start prematurely.
Now when the user has made their bet and the race is now on, well
now we're going to need to get hold of a random number.
We're going to use the random module to get hold of a random int between the
range of 0 and 10.
Now randint is actually inclusive,
so the random number could be zero all the way up to 10.
So now we're gonna call this the rand_distance,
and this is going to be the distance that one of our turtles is going to move
forwards by.
So we want some sort of turtle.forward and the distance that it goes forward
is the random distance.
Now we have lots of turtles that we've created,
but we kind of haven't really done anything with them.
What we want to do instead is to have some sort of list of turtle.
So we'll call all_turtles,
and this list starts out as empty.
But every single time we create a new turtle,
then we can append that turtle to this list. So at this stage,
it doesn't really make sense to call all the turtles tim anymore, right?
Because they're all going to be individual instances.
So let's go ahead and refactor and rename this to a new_turtle.
And now what's happening in our for loop is we're creating a new turtle and
each of those new turtles are going to be appended to our all_turtles list.
So now we're going to have a list of multiple turtle instances,
and each of those instances is going to have a different state.
So for example,
they already start out with a different Y-position and a different color.
But later on,
we're also going to get them to move forwards by a different amount.
So we can loop through our list of turtles,
so for turtle in all_turtles,
let's go ahead and create a random distance for each of them and then move that
turtle forward by the random distance.
So now if we run our code
and see it in action,
you can see that once all of the turtles have gone into their starting
positions, they stop creeping along each time by a different amount.
Now, however, our turtles are actually going to keep going until forever.
It's basically a loop that's never going to stop.
So let's think about what the stopping conditions should be. Well,
once any of these turtles have actually reached the end of the screen
which is the X-value of +250,
once they've reached this line, then that's kind of the end of the race,
right?
But a turtle object is a 40 by 40 object.
So if we're only detecting for the 250,
then our turtle would have already overshot.
So instead, we want to detect when the turtle has reached the 230 mark. Back in our
code in our for-loop,
we can check to see if the turtle that we're currently looping through,
if it's X-coordinate is greater than
230. Well, in this case, it's basically won.
Now at this stage,
if we print this current turtle's color,
then you'll actually see something a little bit strange.
You can see that firstly,
it prints multiple values because the while loop is still continuing and the
other turtles continue to go forward.
But the first value is going to be the turtle that won.
And you can see it prints yellow and yellow.
So what's going on here? Well, if we look at this color method,
you can see that you can either use it to set the pen color and fill color,
or it will return the pen color and fill color.
So when it prints out two colors,
the first one is going to be the pen color and the second is going to be the
fill color. So if we only want to know the pen color,
then we can just get hold of the turtle.pencolor.
This is going to be the color of the body of the turtle. So in our code,
we can say that the winning color is equal to the current turtle.pencolor.
And then we can now check to see if the winning color is equal to the user's
bet, because if this is the case, well then the user has won, right?
So we can tell them you've won.
And then we can tell them the color of the winning turtle.
Now, however,
if this is false or rather in the else statement,
well, in that case, we're going to have to print the same thing
but now we're going to tell them that they've lost.
Yeah.
Finally, when the first turtle reaches the X-coordinate,
when this first color gets printed,
we want to stop the while loop. This way
the remaining turtles don't continue to nudge forward
and we get end up with lots of winners like this. So inside this
if statement, when the turtle's X-coordinate has surpassed 230,
we're going to change the is_race_on to false.
Now we're ready to test out our code. And again,
I'm going to bet on the red turtle and I'm going to speed up the playback speed
of this race when I'm editing this video.
And now the game has ended and you can see that the blue turtle is the one that
first got its head across the finish line.
And it tells me just as much. I've lost and the blue turtle is the winner.
So we've now used Python turtle to build a very simple turtle racing game.
And we're starting to use these X and Y positions in the turtle coordinate
system. Now, these coordinates take a little bit of getting used to,
especially thinking about things such as if a turtle is 40 pixels wide,
then in order to get the turtle to the starting line
we have to subtract half of the width of the turtle, which is 20.
So then 250 minus 20 becomes 230.
And it's things like this that takes a little bit of getting used to.
So what I really recommend is to have a play around with these values,
make it smaller, or make it larger, change the size of the screen.
And just until you're really familiar with how the coordinate system works
before you proceed to the next lesson, because as you keep going,
I'm going to presume that you've already had a play around with it and you know
exactly how it works. Now,
the other thing that we saw a lot of in this project is this concept of having
multiple objects created from the same class. So in this case,
we're using the turtle class to construct a turtle object called Timmy,
but we've also got a separate object called Tommy. And Timmy and Tommy are both
Tuttle objects, but they're different instances. So they can act independently,
they can have different appearances, they can have different colors,
different attributes, and also a different speed of movement.
So we've seen in our turtle race that each of these instances can act of their
own accord and have different state.
And that's shown in the different speed of movement and this capability of
creating multiple objects which can act and behave independently
is really the secret to why Object Oriented Programming can be so
powerful.
We can create so many of these objects and get them to do our bidding in various
parts of our program. And in the coming lessons
as we build more and more complex projects,
you'll see this concept of having multiple instances with different state being
shown again and again. And we're going to come to see and enjoy the benefits.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 20 of 100
Days of Code. Today
is really exciting because we're going to be using the knowledge that we've
gained about Object Oriented Programming
as well as what we learned about how to use the turtle module to build the
famous snake game. Now,
this is probably one of the most famous mobile games that ever was,
and it's definitely one of my favorite. And my history with it goes back all the
way to my very first mobile phone,
the Nokia 3310. It might be showing my age a little bit here,
but this was my first ever mobile phone.
I remember loving it so much that I actually had it next to my pillow when I
went to sleep. And this was probably one of the first affordable mobile phones.
And it was endlessly customizable with different cases and different keys.
But the most exciting thing about it
was the snake game. I would compare
with my friends and see who got the highest score in snake
and we would spend days and days playing this game. And compared to the iPhone
games of today, of course, this was very, very simple, but nonetheless,
it is still super addictive. Over the next two days
this is the game that we're going to build. A snake game that has,
um, a moving snake, which you control using your keyboard,
and you can go and get food,
and then it grows in length as it eats more food.
And you have to make sure that you don't end up getting tangled or hitting the
wall.
And the goal is to eat as much food as you can while staying alive.
There are some people who are truly masters at this game, um,
which I personally am not,
but they managed to get their snakes to crazy lengths and start having these
strategies for how you can avoid hitting your tail and how you can keep going.
So once you've built your snake game, you'll be able to play with it,
and you'll be able to show off your high scores to the rest of us,
but I'm sure you're going to do a lot better than me.
It's not that hard to beat me at snake. As always,
when we're thinking about a complex problem
the first step is to break down the problem.
And I'm going to break down this problem of building the snake game into seven
separate steps.
And the way we're going to do it is we're going to tackle the first three steps
on Day 1 and the last four steps on Day 2.
So we're going to split up this game into two parts and we're going to tackle it
over two days. The first step is to create a snake body,
and we're going to do that by creating three squares on the screen,
all lined up next to each other.
And then we're going to figure out how to move the snake so that it continuously
moves forward
and all we have to do is tell it to change direction. Afterwards,
we're going to figure out how to control the snake using keyboard controls.
So we're going to be using the up, left, down, and right arrow keys to move our
snake across the screen.
And that is what we're aiming for by the end of today,
Day 20. On Day 21,
we're going to continue and we're going to build out the last four steps of the
snake game.
Then we'll need to start putting some food onto the screen and started to detect
the collision with the food so that once the snake hits the food,
then a new piece of food gets created randomly on the screen at some sort of
random location.
And then it's a matter of keeping track of the score and creating a scoreboard.
So we're going to learn how to write text in our program so that once the snake
hits a piece of food, the score automatically updates.
And then next we're going to figure out when the game should end.
So one of the cases when the game should end is when the snake has collided with
the wall. And at this point we should see game over,
show up on screen and the snake should no longer move.
And then finally,
the other reason why our game could end is when the snake has collided with its
own tail. So the snake basically can't chase his own tail.
And as the snake gets longer, this problem is more likely to occur.
And when their head hits any part of the body of the snake, then it's again,
game over. So these are the seven steps
that it takes to create the snake game.
And once you're ready, we're gonna get started with step one on the next lesson.
So I'll see you there.
So to start off,
go ahead and create a new project called snake_game in PyCharm.
And then inside this project, we're going to create a new main.py file.
And inside our file, we're going to need our normal imports.
So I'm going to say from turtle import the screen class and also the turtle
class. Now,
the first thing we're going to do is we're going to create a new screen,
which is basically going to be the window that shows up.
And then we're going to set up our screen so that it is 600 by 600.
So the width is going to be 600 pixels and the height is also going to be 600
pixels. And notice how I'm using these keyword arguments
so that it's a little bit clearer to the next person looking at this code
what's actually happening here. Now,
the other thing I want to change is the screen's background color.
So there's a method called bgcolor and inside here
we're going to write the text black so that we end up with a black screen.
Now,
another thing that you might not have seen before is how to set the title of
the window that shows up. And we do that through a method called title,
and you can name your program here. So I'm going to call it 'My Snake Game',
but you can of course call it whatever it is you want. Now finally,
at the very bottom of the file, I'm going to say screen.exitonclick.
So this way, when I actually run it, it doesn't just disappear straight away
and it waits for me and I can look at what's actually happened so far.
So I'm going to click run and then select my main file.
And once it pops up,
this is what you should see, a 600 by 600 square window
and then at the top of the window, you'll see the name of your program,
which is My Snake Game. And the background is now black.
Now that we've set up our screen,
we're ready to tackle the first of our seven steps,
which is to create a snake body.
And we're going to create three squares
which are each going to be turtles,
and they're going to be lined up next to each other along the horizontal axis.
So let's think about this. When we create a new turtle,
it has a dimension of 20 pixels wide by 20 pixels tall.
And if we want three of them lined up next to each other,
then we have to think about how we create their coordinates. As a challenge,
I want you to think about how we can create this. Here
we have three separate squares
which are each a turtle object and they're shaped like a square and they have a
white color. Now, they're positioned
so that the first one is (0, 0),
the next one is 20 pixels to the left and the next one is again
20 pixels to the left so that none of the squares overlap with each other,
but there's also no gaps. So it looks like a whole snake.
This is your challenge
and you might have to think about a few of the things that we've done before in
order to achieve this. So browse the documentation,
look back to the previous code that you've written and see if you can solve this
challenge. Pause the video now.
Alright.
So the first thing we're going to need to do is to create some sort of turtle,
right?
So let's call this segment_1 and this is going to be a new turtle.
And remember that when we initialize the turtle,
we can already specify the shape.
So we can either say shape = "square",
or simply just leave it as square. So now at this point,
we should end up with a square turtle, but because it's black,
when we run the code, we won't actually see it on screen.
So let's change this segment color to white.
And all we have to do is write the word for the color
and now when we rerun our code,
you can see a white square at the center,
which is at position (0, 0).
Now the next step is to create our other two white squares.
So let's go ahead and copy these bits of code,
and I'm going to create three of them in total.
So segment_2 and segment_3.
Now here, we're going to create the same thing,
but we obviously have to change the positioning because otherwise we end up with
three squares all on top of each other,
and we can only see one square because this is a 2-D image.
So let's go ahead and make segment_2 go to a different position.
So the first thing we have to specify is the X,
which you remember is the horizontal axis here.
And if we want another square to the left of it,
then we're going to have to go to -20 from zero.
That way it will be shifted to the left by 20 pixels.
Let's say go to -20
and then the Y-axis is going to be zero because it's not going to move up or
down.
Now let's take a look at the result of this and you can see we've now got two
squares lining side by side,
but the third square is still at the center.
So the third segment is going to be shifted a further 20 pixels.
This is centered on (0, 0), this is at (-20, 0),
then this has to be at (-40, 0).
So let's tell our segment_3 to go to (-40, 0).
And this is what we see.
Did you manage to achieve this or did you do it in a different way? Now,
a much easier way of creating this would have been to use a for loop.
For example, we
could have created a list of
starting positions
and this could contain some tuples.
So we know that in order to specify where the segment should go to,
we have to provide a tuple, which is a X and a Y value.
And we know that we can create a tuple just by using a set of parentheses and
then adding values in there, separated by commas.
So if the first segment has to be at the center, then that's going to be
(0, 0), and then the second piece is going to be at (-20, 0),
and the third piece is going to be at (-40, 0).
Now we can create
a for loop. So for
position in starting_positions,
let's loop through this list and create a new segment for each of those
positions. So now we're going to create a new segment
that's a square turtle, that's going to be white,
and we're going to get the segment to go to the position that we're currently
looping on. Now we can delete all of that code
and when we run our code again, you can see we have the same effect.
We have all three pieces. So if you can't remember how tuples work,
be sure to go back to the lessons on tuples in Day 18,
where we talked about how to write them and how they work.
But that completes our first step.
We've managed to create three segments that will comprise our snake
and in the next lesson,
we're going to figure out how to get our snake to start moving by itself on the
screen. So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In the last lesson, we managed to create our snake's body by creating three
squares that were each turtle objects. Now in this lesson,
we're going to move on to the next step where we actually move our snake
automatically across the screen without having to do anything.
So this way the snake is continuously moving forwards and all we have to do as
the user is just to change its direction. Now,
how would we go about moving the snake? Well,
we've already got these different segments that are created, but at the moment,
there's no way of organizing all the segments.
They're kind of just created and placed on screen.
So let's put them into a list called segments,
and let's start out that list as an empty list. And then later on,
once we've created each new segment,
we go ahead and append it to this list.
If we want something to continuously happen in our program,
the way that we've usually done that is through a while loop.
So let's create a new variable called game_is_on and let's set it to true.
And while game is on,
then we're going to move each of the segments.
The simplest way that I could think of to move this segment is to loop through
each of the segments in our list of segments,
and then to get each of these to go ahead and move forward.
So let's say we move forwards by 20 pixels.
Let's go ahead and run this program and see what we get.
The first thing we notice is that the behavior is very weird.
We've got a line that's being drawn
and that comes from each of the segments
which are individual turtles.
And they're all drawing this line as they're moving.
The first thing we want to fix is that line.
So when we create each new segment,
before we tell it to go to its position,
let's go ahead and tell it to pull the pen up. This way
it won't actually draw
and all that we'll see is the actual turtle pieces.
So now we see our three turtle pieces scurrying along like some sort of weird
Caterpillar, but definitely not in a snake like way.
How can we fix this?
One of the things that you notice about turtle is it will first create the
turtle when it runs this line,
the turtle will get created at the center positions, so coordinate (0, 0).
And then it will be moved to whatever position we tell it to go to.
For example, for the third segment, it starts out life at (0, 0)
and then as soon as it gets told to go to this position, it goes to (-40, 0).
Now we can see that happening on screen.
When we created our snake body,
you could see each individual piece being created and then moved to their
location. Now, if we wanted to turn off that animation,
then we would have to use one of the screen class'
methods called tracer. And tracer takes a number as a input,
and it turns the animation on or off.
And when the tracer is turned off,
then we can use the update method to tell our program when to refresh and redraw
the screen. When we think back to the old TV monitors,
the cathode ray tube monitors or CRT monitors,
the way that they worked is by painting on a strip of color line by line
by line, slowly covering the entire screen.
And then once it's done one screen, it's going to go back to the top
and then it's going to paint the pixels for the next scene. And effectively,
it's kind of like how a GIF animation works.
A gif animation is composed of many images. So for example,
if we wanted to animate,
we would increase this line and then we would start drawing out a leaf until
eventually we end up with an animation like this. Now,
when that's all combined and played back very quickly,
then this is the animation you see. In our game
what we could do is we could describe each of these scenes and tell our program
when it should redraw each picture.
So that way we could start out with one picture and then hit update and then do
something else on screen,
maybe move each of our segments and then tell the screen to update again
to show the user the new result.
And then each time we make the changes we want to happen
and then call that update method to tell the screen
to show a new image each time. Let's first turn off the tracer.
So the tracer is a method in the screen class
and in order to turn it off, we're going to set it to zero.
So now once the tracer is off, if we actually try to run our program,
you can see it's just a black screen and nothing will happen.
Even though we've got our while loop and we've got our for loop and lots of
things are meant to be happening, but until we call update,
the screen is not going to refresh and it's not going to show us what's been
happening in our code.
So let's say that we decide to call update after all of the segments have been
created, so right about here. Let's call screen.
update. And now if I hit run,
you'll notice that pretty much immediately. As soon as you run the program,
our snake body will show up, not piece by piece,
but in its entirety. Now, if on the other hand
I move our screen.update line of code into the while loop so that once each
segment moves, I get the screen to update,
then this is what you're going to see.
You see each of the pieces moving along one by one.
Now it's not really clear what's happening.
So I'm going to slow it down a little bit.
And I'm going to do this by importing the time module.
Now I'm going to add the time.sleep and I'm going to get it to sleep by one
second.
So this basically just add a one-second delay after each segment moves.
So each segment moves, the screen updates,
and then we sleep for a second before the next time this happens.
Notice how in this case,
our snake is moving piece by piece.
So first this first piece, and then the second piece,
the third piece with a one-second delay between each movement.
Now,
what happens if we move this screen.update to outside this for-loop?
So basically we only update the screen
once all of the segments have moved forwards.
Now notice how our snake is moving forwards as an entire piece.
It's going to move all three segments forward before the update gets triggered
and we refresh the graphics.
So it looks like as if the whole snake is moving as one piece. Now,
instead of getting it to delay by one second after each segment has moved,
if I move this up here
then it's only going to be delayed by one second
after all three segments have moved. This way
our snake is moving a little bit faster. And we can make it move faster still
if we cut the amount of time that we're sleeping.
So let's change it to 0.1 second sleep
and you can see our snake is now moving at a reasonable speed.
Now you might think that we've solved the challenge and we've now got our snake
to move automatically forwards, but there's a problem.
How do we turn our snake?
Let's see what would happen if we control the snake head and change direction.
Let's say that at some point, we want to turn the snake so that it turns left.
Well, what happens then?
So this first piece is now facing up,
the second piece is going to continue moving forwards as does the third piece.
Now on the next iteration of that for loop,
that first piece is going to keep moving towards North while the second and
third pieces are going to keep moving forward because they're not going to
change their own heading.
We'll get this strange behavior because our snake segments are not linked. To
illustrate this, let me go ahead and change the first segment,
so the segment at index zero, and get it to turn left by 90 degrees.
And notice when I run the code,
you see how that head is moving in a circle all by itself,
and the body has completely left the head and has continued to go forward.
So how can we solve this? Well,
we have to rethink the way that we move our segments. Again,
we have our three segments, but if instead of moving everything forwards,
what if we get our last segment, so segment_3
in this case, to move to the position of the second to last segment,
and then the second segment to move to the position of the first segment,
and then the first segment itself to go forward by 20 paces?
And if we go back to that situation where we're trying to turn our snake,
then in this method, it will still continue to work.
So we've got our three segments, one, two, and three.
Our third segment goes to where the second segment used to be,
second goes to where the one used to be,
and then the one is going to turn and then move to the left.
Now the next turn is the interesting part
because at this point we saw how
if these two pieces just continue moving forward,
they're going to move away from the head of the snake and it's going to move in
opposite directions. But using this method,
our third segment is going to move to where the second segment used to be,
the second goes to where the first used to be,
and the first continues moving forward. This way,
our snake has pretty much straightened out as you would expect this snake to
behave. Now, it's just the matter of actually implementing this,
which is the hard part.
So I'm going to go ahead and delete the part where I told the snake to turn left
and I'm going to delete this for loop
which just moved each of the segments in our list of segments forward by 20
paces. Now, instead, what I'm going to do is I'm going to create a for loop,
but this time I'm going to loop through each of the segments going from the last
segment to the first segment,
so basically in reverse order. Now to do this,
I'm going to use the range type of for-loop.
So I'm going to say for segment number or seg_num in the range,
and this range is going to have
a start, a stop,
and also a step.
So the start is the number that we're going to start
the range from, the stop is where the range is going to end,
and the step is how we're going to get from the start to the stop. For example,
if we wanted a range of 1, 2, 3, then of course start is going to be 1,
stop is going to be 3 and step is going to be +1. Now,
if we wanted a range of 3, 2, 1, however,
then the start is going to be 3,
the stop is going to be 1 and the step is going to be -1.
In our case,
what we actually want is actually to go from 2,
1, 0.
So the start will be 2, the stop will be 0, and the step will be -1.
Now, unfortunately, even though we have these named parameters,
because the range function in Python is actually something that's not quite pure
Python, it's something that comes from the C language,
it doesn't actually let us use these names.
I'll show you when we run our code, this is actually going to give us an error.
But for the time being,
it's actually much easier to visualize this as we write the code inside this
for-loop. So in this case,
the segment number is going to be equal to 2, and then 1,
and then finally 0.
Now we're going to use that to get hold of the last segment from our list of
segments.
So we can tap into that list and then get hold of the last one
using that seg_num.
And then we're going to set it to go to a particular X and Y position.
Now the X and Y position that we want it to go to is going to be the second to
last segment's position.
So how can we get hold of the second to last segment? Well,
we're going to get hold of the segments and then pass in seg_num but then
-1. So when we first start out, we start out with 2.
So the segment at position two is going to be the last segment.
And then the segment at 2 - 1 is going to be the second to last segment.
Now this one we're going to get hold of it's X coordinate
and we're going to set this to a variable called new_x,
and then we're going to do the same and get hold of the new_y.
So we're going to get hold of the second to last segment's Y coordinate,
and then we're going to use these coordinates, new_x and new_y to tell this last
segment to go to the position of the second to last segment.
Now, as I mentioned before,
this range function comes from the C language.
So if we run it with these keyword arguments
it's actually going to give us an error
and it tells us that this range function takes no keyword arguments.
So while it's really nice to use it to visualize it,
if we actually want it to work, we have to delete these.
But just before I delete it,
I want to this so that we're no longer using these hard-coded numbers.
So instead of going from 2 to 0,
we want to go to the length of the segments.
So in the future, if we had 10 segments or 20 segments,
that our code would still work. Now,
the length of the segment is actually three to begin with.
And we know that lists start counting from zero,
so 0, 1, 2, ... the last position is going to be the length - 1,
and then we're going to stop at the zeroth segment.
So now we can go ahead and delete these named arguments.
And we end up with this. Now we can run our code and we won't get any errors.
Notice how all three of the segments went to the same position,
the position of the first segment. So in addition to moving these segments,
remember that we also have to move the very first segment actually forwards by
say, 20 paces. So at the very end of all of this code
outside of the four loop,
we're going to get hold of the first segment, so segment at position zero,
and then we're going to get it to move forward by 20 paces.
So now when I run this again,
you can see our snake is now moving freely forwards and even if at some point,
the snake needed to turn,
let's say it turned left by 90 degrees,
then our code is still going to work.
Notice how our snake is now turning in a circle and all of the subsequent
pieces are following the head along its path. That's it.
This is the code that will get our snake to automatically move forwards.
Now, there was quite a few concepts mentioned in here,
and you have to think about the segments in terms of how they move in the graph
and also this idea of getting hold of the last segment and then telling it to go
to the position of the second to last segment and then doing this for all of the
segments.
So it's a little bit mind-bending and it might be worth just taking a second
look at this code and going back in the video where I explain how this worked in
the slides, just so that you're really clear with how this works.
Once you are, then you can move forward and head over to the next lesson.
So far,
we've managed to get our starting segments for our snake to appear on screen.
And then we managed to get our snake to automatically move forwards and to
figure out a way for the tail of the snake to follow where the head is going.
Now it's time to tidy up our code a little bit so that all the parts that are
related to the snake's behavior and the snake's appearance go into a separate
class. So that by the end of the whole project,
we should end up with three classes; a snake class, a food class,
and a scoreboard. And all of these classes will be in separate files,
managing only one thing.
And the goal of the refactoring is so that you could create a separate file,
snake.py, import the snake class that you've created in that file.
And then once you initialize this snake,
it will do everything that we have so far and create our three segments snake
onto the screen. And then finally, while the game loop is running,
we're going to get the snake to continuously move forward just by calling snake
.move. This is what you're aiming for.
Have a think about how you can take the existing code that you've got in the
main.py and extract all of the snake related functionality into a separate
snake class and make your main.py end up looking like this.
The program should do the exact same things as before.
The only difference is how the code is organized. Have a think about this.
You might need to revise some of the things you learned about how to create
classes, how to create objects from the previous lessons.
But pause the video,
I want you to give this a good try before you come back when we'll go through
the solution together.
Alright.
So the first thing we need to do is of course,
to create our snake class. And remember that in Python, class names are in Pascal
case, so the first letter needs to be capitalized.
And then inside this class, I'm going to create my init.
Now the code in here is going to determine what should happen when we initialize
a new snake object. So firstly,
I'm going to take the starting positions and take it over to our snake.py.
Now, I'm actually going to put this in as a constant. So right at the top,
and remember that in Python,
the constants are named with all caps like this,
and also with snake case with underscores separating each of the words.
Now we can use these starting positions inside our snake class to create our new
snake. So we're going to need to move our segments over as well.
So let's create a new attribute that's associated with our snake class called
segments. And remember,
we're going to need to use self when we're working within a class.
After that, we're going to create our snake.
So I'm going to create a method called create_snake down here.
And this method is going to do everything that we previously had over here,
but we're going to move that into this method.
Now there's a couple of things we need to change. Firstly,
we change these starting positions into a constant,
so let's make that consistent.
Second thing is that we need to import turtle into this file from the turtle
module in order to use it to create a new segment.
And then finally, in order to refer to our attribute segments,
we have to say self.segments and then append this new segment to our snake
segments. That's this part done.
The next thing we need to do is to get rid of this code and move it inside the
snake. So again,
I'm going to create another method that's associated with the snake class called
move. So when the snake moves,
it's going to look to this code to figure out how it should do that. Again,
because we're inside our class, it's no longer just segments.
It's now self.segments.
So let's go ahead and replace it in all the places where we have our red
underlines and now that's pretty much it for our snake class.
We can create a new snake object and each time we do that,
it creates a three-segment snake using the starting positions
which are declared at the top. So if we want the snake to show up on screen,
then we're going to have to first import the snake class from the snake file,
and then we're going to create a new snake object from that class.
And once this line gets triggered, then we're going to be calling
create_snake and our three-segment snake will show up on screen like this.
Now the next step is while the game is on,
the screen is going to update every 0.1 second.
So that's essentially what this is doing.
It's saying that delay for 0.1 second and then refresh the screen.
And every time the screen refreshes,
we're going to get the snake to move forwards by one step.
Now at the moment, each step is defined here as 20.
So again, I want to extract that into a constant up here,
so we're going to call it the MOVE_DISTANCE
and we can set that to 20 and then change this to use the constant here.
And the reason why we have all these constants is so that if we wanted to tweak
our game,
say if we wanted the snake to start at a different position or for it to move
further each time, then we don't have to dig through the body of our code.
All we have to do is look at the top,
look at all the things that we can change and then change it accordingly.
So now coming back to our code here,
all we now really have here is just these few lines of code and everything that
is snake related,
creating the snake or moving the snake is now abstracted into it's own class.
This way when something goes wrong with our snake,
we know who's responsible and which file to dig through
to figure out the reason. Now, at this point,
if we go ahead and rerun our code,
you can see that our program works exactly the same as before.
Nothing should have changed and nothing should have broken ow because our game
isn't yet able to go into the game over sequence,
there's no way of stopping the snake other than hitting the stop button.
So don't worry if at this stage inside your console
you see a lot of red and it says things like keyboard interrupt,
or trace back errors. All of these are normal.
The thing that you're more concerned about is whether if, when you run the game,
whether if it actually works like it used to,
so namely your snake moving across the screen.
If it does exactly what it used to and your main.py is now much simpler and
all of your snake functionality and behavior and appearance is now inside its
own class, then you have successfully achieved the goal of this lesson.
So we've now managed to create a snake body, move the snake,
and we've even managed to put our snake related code into a separate class.
Now the next step is to figure out how to control the snake.
Now we're going to control the snake by using the up, down, left, and right arrow
keys.
And we're going to be using our key bindings that we learned in yesterday's
lessons to be able to translate this into a change in direction of the snake. In
our code right after we create our snake,
we're going to call the screen.listen method to start listening for
keystrokes.
And the keystrokes that we're going to listen for are the up, down, left, and right
arrow keys. Now those keys are described by a string.
So it's a uppercase 'U' and then a 'p' so this would be up.
And then it's again, uppercase 'Down', 'Left',
and 'Right'.
These are the keys that it will detect, obviously the up,
down, left, and right arrow keys on the keyboard.
The function that you're going to bind it to is going to be a function in the
snake object and it's going to have the same name. So for example,
it'd be snake.up,
and that will be triggered when the up key is pressed.
And then the same thing happens with snake.down when the down key gets
pressed and then again with left and right.
Your job is to have a think about how you can create these methods up,
down, left, and right, in the snake class
so that when the up key or the down key is detected,
you can move the snake and change its heading accordingly.
So remember that up is going to be towards North, down is going to be South, left
is going to be towards the left of the screen and right is going to be towards
the right of the screen.
So have a think about the headings that we spoke about in previous lessons.
And if you need to, it might be worth just setting up a brand new project,
getting a turtle up and running and then setting it's heading from zero all the
way to 360, just to see which direction it's actually facing.
If you managed to complete the challenge,
you should be able to control the snake
and even though it's going to continue moving forward,
you now determine which direction it moves in by using the arrow keys.
Pause the video now and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right. So I've already created all of these lines of code
which is going to get the screen to listen for these key strokes.
And then when it detects it,
it's going to call these methods in the snake class.
So inside our snake class, let's go ahead and create those methods.
So we've got up,
down,
left, and right.
Let's think about how we can turn the snake up. In order to turn the snake,
the segment that we're most interested in is the first segment.
That's basically the head of the snake.
So we could tap into self.segments and then get hold of the zeroth segment,
which is the first one, and then change its heading by calling setheading.
And then we can tell it to, for example, if it's up,
then it should actually be turning to the 90-degree direction,
which is actually towards North.
Now I'm going to go ahead and put a pass on all of these other methods,
just so that we can actually test our code and it doesn't give us any errors
because these functions are currently empty. Now, if you don't have the pass,
it won't like it because Python doesn't like the idea of empty functions.
But now we can at least just test this one thing.
So when we run our code,
we should be able to hit the up key and you can see the snake changed direction.
Let me just do that again.
And this is because we managed to get the first segment,
the head of the snake, to change
it's heading to 90 degrees and then the rest of the body will follow because
it's continuously moving on every tick of the clock.
So using this, we can now set the rest of the methods.
But because we're going to need the head of the snake quite a few times in our
code, it might make sense to actually create a separate attribute.
So after we've created the snake, after we've got some segments inside this list,
we can create an attribute called head,
which is going to be the head of the snake.
And this can be equal to self.segments at index zero. Now,
remember if you have this line of code above the create_snake,
it's probably going to error out because at this point the segments is empty
and if you try to get the first item from it, it's not going to allow you to.
So look at the positioning of the code here. Now, once we've got this set,
we can go down here and change everywhere
where we need to use the head of the snake. So for example,
when we're moving the head forwards and when we're moving it up,
left, down, and right. Now we can set
each of these headings. Up is going to be a heading of 90, down is going to be
270,
left is 180 and right is 0.
These directions are just simply counter-clockwise.
So the turtle starts out pointing towards East and that's a heading of zero,
and then going anticlockwise, up is 90, left is 180, down as 270.
This can be easily verified just by testing out some numbers, right?
You could just put some numbers in there and then just try it out and see which
direction it goes and then you'll be able to figure it out.
But we've also mentioned this in previous lessons
so you could also go back and take a look at when we looked at the heading of
the turtle. So now if I go ahead and run this,
then you should see that I can now freely control the snake by going left or
right or down or up. And if you managed to do this,
then you should consider yourself successful. Now,
while I was testing this code,
I realized that there's something about the snake game that we haven't really
accounted for.
And it's the fact that the snake can't move back on itself.
It can't go forwards and then go the opposite direction because that requires
the head to change directions.
And this is not allowed in the official snake game.
So how can we code this into our game? Well,
we have to figure out when the head is pointing towards down direction,
then we shouldn't allow it to go up. And similarly, when it's pointing up,
we shouldn't let it go down, when it's pointing right
we shouldn't let it go left. So at the top here,
I'm going to create some constants.
I'm going to create a UP direction and it's going to be 90, DOWN direction is going to
be 270, LEFT is going to be equal to 180 and RIGHT is going to be equal to
0. So now that I've got all of these as constants,
I can go in here and set the heading to instead say UP when it needs to go up,
DOWN, LEFT and RIGHT. In addition,
we're going to do an if check.
So we're going to say if the current self.head.heading
is not equal to down, well, in that case,
it's allowed to move up. So this way,
it just means that if the current heading is pointed down,
it can't move up. But for all other directions,
if it's already moving up or left or right,
then it can change the heading to up.
Now be really careful here because it's not just self.head.heading,
it's actually heading as a method because remember that the head of the snake is
the first segment of our list of segments
and each segment is a individual turtle.
The turtle has a heading method
which will give you a direction in terms of these 360-degree numbers,
and then we can use that to check to see if it's equal to down.
And if it is, then it's not allowed to go up.
So using this logic,
see if you can complete the rest of the three methods so that when you run your
code, you can turn in all directions.
But when you're facing one direction,
you can't go backwards, like this.
Okay?
Alright. So it's going to be pretty straightforward.
If it's already going up, then it's not allowed to go down.
If it's already going right,
then it's not allowed to go left. And finally,
if it's already going left, then it's not allowed to go right.
So this way, even though our snake can move freely through the space,
it can't go back on itself. And there we have it.
We've now managed to create our snake, get it to move and control it
using our key presses.
Even though it seems like our game is still not quite there,
we've already come so far.
So this comes up to our hour mark
and it's now time to take a break, refresh your minds,
look at some of the concepts that you might be confused about that we covered
today,
especially this concept of using the update to refresh the screen,
as well as using the timer
to delay the refresh so that we can control how often it happens.
And then using our key bindings as well as separating all classes.
We looked at a lot of things today. Now, tomorrow,
once you're rested and fresh and ready,
we're going to be finishing up the snake game.
And we're going to be learning about inheritance as well as slicing
and we're going to be building out the full functionality of this game.
So I hope you're looking forward to it. I certainly am. I'll see you tomorrow.
Hey guys,
welcome to Day 21 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to learn about class inheritance, slicing,
and we're going to be finishing up our snake game. Today
I wanted to introduce you to another really important concept in Object Oriented
Programming,
which is the idea that classes can inherit from other classes,
inheriting attributes, inheriting methods,
basically a way to make it simpler
to modify classes and give them more capabilities.
Now we're also going to be looking at how Python allows us to slice things like
lists and dictionaries. And we're going to be looking at how we can do that.
And once we've acquired all of these skills,
then we'll be able to finish up our snake game and complete the last four
stages. So detecting collision with food, creating a scoreboard,
detecting collision with the wall and with the tail.
Once you are ready, head over to the next lesson and let's get started learning
about class inheritance.
Let's talk about another feature of Object Oriented
Programming that's really, really handy.
And it's something that we call class inheritance. How does this work?
Well,
let's say that you codet up a robot chef and you give it a bunch of
functionality. You tell it how to bake, how to stir, how to measure.
And then at some point you decide actually, you know, in my restaurant,
I also need a pastry chef.
Now this pastry chef will need to know some of the things that a chef knows how
to do, but it also needs something extra.
So you don't want to create this pastry chef entirely from scratch. Instead,
what you want to do is you want to be able to take the methods you've already
defined for the chef class and then just add to it,
add a few other relevant methods
like how to knead dough or how to whisk some eggs.
So it's process of inheriting behavior and appearance from an existing class is
known as class inheritance. When we're talking about class inheritance,
you can inherit both appearance, so attributes,
like for example, if you inherited the same eyes as your mother,
or if you inherited the same nose as your grandfather,
but you can also inherit behavior.
So maybe you chop tomatoes in the same way that your dad chops tomatoes.
And if you believe my mother, I'm lazy in the same way that my dad is lazy.
So not only can inherit appearance, but we can also inherit behavior.
Now, how does inheritance actually work in terms of the code? Well,
we can define a class, let's call it Fish,
and it has an initializer.
Now in order to get this Fish class to inherit from another class,
all we have to do is to
add a set of parentheses after the name of the class and then provide the
class that we want to inherit from.
So in this case our fish is inheriting from the animal class.
And then in order to get a hold of everything that an animal has and is, so its
attributes and methods, all we have to do is inside the init,
add this super().__init__().
And the super refers to the superclass.
So basically, initialize everything that the superclass can do in our fish
class. Let's take a look at this in terms of real code.
First,
I'm going to create a animal class and this animal class is going to have an
initializer where we're able to define some attributes, right?
So let's say that all animals have, um, two eyes.
So num_eyes = 2. Now at the same time,
I'm also gonna define a method associated with this animal class.
Let's say that all animals know how to breathe.
So inside this breathe method, I'm going to keep it quite simple.
I'm just going to say inhale, exhale.
So that's breathing done. Now later on,
I decide to define a fish class and this fish class probably also knows how to
do certain things. So for example, maybe it knows how to swim, right?
Right now, if I create a object from this Fish class,
let's say I create an object called nemo that's created from the Fish class,
then I can say nemo.swim.
And you can see when I run this code, it says that Nemo is moving in water.
Now,
what if I wanted this Fish class to inherit everything that the animal class can
do,
including the attribute number of eyes and also the method breathe.
All I have to do is to add this animal class after the name of the fish class
inside parentheses,
and then I have to add the initializer and inside the initializer,
I have to trigger a call to the superclass, which is in this case,
the animal class.
And then I'm going to call the initializer, like this.
So now what these two parts of the code does is it allows anything that's
created from my fish class to inherit all of the attributes and methods from the
superclass, which is the animal class.
Now I can get my Nemo to start breathing. And you can see
if I hit run, then it will also inhale and exhale.
And in addition,
if I wanted to print nemo.num_eyes,
then you can see this is also going to print 2.
So now my object that's created from the Fish class now has access to all the
attributes and methods from the superclass that inherited from the animal class.
Now, what if I wanted to inherit a method?
So get all the things that it does, for example, the breathe method.
But what if I wanted to modify it a little bit? So for example,
a fish does, in fact, breathe, but it kind of breathes underwater.
So let's say I want to define the breathe function
and I wanted to have the same functionality as the superclass
which I'm inheriting from. So I want to print inhale, exhale,
but I also want to do something extra. Well, in this case,
we would get hold of the superclass and then call breathe on it.
This means we're going to do everything that the breathe method from the
superclass does, so all of this, but afterwards
we're going to do something a little bit more special. So we're going to say
we're doing this underwater. Now,
when this line nemo.breathe gets run,
you can see what happens is it will print out inhale, exhale
and this comes from the super class' breathe method here.
And then afterwards, it will print its own unique twist on breathing,
which is doing this underwater. By learning about inheritance,
what it allows us to do is to take an existing class that we've created or
somebody else has created,
and then build on top of it without having to reinvent the wheel and redefine
everything that's in that class. So in the next lesson,
I'm going to show you how we can inherit from the turtle class to upgrade the
turtle
to be able to do extra things such as creating a piece of food or creating a
scoreboard. For all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right. So now that we've learned all about inheritance,
it's time to apply the theory to our snake game,
and we're going to use it to detect collision with food.
Our snake should be able to head a piece of food,
which is just going to be a blue circle. And every time it touches the food,
the circle moves to a new, random location on the screen.
If we take a look at our code,
you can see that the main.py controls the entire game.
It dictates how the screen should behave and how the snake behaves.
Now, everything that's to do with a snake,
it's a parent's and behavior, is all captured inside a class.
So everything snake related is inside the snake class.
So what we want to be able to do is to create a new food.py file
and this food.py is going to be its own class.
And the food class is going to know how to render itself as a small circle on
the screen. And then every time the snake touches the food,
then that food is going to move to a new random location.
So let's create the initializer for this food class.
And one of the things that we're going to need to do is we're going to need to
import turtle. So from the turtle module,
let's import the turtle class.
And this piece of food that we're going to see onscreen is going to be a turtle
object. Instead of creating it as an attribute in this class,
so self.food = turtle like this,
what we want to be able to do is we actually want this class, food, to inherit
from the turtle class.
So that way this food class is going to have all of the capabilities of the
turtle class,
but it's also going to have some specific things that we're going to tell it
how to do so that it behaves like an actual piece of food.
Here's a quick challenge. From what you learned in the last lesson,
can you figure out how to make this food class inherit from the turtle class?
Pause the video and give that a
go.
All right.
So we mentioned that there's only two steps we need to do. First is after the
name of the class
we add some parentheses and then put in the name of the class that we want to
inherit from. So in this case, it's the turtle class.
And then the next thing we need to do is we need to call the turtle's init
method inside the food's init method.
And you can see that as soon as you've added this inheritance here, this init
starts giving us a warning. And when you click on it, you can see
it says call to __init__ of superclass is missed.
So it actually knows what we need to do next.
That means if we click on the light bulb,
we can actually automatically just add in the superclass' call. This,
of course, you could just type it out and it's good for practice,
but in case you're ever wondering if you get these warnings,
you can always take a look at what PyCharm is recommending.
Now we've actually created our food class and we've inherited from the turtle
class.
What that means is we can now start using things that are from the turtle class.
For example, I can straight up say self.shape,
and it knows what shape is.
This is a method that the turtle class has that I'm now going to modify in my
food class. So when I initialize a new piece of food,
I'm going to make sure that it has a circular shape,
and I'm also going to get it to pen up so that it doesn't draw.
And then I'm going to define it's size.
And there's something called a shape size which I can use.
And what this allows me to do is to stretch the turtle along its length and
along its width. Now I'm not actually going to stretch it bigger than it is.
It's normally 20 by 20 pixels,
but I wanna turn it into 10 by 10 pixels.
So I'm going to stretch the length by 0.5,
so I'm basically going to half it.
And then I'm going to stretch the width also by 0.5.
So now it should be a 10 by 10 circle
which I've created by defining the shape size. Now,
remember all of these methods, shape, size,
pen up, shape, comes from this turtle superclass and we're only able to use it
because we're inheriting from the superclass so that our food class is now also
sort of a turtle, but it's more like a souped-up turtle. Finally,
it let's go ahead and define the color which I'm going to set as blue,
but of course, feel free to set it as anything you like.
And I'm also going to set the speed of my turtle to fastest. This way
I don't have to look at the animation of the food being created at the center of
the screen, and then moving to the location that I want it to.
Speaking of moving, we're going to need to use the goto to get it
to go to a random X, Y location.
So let's import the random module and let's create a random X,
which is going to be random.randint. Remember that our screen is 600 by 600
so that means our X-axis goes from -300 to +300
and our Y-axis goes from +300 to -300.
Now we don't want our food to be right at the edge of the screen,
cause it will be really hard to get the snake to go to right at the edge.
It'll probably just die on the wall.
So we want to maybe subtract this a little bit.
So we can go from -280 to +280 and the same on the Y-axis.
So let's generate a random integer from -280 to +280
and let's generate a random Y-integer in the same range.
So now we can tell our food to go to a random X and a random Y. All of this
is going to happen
as soon as we create a new food object from the food class.
Remember, whenever you initialize a new object from the class, the
init gets called. Back in our main.py
right below where we initialized our snake, we're going to initialize our food.
So food equals the food class and then parentheses.
And of course we need to get hold of our Food class from the food file,
like this.
Another thing you'll notice is that this turtle is now grayed out because we're
not using that class anywhere inside the main.py. So we can delete that
which gets rid of all our warnings on this page
and we get the green checkmark. Our food.py looks good,
our snake.py looks good,
and we're now ready to go ahead and run this code.
Notice how we've got our snake moving around on screen.
And at this point it doesn't really matter about the walls.
It's just moving around anywhere it likes. But more importantly,
we've got our food being randomly generated on the screen right here.
Now the next step is how can we detect when the snake and the food have come
into contact and then to tell the food to move itself to a new
random location? Well, we're going to do that inside our main.py.
Right after we've got our screen updating, our snake moving,
then we're going to detect
collision with food.
And we're going to do that by using a method from the turtle class called
distance.
The distance method works by comparing the distance from this turtle to whatever
it is that you put inside the parentheses.
So the X could be a pair of numbers, X and Y,
or it could simply just be a turtle instance.
So you're comparing this turtle against another turtle,
and you're trying to get hold of the distance between the two turtles.
So what that means is we can check to see if the distance from the first segment
of the snake,
so it remember that would be snake.head.distance,
and then the distance that we want to know is what is the distance from the
snake's head to the food. At this point,
you can check to see if it is less than a certain amount,
then it's pretty likely that the snake head is now colliding with the food.
So we know that the food is 10 by 10.
So if we add a bit of a buffer, let's just say,
if this snake head is within 15 pixels of the food or even closer,
so if the distance is less than 15,
then we can be pretty much certain that they've collided.
So let's go ahead and print something. I'll just write nom nom nom.
So if we go ahead and run our code and let's just get our snake back into view,
and if I now go and touch this piece of food, if I can,
then you can see nom nom nom being printed in the console.
Now let's go ahead and touch it again. You can see,
as soon as I collide with that food,
I get that print statement executing.
So now, instead of just writing nom nom nom,
let's figure out what we need to do next.
What we want to happen is the food should go to a new random location.
And, of course, that comes from this part of the code.
So why don't we go ahead and create a new method which we'll call refresh.
And this refresh method is going to create a new random X,
a new random Y, and then get the food to go to that new, random location.
Then inside our init, we can simply just call self.refresh.
So be careful that you didn't right reset because that's one of the methods from
the turtle class that we're inheriting from.
But what we actually want is to call this refresh method so that the food goes
to a new random location. And then back inside our main.py,
when the snake head collides with the food,
then we're going to get the food to refresh its own location.
So check this out. Now, when I hit the food,
then you can see the food now appears at a new,
random location. Like that. Now,
depending on how accurate you want the snake to hit the food,
so it might need to hit it dead on,
or if you're happy with it just gliding past and counting that as a collision,
then you could decrease the number here from 15 to 10.
Now I've done a bit of testing and this number seems to be the best distance in
order to get a valid collision,
but feel free to tweak around with the number and see how it goes. There we go.
We've managed to figure out how to create a piece of food by inheriting from the
turtle class, get the food to be generated,
and then to move to a new random location
every time the snake head collides with the food.
Now I know that in the snake game,
the snake segments increase once it hits a piece of food,
but we're only going to add that functionality at the very end of this project
when we're detecting collision with the snake tail.
So don't worry about that for now.
Guys, we've already come really, really far.
We've done all of this and now we're on this stage, creating a scoreboard.
So what we want is to be able to write some text in our program that keeps track
of the score, of how many pieces of food we've actually managed to eat. Now,
the score should update every single time we hit a new piece of food and it's
going to stay there and keep updating itself
every time we hit a new piece of food.
Now this scoreboard is also going to be a turtle.
So one of the things that you can do with your turtle is you can get it to write
a piece of text.
And this is what the method looks like in the documentation.
You can tell it what it should write, what kind of alignment you want,
do you want it to be in the center of the screen,
on the left or right side of the screen? And then what kind of font you want?
So the font name, font size and font type,
so normal or heavy or bold or underlined,
and we would call it more or less like this.
So here's a challenge for you.
I want you to go ahead and create a new file called a scoreboard.py.
And inside this file, I want you to create a new scoreboard class.
Now,
this scoreboard class is going to inherit from the turtle class,
just as we did with the food class.
And then the scoreboard is going to be a turtle
which knows how to keep track of the score and how to display it in our program.
Feel free to choose whatever font you want, whatever size you want,
but the end outcome we're looking for is something that looks a bit like this
and the score is going to need to be tracked inside that scoreboard class.
And it needs to be increased by one every single time the snake eats a piece of
food. You're going to need the help of the documentation,
you're going to need to read up on how this turtle.write method works,
and you're also probably going to need this turtle.clear so that you clear
the writing every time you update the score.
Have a think about how you would solve this and then go ahead,
pause the video and give it a go.
[inaudible]
All right.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to create my scoreboard class.
And as I mentioned,
this class needs to inherit from the turtle class.
So from the turtle module,
let's get hold of the actual turtle class so we can use it inside this file.
And then I'm going to add it to my scoreboard as the superclass.
Now, if I create my inits,
I can go ahead and use this light bulb to insert the superclass call.
So now my scoreboard is a class that can do everything a turtle class do.
And one of the things I want it to do is I want it to keep track of the score.
So let's say it starts out at zero,
and we want to be able to write this onto the screen. So we can say self.
write, and let's use an f-string to say score,
and then we can insert the self.score value in here.
And then we can add whether if we want it to be aligned to the center,
for example, and then we can also add a font if we need to.
Let's use the same font as here, Arial,
and then we're going to make the font size a bit bigger,
and then we're going to keep it as normal.
So I'm going to choose an Arial font, size 24,
and then the style is going to be normal.
And as you can see here,
I'm getting a warning here and it's telling me that it expected a tuple,
but instead it just got a single string.
So let's just compare this against the documentation code
and you can see that this is meant to be a tuple instead of just a single piece
of string. So let me go ahead and fix that.
Let's add some parentheses around this,
and then this Arial is going to be a string,
this 24 is going to be a number and the normal is going to be a string.
And now our errors have gone away.
So now going back to our main.py
let's go ahead and create our scoreboard
as an object from the scoreboard class,
which of course means that we need to import it into this file.
So from the scoreboard file import the Scoreboard class.
And now if I run this code, somewhere in the middle
there I've got a scoreboard,
but because it's actually black, you can't really see it.
It's really important that we change the color of the scoreboard turtle before
we write the text,
because if it was written as black and then we change it to white,
you still won't notice a difference.
So if I change the self.color right here to white and I hit run,
then you can see that scoreboard showing up.
But if I move this line of code to after we've written it,
then it won't actually make a difference. It's still written in black
somewhere on there. Now, in addition,
we want to get rid of the turtle that shows up when we create our scoreboard
because all we want it to do is we want it to write,
we don't want it to actually show up a turtle. Self.hideturtle, and
now that little arrow disappears.
And we probably don't want this scoreboard to be bang in the middle.
So let's move it.
Let's tell it to go to a particular X and Y position.
Now, in example, here, I've got it in the center, right at the top.
So we can keep the X as zero, but let's move the Y further up to the top.
So let's say something around 270. And now if we test it again,
you can see that the turtle went to the top,
but this happened after this line was already written. So again,
this needs to happen before we write.
And now if we refresh, you can see it's moved to the top,
but it's also drawn on a path to do that. So instead of doing that,
we can tell it to self.penup before it moves to this location.
There we have it. We've got our score showing up at the top. Now,
all that's left to do is to keep track of the score and to increase it whenever
the snake hits a new piece of food.
So we know that that happens inside this if statement,
when the snake head collides with the food, then we refresh the food,
but we also want to increase the score.
So let's go ahead and create a function inside our scoreboard class called
increase_score.
And this function is going to take the self.score and add one to it.
And then it's going to call self.write.
So now back inside our main.py,
we can get whole of our scoreboard object and tell it to increase score
whenever the snake collides with the food. So let's test this again.
And if I manage to hit the food,
then you can see that the score is being updated,
but what's happening is that the score is being written on top of the previous
scores. So it's just all overlapping with each other.
So instead,
what we need to do is between each time we update the scoreboard,
we actually have to delete what was previously on there.
And because we've now got these two lines
which are pretty much identical in two places,
let's go ahead and create a function instead. We'll call update_scoreboard,
and inside this function, we'll have our self.write.
And we can call self.update_scoreboard here and also here.
So now before we increase the score and call update scoreboard,
we can call self.clear to clear the previous text that was written by this
turtle, which is the scoreboard. Now, if we run this again
you can see that when I do score,
my scoreboard is wiped and then the new text code is written.
So it doesn't overlap with the previous scoreboard.
The final thing I want to do just as a finishing touch is I don't like having
these hard-coded pieces of text inside the body of my programs.
So instead it would be much better if we could take these pieces of texts out
and create constants with them.
So we could have one that's called ALIGNMENT set to center,
and then another one called a FONT,
which is going to be set to this tuple.
And then I can use these constants down here,
so align = ALIGNMENT, font = FONT. That way,
when I decide that I want to change something about the alignment or the font,
so for example instead of Arial,
I might go for something that is a little bit more video-gamey
sort of font like courier,
then I don't have to dig through the body of my program to find out where it was
defined. I can just look at the top
which contains all the constants and then fix it right here. That shouldn't have
changed any of the functionality. It's just made our scoreboard look a bit more
video-gamey, and you can see how it works perfectly.
We've coded up the majority of this game now already.
All that's left to do is to define the two situations where we might get game
over.
And that is detecting collision with wall and detecting collision with tail.
So let's tackle the easier one first. We want the snake
once it gets past a certain point
that's very close to the four walls to trigger the game over sequence.
So we know that we have a 600 by 600 screen and the X and Y axis go to 300 and
-300 at all four sides.
So if we create a boundary box that say 280 here,
280 here, -280 and -280,
then as soon as the snake head touches that position,
then once it zoomed past it,
then we can say that the snake has pretty much hit the wall.
Now this number is not perfect,
it's just what I found to work after doing a lot of testing.
And this is the case with a lot of games, you have to test it, run it,
see if it works the way you want it to. But let's go ahead and add a comment,
detect collision with a wall,
and let's create our if statement.
So what we want to say is if the snake.head has a X coordinate that is
greater than 280, so it's gone too far to the right,
or if it has a X coordinate that is less than -280,
so it's gone too far to the left,
or if it has a Y coordinate
that's greater than 280, so too far to the top,
or if it has a Y coordinate that is less than -280
so it's gone too far to the bottom, if any of these four situations occur
then it basically means that the snake has hit the wall.
So what do we want to happen when the snake hits the wall? Well,
we want to change this game_is_on to false because what that's going to allow us
to do is to exit the while loop and basically
end the snake movement and end the game.
Let's go ahead and test this out.
So let's let the snake hit the wall and you can see it no longer continues
moving forward. But for the user, this might be a little bit confusing.
It doesn't seem like it's actually game over. It seems like it's just crushed.
So let's go ahead into our scoreboard
which does a lot of the writing and let's create a new function
which is going to be called game_over.
And this game_over function is going to simply just write some texts,
not the score, but instead
it's just going to write 'GAME OVER' onto the screen using the same alignment and
the same font. But instead of it at the position
which we initially defined which is right at the top,
let's go ahead and get it to go to the center, which is at (0, 0).
So now when the snake hits the wall,
not only does the snake stop moving,
but we're also going to get the scoreboard to trigger the game over a sequence.
So that means when it hits the wall, game over shows up in the middle of the
screen, and you can still see the score that was written previously
because we don't actually hit clear before we write this game over.
And this means that the user can see that the game is over, the snake has stopped
moving, and they can see their final score.
So let's try to score some points. And once I've done that,
I'm gonna hit a wall and it's game over and I can see that my score was 2.
All right guys, we're at the final stretch.
All we have left to do now is to figure out how we can detect when the snake
collides with its own tail. As a snake gets longer and longer,
it's more likely that at some point the head might hit some part of the tail. And
in the snake game, this means it's game over.
So we have to figure out how we can detect this and then trigger the game over
sequence.
One of the things that we've left until now is a way of extending the snake
every time it gets some food,
because at the moment what's happening is our snake is staying the same size
with only three segments. But now we need to change that.
We need to add a segment to the snake every single time it hits the food so that
it grows in length and we can start detecting collision with the tail.
The place we're going to do that is inside our snake class.
So we're going to create a function that's going to be called extend.
And this extend function is going to add a new segment to the snake.
So we're probably going to need another function,
which is going to be called add_segment,
and this is going to require the position to add the segment to essentially.
Notice how this is the part of the code where we actually add the segment.
So lets take it out of the for loop and put it into the add_segment.
And so we can now call this function, self.add_segment
and then pass in this position that we're looping through.
These two functions together are going to create our snake.
But in addition,
we're going to use this add_segment when we want to extend the snake.
But what position do we want that last piece to go to? Well,
we're going to get hold of the list of segments and we're going to get hold of
the last one. Remember that with lists in Python,
you can write
a negative number so that you start counting from the end of the list.
For example, if our list was 1, 2, and 3,
then this list at minus one position would be
3.
Effectively
we're getting hold of the last segment in our list and then we're going to get
hold of it's position. And remember,
this is a method that comes from the turtle class and we can call it by writing
position and then parentheses and we'll get the position of that segment.
And then we're going to add this new segment
to the same position as the last segment.
So now if inside our main.py
every time our snake collides with the food,
then not only are we going to refresh the food,
but we're also going to get the snake to extend itself.
So lets go ahead and run this game again. And notice how this time,
once I hit the food,
the snake actually extends itself and it gets longer each time.
So now we're able to think about how to detect tail collision because as the
snake gets longer, this tail collision becomes more of a problem.
We're more likely to get tangled with our own tail.
Let's go ahead and add a comment here which will say 'Detect
collision with tail.' And the way that we want to check this is we wanna say if
the head collides with any segment
in the tail,
then this means that we're going to trigger the game over sequence.
So how can we detect if the head collides with any segment in the tail?
Well,
we could loop through our list of segments in the snake.
So we could say for segment in snake.segments,
so out of all the snakes segments, let's go through each one of them.
And then we can say that well,
if the snake.head has a distance of,
let's say, I don't know,
less than 10 from any of those segments that we're currently looping through, well
that probably is a collision, right? So in that case,
we're going to set the game_is_on to false and we're going to get the
scoreboard to trigger the game over sequence.
Now there's just one problem with this. If we go ahead and run the code
as it is, you can see that immediately we get game over.
And the reason is because out of all of the snake segments,
the head is the first segment.
So when we loop through each of the segments,
the first segment is going to be the snake head.
And so we're detecting if the snake head has a distance to
the snake head of less than 10, which of course it is going to.
So we need some sort of way of bypassing the snakehead.
So we could say if the current segment that we're looping through is equal to, so
double equal, to the snake.head, well, in this case,
we're going to pass. But if this is not the case, so in the elif
after the if statement,
then we can check to see if the snake head has a distance to the segment of less
than 10. Now, if we rerun this code,
you'll see that it works exactly as we expect it to.
We can move our snake around and as soon as the head hits the body,
then it's game over for us.
We've pretty much now completed the snake game. But in the next lesson,
I want to talk about a special functionality in Python
which is called slicing.
And this is something that you will often see in code in the wild,
and we'll use that to improve our code just a little bit more. So
for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Now while our snake game works now with all of the functionality that we set out
to create,
there's just one thing that bothers me a little bit about this code, and it's how
wordy this section is.
All that we're trying to do is make sure that we're detecting the distance from
all of the segments that we're looping through in snake.segments
other than the first one.
Surely there's an easier way of doing this rather than writing all of these
lines of code. And indeed there is. But in order to use it,
we have to learn about a Python concept known as slicing.
Let's say that we had a list of piano keys all the way from a to g, and we wanted
to get hold of a small section of this list.
Let's say we wanted to slice the list so that we only get the c,
d, and e keys from this list. How would we do that
using Python? Well,
one way of doing that is you could write a for loop and you could check, well,
is it c, is a d, is it d. If so, then add it to a new list.
But that's really convoluted. We have a much,
much better way of doing that in Python. And it's known as slicing.
This is what the syntax would look like. We would get hold of our lists,
piano_keys, and then we would use a set of square brackets,
but instead of accessing just one item with a position,
we get a set of items by slicing it from position 2 to position 5.
This might be a little bit confusing because we know that a is that position
0, b is at 1, c is at 2,
but the one at position 5 is actually f, so how does this get us c, d, and e?
Well, you have to visualize it like this.
Imagine that zero position is actually at the beginning of the list before where
a starts. And at the end of the list,
we're actually at the slicing position of 7.
If we think about it this way,
then the way that we're slicing this list is going all the way from position 2
to position 5 then of course, we would end up with c, d, and e.
If you take a look at this code in my Repl.it,
I've essentially got the same code that we saw in the slides
and we're slicing this list of piano keys from position 2 to 5.
When I hit run, you will see that what gets printed is c,
d, and e, exactly the slice that we wanted. Now,
there's other things that you can do with slicing that's pretty cool. So,
for example, if you wanted to slice from position 2,
which remember is right here
because we're starting at 0, 1, and 2,
and you want to slice it all the way to the end of the list, well,
you can just emit the second number. You can have two and then a colon.
Now, when you slice this you get all of the rest of the list
starting from the position that you specified.
And this works in the opposite direction as well.
Let's say that we want to get hold of everything up to position 5. Well,
we could omit the first number, add a colon,
and then after the colon specify the end slice position.
And now we get all of the items in the list up to that position 5.
In addition to just slicing between two numbers,
we can actually specify a third number after another colon.
And what this number does is it sets the increment. For example,
we wanted the slice from a position 2 to position 5,
but we want to only get every other item.
So then it would give c, it would skip over the second one,
and then it would give us e. And if I hit run, this is exactly what you see.
So let's say I wanted to get hold of everything in this list
but I wanted every second item. Well, then this is what my code would look like,
go from the beginning to the end and then skip every second one.
And I end up with a, c, e, and g.
Now to extend this a little bit further,
we can actually use this neat trick to specify a -1 as the increment
and what this does is it will actually reverse this list for us going from right
to the end to the beginning. So essentially the increments are by one,
but it's by -1, so that way we get the list starting from the end
all the way back to the beginning.
And this is a really neat trick that you'll see a lot of people use when it
comes to manipulating lists and tuples. So speaking of tuples,
this method of slicing also works for tuples.
So let's say we had a piano tuple,
which remember is defined by a set of parentheses with items inside separated by
commas. Well,
we can use the same method of slicing to work with our tuple.
So we use our square brackets,
let's get hold of the items from section 2 to 5.
Then when we hit run, you'll see it gives us mi, fa, so.
So coming back to our code, I have a challenge for you.
Can you figure out how to use what we've just learned about slicing to
change this code so that we get rid of this
if statement where we're passing over the snake head so that we are in fact only
checking that the snake head has a distance to every segment other than the first
segment, less than 10? If you managed successfully to do this,
you should be able to get rid of this
if statement, change this to a single if statement and somehow figure out a way of
making this code work using slicing. Pause the video and give this a go.
Alright,
so we know that we want to loop through every segment in snake.segments
other than the first one. Well,
all we need to do is simply slice this list of segments. So we can get hold of
everything that starts off from position 1 to the end,
by writing 1: nothing.
This will give us everything inside the list other than the first item, like
so.
And then we can use that segment to loop through it and then check every segment
in the tail against the distance to the head. And now when you run the code,
you can see that it works just as perfectly as before,
but we've now vastly simplified our code using the power of Python
slicing.
Have fun playing with your snake game and be sure to let me know your highest
score because I can't seem to get past 10.
And you've pretty much seen in this tutorial how bad I am at this game,
but I'm sure you can do much better. And on top of that,
think about ways that you might want to customize your snake game.
Maybe you want to change the food to have a different color or a different
shape, maybe your snake is actually going to eat turtles, I don't know.
The world is your oyster.
Now that you've learned about so many more concepts in Programming
including inheritance in OOP as well as slicing lists and tuples.
So I hope you've had fun building this game and I'll see you tomorrow.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 22 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be building the famous pong game,
and you're going to be doing this by using all of the skills that you've learned
up till now.
Pong is a classic arcade game,
probably one of the first arcade games that ever was.
And it has a really simple premise. It's basically just a ball
that's going across a table and two players each control a paddle
bouncing the ball back and forth. If you miss the ball,
then the other player scores a point.
Now the history of pong is itself kind of fascinating.
It was created and written by this guy, Allan Alcorn.
And he was a fresh recruit to the Atari company.
And in order to test his skills,
they decided to get him to create a game, from scratch.
And this game happened to be pong,
which became a huge success selling loads and loads of machines across bars and
pubs in the world.
It eventually became so successful that a lot of these bar owners were calling
up Atari saying, Hey, your machines are braking after only a few days.
And the reason when they investigated was because the machines were chock-a-
block full of money.
People were putting their quarters in to play pong and the machine was getting
full too quickly.
So this is the legendary game that we're going to be building today. As a ways,
the first step is to break down the problem.
And I want you to have a go at this,
think about how you would take this pong game that you've seen here,
and which components would we need to write code for, which components might fit
well in its own separate class,
and how might we break down the logic of this game so that we can solve it piece
by piece. Now, I want you to take a piece of paper,
take a look at the game screen right here and make a note of which components
you think could be separated into their own classes. Briefly,
pause the video and jot down some notes on how you might structure the code for
this game.
Now I've broken this tutorial down into eight pieces.
Keep a piece of paper to hand throughout today so that you can compare your
structure to the sample solution.
Pong is a much more complex game than snake.
So pausing to think about the structure of the code now will help you a lot more
in the upcoming lessons and it'll make it easier for you to see how everything
fits together. First, we're going to figure out how to create the screen,
how to create and move a puddle, and then create another puddle
so we can have a two-player game and then create the ball and make it move
constantly across the screen and figure out when it collides with a wall and
make it bounce back and then detect when there's a collision with the paddle to
know when to bounce it back. Finally, we'll figure out when a user scores,
when the paddle misses the ball, and we'll keep the score using a scoreboard
like before. Now, if you're feeling really confident,
you can, in fact, just create a blank project,
go through these steps one by one and see if you can code up this game by
yourself. But what I recommend though
is to go along with the videos and I'm going to explain each of the problems one
by one, and you can have a go at building it alongside with me.
So if you decide to follow along with me,
head over to the next lesson and we'll get started.
If you decide to create everything from scratch,
then pause the video and start creating the game now.
The first challenge is pretty simple.
We're just going to create the starting screen.
It's going to be a screen that has a height of 600 pixels and a width of 800
pixels. It should be black in terms of the background color,
and it should stay on the screen until we click on it.
So using what you've learned so far,
go ahead and set up the starting code for our project.
All right. So I've created a brand new project which I've called pong-game,
and I've created a main.py. Now,
the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to import a screen from the turtle
module.
And then I'm going to create a screen object from the Screen class,
and then I'm going to set the background color to black.
And then, of course, we'll need to set up the screen so that it has a width of
800 and a height of 600.
So now if I run this code as it is,
you'll see that it flashes up and it disappears.
So of course we need that exitonclick method.
As well as a final finishing touch, this is completely optional
but it helps to identify the program,
we can change the screens title to say Pong.
And now when I run the code, you can see that this window now says pong.
So we now have our 800 by 600 screen,
and we're now ready to head to the next step where we create our paddles.
So now that we've created the screen we're ready to go ahead and create and move a
puddle. So
the paddle that we're going to create is going to be on the right side.
It's going to have a width of 20,
a height of 100 and be positioned at 350 pixels on the X-axis and then 0 on
the Y-axis. So this is the sort of positioning we're looking for.
And additionally,
we should be able to hit the up and down keys on a keyboard to move the paddle.
Each key press should move the paddle up or down by 20 pixels.
Have a think about how you might create the code for this and pause the video
and complete the challenge.
All right. So to create this paddle, it's going to be created as a turtle.
So let's go ahead and create our paddle from the turtle class and I'm going to
set the paddles shape to a square.
In order to stretch it so that it's 20 by 100 pixels,
remember that all turtles start off as 20 by 20
so that means in the width
we have to stretch it by five, and in the length, we leave it as it is in order to
make it 100 by 20.
So let's go ahead and hid up paddle.shapesize
which is what we've been using so far. And then in terms of the stretch width,
we're going to make that five. And then the stretch length is going to be one.
Now we have to make sure that our paddle has a color of white
so that it's actually visible when we run our code. And you can see there it is,
there's our paddle. And as always,
it gets initialized in the center at the coordinate (0, 0).
So in order to move it to the position we want to,
we have to get it to go ahead and pen up,
and then we can tell it to go to the position that is 350 by 0,
so 350 on the X-axis and 0 on the Y-axis, like that.
Now, the next thing we need to do is figure out how to get it
to move up and down.
So, of course, we need some sort of way of getting our screen to listen for
keystrokes. We're gonna call screen.listen
and then we're going to call onkey in order to listen for the "Up" key.
And then when that happens, we're going to get the paddle to go up. Now,
remember as always, when you were using a function as a parameter,
you don't want to add the parentheses. If you do, it won't work.
Now let's create our go_up function.
And this function is going to take our paddle and move it so that it goes to a
new position. The new exposition is X not going to change.
The only one that's going to change is the Y position.
So the Y position is going to be the paddles current ycor,
but it's going to go up, so it's going to need to
plus let's say by 20.
Now we can tell the paddle to go to its current paddle.xcor.
So we're not changing that. And then to go to the new Y position.
Now, this go_up function is going to be called whenever the Up key is detected.
And if we copy this and we make a similar version of this function,
which is called go_down and we can subtract 20 instead.
So now we can copy this line and make it call
go_down when the down arrow key is detected.
So now we've created our paddle and when I hit up, it goes up, when I hit down
it goes down. And this completes the first part of the challenge.
But here's a question. When I hit run,
you can see that the paddle first gets created in the center,
and then it moves to the location where it needs to go to,
which is 350 on the X-axis, 0 on the Y-axis.
How can we get rid of this animation so that we don't have to look at the
paddle move to the position?
Have a think about what you've learned in previous lessons and see if you can
solve this problem. All right.
So you might remember from previous lessons that there is a tracer method on the
screen which controls the animation.
And in order to turn off the animation, we can put a zero in that method.
But when we run our code, as it is right now,
you'll see that there's no animation.
There's not even a paddle of showing up anymore.
Remember that when you turn off the animation,
you have to manually update the screen and refresh it every single time. To do
that, we'll need some sort of a while loop.
And the while loop is going to check for some sort of variable.
So let's create a variable called game_is_on and set it to true
and while the game is on,
then we're going to call screen.update. Now,
if I run the code again, you'll see that my paddle
now goes directly from the center to the position because the first thing
that happens is the animation gets turned off,
the paddle then gets created in the background
and then finally it gets to this point where we actually update the screen and
show everything that's happened in the background so far.
Did you manage to complete this challenge and create the paddle and get it to
move up and down using the keystrokes?
If not be sure to review some of these methods in the turtle documentation and
have a play around with the code until you're fully happy with what's going on
so far. Now,
if you had created the paddle in a separate file as a separate class,
don't worry. We're going to do that next.
We're going to refactor this code so that it's fully compliant with Object
Oriented Programming. But if you've already done it,
then you're just one step ahead.
And that is where we're heading to in the next lesson.
In the last lesson we created and managed to move a paddle up and down.
Now in this lesson, we're going to figure out how we can create
another paddle,
but we don't want to repeat all the code that we've written so far.
So we're probably going to need the help of a separate paddle class.
So if you haven't already created
your paddle inside a separate file and a separate class,
then this is the time to refactor your code so that you can create
another paddle object from the puddle class easily and effortlessly.
Here's what we're aiming for.
We're aiming to get rid of all of this paddle related code and move it into a
separate paddle class.
And then subsequently we want to be able to create a right paddle simply by
creating it from the paddle class.
And then we can create a left paddle from the panel of class. Now because the
right paddle has a different coordinate from the left paddle,
we'll need to pass in the position of the right and left paddle as a tuple.
So we might say something like the X will be 350 and the Y will be 0.
And on the left paddle,
the X will be -350 and the Y will be 0.
So have a think about how you can make this code work and refactor this
code into a separate paddle class
and this paddle class should inherit from the turtle class.
Overall, our program should work pretty much the same as before.
The only difference being that we now have a left pedal
which can move up and down with the w and s keys on the keyboard.
Pause the video and try to complete this challenge.
All right. So the first thing we're going to need is a new file,
which is going to be called paddle.py and paddle.py is going to need the
turtle class from the turtle module. So let's go ahead and import it.
And then I'm going to create this Paddle class, and of course,
all classes start off with a capital letter.
Now, this class is going to take all of this paddle creation code
and it's going to carry it out when we initialize a new paddle
object. This paddle object, in order for it to be a turtle
object, we're going to get it to inherit from the turtle class like this.
And in order to get all of the abilities,
the methods, and the attributes of the turtle class,
we need to get this superclass to initialize itself.
The next thing we're going to do is figure out how we can get our paddle to
change its shape, change its color and all of these other things.
So we can get rid of this line entirely because our paddle class is now the same
as a turtle class. And then for the rest of these,
instead of writing paddle.shape or paddle.color,
we're going to hit command R or simply go to edit,
find, and then replace,
and you can take a look at the shortcut on your computer of how to get hold of
this replace screen. So what I want to replace is
everything that is paddled. here in my code,
and I'm going to replace it with self.,
because now we're inside the paddle class
which is effectively the same as a turtle class with some added extras.
We can tap into our methods and our attributes by simply using the self keyword.
Now,
the very last thing we need to do in order to make this work is to go ahead and
import our paddle from the paddle.py.
And once we've imported it, we need to address this warning.
Notice how it's highlighting this area
and it's telling us that this is an unexpected argument because the paddle
class doesn't actually take any inputs when it's initialized.
It's just got the self here. But in fact,
we do need a position being passed over.
So this position is going to determine where the paddle is going to go to,
because remember the left paddle is going to have a different coordinate from
the right paddle.
So now that we fixed that, this is now completely valid code.
And if we run our code as it is,
you'll see our paddles being created and looking exactly the same way as before
but now we've got one extra paddle. Going down here with our go up and go down
methods,
ideally, we would want them to live within our paddle class.
So we want them to be methods inside this class.
And remember that methods always have a first attribute as the self.
Now, in addition, we have to, again,
replace this paddle. with self. so that it's actually referring to the object
that's created from this class to get its Y coordinate or get its X coordinate.
Now, coming back to our main.py,
we'll have to modify this code a little bit because this go_up and go_down
function is now gone,
and instead, we now have the r_paddle.go_up and r_paddle.go_down.
So the right paddle is going to be controlled by the up and down keys,
but the left paddle, we can get it to be controlled by some other keys. Now,
in our case,
I'm going to choose the 'w' to go up and the 's' key to go down.
So we're going to need another set of these screen.onkey method calls.
But in this case,
this is going to get the left paddle to go up and the left paddle to go down. And
to go up is controlled by the 'w' key
and to go down is controlled by the 's' key. So now,
if we run our code, you can see that when I moved w it goes up, when I move
s it goes down, and up and down moves the right side of the paddle.
So notice how
now that we've refactored our paddle related code into a completely separate
class, firstly,
our main.py is now a lot simpler.
It's clear of all of this paddle related code.
And on top of that, if I wanted to create a third paddle
let's say I wanted you to create a top paddle for some reason,
then all I have to do is just call the paddle class and then pass in a tuple
for the location of this paddle.
So let's put it at, I dunno, 100 by 100.
If I hit run,
you can see there's a third random paddle and I didn't have to write
any of this extra code or any of the related methods. We can create as many of
these paddles as we want because we've now got this paddle class.
So with these examples,
I hope you're getting the sense of how important classes are and just how
important they are when it comes to the development of a more complex project
like this pong game. Now in the next lesson,
we're going to continue building out our program and we're going to create our
ball class and get the ball moving.
Now that we've created both paddles
the next obvious step is to create the ball and get it to move.
So this ball is going to be created as a separate ball class and the ball object
that we're going to create from it will have a width of 20, height of 20, and it's
X and Y position will start out at the center of the screen,
so (0, 0). Now when the screen refreshes,
the ball is automatically going to move on the screen and it's going to move up
and also to the right.
So it's X and Y positions will change on every refresh of the screen.
So this is going to be a little bit more challenging and will require a little
bit of thinking from your part.
But I want you to pause the video and give this problem a bit of thought and see
how far you can get in trying to get the ball to move to the top-
right edge of the screen. Pause the video and give that a go.
All right. So to start off, this time
I'm going to create a ball.py file and inside
this ball.py is where we're going to create our ball object.
So firstly,
I'm going to import my turtle class and then I'm going to create my ball class
which is going to inherit from the turtle class.
And then I'm going to do all of the usual initialization.
And now we're ready to create our ball class.
This ball is going to, firstly, have a white color.
And in addition, it's going to have a shape that is going to be a circle.
Now I know that in the original pong game,
the table tennis ball is actually a square. So you can keep it a square
if you want to be historically accurate, or you can change it to
a circle like I have here to make it look more like a ping pong ball.
Now, in addition,
we're going to need to get it to pen up so that it doesn't end up drawing across
the screen.
And now all we need is to initialize our ball from the ball.py
and we're going to do that just below our paddles.
So I'm going to create a new ball object from the ball class.
And now if I hit run,
you'll see our circular ball show up in the center of the screen.
The next problem is how do we get the ball to move towards the top right corner
of the screen?
So that's going to involve a change in the X coordinate as well as the Y
coordinate. In our while loop here
where our screen is updating,
we're going to call a method in the ball class
which is going to be called move. And this move method
which we'll define now is going to be responsible for moving our ball.
And the way that it's going to move is it's going to increase on the X and also
increase on the Y. Let's create a new X coordinate
which is going to be the current self.xcor plus a arbitrary amount.
So let's say increase by 10.
And then the new Y is going to be the self.ycor increased by the same
arbitrary amount. And then finally,
we can get our ball to go to this new X and new Y.
So now when we run our code,
you can see that our ball immediately goes off the screen to the top right
corner. If we want the ball to slow down a little bit,
we can do one of two things. Either
we can go into the move method and change this 10 here to say a 1.
That way, every time our loop runs, our ball will only move one pixel.
Alternatively, we can pause the loop for a short time during each iteration.
Moving the ball at a tiny amount does work,
but I'm going to go with the second option and import our time module.
Then I'm going to get our while loop to sleep for a little bit in between each
of the updates.
So, I normally start off with just a 0.1 second sleep,
and you can see now a ball moves at a more reasonable pace
and we actually have a chance of catching it with one of the paddles.
That's all there is to it. We've now created on the ball class, initialized
a ball object and we've got the ball to move on every refresh of the screen.
Now we've done most of the easy parts,
getting a paddle and a ball up and running on our screen.
The next few parts are going to be a little bit more tricky.
And the first thing we're going to tackle is how to detect collision when the
ball hits the wall at the top and the bottom and getting the ball to bounce.
Now, we only need to detect
collision on the top and the bottom walls
because when the ball hits the right or of the left edges of the program,
it should actually be caught by one of the paddles. And if it isn't,
then that means that player has missed the ball
and it's a point to the other side.
So we need to focus on how can we detect when the ball has collided with the top
or bottom walls,
when has its position gone past a certain point that it probably is going to
collide with the wall. We've done something similar in snake, but it's again
time to revisit this topic. Now on top of that,
we have to figure out how do we get the ball to actually bounce?
And what does bouncing actually mean in terms of changing the position of the
ball?
When the ball is constantly going up in the Y value and going up in the X value
in order to travel in this direction,
what actually happens to the X and Y values when it bounces?
Which one gets reduced and which one stays constant?
Have a think about those questions and play around with some of those numbers
and see if you can complete this challenge by yourself. If you get stuck
or if you just want to check the answer,
then come back and I'll go through the solution with you.
All right. So it's going to be inside our while loop
where I'm going to be detecting the collision with the wall.
And in order to detect the collision with the wall, essentially,
what I'm going to say is that if the screen is 600 by 800,
when the ball is at a Y position
that is above 300,
remember 300 is half of 600,
and the Y-axis goes from 0 to 300 and 0 to -300.
So once the ball is past 300,
then it's going to be way past the wall, right? So at that point,
I can be pretty sure that it's going to hit the wall
or it has it already hit the wall.
So that will be my criteria for detecting collision.
So it can say if the ball.ycor is greater than 300,
well in that case it's basically gone too far up and it's hit the top wall. Now,
in addition, I can add a or statement to say
if the ball.ycor is less than -300,
then that means it's gone too far down and it's hit the bottom wall.
So in this case, it needs to bounce.
So we need to figure out how to get our ball to bounce.
And we're going to create a bounce method in our ball class in order to tell it
how to do this. Firstly,
we're going to need to figure out a new Y because the Y coordinate needs to
essentially reverse. So,
whereas previously our Y coordinate was going up and up and up increasing each
time, when it hits the wall it needs to reverse direction.
So if it was increasing,
it needs to decrease. If it was decreasing, it needs to increase.
So basically we need the opposite of what it currently is. To do that,
the easiest way is to create a attribute
which I'm going to call x_move and another
which I'm going to call y_move.
These are going to start out at 10,
and every time we move our ball we're going to say,
self.xcor + self.x_move,
and plus self.y_move.
This basically hasn't changed anything.
It's just that every single time the ball moves,
it's going to increase in the X coordinate by 10 pixels
and also increased by 10 pixels in the Y coordinate. Now,
when we bounce however,
we need to change our y_move
so that it's the opposite in terms of direction of what it used to be.
So if it used to be +10 we want it to be now -10,
and if it used to be -10, we want it to be now +10. To do that,
all we need to do is multiply it by - 1.
So that means if y_move is currently equal to 10 and 10 is being added to the Y
coordinate, then this ball is moving upwards.
But when we reverse the direction by multiplying it by -1,
now that is now -10.
So we're now adding -10 to the Y coordinate
which is the same as subtracting 10. So this is some basic high school math
that's going to get our pong program to start moving in the right direction.
Now, back in the main.py under these conditions
when the ball has hit the top or the bottom,
we're going to get the ball to bounce.
And now if I hit run, you should see that when the ball hits the top screen,
it comes right back, exactly in the way that we want it to.
But the only thing that we might need to tweak
is look at how far it's gone before it actually bounces. It completely disappeared
of the screen before it actually makes a bounce.
So we can adjust these values accordingly.
So I think it works best that when we actually have it as 280.
So remember that the width of the ball is 20 pixels
so if we're 20 pixels away from the wall,
then that's pretty much where we need to bounce. So if I run this again,
you can see that the ball hits close to the wall and then it comes right back.
So this will take a little bit of thinking to get your head around it.
The best way to really understand this is to print out the values of the new_y
and also of the y_move
and also after you've modified the move in the bounce. Look at those numbers
and you'll eventually be able to understand what's actually happening to the
position of the ball. But effectively,
all that we're doing is we're defining an amount that the ball is going to move
by in the X and the Y axis.
We're adding that amount to the X and Y coordinates in order to move the ball.
And when the ball needs to bounce off the top and bottom walls,
we reverse the y_move number so that we get it to subtract instead of add.
And that moves it in the opposite direction.
So we figured out how to detect
collision with the top and bottom walls and make our ball bounce off the walls.
The next thing we need to do is to detect when there's a collision with the
paddle and make the ball bounce off the paddle.
This is probably going to be the hardest part of this program yet
so I wanna talk you through the logic. Now,
how can we know when the ball has hit the paddle? Now,
normally we use the distance method to check what is the distance between the
ball and the paddle. And if it's less than a certain amount,
then we can be relatively sure that they've made contact with each other.
So the code that we normally use would be something like this.
We get our ball and we check its distance from the paddle.
Now remember that our ball has a width of 20 pixels and our paddle has a
width of 20 pixels. Normally we would say, well,
if that distance between the two of them is less than 20, well,
then they've probably made contact, right?
But the problem occurs when the ball hits the paddle, not right in the center,
but at the edge of the paddle,
because this distance measures the center of the ball from the centre of the
paddle as the distance.
So you can see that this distance is way bigger than 20,
so it's not going to register as a collision.
How can we solve this problem? Well,
we could add on an additional condition. We could check well
if the ball has gone past a certain point on the X-axis,
if it's gone far enough over to the right and it's within a 50 pixel distance of
the paddle,
then that also means it's made contact with the paddle. Inside our main.py
I'm going to add a comment to detect collision with right paddle.
So let's experiment with some numbers here and see if we can get the ball to
bounce off the paddle. In this case,
we're going to check if the ball.distance to the r_paddle is less than
50 and the ball.xcor is greater than 340.
If the ball has hit the right paddle,
let's print something to the console to test our code. Let's print made contact.
So if we run this code and I manage to make contact with the ball,
you can see that it says 'Made contact' in our console.
So instead of just printing made contact,
what we want the ball to do is to again, to bounce. Now,
this bounce is a little bit different from the last bounce,
because the previous one was changing its Y coordinate so that it moved in the
opposite along the vertical. But in this case,
we actually want it to move along the opposite direction in the horizontal
because the paddle is here and the ball is coming this way,
we want it to go back this way. So instead of just calling this bounce,
I'm going to right-click on it and then refactor and rename to bounce_
y because this is bouncing in the Y-axis. Now,
once we hit refactor, it'll change it here and it will change it here.
Now on top of that, I'm going to define my bounce_x,
so it bouncing in the X-axis, and this is very similar.
We're going to change the x_move,
so the amount that the ball moves each time when the move method is called and
I'm going to multiply it by -1,
so reversing the X direction.
And then when our collision is detected,
we're going to get the ball to bounce in the X direction.
So now if we run our code,
you can see that even though this only works on the right paddle,
when the ball hits the right paddle
it moves back and it bounces back towards the left.
It changes the direction that it was moving in the X-axis.
So now lets add the collision for both paddles because they both need to bounce
in the X-axis
and so we're going to tag onto this a 'or' statement and we're going to say
or if the ball.distance to the left paddle is also less than 50
and on top of that
the ball.xcor is less than -340.
So this basically checks to see if the ball has gone far enough to the left as
to be past the paddle and its within a distance of 50 pixels from the left
paddle. So if we run the code right now,
you can see that not only does our ball bounce when it hits the right.
So now when we run the program again,
you can see that not only does the ball bounce on the right paddle,
it also bounces when it hits the left paddle.
Now there's a little bit more tweaking that we can do with the coordinates because
you can see that when the ball hits the paddle,
it goes a little bit too far before it actually reverses direction.
So we can change this to a slightly smaller number if we want it to bounce
before it's within the actual paddle.
So we can change this to 320 and this one also to 320 and notice what
happens now. Before it hits the actual paddle,
it now actually bounces and it doesn't look like as if the ball's fallen into the
paddle before it turns back. And there you have it.
Now we just have to figure out what should happen when the paddle misses the
ball. For all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.
Now we're pretty close to the end of the program.
We've managed to do pretty much everything other than detect when the paddle
actually misses a ball. And if the right paddle misses the ball,
then the left player gets a point.
And this should trigger a restart of the game where the ball goes back to the
center and starts off in the opposite direction.
In order to do this,
to detect when a paddle has actually missed the ball, effectively,
what we're checking is that the ball has gone past a certain point on the
screen. So we know that we're already
checking when the ball goes past this line and it's within 50 pixels of the
paddle,
then it should bounce back because that means the ball was caught by the paddle.
But if it goes further than that, if it goes beyond that on the screen
like over here or over here,
then that means it's a miss and we should reset the ball.
Have a think about how you might create this behavior,
and as a challenge to yourself, see if you can complete the code.
So I'm going to add another comment here
which is going to be detect when right paddle misses.
The right paddle has basically missed the ball
if the ball.xcor is beyond 380.
We know that the width of the screen is 800
and we know that the paddle is at 350.
So the paddle basically goes from 340 to 360,
and if it's already gone past 380,
then the paddle has definitely missed the ball. So in this situation,
we're going to get the ball to reset its position.
And this is going to be a method in the ball class.
So let's create it and I'm just going to paste it in
so I don't make any errors in terms of the naming. Resetting the position of the
ball is going to involve getting the ball to go to the original position.
So we can tell self to go to (0, 0).
Now, if we run our code,
you can see when the ball has gone past a certain point and it's not caught by
the paddle, it goes back into the center.
But we want the ball to go in the opposite direction
once it's been missed by the right-sided player. It's time for the left-sided
player to get a turn.
So in addition to getting the ball to reset its position,
we're going to get the ball to reverse its X-axis.
So we're going to call self.bounce_x.
Now notice how when the ball gets missed,
then its direction gets reversed,
it starts off in the center and it goes off in the opposite direction.
Let's go ahead and define the left-sided paddle miss.
And we can do that by simply saying ball.xcor is less than -380.
And in this case, we're again going to get the ball to reset the position.
Now,
the reason why I've got these in separate if statements is because later on,
we're going to need to detect when the right-sided player or the left-sided
player actually gains a point. So when the right paddle misses,
the left player gets a point, when the left paddle misses the right player
gets a point.
Now when the ball goes past the right edge and it's not caught by the paddle,
then it starts off in the center and it moves to the left.
When it's not caught by the left side of the paddle,
it starts off in the center and it goes to the right.
All that's left to do is to figure out how to do the scoring.
And that is what we're going to do on the next lesson.
To start, we're going to need to create a new scoreboard file.
And then inside this file
we're going to add our usual imports and we're going to create the scoreboard
class.
Now the scoreboard class is going to inherit from the turtle class,
so we can go ahead and add all of our inits and our super.init.
Now let's define our scoreboard.
It's going to have a white color so it shows up on the black background,
it's going to have pen up because we don't want it to draw,
and it's also going to have its turtle hidden because we're only interested in
it being able to write something.
And the thing that we want it to write is the current score.
Let's go ahead and create some attributes for the scoreboard class.
One is going to be the l_score which starts off at zero,
and the other is going to be the r_score which starts off at zero.
So our scoreboard is going to keep track of how the left player and the right
player are doing.
And then it's going to write this onto the screen.
So we're going to write the self.l_score first,
and we're going to change the alignment to center and also change the font to
something quite large,
like a courier font with 80 points and have a normal weight.
Where do we want this to be written though? Because by default,
this is going to be written at the center of the screen, (0, 0).
But instead,
what we want it to do is we probably want it to go to somewhere on the top-left
of the screen. This is the left player score.
So you can have a play around with the coordinates,
but I found that -100 in the X-axis,
so a little bit to the left of the center and then 200 on the Y-axis,
so near the top of the screen seems to do well for this left-sided score.
Now let's make this show up by going back to our main.py and importing our
scoreboard class and creating a new scoreboard object.
So when we hit run, you can see that big zero show up bright here.
Now,
the next thing we need to do is to show the right-sided player's score.
We're going to make our scoreboard go to the opposite side of the screen,
so that's going to be +100 and again
with a Y value of 200.
And then we're going to get it to write the right-sided score,
so our score, and we're going to have the same alignment and the same font.
Now you can see 0 0 when the game starts out. Now,
what we actually want our scoreboard to do is the keep track of the score.
So when the right paddle misses, it's a score to the left-sided player.
We can define that in our main.py.
When the right paddle misses,
then we're going to get these scoreboard to
give the left side a point.
So maybe we could have a method called l_point in our scoreboard that increases
the point in the left-sided player.
So we can say self.l_score +=1.
In addition, we're going to need to update our scoreboard,
but all of that code is stuck in the init.
So let's go ahead and move it out into a separate function
which we'll call update_scoreboard.
And we can call self.update_scoreboard
when we first initialized the scoreboard but also when we score a point.
Now, when we run our code,
you can see that when the right-sided misses, our left
side gets a point. But at the moment, it's overwriting the previous score.
So to prevent that,
we have to add a self.clear before we update the scoreboard.
And you can see now it erases everything that used to be there and it updates
the score. So we've addressed when you are right paddle misses,
but what about when our left paddle misses? Well,
we should have a method called r_point as well
that gives the right side a point.
So let's add that over here.
Increase the r_score by one and we'll again call
update_scoreboard.
Right.
Now when our left side misses, we get a point to the left,
and when our left side misses, we get a point to the right.
That's pretty much all of pong. Now,
if you want an extra challenge both in terms of playing pong
as well as the code,
see if you can figure out a way of getting the ball to increase its speed
every time it hits a paddle,
because that will make the game a lot more exciting instead of having it always
move so slowly. If you can't figure it out,
then continue watching and I'll show you the solution.
So in order to speed up the ball,
the key is in how much time we make our game loop sleep.
Because the shorter that this sleep is,
let's say instead of 0.1 second
let's do 0.01 second.
And if we run now, you can see our ball moves a lot faster.
Let's make it even more extreme and add another zero.
So how can we reduce this number by a little bit each time,
but never make it go into the negative
because if this becomes a negative number,
then we actually get an error over here telling us that the sleep length must be
non-negative. In order to do this,
we have to figure out a way of making this number a little bit smaller each
time.
So let's make this number a attribute in our ball class.
Now I don't want to call it speed because that might be a bit confusing because
the turtle class already has a method called speed
as you can see here. So instead I'm going to call it move_speed,
and I'm going to set it to 0.1.
So now inside our main.py, instead of having a hard-coded
number I'm going to get hold of my ball.move_speed.
Now, every single time our ball bounces in the X-axis,
it means that has been touched by a paddle.
So inside this method, in addition to getting it to reverse its direction,
we can get the move_speed to reduce by multiplying it by a decimal number.
So I've stuck with 0.9 because that seems to work for me.
So for example,
if we start out with a value of 5 and we multiply that by 0.9,
it becomes 4.5.
And if we multiply that by 0.9 becomes 4.05.
So basically each time the ball bounces on a paddle,
it's going to increase in speed. But this can't go on indefinitely.
When we reset the game once one player has lost,
we have to set this move_speed back to the original 0.1,
just so that it doesn't keep on increasing in speed indefinitely.
So now you can see whenever the ball hits a paddle,
it will increase its speed ever so slightly making it just a little bit more
challenging for the players.
Now you can of course tweak around with that number so instead of 0.9,
you could have 0.5, which basically haves the speed each time,
but have a play around with that and see what you prefer. Now
one last thing to mention before we finish off today is that when I'm testing
this program on my computer,
it seems like when I hold down the up hey or the down key,
my paddle will continuously move.
But there seems to be a bug with turtle where if I hold down the 'w' key,
it can only move one bit at a time,
but it doesn't seem to affect the 's' key.
So I've been doing a bit of digging around online
and I can't figure out exactly why this is. If you manage to figure it out,
then feel free to add it to the Q/A so that
other students can learn from it. But so far I've been coming up empty.
But this is just a warning
in case you find this behavior as well on your computer and you get confused and
thinking it's something wrong with your code. It's not.
It's something about the turtle module that causes it to behave like this.
So don't worry if that's happening to you.
And if you're playing pong with a friend,
you can always trick them to use the left sided player.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 23 of 100 Days of Code. Now,
today we're going to be building towards our second capstone project,
and this is going to be a turtle crossing game.
You might've played Crossy Road. So this is a similar concept.
We have a whole bunch of cars going across a super busy multi-lane highway
and our turtle is the player who has to cross the road.
This is what the gameplay looks like. The player controls the turtle
which can only go forwards, and
there's a whole bunch of randomly generated cars
which are going horizontally across the screen. Now, once a player
reaches the other side of the screen, the cars speed up,
but the player goes back to the starting position,
ready to cross the screen again. Now,
at some point when the player turtle hits a car,
then that is game over. It's a pretty simple game,
but it's going to test you on a lot of things that you've learned so far,
including how to great classes, how to inherit classes,
how do you use the objects created from those classes and also your knowledge of
the turtle coordinate system and the turtle game engine.
Once you are ready, head over to the next lesson where you'll find the starting
code for this project, and also you'll be able to choose your difficulty level.
So head over there and get started now.
Now, hopefully you've already downloaded the starting project,
so you can go ahead and click open in PyCharm,
find the location where you've downloaded your turtle-crossing-start and make
sure that you've unzipped that zip file
and you've got the actual folder, which contains all of the starting files.
So select the folder and then click open and we have to configure a Python
interpreter and make sure that your Python interpreter is at a minimum of Python
3.8. So you can use 3.9 or above,
but if it's lower than 3.8,
you might get some errors and some problems. Refer back to when we first started
out using PyCharm and we installed Python if you get stuck on this.
Now, if you take a look at inside our project folder,
you can see I've already created four files for you.
These files are pretty bare bones,
but if you take a look at the main.py file
which is your starting point for your program,
you can see that I've written a little bit of code that we learned about in
previous lessons.
So we've created a screen object and we've set up the screen to be 600 by 600
pixels.
And then we've turned off the tracer by doing the tracer(0),
and instead, we're getting the screen to update every 0.1 seconds.
So within the while loop, the code is going to run every 0.1 seconds.
So whatever it is that you put inside this while loop,
it's going to be refreshed every 0.1 seconds.
Now, you'll also see that I've imported some classes from these files; player,
car_manager, and scoreboard. Now,
inside these files,
I've created the starting point for each of the classes.
The player class is going to be the turtle which we're controlling to cross
the road,
the car manager is going to generate all of the random cars and move them
across the screen,
and then the scoreboard is just going to write the level that we're currently
on and also the game over a sequence. Now,
inside each of these classes, I've got pass written here
just so that the linter will stop screaming at me. So,
as we mentioned before, Python doesn't like things are empty,
so empty functions, empty classes, and you'll get these errors.
Instead of getting these errors, all I've done is simply written pass
which essentially just makes this an empty class.
So when you're creating these classes,
just delete the pass and you can create it as you would normally. Now,
in addition, we've got all of these constants in here. For example,
the starting position of the player turtle,
how much the turtle should move each time and where the finish line
is on the Y-axis. In the car_manager
we've got the colors of the cars,
we've got the move distance of each of the cars on each refresh,
and we've also got how much the move distance should increase every time the
user levels up. Finally, we've got the scoreboard
which just contains the font that you are going to use to write out the score
board. That's pretty much an introduction to the starting file.
So once you're ready,
feel free to head over to the next lesson and get started with each step of the
game.
All right. So just as previously,
we've split up this large problem of building the game into five smaller
sub-parts. Firstly,
moving the turtle, controlling it with the keypress, creating and moving the
cars automatically across the screen,
detecting a collision with the car and detecting when the turtle reaches the
other side. Finally,
we create a scoreboard that keeps track of which level we're on
and also that shows game over at the end.
So the first step is to move the turtle using a keypress.
The turtle can only go forwards, and every time we hit the Up key
the turtle moves forward by a set amount until it reaches the other side of the
screen. This is the first thing that we're going to tackle. Now,
because this is related to the functionality of the player,
let's go ahead and create this inside the player class.
I'm going to delete that pass
and I'm also going to import the turtle class from the turtle module.
Now, our player is going to inherit from this turtle class.
So inside our init,
we're going to need to add the super.init
or you can add it automatically using the light bulb.
So now this player class can do everything that a turtle class can do and we can
make it do even more.
The first thing we're going to do is we're going to set the shape of our player
and we're gonna set it to a turtle.
The next thing we're going to do is we're going to call penup so that this
turtle just remains a shape and it doesn't draw. Finally,
we need to get it to the starting position and get it to face North.
We can do that by setting self.goto and then we can set it to go to the
starting position,
which you can see is a tuple because it's enclosed inside parentheses and you've
got values separated by a comma. Finally,
we're going to set the heading of our turtle so that it faces North,
which is 90 degrees.
So now all we have to do is go back into our main.py,
after we've set up our screen,
let's go ahead and create a new player from the player class.
Let's go ahead and run this code.
...
And you can see that we've got our little turtle showing up here at the center
of the bottom of the screen and it's facing North.
So now the next thing we need to do is to get that turtle to move upwards
every time we hit the Up key.
That means we're going to need to get our screen to
listen for events. After calling screen.listen,
we're going to get the screen to listen to a keystroke. So we can use onkey to
set the Up key as the key to listen to.
And then when that happens, then we're going to call player.
go_up. And remember that when we're calling methods inside the listener,
we don't want to add the parentheses because this will trigger it at the point
where it evaluates this line of code. Instead,
we want to trigger this function only when this Up key is detected.
So now all that's left to do is to go into our player.py and define that
function go_up.
So how can we move our turtle up? Well,
we can get our turtle so self,
and then we can get it to move forwards by a distance.
And the distance is going to be the move distance that's set in this constant
here. This means that later on when we want to change the move distance
if we want it to go further each time, we can just edit it at the top of the
file instead of digging through the code.
Now let's run our code again and let's just make sure that it works.
So now every time I hit the Up key
my turtle moves up and it keeps on going until it reaches the other side of the
screen. So that's the first step completed. Now,
if you think you can complete the next step by yourself,
then head back to that list of problems broken down and see if you can tackle
the next one by yourself. If you can't or if you need some extra help,
then you can always come back to the videos and I'll walk you through the steps
one by one.
In the last lesson, we managed to figure out how to get the turtle
to move with a keypress and that's with every press of the Up key
the turtle moves further towards North.
Now the next task is to create and move the cars.
The cars need to move from right to left and they need to be randomly generated
along the Y-axis here.
So they need to be generated right to the right edge of the screen and they can
appear anywhere along this line,
and then they're going to move automatically towards the left at a fixed pace.
Each of these cars,
you can see, are going to be turtles and they're going to be 20 by 40
pixels. So we mentioned that by default
every turtle that we create is 20 by 20 pixels.
So we'll need to stretch the turtle to make it into this shape.
Now that we are concerned with the cars let's create our code inside the car
manager.
The first thing we'll need to do is to import the turtle class from the turtle
module and our car manager is going to have a init where we create all of our
cars. So I'm going to create a list called all_cars,
and it's going to start out being an empty list. Now,
at some point,
our main.py is going to call a function from the car_manager called create_
cars.
And this method is going to create a random car somewhere along the Y-axis with
a given dimension. Each of these cars,
so let's call it a new_car, is going to be a turtle object and it's going to be
created in a square shape. Now, in addition,
we're going to have to change the dimensions of this turtle
and we're going to use that method that we used before
which is this one, shapesize.
Now, what shapesize allows us to do, if you remember,
is it allows us to stretch our turtle along the width and along the length.
So we want the width to be double the original size,
so two times 20 pixels is 40 pixels and the length we don't want to be stretched
at all.
So we're going to say it's one times the original length. In addition our new
car is not going to draw, so we're going to get it to penup.
And also our new car is going to have a random color. So we can set the color and
then we can import the random module so that we can use one of these colors in
this list.
And we can say random.choice and then pass in our list of colors from this
COLORS constant. Finally,
we're going to define where it's going to go on the screen. To do that
we need to define a random_y position.
So this again is going to be created from the random module and we're going to
use the randint and then we're going to define somewhere along this Y-axis,
which is the vertical, somewhere for this call to be generated at.
So we know that our screen is 600 by 600, so
that means the Y-axis goes from +300 to -300.
But we don't want the car to be generated all the way to the edge because
remember the turtle needs a bit of starting space and also a bit of ending
space. So you can play around with this number,
but I've ended up going with -250 to +250.
This means that we get a good range in the middle of the screen and that the
turtle has a bit of empty space at the beginning and also at the end when it
needs to move across. So now that we've defined our random_
y, we can tell our new_car to go to the x position
which is going to be the very edge of the right screen,
so that's going to be +300, right to the edge.
And then the y position is going to be the random_y that we just created.
And finally, once we've created our new_car,
we're going to append it to our list of all_cars which of course,
because it's defined in a class, it has to have the self in front of it.
So self.all_cars.append,
and then we're going to append this new car that we've just created.
Now, coming back to our main.py,
let's create our car_manager from the CarManager class,
and then we're going to use it inside our game loop here
so that on every refresh of the screen,
every 0.1 seconds,
we're going to get the car_manager to create a new car.
And strictly this probably shouldn't be plural because each time we call this
method, it only creates one new car.
So let's change that method so that it only creates one car,
but it creates one car every 0.1 seconds.
Now at this point in time if we run our code,
you'll actually see nothing happen because the cars are being created at this
right edge here
and it's not yet visible on the screen. To make it visible
we have to move our cars across the screen.
Let's create another method which we'll call move_cars because this method is
going to go through our list of cars,
so for car in self.all_cars,
and for each of those cars, it's going to move it towards the left
by the move distance that we've defined up here.
So to do that, all we need is to get the car
to move backwards by the starting move distance.
Now it's going to loop through our list of all_cars that were created
and then for each of the cars,
it's going to move it backwards by five paces.
So now in addition to getting the car manager to create a new car on every
refresh of the game loop,
we're also going to get it to move all of the cars by five paces.
Let's hit run
now and you should see that we've got our cars being generated,
but notice how I've made a slight error in the stretch. Instead of stretching it
along the length, I've stretched it along the width
and this is why we've got this random array of shapes moving.
So let's go back to our car manager and change the width to stretch by one and
stretch to the length by two. So now if we rerun our code,
you can see the cars are now the right shape,
a rectangle that looks like it's moving to the left.
Now notice how, in my case,
the cars are being generated far too frequently.
We've got way too many calls and it's impossible for our turtle to cross the
road.
So we need to figure out a way of how we can reduce the number of cars that are being
made. Instead of creating a car
every 0.1 seconds at every refresh of the game,
we need to slow this down a little bit.
And one way we can do this is by using a random number.
Let's say that we create a random_chance
which is going to be a one in six chance,
so it's almost like throwing a dice. If you get a one on the dice,
then we create a car.
We can do this by getting hold of our random module,
creating a random int between one and six
and then we can say that if the random_chance is equal to one,
then, and only then do we actually create a new car.
So this basically ensures that every six times the while loop runs a new car will
be generated.
Now it's not going to be precisely every six times because there's some degree
of chance involved. But notice when we run our program
now, see how the cars are now being created much less frequently.
And we've actually got some space for our turtle to cross.
So that is how we create and move our cars across the screen and make sure that
they don't occur so frequently that our turtle has no chance of crossing the
road. I hope this walkthrough was helpful.
Don't worry if your code doesn't look the same as mine, it doesn't have to.
What matters is if you're able to achieve the desired functionality of the game.
There are a million different ways that you can solve this problem.
And as long as it works, whatever way you choose will be the best way.
Now in the last lesson we created these rectangular cars randomly along the Y-
axis.
And then we managed to get them to move across to the left side of the screen.
The next step is to detect when the turtle collides with the car.
So that way, when the turtle hits one of the cars,
we can stop the game and prevent further cars from moving. Inside our while
loop I'm going to detect the collision with the car here.
So I'm going to get hold of all the cars in the car_manager object and I'm
going to use a for loop to loop through each of the cars in that list of cars.
And then we're going to detect whether if the car has a distance to the player
object that is less than 20.
Remember that our cars are 20 pixels in height by 40 pixels in width.
If the player is less than 20 pixels from the center of the car,
then it probably means that it's collided with the car.
So if this distance is less than 20,
then we're going to stop the game.
And the way that we stopped the game is of course,
by turning this game_is_on from true to false.
Let's run our code again and let's see this in action. So we can move our turtle,
we've got randomly generated cars moving across and let's just park our turtle right
here. When that car hit our turtle
it immediately stopped the game. Now,
if we want to take a look at what's happening
so for the screen to stay open instead of closing
once the process is finished, we can tell it to exitonclick.
So now let's run our code again and notice this time
if we collide with one of the cars
you can see that it stops and it waits for further instruction,
which eventually is going to be just the game over text showing up on screen
and we also the final level showing up on screen. That's it.
That's how we detect collision between the car and our player.
In the last step,
we figured out how to detect when the player turtle hits a car and to stop the
while loop which stops the game at that point.
Now we're going to figure out how we can detect when the turtle reaches the
other side of the screen so that once our turtle makes a successful crossing,
then we can return the turtle to the starting position and speed up all the
cars. So I'm going to do that right here,
and I'm going to detect a successful crossing.
So what is a successful crossing? Well, the player turtle has the reach
the finish line, right?
Which we've defined the Y value for as 280 here in the constant.
Now you could do this in a number of ways.
You could define a method here or simply just get hold of the player's position
and then figure out if it's over 280 inside our main.py.
Now I'm going to create a method here instead
and I'm going to call the method is_at_finish_line.
This method is going to return true
if the turtle is at the finish line and false while it's not.
So how do we detect this? Well,
we can get our self.ycor
and we can see if that is greater than 280,
which is our finished line Y value.
What that means we've pretty much gone over the finish line, right?
So if this is the case, then we're going to return true.
But while that's not the case, any other time when we check this,
we're going to return false.
So now coming back to our main.py,
we can call our player.is_at_finish_line and we can say,
if this is true, well in that case
we're going to get the player to go back to the starting position.
So inside our player class let's create yet another method which I'm going to
call go_to_start.
And this just involves getting our player to go to the starting position
which we've defined here in a constant.
So notice how we've got a little bit of repetition here,
so we can actually delete this line and simply call self.
go_to_start. Back in our main.py
once the player is at the finish line, we're going to get the player to go
to the stat.r And if we go ahead and run our code
as it is right now,
you can see that once the turtle makes it across the road,
[inaudible]
it goes back to the starting position.
Now the very last thing we need to do is to increase the speed of the cars when
the player reaches the other side,
because effectively they've just gone to the next level.
What we can do is when the player reaches the finish line,
we can get the car_manager to increase the speed of the cars.
Let's create a method inside our CarManager class
which we'll call level_up. And in this method,
we're going to get the cars' speed to increase by 10 every time.
So if we have an attribute called car_speed and we initially set it as the
starting move distance,
and then we use this car_speed to determine how far it should move backward
each time. Well then when we level up,
we can say self.car_speed now increases by the increment that we've defined
here, which is the move increment.
So now when our player reaches the other side at the finish line,
then in addition to getting the player to go to the start,
we're going to get the car_manager to level up our cars as well.
So now when my turtle reaches the other side of the screen,
not only does the turtle go back to the original position,
but the cars also increase in speed.
In the last lesson,
we figured out how to detect when our turtle reaches the other side of the
screen. And when this happens,
we return the turtle player to its original position
and we also increase the speed of the cars by the move increment that we
defined as a constant. So in this lesson,
what we're going to do is the final step,
which is to create a scoreboard that keeps track of which level the turtle
player is on, and also when the turtle hits one of the
cars to display
the words game over in the center of the screen. To do that,
we're of course going to go inside our scoreboard class and again
we're going to need the help of the turtle class.
So let's import that from the turtle module and I'm going to make my scoreboard
a subclass of the turtle class.
So it's now inheriting from the turtle class.
And once we've defined our init and managed to get it
to inherit everything from the superclass,
then our scoreboard is now able to do everything a turtle class can do.
What do we want it to do? Well,
we have to initialize it with a couple of things first. For example,
we probably want to start out by hiding the turtle,
we just want to use it as a pen to draw. And in addition,
we don't want it to move and draw. So we're going to pull the pen up.
We're going to be using the write method instead.
And what we want to write is the level, right?
So the current level that the player is on. In order to do that,
we also have to keep track of the level.
So let's go ahead and create a new attribute
which I'll call level and let's start at level 1.
So then we can insert this right here with self.level
and in addition to writing this text,
we can define what we want the alignment to be.
So I want this to be on the left and also what the font to be.
So I'm going to use this font that was declared up here as a constant. Now,
inside our main.py next to where we've defined our player and our car_
manager
I'm going to create this new scoreboard object and that's going to be created
from the scoreboard class. Now notice when I run the code as it is,
you can see that our level is left-aligned,
it's got the font that we defined and it's writing the text that we want,
but it's not in the right position. To define the position
we have to do that right before we tell the scoreboard to write,
so right here, but after where we've got our penup.
So this way we don't draw a path to where we're going to.
So now we're going to define self.goto,
and I'm just going to get it to go to probably the top left corner.
So that's going to be probably -280 and then it's going to be
+280 on the Y. Now, if we just check the positioning,
you can see that it's a little bit too far up on the Y-axis.
So it lets move it down a little bit and you can tweak these things until you
get to the point where you're happy with its positioning.
So I think this looks pretty good. Now,
in addition to writing the level,
we actually have to update it every time the player levels up, right?
And they do that when there's a successful crossing.
So at some point here,
we should be able to call scoreboard and we should be able to get the scoreboard
to increase the level.
So let's go into scoreboard and let's define that function, increase_
level.
And the first thing to do when we're increasing the level is of course getting
hold of this self.level and then adding one to it each time.
In addition, we're going to need the level to be rewritten again.
So let's cut this out of the init and let's instead define a custom method
which we'll call update_scoreboard.
Yeah.
Inside this update_scoreboard, we can write the current level.
So now inside the init
we can call self.update_scoreboard
and also when we increase the level,
we can call self.update_scoreboard.
Now at the moment, as it is,
it's going to overwrite what used to be on the scoreboard.
So at the moment it's on level 1,
but once I make a successful crossing,
you can see that level 2 is going to be overwritten over level 1.
To prevent that when we update the scoreboard,
we have to get the scoreboard to clear itself
so that it deletes all the previous stuff that it wrote. This way
when we actually run our code
you can see that our scoreboard will refresh and clear the previous text and
write the new text each time.
So now the final thing to do is to write the words game over in the middle of
the screen when the game ends. To do that, I'm going to create
another method here
which I'll call game_over. And inside this method,
we're going to get our turtle to go to the center.
So we're going to say self.goto and the center is, of course, at
(0, 0), and then we're going to get it to write,
but this time we're not going to write the level anymore. Instead,
we're going to just write the words GAME OVER in all caps.
And I want the alignment to be centered and I want the font to be the default
font. Now, when we actually detect a collision,
not only is game_is_on going to be false,
but also we're going to get the scoreboard to show the game over sequence.
So now we can run our code and you can see that when my turtle collides with a
car,
then it says game over in the center.
And because when we wrote game over, we didn't clear any of the previous texts,
the user can see at the highest level that they managed to reach.
That's it. That's the entire game.
Hopefully you've managed to build this entire game by yourself and you're just here
to check a few niggling issues. But if you struggled with this code,
then I really recommend to review the previous lessons where we created the
snake game or when we created this turtle crossing game
and try to see if you can create these two games from scratch by yourself
by looking at how the game works. Because if you continue forward,
things are only gonna get more complex.
And I'm assuming that you're going to take the time to review and revise before
you continue.
So have fun playing with the turtle crossing game and be sure to let me know in
the Q/A what your highest level is that you managed to reach and also
remember to attach a picture or it didn't happen.
And this is a great project for you to customize.
So think about what you might want to change
like the colors or the shapes and make the game really your own and then take a
screenshot of it and share it with us in the Q/A so that we can all
appreciate and congratulate you on your work.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 24 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to learn about working with the local file system and also
understanding how directories work. And by the end of the day,
we will have improved our previous snake game where previously or currently the
way that it works is it just games over once we hit a wall or once we hit a
tail, which is fun, but it could be better.
Imagine if we could also keep track of the high score.
So if a user gets a score that's higher than the previous high score,
then if they game over, then the high score is going to be updated so that we can
keep trying to better ourselves at snake.
And once we've learned all of those skills of manipulating file systems,
reading and writing to file, then we're going to create a project
that's going to save us a lot of hassle and automate our lives a little bit
using Python. So the situation is
let's say you need to write lots of letters. Maybe you having a birthday party,
maybe you need to write wedding invites,
or maybe you just need to email all your clients. Well,
let's say that you wanted to personalize a part of that file
say, for example, the part where you say dear name. Well,
if you had a list of names and you wanted to create separate letters using each
of those names, so maybe one that says 'Dear James', one that says
'Dear Emily'
and then we just worked down the list and keep replacing parts of our letter
with the names in our list.
So we end up with a whole bunch of letters ready to send out.
Depending on what kind of jobs you might have,
this is something that could come in really handy as a part of your work
or maybe just in your day to day lives.
And we're going to get started using Python to automate parts of our lives,
and get Python to do a lot of the repetitive tasks that we don't want to do.
And so we can spend more time watching Netflix and playing video games.
First, let's start by improving our snake game,
getting it to be able to keep track of the high score that we attain each time
we play the game so that we can see what our high score is and keep striving to
better ourselves.
Open up the snake game in PyCharm that you created a few days back. Now,
if you can't find your snake game project,
or if you've made some significant changes to it where it might be confusing to
follow along with the tutorial, then simply just head over to this URL
which is in the course resources
and then you can go ahead and hit download as a zip, unzip
the downloaded file, and then open it inside PyCharm
and you should end up with the same project as I have here.
And once you've done that,
then we can begin to start adding the functionality to keep track of the high
score. Firstly, I'm going to add
another attribute to my scoreboard, which is going to be called high_score.
And again, it's going to start out as zero. Now,
the next thing I'm going to do is I'm going to replace this game over method
with a new method. We're not going to stop the game and write game over anymore.
Instead, we're going to reset the scoreboard.
So what happens when we reset the scoreboard? Well,
we need to figure out if the current score that the user has attained is greater
than the high score of all time. And if that is the case,
then we're going to update the high score with the value of the current score.
So the code for that would look something like this.
If self.score is greater than self.high_score,
well in that case then self.high_score is going to be equal to self.score.
Now, this looks a little bit confusing at first,
but if you just go through the logic and think about how you would create a high
score saving mechanism,
then you'll pretty quickly understand what's going on here. Now,
once we've updated the high score, the next thing to do is to reset the score.
So I'm going to reset it down to zero. Now, remember the order of your code
matters a huge deal because if you first set the score to zero,
then it's never going to be greater than the current high score.
So this will never get triggered.
So as always, be careful where you're writing your code. Now,
after we've set the score, then we need to update the scoreboard.
Now,
one thing that I've changed about the scoreboard is previously when we increased
the score,
I've used the self.clear and then self.update_scoreboard.
But it actually makes more sense for this clear to happen
every single time we update the scoreboard.
So I've added this method call here before we actually write the score.
The reason why I couldn't do this previously is because when we wanted to show
game over,
we wanted to keep the score on the screen and then for
the score board turtle to go to the center and write game over so that both of
these things show up on screen.
But now that we're getting rid of our game over method,
then we can go ahead and move that clear to update scoreboard
and then we don't have to call it twice, both in reset and increase_score.
Now, in addition to writing the score,
I'm now also going to write the high score,
and this is going to be using an f-string to insert self.high_score.
Now, if we run this game as it is,
you can see it says score 0, high score
0 using these initial values.
But as soon as it hits the wall,
it ends because in our main.py
we change this game_is_on to false and that ends our while loop.
Instead,
what I'm going to do is I'm going to delete this game_is_on equals false and
also delete it when we collide with the tail.
And I'm also going to delete the part where we call game over from the score
board. Instead, I'm going to get the scoreboard to reset itself.
So that way the score gets reset to zero and we're ready with the next round.
So now if I run this game again, you can see it says, score is 0,
and then as soon as we get a higher score and we end up dying, like
so, then our high score goes to 2.
But our snake kind of just disappears because it continues moving in the same
direction and it's now probably somewhere, all the way down to the left.
What we do instead? Well, our snake also needs to be reset.
So let's create a reset method inside the snake class as well.
And all we're going to do is we're going to get all of the segments to clear.
And when I hover over this clear,
you can see what it does is it's going to remove all of the items from that
list.
So all of the segments that we've added already to the list of segments is
going to be deleted. And then once we've gotten rid of all the segments,
we're going to call self.create_snake again,
so that we create another three-segment snake in the starting position.
Now, in addition,
I'm also going to set the self.head as the zeroth element from that list
of segments.
So basically we're doing everything that is in the init because we're going to
initialize the snake again, back at the center.
So now if I go back to main.py, and in addition to resetting the scoreboard,
I also get my snake to reset,
Right?
At this point, when I run the code,
you'll notice that it's not behaving quite the way you expect it to. So I can go
ahead and score, and when I die, I get the high score,
but my old snake is still lingering on screen.
So even though we've cleared the segments,
we don't actually get rid of the turtles that are still onscreen.
And in order to get rid of them,
we actually have to send them to a different location. In our snake reset method,
just before we clear our segments,
so while we still have access to all of them,
we're going to use a for loop to loop through all of the segments in the list of
segments and tell each of them to go to a place that is off the screen.
So our screen is only 600 by 600
and I'm going to tell it to go to 1000 X, 1000 Y.
So it's gonna disappear off the screen. So this way,
notice how
when the snake hits one of the walls or when it hits its tail,
instead of sort of just staying there,
it actually disappears into a location that's off the screen.
So that way we can keep track of our high scores,
we can continue to get higher scores,
and if we get a score that's not quite as high as the high score
and we end up dying, then the high score stays as the previous value.
Now, the only thing about this game is that in order to end it,
we have to hit the stop button here. But once we've done that,
it also reveals the crucial flaw in our code.
Because if I run our program again, you can see that, wait,
what happened to the high score, right?
We had a high score of 3 previously. So, huh?
What exactly is happening? Well, the reason is actually quite simple.
We know that if we create a variable, let's say we create a variable called a
set it to equal three,
and then at some point we set a to be from the input.
So now when I run this code,
you can see that initially a is equal to three,
but then the next line I asked the user, 'what do you want a to equals?'
I'm going to make it equal to 12. Now at this point,
if I go ahead and access this variable a inside the console
just by typing a and then hitting enter, you can see it's equal to 12.
Now, similarly, I can add some print statements here.
I can print the value of a
and then also print the value of a after we modify it. So again,
you can see initially it's equal to 3, but then I decided to change it to 12.
So now it's equal to 12.
Now what happens if I rerun the code. A is equal to three
aain.
Its reset itself because the code is being rerun and the previous state is not
being remembered. In our case, we've got this high score variable
which initially starts out as zero.
And at some point during the game as we progress,
we modify this high score variable to equal a new value,
let's say three.
So now if I go ahead and print my high score,
you can see that it's equal to 3.
But as soon as I rerun the code and this goes through,
then all of that progress gets reset.
And now if I print the value of high score, you can see it's again,
equal to zero. So this is what's happening in our program as well.
So how might you keep track of the score if you weren't using Python?
Well,
you might open up a word document and then write down your high score in that
document, close it down, and then the next time you play the game,
open up that file again and see what your previous high score is.
We're going to try and do the same thing,
but using Python to read and write to a file so that we can save our progress
and be able to retrieve our previous high scores
each time we play the snake game. To find out how to do that and to solve this
problem, head over to the next lesson
and we'll talk about how to use Python to open, read, write,
and close files on your system.
In this lesson,
I want to talk about the file system and how you could use Python to open up
files, read files, write to the files, and also close them down again,
all without touching the mouse.
So that way we can start saving our high scores into a file and retrieve
it the next time we open up our program.
Let's start out by trying to do some of the simplest things with a file, reading
and writing.
Now I've created a new project using PyCharm called day-24,
and I've created my main.py where we're going to write our Python code.
But in addition, I'm also going to create a new file
which is going to be called my_file.txt.
So this is going to be a text file. Now, inside this text file,
I'm going to write some text. Hello, my name is Angela. And if you want,
you can actually find this text file inside your project folder,
and you can actually open it up with your native text editing software.
So TextEdit on Mac or Notepad on Windows.
And you can see it's just a bunch of text. There's nothing really special here.
But what we can do using Python is that we can actually open up that file.
So, notice how this method, open, is a inbuilt method.
So you don't have to import anything, you can use it directly.
And it takes a number of inputs;
the file that you want to open, the mode that you want to open that file in,
and a whole bunch of other optional things that you can specify. In our case,
I'm going to specify the name of my file as a string,
so my_file.txt.
So remember that extension.
And then I'm going to open this file and I'm going to save it inside a variable
called file. So when we hit run right now, nothing's really going to happen.
You're not going to see anything happening, but behind the scenes,
Python has already opened up this file and its ready for the next operation that
you might want to do on that file.
So the next thing I wanna do is I wanna read the file and this read method
returns the contents of that file as a string.
So we can now save it inside a variable called contents
and I can go ahead and print out this contents.
So when I hit run right now, you can see what gets printed out
is the content from my_file.txt.
And if I go ahead and modify my file to add some more lines and I hit run again,
you can see that all of the lines are being printed
once we've opened the file, we've read the file,
and we print the contents that we have read. At the end of all of our work,
what we have to do once we're done with that file that we've opened
we also have to close it. If there's an open,
there's probably going to be a close. Now, why do we need to close the file?
Well, once Python opens up that file,
it basically takes up some of the resources of your computer.
And at some point later on,
it might decide to close it and free up those resources,
but we don't know when that's going to happen and if it will happen.
So instead, we're going to tell it to close down the file manually using this
line of code.
It's a similar concept to having lots and lots of tabs open in your browser.
While it's kind of convenient to have all of these tabs open,
if you actually want your computer to perform at its best
you actually want to only use as many tabs as you need.
Every extra tab is going to add a little bit of burden to your computer
and especially if you're using a very heavy application like Chrome
which likes to take up a lot of resources of your CPU and your computer.
If you have more than 20 or 30 tabs,
you'll notice a significant decrease in the speed of your computer.
So here's a computer tip as well as Programming tip,
always close down tabs that you've opened and always close out on files that
you've opened. Now because it's kind of hard to remember to close a file because
we might be doing lots of other things in between the open and close, right?
We might be writing to the file,
we might be modifying it or reading it line by line or doing lots of different
things. So instead,
what many Python developers opt for is a different way of opening the file.
We can use a 'with' keyword. And 'with' we can open this file and then we can open
it as whatever it is we decide to name. So this you can name to anything.
You can name it as f, you can name it as file.
It's basically the equivalent to that variable that we created earlier on which
stored the opened file.
Now we can indent the rest of this and I can delete this file.close.
And you can see that it works exactly the same as before,
but now we no longer have to remember to close our file just by adding some
keywords here.
This 'with' keyword is going to manage that file directly.
So as soon as it notices that we're done with it, it'll close down the file.
It kinda makes me wish that something similar for tabs existed,
but let's get back to our Python code.
So now that we've opened up my_file.txt,
we've saved into a variable called file,
we've read that file and saved the contents that we read into a variable called
contents, and then we've printed it. Now, what if instead of reading the file,
I wanted to write to it? Well,
it's just as simple. So we can get hold of our file and then call
write.
And we can put any sort of string inside this write method to put into our file.
So let's put some text, let's call it new text.
And I want this new text to be written into my_file.txt.
And if we run the code as it is, you'll notice that it doesn't work
cause it says that unsupported operation,
this file is not writable.
And this is because we opened up the file in read-only mode.
So remember when we took a look at some of the parameters for this method open,
one of them was called mode and by default, it's set to read-only,
so 'r.' Now if we want to write to it, so make it editable,
we have the change, the mode to 'w' for write.
So now if I run the code again,
you can see that process finished with exit code zero
which we know to mean that everything was successful.
And if I take a look inside my_file.txt, all of the previous text
got magically deleted and replaced with the new text that I wanted to write.
Now, if you don't want to delete everything that is in the file
but you just want to add to it,
then you can change this mode from 'w' to 'a' and 'a' stands for append.
So just as we like to use list.append
and then we can add something to the end of the list, well,
the same thing happens with appending and writing. So I can write my new text and
I can add a new line, remember we can use \n to
add a new line, and then add the new text.
And now take a look at the after version when I hit run and we write this new
line and new text by appending it to my file.
It's gone at the very end of the file here. Now,
one of the important things you need to know when you're writing files is when
you try to open a file in write mode and that file doesn't exist,
then it's going to actually create it for you from scratch.
So let's go ahead and create a file
which I'll call new_file.txt,
make sure you've got the extension in there.
And we have the mode as write set. Because this new_file.txt doesn't exist
in this folder, then it's actually going to create it for us.
So now when I hit run, you can see that once this goes through,
that new file gets created and the new text has been written inside.
Now, remember this only works when you're in the write mode and when that file
doesn't currently exist.
So those are some basic
ways of working with the file system. We can open and read, we can open and
write. And by using these different modes, append, read,
or write,
we can define what it is that we want to do with that file that we've opened.
Now that we've learned how to work with the file system, in the next lesson
I want to show you how we can fix our snake game so that we can write to
a text file our high score. And every time we open up and run our game,
we fetch that file and see what the previous high score was so that we can load
it into our game. So for all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.
It's time for your challenge.
You've already seen how we've managed to get the snake game
to keep track of the high score.
And when the user scores a number that's greater than the high score,
then we replace that high score with the new value. But unfortunately
as you saw previously, at the moment when we run this game and we achieve a new
high score, the next time that we run the game again
that is completely lost.
So the first thing I want you to do is to right click on your project,
create a new file and call it data.txt.
So we're going to create a data text file.
Now this data text file is just going to contain a single number,
zero.
And we're going to use the data that's in this data.txt file to keep track of
the high score.
And it's your job to figure out how you can convert this simple attribute here,
high score, to instead of using a number that we've just created in the code,
I want you to use the number that's inside data.txt.
So you'll need to read from it here and then later on,
you'll need to write to it when we reset the game and check
if there is a new high score. Everything going well,
you should be able to run the game,
achieve a new high score and then stop and rerun the game and still see that
high score showing up. Think about what you learned in the last lesson,
have a think about how you can convert the text in here into a number using
what you've learned in previous lessons and pause the video and give this
challenge a go.
All right.
So we know that we've already got this file, data.txt, and it already
contains the number zero. So instead of using this line of code,
we're going to be reading from that file to get that zero.
Let's delete this line of code. And instead,
I'm going to open my file with the file name
that is data.txt. And the file name is, of course, a string
like you see here wrapped in quotation marks,
and we're going to use the with keywords so that we don't have to bother about
closing the file again.
We can get Python to manage it for us. with opening this file,
and I'm going to save that file to a variable called data.
Now I'm going to use that data and read from it. Now,
once I've read from it,
I should end up with some sort of string that's going to represent the contents
of this file.
So that string will need to be converted to an integer
if we want to use it as a number
which we can increase and change in our game.
So I'm going to type convert it into an integer. And then finally,
I'm going to save that as the value for our new attribute,
self.high_score. That's the reading part done
and if we run our code as it is,
it should already work as it did before,
but it won't have the feature that we want
which is to be able to quit out of the game,
stop and rerun.
So it still not saving the latest high score to that data.txt.
You can see it's still zero. So where do we want to save it? Well,
it's got to happen every time we adjust the high score.
When the score is greater than the current high score,
we set the high score to the new score. But in addition,
we're going to read from a file data.txt.
So let's use our syntax with,
and then open, again, and let's pass in the name of our file, data.txt.
And remember that we also need to change the mode to 'w' for
write because otherwise, it's not going to let us write to that file. Now,
once we've opened it and we've saved it as a variable called data,
then we can write to that data using data.write.
And what are we going to write to it? Well, we have to write a string.
So let's use an f-string to convert our current self.high_score into a
string, and then write that into our file, data.txt.
Now notice what happens when I run my code.
So I'm going to achieve a new high score of, um,
2, which I'm very proud of. And now if I hit stop,
take a look at data.txt. It's been updated,
it's been rewritten by these two lines of code.
So now if I rerun my program,
you can see it already is showing my previous high score of 2,
and I can keep playing this game and accumulate my high score
and all of that data will be saved to my file
data.txt, like that.
So did you manage to get this right? And by the way,
if you see this keyboard interrupt, don't worry.
That's just because we clicked on the stop button to stop our program because it
wants to keep on going forever until we achieve the highest score of them
all. The point of this exercise is to try and get you to review what we learned
in the last lesson, which is opening a file, reading the file,
and also writing to the file and remembering the mode that we have to change.
And hopefully, you'll start to see how this could be really useful in terms of
improving the usability of our programs in our games.
Now in the next lesson, we're going to talk more than just about files.
We're going to talk about file paths and directories.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
All right.
So we've seen how we can open and close files as well as read them and write to
them. But files don't just have a name.
They also have a path or a way of getting to them.
For example, here in this map,
if we wanted this dinosaur to get to the golden egg,
there's many paths that it could take.
But if we wanted to give it some directions as to how it might arrive on this
path, well we might say, you know, continue forwards at the volcano turn, right.
And then when you see a snake turn right again,
and when you see the coconut tree turn left and you will get to the cave with
the egg. Now on computers, it works quite similarly,
but we have to remember that on the computer there's files and there's folders.
So files can live within folders and you can navigate through several folders
deep in order to get to a particular file.
So let's think about what the file paths might be for a computer that has a
structure that looks like this.
So the first thing to note is that at the very root of all of the files and the
folders is basically the origin, right? This is the root folder.
And on a Mac,
you can see that our PyCharm projects live within my users folder, inside a
folder called users inside a folder called Macintosh HD.
So if I have this folder selected right here, I can say
go to enclosing folder, which is this one.
And then if I keep doing this,
you can see it keeps jumping up until it can go no further.
So the root on a Mac is the Macintosh HD, the hard drive.
And that in terms of a path is represented by a single forward slash.
Now when you're on a Windows computer however,
the root folder is usually your C drive.
So that becomes your root folder. Inside our root folder, our
Macintosh HD or a C drive,
we have a folder called work. Inside that folder
I've got a report Word document as well as a project folder.
And then inside that project folder, there's a PowerPoint called talk.
Now, if we think about the file paths for each of these things,
this is what they might look like.
The route is obviously just a /, the work folder will be
/work, report will be /work/ report.doc, project will
be /work/project, and finally,
the talk will be /work/project/talk.
ppt.
So this path is kind of like the direction that we were talking about
previously.
It's a way for the computer to navigate to the file of interest
which in this case might be the talk.ppt.
And we have to give it directions for which folder to go into and then which
folder, and then you'll find the file with this name. Now,
this is known as an absolute file path.
Absolute file paths always start off relative to the root.
So you always see a forward slash to begin with, and sometimes you'll see
C: or on a Mac
you'll just see the /. This absolute file
path is basically a path that starts from the origin,
the route of the computer storage system.
Now there's also something called a relative file path.
Taking this talk.ppt,
we know that the absolute file path is /work/project/
talk.ppt. But
what if we were actually inside this project folder?
So let's say that at the time when we're trying to get to this talk.ppt
we're actually right here.
Now this, in computer-speak, is called the working directory.
It's basically the directory or folder that we're currently working from.
And once we've established a working directory,
say that we are right here,
then we can use what's called a relative file path to get to a file that we're
interested in. So given that we're here and we're trying to get here,
the relative file path is simply just ./talk.ppt.
The ./ signifies
look in the current folder for this file.
If we switch up our working directory and let's say we are now working from the
work folder, how do we get to this talk.ppt? Well,
the absolute file path would not change for this file,
but the relative file path would now be ./project/talk.ppt.
So we're walking from here to here to here.
Now, what if we wanted to go upwards in the directory tree?
Let's say we wanted to get a hold of this report.doc,
but we all currently working inside this project folder.
How do we go one step up? Well, we would right ..,
so two dots now, /report.doc.
So we're inside this project folder, we're coming out of it to the parent folder
which is the work folder, and then we're getting hold of this file.
So that two dots represents going one step up in the hierarchy to the parent
folder, which this case is the work folder.
Now what we've been doing is we've been writing code inside our main.py.
And that main.py has usually been inside some sort of project folder. When
we're trying to get hold of a file this is basically where we are at.
So our working directory is the work folder.
So that means if we wanted to get access to this report.doc file from our
main.py,
all we need to do is write ./report.doc because we're working within
the same directory and we're just getting hold of this file.
Now, when you're using relative file path, you can use this ./
but you can also shorten it and get rid of it as well.
This is why we've been able to open this my_file.txt
which is in the same folder as my main.py and notice how these two files are at
the same hierarchical level. So let's do a quick challenge.
I'm going to delete the part where we write to the file and I'm going to change
my file
so it just has one sentence and I'm going to locate this file by using 'Reveal in
Finder' and on Windows that would be right-
click and Show in Explorer.
And it would show you the location of that file in your computer system.
Now, what we're going to do is we're going to move this file to the desktop.
Right?
And what I want you to do is I want you to go to the desktop, right-
click on that file. And if you want a Mac, I want you to click on get info.
And if you are on a Windows,
I want you to right-click and go to properties.
Now what you're looking for is this location here.
Now you can see that this current file,
new_file, is located under the root folder,
which in this case is the C:\Users\London
AppBrewery\Desktop\new_file.txt. On a Mac
you can see that it's located under the root folder,
which is Macintosh HD slash users slash Angela slash desktop slash my_file.
txt. Here comes your challenge.
Now that we've moved our file away from our project,
I want you to fix this code so that when you run it,
it won't give you this file not found error because at the moment there is no my_
file.txt in the same working directory as our main.py.
It doesn't exist inside this folder.
Have a think about what you've learned so far and see if you can change this
path so that our code works again.
And it's the same on Windows.
Use the location of the file on your computer and use the absolute path in the
code to get it to work. Pause the video now.
Okay
All right. Here's how you would use the absolute path. So we know that our,
my_file.txt is located in the root folder and then it's
users, angela, desktop. So let's go ahead and change this string.
Let's start at the root and then let's add the next folder,
which is users.
And then let's add another slash and then we go to the next folder,
which is Angela. Now of course, this will be different for you,
but finally we go to our desktop and then we can get to our,
my_file.txt.
So this is the full path to get to this file.
So now if I run this code again, you can see it's able to read the file,
there is no errors, and it's getting hold of the contents of the file.
Now on Windows, it's a similar story.
So we know that the location of the file is root,
then users, then LondonAppBrewery, then desktop. Again,
this of course will be different for you depending on your username,
but you should see it in your location
when you take a look at the file properties. So let's change this.
Let's start out at the root, which is the C drive,
and then let's go to users.
And then we go to our username which is LondonAppBrewery
,
and then we go to our desktop and that is where it should find this new_file.
txt. So now when I hit run,
you can see that it's able to fetch that file and print the content without any
errors. Now,
one of the peculiarities about file paths in Windows and Mac is that in a Mac,
the path,
each of the folders are separated by a / whereas on Windows,
they're separated by a \. But as you've noticed,
when we're writing Python code, we don't care about that.
We can just write it as / and making sure that we have the root,
which represents the C drive, so this entire part,
and then we have our folder, the next folder, the next folder,
the next folder, et cetera. So now comes the next challenge.
You can see that this path follows from the root folder,
which is the C drive and on the Mac,
it's also from the Macintosh HD.
So what if we wanted to change this so that it's relative to our current main
.py? Our main.py
if we go to 'Show in Explorer',
you can see that the path for this file is the following.
It's under
Users/LondonAppBrewery/PyCharmProjects/WindowsDemo.
So that's the name of my project. And then afterwards,
it's my main.py. So this is a bit of a tricky question.
Given that this file is inside this current folder or whatever it is that you
have as your folder which contains this file,
how can you get it to use a relative file path so that it jumps back two folders
to the LondonAppBrewery folder and then goes to Desktop and then to new file?
On our Mac, it's a similar story. So we go to 'Reveal in Finder'.
We can see this is where we are currently.
So our current working directory is this day-24 project folder.
So if we go one level up and the shortcut is command + up,
we go to our day-24 folder. So this is our working directory.
Now, if we want to go up one level,
we can go to go, and then go to including folder,
so one level up that gets us to PyCharm projects.
And then if we go one level up further, we get to our Angela folder
at which point we can then navigate downwards to Desktop/my_file.txt.
This is your challenge.
Figure out what the relative path to the text file on your desktop should be
then modify the code and get it to work. Pause the video now.
The way that we would modify this is in order to get to this Angela folder where
we can continue to our Desktop and then to my file,
we have to go up two levels.
So that translates to ../../
and now we're inside the Angela folder.
So we can start going down. And PyCharm is smart enough to know what your
folder structure looks like.
So it will start giving you hints as to what folders are accessible at this
level.
So I can get to Desktop and then I can get to my_file.txt.
And if I go ahead and run my code,
you can see it's able to read and print the content of that file.
The main difference between an absolute file path and a relative file path is
the absolute file path is always relative to the root of your computer. On
Windows that's the C drive, usually anyways
unless you've changed it. And on a Mac,
it is the Macintosh HD.
Now the relative file path is relative to your current working directory.
So it depends on where you are and where you're trying to get to. Now,
depending on the situation and where that file you are interested in is located,
you might decide to use the absolute file path or the relative file path.
And you can see that in this case
it's not necessarily that much shorter or that much more easier to understand.
So if you know how to do both,
then you can adapt to the situation and figure out which one is most
appropriate. Now I know that paths can be confusing.
So that's why I've come up with a whole bunch of quiz exercises for you in the
next lesson for you to get more the practice with file paths so that you can
feel confident leaving this lesson.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right, guys, it's time to put what you've learned to the test. Now in this project, we're going
to be doing a little bit of mail merging.
So mail merging is where you take something like what
we have a list of names, for example, and we want to insert each of these names into a letter.
So instead of saying dear [name], you are invited to my birthday the Saturday, it should say dear
and then it would replace that with whatever is here.
Take a look at this example file.
You can see that it replaced the name placeholder with the first name in the invited_names.txt
file.
Your objective is to write some python code to automate the process.
So what you're going to end up with is a bunch of letters, one for each of the names inside the invited_
names.txt and the letters are going to be named like this: letter_for_ and
then the name of the person.
And they're going to be saved in a txt format, which you can open either in Google Docs or in Microsoft
Word.
And it's basically ready for printing.
So I've made it a little bit harder for you by adding in a whole bunch of folders.
And each of these files are nested inside a bunch of folders.
So, for example, starting letter is inside letters, which is inside input.
And then the letters that you're going to generate are going to need to go into this folder called Ready
ToSend, which is inside output. And no cheating.
I don't want you moving around any of these files.
You're going to be using what you've learned about directories and file paths to do everything without
needing to drag and drop or move anything around manually.
I've got some starting files for you.
So the first thing I want you to do is to go to the course resources and download the zip file, which
will be your starting project code.
Once you open it within PyCharm, it's going to ask you to configure the interpreter. So you can either
go ahead and click on that pop-up, or if it disappears, then just click on the event log and then click
on Configure Python Interpreter and then select the latest interpreter that you have installed.
So in my case, it's 3.8, but by the time you're watching this, it'll probably be
3.9 or even later.
And once that's done, then you can go ahead and have a look inside main.py.
So here I've got some instructions for you.
First, you're going to create a letter using the starting_letter.txt, which is right here
nested two folders deep, and then you're going to use each of the names inside invited_names.
txt to replace the part where it says name with the actual names that you see in invited_names.txt.
And then you're going to save each of those letters that you've generated inside the folder ReadyTo
Send.
And you can take a look at the example if you want to see what the final outcome looks like.
So it's going to be the name without any spaces afterwards, just a comma.
Now there's going to be a few things that will trip you up along the way.
And I'm hoping that you're going to use your knowledge about how to get help from Google and Stack overflow,
as well as some of these hints that I've left in here for you.
So the hints take you to three pages of Python documentation, and they're chosen because the methods
that are featured in them will definitely help you in this project.
In fact, some of the things that you're going to try to do won't be possible unless you take a look
at each of these pages of documentation, read through it, and understand what the methods do.
Now, as always, with a lot of tutorials, it's impossible to teach you every single method.
And it would be really, really tedious if I just went through all of the methods that are available in Python
and showed them to you individually.
So instead, you have to work just as a pro developer does which is to find out information when you
need it and to quickly understand what's happening and how to use the information you found on the fly.
Don't worry if you haven't seen me use these methods before. You will get more practice by using
the documentation, figuring things out yourself, and implementing things that you haven't seen before.
Once you're ready, go ahead and take a look at each of these links, see what each of the methods I've
linked to does, and then go ahead and try to tackle this challenge.
So pause the video and I'll see you on the other side.
I hope you've given that a good go and now I'm going to run through the solution with you. Here,
I've got those three links open and they're all documentation on W3schools for different methods
in Python.
The first one is a method called readlines.
It's really important that you have that
's' because there's also another method called readline, the singular form.
What readlines does is it returns all the lines in the file as a list where each line is an item in
the list object.
For example, we can run this example and you can see that inside this demo file, readlines, there's
several lines in that file, and each line after running this method, gets added as a item inside a list
like this.
Now, the next method I showed you is the python string replace method.
And what this method does is it will replace a specified phrase with another specified phrase.
If the starting text was 'I like bananas' and you do txt.replace, you can replace the part where
it says bananas with apples.
And when you print, you can see the end outcome changes that text to I like apples.
Now, the final method that I showed you is the string strip method.
And what this does is it will remove the spaces at the beginning and at the end of the string.
So if our starting text has a lot of whitespace at the beginning and the end, and then we do txt.
strip, it'll get rid of all of that extra space and it ends up with just the word.
Now, if you have a space in between, another word
like this, if we hit run, then you can see that it keeps the space in between the words, but it gets
rid of any spaces on either side, which is really, really handy.
And you're going to see hopefully why it's really, really useful.
So now that we've reviewed these three methods that we haven't seen before, and normally you would probably
find these when you actually get stuck and when you're searching Stack Overflow.
But now that you're aware of those methods, let's go ahead and create a letter using our starting letter.
So I'm going to go ahead and delete everything in here.
And now let's go ahead and tackle this challenge.
So the first thing I want to do is to get hold of all of the invited names
and I want to turn them into a list. Now
I can, of course, rather tediously go and add some square brackets, add some quotation marks around
it, and then add it into my main.py.
But I don't want to do that.
Instead, I'm going to get Python to read the file.
So using our classic syntax with open, I'm going to open up that file.
But in order to open it up, I need to specify a string which is going to be the path that leads me
from here to here.
So let's think about how we might get there.
Now, this input output folder is on the same hierarchical level as our current file where we're writing
our code.
If we want to use a relative file path, we can simply say go into the current folder which is mail-
merge-project-start and then find a folder called Input.
Inside this folder called Input,
we're going to go to another folder called Names.
And then inside that folder of names, we're going to get a hold of that file called invited_names
.txt.
And PyCharm is super clever and it helps you out with a lot of typing.
So it saves you some time as well.
And then I'm going to save it as names_file.
Now that I've got this file open
I'm going to go ahead and read it.
So names_file.read. And once I've read it, I'm going to save it to a variable called names and
then I'm going to print out my names.
So now if I go ahead and hit run my main.py, you can see that it prints out all of these names individually
because it's getting hold of everything that's in here and just printing it out.
Now, at this point, I would really like these names to be in the format of a list.
So if you remember, that's where this readlines method is going to be really helpful because it returns
a list containing each line inside the file as a list item.
Now, instead of saying names_file.read, let's replace that with readlines.
Now, when I hit run, you can see it prints out names, and names is now magically turned into a list.
So now that we have our list of names which we've extracted from our invited_names.txt, then
we can go ahead and proceed to the next step where we're going to replace this placeholder in our starting
letter with each of these names.
Let's go ahead and create a constant at the top which I'll call PLACEHOLDER, and I'm going to set
it as the string which is the square brackets and then the word name because this is the string
that we want to replace from our starting letter.
The next step is to open up our starting letter.
So again, I'm going to use open and then I'm going to specify the path.
So from here, I'm going to go into the folder that's at the same level as this file,
so using the ./ and then I'm going to go into input again and then I'm going to go into instead
of names, I'm going to go to letters.
And I'm going to get hold of my starting letter and I'm going to open this as the letter_file. With the
letter_file
I'm simply just going to get a hold of the letter_contents by saying letter_file.read.
And this is going to be a normal read because I want all of the content inside that letter and it's
now going to be saved as a string inside my letter_contents.
The next step is to go through the letter contents and replace that placeholder with the actual name
that we've got in our list.
To do that we'll need the second method that I showed you which is the replace method. So we can get
hold of the text call, replace,
and then the output of this method will be a new string which has modified
this tex. I in our case we'll need a loop. So we can say for name in our list of names, let's go through
each of the names in that list and then let's get the letter_contents and replace the placeholder,
so the old string, with a new string which is going to be the name.
And once we've replaced it, then we're going to save it into a new_letter.
Now that we have our new letter, let's go ahead and print it out and see what it looks like.
So you can see all the contents of each of the letters being printed, but other than the very last
letter that looks pretty normal, every other letter has a new line after the name.
So remember when we printed out each of these names, you can see that after each of the names that
they've extracted from this list of invited names, there's a new line that's being added,
and you can see that with this \n.
The only one that doesn't have a new line is the very last one.
What we need to do is to strip the new line. Does that remind you of something?
Well, we have a method that we saw called strip which can take away any of the spaces at the beginning
and at the end of the string.
And then we can end up with an output which is the string without any of those leading and trailing
spaces.
We're going to loop through each of the names and then we're going to take the name and we're going
to call strip on each of those names.
And then we can save it to a variable called stripped_name.
And now we can use that stripped_name instead of the name.
Now if I go ahead and print out our new_letter,
you can see that each of the letters look exactly like how we want them to be. All we need to do now
is to write them into a new file. In previous lessons
I mentioned that when you open a file that doesn't exist, Python will actually create that file for
you.
Again, using our with open, I'm going to navigate to this ReadyToSend folder. Going from where we
are in main.py,
we're going to go to the output folder and then we're going to go to the ReadyToSend folder.
And then inside the ReadyToSend folder is where we're going to create our new file.
So let's think about what we want our file name to look like. In the intro I showed you
this is the format for each of the files; letter_for_Aang.txt.
And then this part is replaced by each of the names.
So let's write that letter_for_ the name and then .txt.
We can use an fstring to replace this part with the stripped_name.
So now we should be creating a new letter for each of the names in our list of names.
So now let's refer to this file as the completed_letter.
What we want to do with this completed_letter, which at the moment is blank, is we want to write to
it.
So to do that, we have to change the open mode from default which is 'r' for read to 'w' for
write.
And this will allow us to get our completed letter and write to it.
What do we want to write in there?
Well, we want to write the new letter that we've created, of course.
That's pretty much the end of our code, and all we have to do is to go ahead and hit run. And once I
hit run, you can see there's a whole bunch of letters that have been generated over here,
and if I click on each of them, you can see that the name placeholder has now been replaced
and I'm now ready to go to the printers and print all of these out.
So did you manage to figure out how to complete this project?
If not, be sure to review the relevant parts of the lessons today so that you're really confident with
what's going on and you understand all of this code.
If you want to take a look at the completed solution, then head over to the course resources and you'll
find a link to the final project code which actually works even within repl.it.
So you can delete all of these files and you can see it generate them from scratch.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 25 of 100 Days of Code.
So today we're going to be learning about how to work with CSV files,
so not just text files as we saw in yesterday's lessons.
But we're going to be working with data files and we're going to be analyzing
that data with a library called Pandas.
This is one of the most popular Python data analysis libraries,
and we're going to get to grips with how we can use it to start getting some
insight into our data. By the end of the day,
you're going to be building a educational and interesting game,
which gets you to guess and learn all of the States in the US. And the
inspiration comes from a quiz on Sporcle
where it has a map of all the States,
it's all blank until you start guessing some States,
and then you keep going until you've managed to get all 50. Or like me,
you get stuck at 30 out of 50.
This game tests you on your knowledge of the names of the 50 States in the US.
So for example, if I go and add another state and I hit
OK,
then that name appears on the map at the location of the state.
The aim of the game is to remember all of the names of the states and to name as
many of them as you can.
So I managed to get to about only 30, um,
but I've never lived in the US so my knowledge just comes from watching TV
shows and general knowledge,
but if you're from the US then you're probably going to do a lot better than
me.
So this is an interactive and educational game that I think that you are going
to enjoy playing. So once you are ready, head over to the next lesson,
and let's get started learning about how to work with data files.
When I was really young, I remember
a piece of homework that I had to do for Geography in school.
And the teacher asked us to basically watch the weather report every single day
on the news and note down what was the temperature,
what was the weather condition of that day.
And then we would end up with the weather condition and temperature for the
previous week. Now at the time,
it was the point in time where a lot of teachers didn't actually really know what
the internet did. So, um,
I realized that I could actually just wait until the day before I have to give
the homework in, go onto the internet,
find the weather conditions for the previous seven days
and then write it out instead of having to watch the weather forecast every
single day. So I don't know what that says about me,
but if you are somebody who enjoys taking shortcuts in life and refuse to do
work that can be done by computers, then you are in the right place.
Learning Python is definitely the way to go.
So inside Google sheets
which you can access by going to sheets.google.com,
I have created a new spreadsheet of the days of the week and the temperature of
each of those days in Celsius and also the weather condition on those days.
This is a replica of that homework from many, many moons ago,
but we're going to be working with this data to learn how we can read data files
and then analyze them and how we can do lots of things with it.
So the first thing I want you to do is the head over to the link in the course
resources which will take you to this spreadsheet.
And then once you've got it open, then go to file download
and I want you to download it in the comma separated values or CSV format.
And you should end up with a file like this.
Now I want you to rename this file so that it's just weather_data.csv
, and then I've want you to create a new PyCharm project
which you can call anything you want.
I've called it day 25. And also create your main.py.
Now I'm going to drag my weather_data.csv into my folder day-25 and click
refactor to move that file into my project folder. Now,
at this point,
PyCharm recognizes that this is a CSV file and it asks you whether if you want to
install some plugins to make it easier to view this file. Now,
at this point,
you can click cancel because we want to view the data as the raw data,
which is in this CSV format. Now,
CSVs are a very common way of representing tabula data,
so data that fits into tables like a spreadsheet. And CSV,
as you've already seen stands for comma separated values.
So that's why when you look at the data,
you can see each row here is a single set of data and each piece of data is
separated by a comma without space.
So we've seen how we can open files, read files, write
to files. As a challenge,
I want you to go ahead and open up this weather_data.csv file inside your
main.py and add each line of data into a list which we'll call data.
Pause the video and give that a go.
Okay.
All right. So we know that we're going to need to open the file.
So it's stored inside the same folder as our day-25.
So we can just use a relative file path to tap into this weather_data.csv.
And we're going to save this data as a data_file.
And then we're going to get the data by reading this data file.
So data = data_file.read.
And not only are we going to read it, we're going to use readlines
which we know will take each line in this file and turn it into an item in a
list. Now, if I go ahead and print my data,
then you can see I've got this list now where each item is a row in that list.
But as you can imagine, it would be pretty painful to work with the data,
which is all in a string format.
And they are still separated by commas.
It would take a lot of cleaning to actually be able to extract each column and
each row. So what can we do instead? Well,
there's actually a inbuilt library that helps us with CSVs because Python is a
language that's used really heavily for data processing, data analysis.
There's a lot of great tools for working with tabula data,
like our weather data. First, we're going to import the CSV library,
and then we're going to, again, open up a file,
weather_data.csv as our data file,
and then we're going to use this CSV library.
And it has a method called reader,
which takes the file in question, which has already been opened
so this is going to be all data_file, and it can read it an output
the data.
So now let's go ahead and print this data and let's see what we've got.
You can see that it's created a CSV reader
object. This object can be looped through.
So if we wanted to get each row inside this data,
we can say for row in data,
go ahead and print each row. And once you've done that,
you can see it's taken each of the rows inside our weather_data.csv,
and separated out each item into a single value.
So for example, on the Monday row,
we've got the Monday as a string,
we've got the temperature as a string and also the condition as a string.
So now it's much easier for us to work with this data.
Using what you know about Python lists
I want you to create a new list called temperatures,
and this list is going to contain all of the temperatures that is inside this
weather_data.csv, like this 12 degrees, 14, 15,
and it's going to be in the format of an integer.
I don't want to see it as a string with quotation marks around.
It should be a pure number so that we can work with it more easily.
So this is your challenge.
Pause the video and see if you can extract all of the temperatures from this
file into this new list.
Okay.
All right. So when we printed out each of the rows,
we can see that we've created several lists where each list contains an entire
row of data from our weather data CSV.
If we wanted to get the temperature,
then it's going to be the item at index one in that list. For example,
if we wanted to get the Monday temperature,
then all we have to do is to tap into each of these rows and get the item at
index 1. If I go ahead and print this,
then you can see we get all of the temperatures,
but also the label for that column.
So if we want to exclude that label,
then all we have to do is use an if statement and check if row at index one
does not equal temp, which is the name of that column label,
then we're going to tap into our list of temperatures and append this row at
index one, which is going to be a temperature number.
So now after we've done the entire for loop,
then we can print out our list of temperatures. And if you take a look,
you can see we've now got a list of all the temperatures
excluding that column title, but they are all in the format of strings.
So if we want to convert that into an integer,
then all we have to do is wrap that around an int.
So that's the goal of the challenge. Now you can of course,
separate out this line into many more lines,
but I think this should make enough sense for you at this stage. While CSV is the
inbuilt CSV reading and writing library,
notice how much faff was involved in just simply getting a single column of
data. What are we going to do if we have more data,
more complex data with way more columns, way more rows and
we want to do more interesting things with it?
This is going to be quite painful to work with.
This is the point where we want to get the help of some pandas.
Not these kinds of pandas. As cute as they are
they're not going to help us with our data analysis.
But instead, I'm talking about the Pandas library and this is a Python data
analysis library
which is super helpful and super powerful to perform data analysis on tabula
data like the one that we have. In order to work with it,
we have to import this library. But because it's not in built,
you'll need to install it into your project.
So the shortcut way of this is simply just a type import pandas
and then once you see the red line,
go ahead and hover over it and then click install package pandas,
and then you can watch the progress down here. Now, while that's installing,
I want to quickly introduce you to the documentation for this library.
It's really well documented and it's really powerful,
so it has a lot of things in the documentation. If you head over
to pandas.pydata.org and then click on documentation,
then you will be able to see all the things that you can do with it.
So there's a API reference,
there's a quick getting started guide as well as a user guide on the key
concepts of pandas. When you're using a new library of any sort, a good idea is
to take a look at their getting started guide if they have one,
because it tells you how you can install it and a number of questions that you
might have, for example,
what kind of data does pandas handle or how can I read and write tabula data.
And it's actually done really, really well. So if you have a moment,
take a quick look at this page. And once you head back to PyCharm,
your packages should have installed successfully. Now,
once we've installed our pandas,
you'll see that it's still grey because we're not using it yet.
If we want to use pandas, all we have to do is say pandas.
and in our case, we actually want to read our CSV.
So we can say read_csv
and inside this method, you can do lots and lots of things,
as you can see by all of the attribute names. But most of these are optional.
The only one that is not optional is the path that leads to the CSV file.
So if we get hold of our weather_data.csv,
then we can read that CSV using pandas.
So notice how we don't have to open the file as a data file,
or you use a CSV reader, it's one step and you're done.
So now we've got hold of our data and if I print out the data,
you can see how beautifully formatted it is.
It's being printed out as an actual table,
it's got the column headings on top of each of the columns and each of the rows
gets given an index so that we can more easily identify how many records we have
and where each one is.
If we wanted to think about that previous task that we tried to do
where we just try to get hold of a single column of data from this table,
then using pandas,
it is literally as easy as saying data and then square brackets,
and then the name of that column. So in our case, it's temp.
And now if I go ahead and print this out,
you can see it's basically already identified the column and it's printed out
all of the data in that column.
So the really smart thing that Panda's doing here is
it takes that first row to be the names of each column
and it automatically knows how to find the data
when you just specify the name of the column like this.
So three lines versus eight lines,
and we get better formatting. It's no wonder that most Python developers,
as soon as they encounter a CSV fault,
they will start using pandas to work with it
no matter how simple the task or project.
So that was a quick introduction to CSV data,
working with CSV data and how to get started using pandas. In the next lesson,
we're going to dive deeper into this library and see all of the common things that
we can do with pandas.
In the last lesson we got started using pandas.
We installed the library and we imported it to read a CSV file.
And then we use that file to get hold of a column
which has been automatically identified as soon as it read this data CSV.
So what exactly are we dealing with here? Well,
one of the most useful things I find is to do type checks on any of the objects
that I'm working with from a new novel library. For example,
we can use the type method to check
what exactly is the data type of this data that we're getting back from pandas.
So if I go ahead and print this one and comment out the second line,
then you can see what we're getting is what's called a pandas data frame
object. In the package overview
they talk about the two primary data structures of pandas: series and a data
frame.
A data frame is kind of the equivalent of your whole table here.
So every single sheet inside an Excel file or inside a Google sheet file would
be considered a data frame in pandas.
Now what about the second part here where we've gotten hold of one of the
columns in our data frame.
If I do a type check on this object and I hit run,
then you can see this is a pandas series
object. The series is the other super important concept in pandas.
And the series is basically equivalent to a list. It's kind of like a single
column in your table.
So the temperature column would be a series,
the condition column would be a series and the day column would also be a
series. So once you've
grasped this idea that the whole table is basically a data frame in pandas and
every single column is a series kind of like a list in pandas,
then you're pretty much half of the way there to understanding how this library
works. Now, if we go over to the API reference,
you can see that this is basically a list of all of the things that you can do
with pandas. And it is a long list of things,
but let's take a look at those two core classes,
the data frame and the series. So if you go to the data frame,
you can see that it has things on how to construct a new data frame,
how to get hold of the index,
how to get hold of the column labels and this whole bunch of attributes that you
can tap into as well as many methods. For example,
if we take a look at this section on serialization IO conversion,
you can see that you can actually convert a data frame to various different file
types. You can convert it to an Excel file, you can convert it to HTML,
you can also convert it to a dictionary. So if you click on this,
this takes us to actual documentation on how you would use this method.
And if you look at the basic Python documentation versus Panda's documentation,
you'll see why this is so much better.
It lists out all of the possible parameters,
it gives you examples on how you can use each of the methods,
and it's also got some related methods that it thinks that you might want to
take a look at. So let's use this method
and what we're going to do is I'm going to get my data and I'm going to call to_
dict, which is going to convert it into a dictionary.
So it let's call that data_dict equals data.to_dict.
And then if we print out our new data dictionary,
you can see that pandas has taken our table and taken each column of the table
to create a separate dictionary for each of the columns.
So we've got day, temperature and condition,
and we can now work with this as if it were a real dictionary.
Now,
if we take a look at the series data type and you take a look at the conversion
section for this type of data,
then you can see that you can actually convert each of the series to a list
if you want to be able to work with it just as you would with any other list.
So we saw that we can get our data and then get the temperature column.
And this, when we printed out the type, was a series.
So we can get this series and then a call to_list,
and this will turn this data series into a Python list.
So let's call that temp_list and let's go ahead and print it out.
Okay.
It would be a list of all the temperatures
and this is now converted into the raw Python data type.
So we can do all of the things that we can do to a Python list
like for example, we could check its length.
So here comes another challenge for you. Given what we've spoken about so far,
can you figure out if you can work out the average temperature in our column of
temperatures? So remember you can always Google
if you don't remember how to calculate the average of something.
So pause the video and give that a go.
Yeah,
All right.
So we know that we can get a list of all of the temperatures in that list,
and we know that Python has a built-in method called sum,
so then we can get the sum of all of the temperatures in our list of
temperatures
and then we can divide it by the length of the temp_list.
The sum of all the values divided by the number of values
gives us the average, which is also known as the mean,
and so if we print this out,
then you can see the average temperature over the week was 17.4. Now an
alternative way of solving this challenge is maybe you took a look through this
list of methods and you might have come across some of the computations and
statistics that you can do with your series in pandas. Now,
one of those methods is the mean.
So you can actually get rid of all of this excess work and take our data series,
which has basically the column of data under the heading temp, and simply call
.mean on it. And now if I print this out,
you'll see it's the same result as before
without a lot of the extra work.
In addition to the mean you can get other things like the median or the mode and
a whole bunch of other things just by calling the right method on the data
series. So here's a challenge for you.
I want you to get hold of the maximum value from this column of temperatures
by using one of the data series methods. Pause the video,
have a look of the documentation and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right, to get the maximum value
we're probably going to need this max method.
So we call this method in the same way as we did before
which is get hold of the data series,
so our entire table is stored in data.
And then we can get the column under the heading temperature, so this is now a
data series, and then we can call that method max on it.
And if we print it out,
then you can see what we're getting is 24.
So the highest temperature was 24.
So you've seen that when we're working with pandas,
it's really easy to get hold of data in a particular column.
All we have to do is just take the data frame,
use a set of square brackets and then specify the name of the column,
which it takes by default as the first row of the data.
So the day column, the temp, the condition.
So if I wanted to get hold of all of the conditions,
then I would say data condition.
And if I go ahead and print this out,
you can see it gets hold of all of the weather conditions and select that column
to print out.
Now an alternative way to using the square bracket notation
where you have to be careful about the string you use here. It has the match
the name of the column, exactly.
Another way that you can work with the columns is simply by calling data.
condition. And the fact that this code is valid at all
means that pandas, behind the scenes, has taken each of these columns and each
of the headings and converted those headings into attributes.
So we can say data.condition or data.day. And if I print that out,
you can see it's actually going to be exactly the same as doing it like this.
So it's up to you which method you want to use to select the columns,
but be aware that if your column name has a capital 'C'
for example here, then your key has to be a capital C
and also your attribute has to be a capital C. So effectively when your using a
data frame like this,
it's almost like you're treating it as a dictionary and you are pulling out each
column by the key. Now, when you're using the data frame like this,
then you're kind of treating it more like an object.
You were saying data.attribute and you get a hold of the data in that
column.
So I'm going to restore everything to lowercase because I find it easier to read
the code. But the next thing I want to show you is a little bit harder,
which is how do you get data, which are in the rows of our data frame.
If I wanted to get hold of the entire row of data for where the day is equal to
Monday, then the way that I would do that in pandas is firstly,
get a hold of my entire data table. And then inside of that data table,
get a hold of the column that I want to search through.
So I'm going to search through the day column, so I can use data.day or data
[day]. Both will work the same.
But once I've got the column, then I can say, well,
we're inside that column
I want to check for the row where the value is equal to Monday.
This is basically gonna return my row that I want.
So I'm going to print this out and I'm going to comment out all of the previous
code other than the place where we created our data frame,
and then I'm going to run my code. And you can see it's pulled out that correct
row were the day is equal to Monday,
and it's given me all of the rest of the data for that row.
So here's a challenge for you.
Can you figure out how to pull out the row of data from our weather data
where the temperature was at the maximum?
So which row of data had the highest temperature in the week.
Pause the video and give that a go.
So we know that we can get the maximum temperature in the temperature column
just by using this code.
Now you can either use this method where you say data["temp"]
or you can use the attribute .temp, which is the code that I prefer.
I don't like writing a lot of strings if I can avoid it. In this case,
we're checking to see which row inside our column of temperatures is equal to
the maximum temperature.
We would say data.temp == data.temp.max.
And then we're going to get our data and access the row that fits that criteria.
Now, if I print out this row then you can see
it was the row for Sunday where the temperature was 24
and the condition was sunny. Essentially when we get our data frame and then we
use some square brackets, and inside those square brackets
if we only put the name of our column, day, temp, or condition,
then we would get the entire column.
But if we fill to that column by a condition say when a particular column is
equal to a particular value, then we actually get hold of the row instead.
Now, once you've gotten hold of the data in the row,
you can actually go one step further because we know that the row contains lots
of data, right? What if we wanted that particular row's
temperature or that particular row;s condition? Well,
let's say that we create a variable called monday
which is equal to our data frame and then searching through that data frame
where the data.day is equal to Monday.
So now with this row, Monday,
we can then tap into the values under different columns by using the same kind
of way that we got data in the entire column over here.
So we can say monday.condition
and if I print this out and just comment these other bits,
Right,
then you can see that I get the actual condition for that particular day,
which happens to be sunny. Now here's a challenge.
I want you to get Monday's temperature,
but because my temperatures are in Celsius,
I want you to convert it into Fahrenheit.
So pause the video and see if you can complete that challenge.
Oh
All right.
We know we can get hold of Monday's temperature by saying monday.
and then the name of that column in the row
which happens to be temp temp. Now,
once we've got that temperature
we can convert it into a normal integer by wrapping the int around that value.
And then if we want to convert Celsius to Fahrenheit,
all we have to do is to multiply the Celsius by 9/5 and then add 32.
So it will be monday_temp multiplied by 9/5
and then add 32.
Right.
So monday_temp_F and then we can print this value out.
Right?
So now when I run it, we get 53.6.
And if I put Monday's temperature 12 into this Google converter,
I get the same value, 53.6.
Now the final thing I want to show you is how you create a data frame from scratch.
So in our case, we created our data frame by reading from our CSV file.
But what if you wanted to create a data frame just from some data that you're
generating in Python? Let's say that I have this dictionary of values
I've got some students and these are their names held on a list.
And then each of them has a score and the scores correspond to the student.
So 76 is Amy's score,
James scored 56 and Angela scored 65. Now,
how would we create a data frame from this dictionary?
It's really simple.
We call our pandas library and we get hold of the data frame class.
And then we initialize that class with some data.
And the data in our case is just going to be our data dictionary.
And now if I go ahead and save this as our data,
so I'm gonna comment out what we had previously and then print out this data.
Then you can see I've now created a table using the values from that dictionary.
Now we can go even further than this. When we've created a data frame,
we can actually get that data frame to be converted to a CSV file.
And this to_csv method takes only one required input
which is the path that you want to save this file.
So let's just create a new file, um,
which we'll call new_data.csv
and when I run this code, then watch over here
you see a new CSV file of being created from thin air
and all of our data has been added to that CSV file.
So we're just getting a glimpse into how powerful this Panda library can be
and we're only really using it to read CSV data and write CSV data
which is a common format that you'll see being manipulated using Python. In later
lessons we're going to dive deeper into data analysis
and we're going to be looking not only at pandas,
but we're also going to be looking at NumPy, Matplotlib, and other libraries that make
it easier for us to work with large chunks of data. In the next lesson,
we're going to be what we've learned to use by analyzing some squirrel
data from central park. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now that you've learned how to do the basics of data analysis with pandas,
it's time to put your knowledge to the test.
And we're going to be working with a really interesting data set. Back in 2018/
2019, a bunch of volunteers went into New York  central park
and they basically combed the entire park to find all of the squirrels.
So this resulted in a huge dataset of squirrels, squirrel numbers,
squirrel fur color and a whole bunch of other things.
And all of this data can be found on the New York city open data website
which we'll link to in the course resources. When you head over here,
you can take a look at all of the data that they collected.
If you take a look at all of the columns in this dataset and click show
all, you can see they've logged the location of each of the squirrels,
they gave each squirrel a unique ID,
they evaluated whether if the squirrel was an adult or a juvenile,
and they looked at what the primary fur color was. So it could be gray, cinnamon
which is red, or black. Now, if you scroll down
there's actually a really interesting visualization of this data,
where they've plotted all of this squirrels
onto a map of central park.
So you can take a look at the distribution of the squirrel population in central
park.
So you can see where the red squirrels are, where the gray ones are and where the
black ones are. So there's only three colors, really.
So what you're going to do is you're going to go to this website,
click on export and download the CSV data.
Now, once you do that,
you'll end up with a 2018 central park squirrel data like this.
Now you're going to pull that data into your day-25 project folder and click
re-factor to move it in.
And you can see that this is a lot bigger than what ever data we had before.
There's thousands of entries,
and it's actually real dedication that these volunteers went around
logging all of this data, observing all the squirrels.
It must've been a very tedious task.
But now that somebody else has carried out the hard part,
we can do some data analysis on that data.
So I want you to comment out everything that you've got so far in your day-25
project
and the goal is for you to use that data and use what you've learned about
pandas
to be able to create a CSV that's called squirrel_count that has a small table
which just contains the fur color, so there's only three fur colors,
and they are logged under the primary fur color column.
And it can either basically be gray, cinnamon
which is red, or black.
There's only three possible values in that column. Now,
what you're going to do is you are going to figure out how many gray squirrels
there are in total,
how many cinnamon ones and how many black ones based on that primary fur color
column.
And then you're gonna take that data and build a new data frame from it,
and using that,
create this final CSV using pandas. Now that you know what you need to do,
have a think about the problem and see if you can complete this challenge.
Pause the video now. All right.
If you've commented out the line where you've imported pandas,
then you'll obviously have to do that again.
So let's think about what we want to do. We want to isolate the column
which is the primary fur color. And if it helps you,
you can actually better visualize the data on this website where they've got a
table preview. So you can see that here is the primary fur color,
and you can see the colors that have been logged.
So our goal is to somehow get hold of this data series
which contains this entire column, figure out how many of them are gray,
how many of them are black and how many are cinnamon. How do we do this?
Well, firstly, let's get hold of our data.
So we're going to use our pandas.read_csv method.
And then we're going to direct it towards this 2018 central parks squirrel census
data. Now, if you want,
you can actually right-click refactor and rename it to something a little bit
shorter. But because I know that PyCharm will actually fill this in for me
as long as I start out with a string
and that that file is in the same folder,
it'll actually type it all out if I just hit enter, then it doesn't really matter.
But of course,
make sure that you don't have any typos in here if you're typing it out,
because otherwise when you hit run, you're going to get a whole bunch of error
text inside your console.
So once I've successfully read that CSV,
I've now got a dataframe. From that data frame,
I can get hold of the column that I'm interested in
which is called primary fur color. Now,
because it's got spaces, it's easier to access that data by using a square
bracket and then putting in the name of that column like this.
This is one of the methods that we showed you. Now,
once I've gotten hold of that column, well
the next thing I need to do is to find all of the rows in that column
where the data is equal to each of the colors.
So there was the color which is gray,
so gray not 'ey'.
And then once we've got hold of all the gray squirrels,
then we're going to pull that out from our data.
So now we should have a bunch of gray squirrels,
and it's probably a good idea to print them out
just to see if that actually worked.
And because I expect there'll be lots of rows with gray squirrels,
it makes sense to make it a plural, grey_squirrels. So now if I hit run,
you can see listed here are all of the rows where it contains a gray squirrel.
Now it redacted this table
so that it can actually display it in the console because we know that there's many,
many columns and there's many, many rows.
It's just showing you the first few rows and then the last few rows and also the
first few columns and the last few columns.
So we can be pretty sure that we've managed to get hold of all of the rows that
contain gray squirrels as their primary fur color. Now,
what if we wanted to know the gray squirrels count? Well,
we could use our length method because remember, once we get hold of the rows
it kind of gets treated a bit like a iterable,
like a list, and can use methods like length on this data.
So now if we print grey_squirrels_count,
you can see that we've got a total of 2,473 grey squirrels.
So now all I need to do is to repeat this process for the other colored
squirrels. So I'm going to call it a red squirrel, even though theoretically,
their fur color is cinnamon.
So I'm just going to copy and paste that in there in case I make any typos and
the final squirrel is the black squirrel.
So those are all three squirrel types,
and if I go ahead and print out all of these,
so the reds squirrel count, the black squirrel count and the gray squirrel count,
you can see that you got mostly grey squirrels, a few red ones and very
rarely do you actually see a black squirrel.
I certainly haven't seen one recently. Now that we've got our three values,
it's time to construct our data frame. So to construct our data frame,
the easiest way is to actually just create a dictionary.
So I'm going to create a data dictionary and this dictionary is going to have
two key-value pairs.
So the first key is going to be the fur color
and this is going to contain the three fur colors, which is, um,
gray, cinnamon or red, and black.
And then, um,
the next key value pair is going to be the count.
So now we can create a list where the first value is going to be the gray squirrel
count, next is going to be the red squirrel count and finally,
it's going to be the black squirrel count. So now that we've got our dictionary
and this is what it looks like,
then we can go ahead and actually turn this into a data frame.
So to do that,
we need to get hold of the pandas and then get hold of the data frame class,
and then initialize it using this data dictionary.
So I'm going to save that as df, df for data frame.
And then the final thing I need to do is to get my df
to convert to a CSV.
So now I get to specify the name of the file,
which I will call squirrel_count.csv
and once I hit run, you'll see that new file show up right here
and you can see that it's constructed my new CSV file with all of the data that
I've extracted from my central park squirrel census
and I've now got a new table with the data that I'm interested in.
So did you manage to complete this challenge? If you found it tricky
working with the data frames and figuring out how to get hold of the columns or
how to get hold of the rows depending on the conditions we're interested
in, then I strongly recommend to just head back the last lesson,
just try to write out the code that we're doing in each step of the video
yourself,
just to make sure that you're a hundred percent sure with what's going on.
Once you are ready, head of the next lesson
we're going to finally build our US states game.
For all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right. It's time to put some of the stuff that we've learned into practice.
And the product that we're trying to build towards is a US states quiz.
One of my favorite websites for quizzes is a website called Sporcle.
And they specialize in quizzes that are basically just you making a list.
And one of the best quizzes they have is the list of US
states. You can head over to this link in the course resources,
and you can start playing this game. They're presuming that there's 50 States in the
US and every single time you type in the name of a state,
then that state gets labelled and you score one point.
The goal is to be able to name as many states as you can remember.
This is basically the game that we're trying to replicate using turtle and using
some CSV data. And this is what the end result looks like.
We've got a turtle screen
which has a background that is an image of the US with all of the states
blanked out.
And what we're going to do is by looking at the shape of the map
and by remembering what the states look like,
try to name as many as we can.
And once we've entered the name and we hit OK, then if it actually exists,
it gets added to the map. It seems simple,
but the code is going to need some of the new things we learn about using data,
especially data from CSVs. Now,
the first thing I want you to do is the head over to the link in the course
resources that takes you to the starting file for the US states game.
Now, once you're here, you're going to fork your own copy of this project
and then you're going to click on these three dots at the top,
and then download this entire project as a zip file.
Remember that you won't see this until you forked the project,
and also if you're not logged in, then when you fork it,
it's going to give you a random name,
which means that when you download it as a zip,
you will have to rename that zip file to us-states-game so that your project can
have the correct name.
So the easiest way, as always, is to just log in, fork a copy of the project and
then download it as a zip file. Once you've done that,
then you can open it up inside PyCharm.
And you can see that there's three files here.
One is called 50_states.csv,
and this is a CSV file that contains all 50 States in the US by name and then
some X and Y value, which we'll talk about a little bit later on.
The next thing you'll see is a blank_states_image.gif. Now,
the reason why it's a .gif rather than a .png or .jpg is actually because
turtle only works with this one image format.
So in order to display an image, we actually need to convert the image to
a gif file, which I have done already.
This file is just an image of all the States of the US blanked out,
so it doesn't have the names. So it's ready for our user to start guessing.
Finally, you'll have a empty
main.py file and this is where we're going to get started.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to import turtle,
so straight-up import the module. And then I'm going to create a screen object
from turtle.Screen class. Now,
once I've got my screen,
then I'm going to change the title of the project to the
U.S. States Game.
And finally, I'm going to get my screen to only exit on click.
This is pretty basic, we've done this lots of times.
But the next thing that we're going to do is a little bit new because we haven't
actually worked with images in turtle before.
One of the things that you can do with turtle is that you can set the turtle's
shape to a new shape. So,
you can set it to a circle or you can set it to a square, et cetera.
But you can actually load in a new image as a new shape.
And the way you do that is you get hold of your screen object and you say add
shape and this shape can be any image file.
So in our case, it's going to be the name of this file.
So I'm going to create a new variable called the image and it's going to store
the file name or the file path of my blank
_states_img.gif.
So this is basically the path to reach my image and that is the shape that I'm
going to load into my screen.
So once I've added the shape to the screen,
then it's now available to be used by a turtle.
So I can say turtle.shape and change it instead of to circle or square or
turtle, I'm going to change it to this image file.
So now when I run my project,
you might like, I have here, get a error like this;
couldn't open this file because there is no such file or directory.
This is really, really common and it might happen to you. In this case,
just be sure that whatever it is that you've typed here actually matches the
name of your image. So as you can see,
it's actually blank_states_img.gif,
and I've only got state without the 's'. So now when we run this again
there should be no problems and I can see
the image show up here. Now that we've managed to load up our image onto our
turtle game,
the next thing we want to do is to figure out the coordinates of each of these
states. For example,
if we wanted the word California to show up over here,
then we need to know what is the X and Y coordinate of this location relative to
the entire game screen.
That way when we actually guess a state like California and hit OK,
it can actually show up with the text to be written on that state itself so that
the user knows which states they've guessed and which ones that they still need
to guess.
But how would you
place the texts on a particular point of the map?
How would you get the coordinates for this point? Well,
after a quick search on Google,
I find a Stack Overflow question that basically is trying to do exactly what we
want. So this is the code that we would need.
So let's go ahead and copy all of it and paste it into our project.
Let's take a look through this code and understand what it's trying to do.
So firstly, we've got a function here called get_mouse_click_coor,
and it takes two values as inputs, X and Y,
and then it prints those out. Next,
we've got our turtle module calling onscreenclick,
which is a event listener.
So it's gonna listen for when the mouse clicks and then it's going to call our
get get_mouse_click_coor function,
and it's going to pass over the X and Y coordinates of that click location.
Finally, we've got this turtle.mainloop.
So this is an alternative way of keeping our screen open
even though our code has finished running.
So it's basically an alternative to our screen.exitonclick. And in fact
if you think about it,
if we wanted to get the click location and our screen exits
as soon as we click on it, then it's not really gonna work very easily.
So we're going to delete this line and we're going to replace it with this
turtle.mainloop, which is going to keep our screen open.
So if I comment out all of this previous code and when I run my project,
you can see it's still keeps the window open. But without it,
it's just going to flash up and disappear.
While this code is running if I click on one of the states,
let's say where California is,
you can see the X and Y values being printed in the console.
So we can repeat this for all of the States on this image and get hold of where
each state lies on this map relative to our turtle screen.
Now, if that sounds really tedious then I have to tell you, it really is.
But lucky for you,
I've actually gone through this entire process and I've logged all of the X and
Y values. Now some of them may be a little bit off the center of the state,
but you know, you can always tweak this if you want to.
But now you know where all of these X and Y values are coming from.
So you don't actually need any of this code because we already have all of the X
and Y values in our 50_states.csv.
All you have to do is to read from that CSV and get those X and Y values.
And then you're going to ask the user for a answer and we're going to do that
through the use of a input.
Remember we can call screen.textinput to create one of those popup boxes
and we can give it a title and we can also give it a prompt.
So when I run this, you can see that this popup box looks like this.
The title is at the top of the window and the prompt is inside the box.
Okay.
And once we type something in here like Ohio,
then I can actually get hold of what the user typed by tapping into this answer_
state. So if I go ahead and print it,
then you can see it will be whatever it is I type into this box.
So now, you know
what is the X and Y value of the location that we need to write our text for the
name of the state that the user has guessed correctly.
You also know how to get the user to enter a new answer through our text inputs.
So in the next lesson,
the challenge begins and you're going to use everything you've learned so far in
order to read from the CSV file and get the game to work.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
All right.
So in the last lesson we did a lot of setup and we got our game to have the
basic features.
It's got a popup that asks us for a states' name,
and when I type a name in here, I can receive it inside my code
using this answer_state.
Now your job is to use that 50_states.csv
to
check the user's answer against all of the states inside this table and see if
it matches one of them. Now,
the user might spell it with a capital to begin with say, Ohio,
or they might just write ohio and it should work for both of these cases.
In addition,
when the user types in a state that is inside that 50_states.csv,
then that state should be written onto the screen at the location where it
exists.
So it remember the location corresponds to the X and Y values that we already
logged inside this data file.
But if the user guesses a state that's wrong,
then nothing happens and our input box appears again
asking for a new input.
Now notice how here in the title of the text input
I'm also keeping track of how many states they have guessed correctly out of 50.
And every time they add a new, um,
new state, then that number updates.
his is going to rely on the knowledge that you've learned about reading from
CSV data,
getting hold of the specific parts of the CSV data,
finding for example, a particular row or a particular column,
and working with that data in order to check to see if the user got the state
right,
and then using the data inside that row to figure out where to write some text
at which X and Y location
so that we can get the actual name of the state written at the location where
they appear on the map. So this is quite a challenge
and I expect that you'll have to think about it and play around with the code
for at least 10 to 20 minutes. So give it the time that it needs,
have a think about how you would break down this problem and try and complete
this challenge. So pause the video now.
Okay.
All right. So I'm going to walk through the solution with you,
but I want you to do a conscience check.
If you haven't spent at least 20 minutes working on this problem, fixing it,
getting it to do what you want it to do, then go back, try again.
You need to feel the struggle in order to learn.
I can tell you how to do anything, but if that answer didn't come from you,
then you're not actually going to make progress. So I really,
really urge you to give it a go before you watch the solution. All right.
So back to our code, the first thing I'm going to do is
I'm going to import the pandas module.
So I'm going to import pandas.
Now I've already installed pandas on the starting project that you downloaded,
but if you're doing this completely from scratch from your own starting file,
then you'll probably get a red squiggly line under the pandas
and it will ask you to install the package. But if you don't have it,
then it means it's already installed and ready to use.
Now we're going to get our pandas to go ahead and read our CSV file, and the
CSV file is called the 50_states.csv.
So once the prompt comes up,
then I'm going to hit enter to get PyCharm to just insert it automatically.
Now I'm going to save that data frame that comes from reading that CSV to a
variable called data.
Now our data has 50 rows of data and the first row is the column headings
for each of them. So we've got the state, the X and the Y values.
Let's have a think about how we might break down this problem that we have.
So when the user types an answer,
we have to check to see if that, um,
answer_state is one of the states in all the states of the 50_states.csv.
The first column is a list of all 50 States.
So if we could somehow check to see if this state that they've guessed is one of
the states in that column, then we know whether if they got it right or wrong.
If they got it right,
then we need to figure out how we can create a turtle to write
the name of the state at the state's X and Y coordinate.
For example, if the user guessed
South Carolina and indeed South Carolina is one of the 50 States,
then we should be able to pull out this entire row and then create a turtle,
make it go to this X and Y location,
and to write the name of the state onto this blank state image in our turtle
game. Let's see if we can tackle this. Now,
the first thing we need to figure out is how do we get hold of all the states of
the 50_states.csv? So we've got our data frame
and if I go ahead and say data, then I can pull out one of the columns.
So the column name is state,
and I can either use that as a key with a set of square brackets,
or I can use it as simply a attribute name.
This gets me the data series which is that first column.
And if I want to be able to turn that into a list,
remember that we saw that method to_list,
and that means we can work with it just like any other list.
So let's call this all_states.
And once we've got whole of this all_states, well,
we can check to see if the answer_state is in the all_states.
This is something that you won't be able to do,
so checking for membership using the in keyword
unless you have converted this into a list.
So once we've figured out that this answer of the user provided is in fact,
one of the states in our 50 States,
then the next thing we need to do is to create a turtle.
So let's create a new turtle, which we'll call t,
and we're going to use the turtle.Turtle class to construct it.
And then we're going to get the turtle to hide the actual turtle shape,
and we're also going to get it to pen up so that it doesn't actually do any
drawing.
But what we do need it to do is we needed to go to a particular X and Y
location.
The X and Y location is going to correspond to the state that the user has
correctly guessed and the row of data from our 50_states.csv.
So how can we get hold of the actual row of data that corresponds to this state?
Well, we can take our data and then inside some square brackets,
we can check that the data.state is double equal to the answer_state.
This is going to pull out the row where the state is equal to the answer_state.
So I'm going to save that under something called state_data.
And now I can tell my turtle to go to state_data.x and state_data.y.
So, because this is a row of data,
then I can tap into it's attributes using the name of the columns,
the X and the Y.
And once my turtle gets there,
then I want it to write the name of the state.
So it's going to be state_data.state. Now,
when we hit run on this code and guess the name of a state that definitely
exists, when we click OK, we're going to get an error.
And it's really important that you get used to seeing errors
because they're going to happen to you all the time. Just as in life
the only certainties are death and taxes, in Programming the only certainty
is you will get bugs and you will get errors.
The important thing is to figure out what's causing the error.
So if we go ahead and copy this error at the end, bad screen distance,
that seems to be telling us what is actually going on.
And then I go into Google and I search for this particular error,
then I can see other people who've encountered this issue.
So if we read through all of this, between all of the subtext,
it tells us that the issue is actually that our coordinates are stored as
strings. We need to get the coordinates into actual numbers.
So the one oversight that you might've made which is really common
is to simply tell it to go to date state_data.x,
state_data.y without first converting them into integers.
So now if we bring back our screen.exitonclick and then run our code,
we can type the name of the state click OK,
and you can see the state data show up on the location that corresponds to that
particular state. Now,
the only problem is we don't want all of this junk to be written here, right?
And this is showing up because we're getting this data from our data series.
So what's a much simpler way? Well,
we've already got hold of the answer that the user typed, right?
So why don't we just write the answer_state?
So now when I type in the state and it matches one of the states in the 50
states,
then it's going to go to the X and Y location of that state and print the name
of the state that the user has typed in.
And because we've made sure that it's a correct state with a correct spelling,
then it doesn't actually matter if we use the answer_state
or if we use the state_data. Now,
if you really want to use state_data instead of answer_state
because say you're writing a different program and you need this functionality,
then you can actually tap into state_data.state,
which will get us the state name from the row corresponding to the matching
state. And then we can use a method called item.
Now, item is a method on the pandas series.
So we know that this is a Panda data series
and you can do a type check on that if you want to confirm.
But what the item does is it looks into the underlying data and it basically
just grabs the first element. So now, if I run the game
as it is and I type in the name of a state,
you can see it fetches the actual value under state_data.state without any
of the index, the zero or any of the other parts of the data series.
So I just wanted to show you that you can actually get a row of data from a data
frame and then get a particular value from that row,
and get the actual raw value from that. But personally, in this line of code,
I prefer using the answer_state because we know it's already been title cased, its
already formatted correctly
and it just makes the code look a bit cleaner and it's easier to understand.
So I'm going to stick with this. So now that it's working,
all we need to do is to get this
to repeat itself every single time the user makes a new guess.
That means we're probably going to have to put it inside some sort of while loop,
what should be our while condition? Well,
we know that the user is going to guess all of the states. And once they've
guessed all of them, then they win, right?
So why don't we create a list of guessed states and set that to equal a empty
list.
And we can check while the length of the guessed_states is less than 50,
then we can continue rerunning all of this code,
getting them to put a new input, checking the input and writing the state name.
But every time the user guesses a state correctly,
then we're going to add this answer_states to the guessed_state.
So we can say guessed_states.append,
and then we're going to append this new answer_state.
So now when I run this code again, then you can see that every time
I guess a new state, this text input pops up again
and I can basically just keep going until I've named all the states.
Now, the next thing I want to change is the title of this text input window.
Instead of saying Guess the state,
I want it to keep track of the number of states I've guessed correctly.
So I basically want to say something like zero or 10 or whatever, out of 50
states correct.
This zero is going to be replaced by a f-string
and we're going to use the length of our guessed_states in order to get that
number. So now when I run this code, you can see that
I start out with zero states, 0/50, and every time I guess
a new state, then it adds to that count
so I can keep track of how many I have guessed and how many I've got left.
Now,
the next thing you'll realize if you test this a few times is even if you get a
state right
but if you actually didn't spell it with a capital C or capital letter to begin
with, then it's not going to accept it. So we don't see 'california' showing up.
And this is because in our state data,
they all have a title case were the first letter is capitalized.
So how can we make sure that our game works
if the user types all lower case or all upper case or title case?
As long as they got the spelling right we should ignore the casing.
So one way of doing this is to take this answer_state
which comes from that text input that the user has entered,
and then at the very end, we can change that to a title case.
So this is a method that's on all strings.
So that means if I start out with a string, which is,
um, angela, and then I say str.title,
then this will give me the same string back
but it will make the first letter capitalized.
This is what we're going to do to the user's answer.
And then we'll be able to check it against all the States.
And now it doesn't matter if the user has typed everything in all caps,
or if they have typed it with all lower case,
or if they've done something really crazy like this,
it will still be accepted.
So we've now got most of
the functionality of our game. In the next lesson,
we're going to figure out how we can get this game to become more of an
educational tool and for it to create a final CSV
when we're ready to exit the game
that's going to tell us all the states that we missed so that we can learn them,
so that we can come back to the game with more knowledge. For all of that and
more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
So we've now got pretty much all the functionality that we want in order for
this to function as a game.
But if we want to be able to use this as a learning tool,
then it would be great for us to be able to have some sort of way of typing an
exit code. Say, if I typed exit,
then I could exit out of the game and then I could get my code to generate a CSV
file that contains all of the states that I missed from all 50 states.
We know that in our while loop we can exit out of it
as long as we use the break statement.
What we can do is we can use an if statement to check
well, if the answer_state was actually equal to the secret code
which is exit, remember that the answer_state is going to be title cased
so we have to check for it with a capital E, and if that happens,
then we're gonna break out of our while loop
which means it's going to end the while loop prematurely,
and we can delete this line so that it actually ends the game
and exits out of the window. So if we test this out,
then you can see we can type our states or we can type exit
and that will exit the game
and we end up with process finished with exit code zero.
This is the moment where we want to generate a new file
and that file is going to be called states_to_learn.csv.
And I want you to generate the CSV
which is going to contain just the names of states
which have not been guessed by the user when they exit the game.
Have a think about how you would achieve this,
pause the video and give that a go.
All right. So let's think about this.
What we want to do is to take the guessed states and compare it against all
states,
and then we want to create a new list of all the missing states.
So let's create a new list called missing_states and then we can use a for loop
to loop through each of the states inside all of the states.
And if we find that a state is not in the guessed_states,
well, then that means it's missing, right?
So then we can tap into our missing states and append this state. And
by the end of this,
we should end up with a list of all of the missing states.
So let's test this code. So I'm just going to type in a few states,
some of the ones beginning with A, so Alaska, um,
Arizona,
Um, uh,
Arkansas,
and what's the last one, Alabama.
Okay. So I think that's all of the states beginning with A,
so now I'm going to hit exit and it's going to give me a list of all the states
that I'm missing. So if we take a look at all the A states,
if we compare it against this list of 50 states, there's no Alabama,
there's no Alaska, and there is no Arkansas because I guessed it correctly.
So this is now just a list of all the ones I didn't manage to get.
So now how can we turn this list into a CSV?
Well,
we can create a new data and that new data is going to be a data frame
which is created from our missing_states.
So this is just going to be a one column data frame.
Once we've created that new data,
then we can go ahead and save it as a CSV.
And we're going to call that states_to_learn.csv,
just as we've typed here. Now,
when I run this code and I've typed
all of the A states, and now I hit exit.
Then you can see we've got a new file
that's just been generated fresh out of the press
and it is our states to learn with all 44 States that I'm missing from my game.
I hope you had fun building this game with me,
and I would love to know how many states you can name the first time you play
this game. Cause obviously the more you play it, the more you get better.
And I hope you'll use this as an educational tool. If you have students,
if you are a geography teacher, if you have kids,
you can get them to play with this awesome program that you've built.
Remember what we've done here can be endlessly customized.
You can make a version for your own country,
or you can make one for the whole world where you have to name each country on
the world map, or you can do some other sort of list,
like name all of the plants on an image or name all of the animals.
The world is really your oyster
and I can't wait to see what you've created using your imagination and how
you've customized the code. So once you've done that,
be sure to post it in the Q/A of this lesson and so that we can all play and
admire your code.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 26 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be learning all about lists and dictionary comprehensions.
This is something that's actually really unique to the Python language,
and it's something that's going to cut down on a lot of the code that we have to
write when we're working with lists and dictionaries.
And by the end of today,
we will build a project to use the NATO phonetic alphabets so that
we can spell out various things on the telephone. For example,
whenever you need to give your name and you have to spell it out,
they might not hear which letter you said.
So normally you'll say something like A
for alpha, n for november, g for golf.
This is what we're aiming to create; a program that works in the console
and it allows us to enter a word. So for example, I just put in my name
which I happen to have to spell on the phone many times and I hit enter,
then it'll return a list of all of the NATO phonetic alphabet that matches each
of the letters in my name
so I can just read it out to the other person over the phone, alpha,
november, golf, echo, Lima, alpha.
And that way I can use this little tool and be able to spell any word I want
easily using the NATO phonetic alphabet.
So I hope you're excited to learn about this big topic of comprehensions, and
once you're ready, head over to the next lesson, and let's get started.
The big topic that we're going to explore today is a concept known as a list
comprehension. And as I mentioned before,
this is something that's really unique to the Python language.
In many other programming languages,
you don't actually have access to something like this.
There's nothing that really compares to it.
And it's something that Python developers really,
really love because it cuts down on the amount of typing and it just makes the
code a lot shorter, and in most cases, a lot easier to read.
So what exactly is a list comprehension? Well, it's a case where you
create
a new list from a previous list. So far we've been doing that using for loops.
So for example, if I have a list of numbers, 1, 2, 3,
and I want to create a new list where each number is increased by one,
well
then I would use a for loop creating a new empty list and then looping through
each of the numbers in that list in order to add one to
each of those numbers.
And then I would append each of those increased numbers to my new list.
And I would end up with a new list that consists of three items,
and it will be 2, 3, and 4. Now using list comprehension
we can take these four lines of code and turn it into one.
And the way that we create a list comprehension looks something like this.
I like to use the keyword method where you type out the list comprehension
keywords,
and then replace each of the words with the actual item in your code.
The way that we would create any list comprehension is we will create the name
of the new list and instead of creating a empty list and then having to append
to it or populate it, we actually going to create it straight in the same line.
So we open up a set of square brackets to denote that we're creating a new list,
and then we have this new _item for item in list
keyword pattern. Here's how it would work.
Let's take that same thing that we did before
where we took you a list of numbers
and we created a new list where each number is increased by one,
and let's see how we would do it using list comprehension.
So the first keyword I'm going to replace is the list.
So this is the list that we're going to iterate through. And in our case,
it's this list of numbers. So let's replace that list
keyword with the actual list, which is numbers.
The next thing that is easy to understand is each item in the list.
So we can call this anything we want. In the for loop here,
we called it n, so why don't we go ahead and call it n again?
This n is going to represent each of the numbers in that list of numbers
just as it does in this for-loop.
And the final keyword that we haven't yet replaced is the new_item.
So what do we want each of the new items to be in this new list?
Well,
each of the new items is basically calculated by taking n and then adding one
to it.
So this line is the expression or the code that we need to execute in order to
get a new_item. So this becomes our final list
comprehension. We have our lists of numbers
and then we create a new list where we loop through each of the numbers, n,
inside this list of numbers
and then for each of the n, we add one to it in order to create the final list.
So when you look at a list comprehension just like this as in the real code,
it can be a little bit confusing to see how would you read it,
which order does it happen.
But when you're using this keyword method that I often use
where you just type out what you need to have inside a list comprehension,
you need a name for the new list, you need a set of square brackets
and then inside the square brackets, you have new_item for item in list.
Then you go through it replacing each of the keywords, list item
and new_item. So I want you to have a go at actually writing out this code.
Go ahead and create a new PyCharm project,
and I want you to go into the Python console.
We're not actually going to be writing code inside our main.py.
And the reason is because the console allows us to write code line by line
and then we can view our variables really easily on the right-hand side pane
here. For example, if I have my list of numbers, 1, 2, 3,
and then I have to write out my list comprehension
where we create our new list which I'll call new_numbers,
and then we have to create our list comprehension.
So the way to remember it is new_item for item in list.
So now go ahead and write this out and see if you can remember how we actually
structure our list comprehension and see if you can get it to work within your
PyCharm console. So pause the video, give that a go.
All right. So our list is of course, this list of numbers.
So let's replace that first.
And then for each of the items in that list of numbers, well,
we can call it anything we want. So I'm just going to call it n or num,
it doesn't matter. But as long as you're consistent in using it
when you create the new item
because each new item is going to be the n,
which is each number in the list, +1.
So now when I hit enter,
you can see I've got this new list called new_numbers created from the previous
list, numbers, and this now has the same number of items
but each item is now increased by one.
Now it's important to remember that when we say list comprehension,
it doesn't strictly mean that you can only work with list.
You can work with other sequences like strings, for example.
So here I've got a variable called name, which is just a string. It's the word
Angela.
And I'm creating a new list by using a list comprehension that has this kind of
code. Now,
I want you to pause for a second and think about what would be in this new list,
what would it look like? And then I want you to try it out inside PyCharm.
So pause the video now. All right.
So name equals Angela, this is the variable that we're working with.
And then I'm going to create a new list
which I'll call letters_list.
This new list is going to be created using my list comprehension.
So it's going to be letter for letter in name. And what this does is it takes
this sequence, this string,
it goes through each of the letters in that string
and then it adds each of the letters into this new list.
So when I hit enter, you can see, this is what letters_list
looks like. It's just split off my string into individual letters
and it's added it into a brand new list.
As I mentioned, these things in Python
like a list or a string or a range or tuple, they're called sequences because
they have a specific order. And when you perform a list comprehension,
it's going to take that sequence and it's going to go through it in order either
be it the letters in the string or the items in a list.
And then it's going to take each of those items in that correct order
and then do something with it, either add one to it, or in this case,
do nothing and just add it to a new list. Here's a challenge for you.
Can you take the range,
which is also a sequence that we can iterate through, and then create a range
between 1 and 5?
And remember that the way that the range works is it's going to take 1 and
then 2, and then 3 and then 4, but it's not going to go up to 5.
I want you to loop through this range and then create a list where each of the
numbers in the range is doubled.
And the final list should look like this. It will be 2, 4, 6,
and 8. Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right. So let's create our new lists
which I'm just going to call range_list.
And we're going to use that keyword pattern to remind ourselves.
So it was going to be new_item for item in list.
And this list, in this case, is actually not going to be a list,
it is going to be a range between 1 and 5.
And then each of the items, we get to give it a name, which I'll just call num.
And then in this new list, what is each new item going to be? Well,
it's going to be num multiplied by 2. So now when I hit enter,
I get my range_list, which is 2, 4, 6, 8.
So its loop through each of the numbers in the range
and its multiplied each of those numbers by 2,
and then its created a new list using each of those numbers.
Now the final thing I want to show you regarding list comprehensions is that
there's also such a thing as a conditional list comprehension.
This takes our keywords a little bit further.
Whereas previously we stopped right here,
new_item for item in list. We can also tag on two more keywords;
if and a test.
What this is going to allow us to do is to only add this new item and only to
perform this code if the test actually passes.
Here's an example. I've got a bunch of names here; Alex, Beth, Caroline,
Dave, Eleanor, and Freddy. Now,
one of the neat things that you can actually do with the Python console is not
only can you view what all of the variables are equal to,
but you can also edit them if you have an issue.
The sharp-eyed amongst you will know that I've actually made a typo in this
name, it's not Elanor, its actually spelled a little bit differently.
So what I can do on the right-hand pane here is I can right-click on that piece
of data that I want to change and then click set value,
and then actually change the data here.
Now that I've got that spelled out correctly, if I type names and hit enter,
you can see it's now been corrected and this is my new list of names.
So using this list of names,
I'm going to try and create a new list of names,
but I only want the short names.
I only want the names which is made up of four letters or less, like Alex or
Beth.
The way I would do this is I would create a new list,
which is called short_names. And then I would use my list comprehension.
And remember, in this case, the keywords are new_item
for item in list. And then if and a test.
So let's fill in the easy parts first.
The list is going to be our list of names, the item I can call it
anything I want. I'll just call it name in terms of the singular form of names.
And then once I loop through each of the names inside my list of names,
what is the new item going to be? Well, it's actually going to be unmodified.
It's just going to be that same name. But in this case,
I'm only going to add that name to the list if it passes this test.
And this test is going to look at the length of the name
which I created here,
so if I named this n then I would be testing it against n and it would be adding
n as well. But because I've called it name
so I'm going to use that name right here in the condition.
So if the length of the name is less than five,
so it has four or less characters,
then I'm going to add that name to my new list. Now, when I hit enter,
you can see that I've got this new list of short names and it only contains the
names, Alex, Beth and Dave.
So this list comprehension is now a little bit more complex because the first
thing it does is it goes through each of the names inside this list of names,
it checks each of those names for its length. And if the length is five,
then it adds the name to this new list.
Now here's a challenge for you.
I want you to take all of the names from this list of names
which are made up of five letters or more, so basically Caroline,
Eleanor and Freddie,
and I want you to turn each of these names to the uppercase version.
What you should end up with is a list where you have CAROLINE in all caps,
ELEANOR in all caps and FREDDIE in all caps.
But of course, you're not going to just type this out,
you're going to use list comprehension.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right. I'm going to call this new list long_names,
cause I haven't eaten for a while and I lack imagination. Now,
in order to create this list of long names,
I'm going to use that new keyword pattern that we learned,
which is new item for item in list
if test. The list is, again, going to be our list of names.
Each of the items we can call it anything we want,
but I'm going to call it name. And if you find that this is too similar to this,
you can call anything you want.
Nom, you can use French or you can just write n or you can do anything you want.
This name that we're looping through is going to be tested in order to see if
we're actually going to create a new item.
So the test, in this case, is we're checking to see if the length of the name is
now greater than five.
And if this name that we're currently looping through passes this test,
then we get to specify what the new item should be.
So the new item is going to be that particular name that passed the test,
but then it's going to be uppercased,
so we're going to call name.upper in order to create the new item
that's going to be added to the list. So now once I hit enter,
you can see the new list that I've created, long_names, has Caroline,
Eleanor and Freddy, all in uppercase.
Essentially, we looped through each of the names in the list,
we took each of those names and checked that they'ree longer than five.
If they were, in fact, longer than five,
then we looked at this part of the code to see what we should do with each of
those names. And in our case, we've turned it into uppercase.
So there's quite a lot of theory covered in today's lesson.
And if you want to see the code that I've been writing so far,
then you can always head over to the day-26-end Repl.it in order to either
download it or just read through the code that I've been typing. Now,
in order to be able to fully understand what's going on,
you can't just watch me talk about it. You have to practice.
So in the coming lessons,
I've got a whole bunch of exercises for you to practice using and creating list
comprehensions for yourself. And that way, once you've done the drills,
you've done the code press-ups, then you'll be able to show off your list
comprehension muscles. For all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now it's time to put what you've learned into practice and to actually learn
through doing. So if you go to Repl.it where you are going to go to day 26.1 List
Comprehension, and you're going to complete this challenge. So pause the video,
head over there,
read the instructions and see if you can complete the challenge.
Once you're done, head back over here and I'll go through the solution with you.
All right. So in this case,
what we're trying to do is we're taking this list of numbers and we're basically
going to write a single line of code here to change it
so that we end up with a new list where each number is squared.
A square number is basically just the number multiplied by itself.
So for example, four squared is sixteen, two squared is four,
three squared is nine. So let's go ahead and create our new list
which it needs to be called squared numbers,
because that's what we're going to print out.
And that's what the automated testing is going to be looking for.
This new list is going to be created using a list comprehension,
so we're going to use our keyword method,
new_item for item in list.
And in this case, we actually don't need to do any conditional checking.
We're taking every single one of these items,
so this is the keyword that we need to fill in. The list,
in this case, is our list of numbers. Each of the items,
we can call it anything we want, but I'm going to call it num.
And this new item is going to be num,
so each of the items in that list, multiplied by itself.
You can either do it like this which will get you the output that you need.
Alternatively, you can use Python's built in exponents,
which is just num**2.
And this will square that number, which will give you exactly the same results.
Now, you're ready to head over to the next lesson where we've got
another list comprehension exercise.
All right. Let's keep working while our brain muscles are hot.
Now we're going to go over to day 26.2,
our second list comprehension exercise.
So head over there, pause the video,
read through the instructions and try to complete the code exercise.
I'll see you on the other side where we'll go through the solution together.
Pause the video now. Okay.
So in this exercise,
what we're trying to do is we're going to take this list of numbers
and we're going to write a list
comprehension do create a new list called results.
Now we're only going to need one line of code again,
because we're going to be using a list comprehension.
And what we're going to do with our list comprehension is to take only the
numbers from this list of numbers which has an even number.
We should basically end up with only the two of the eight and thirty four,
because every other number in this list is odd.
We're going to create our results which is on your list,
and then we're going to put in our keywords.
So it's going to be new item for item in list,
and because this time
we're not taking every single item from the original list that we're looping
through,
we're going to need to add a if statement to make a conditional test.
So let's start with the easy thing.
The list that we're going to iterate through is our list of numbers.
Each of the items I'm going to call num, and for each of those numbers,
we're going to test to see if the number modulo by two,
which remember means number divided by two and then get the remainder.
If that remainder is equal to zero, well
then that means that that number is even. If you remember from previously,
we could use modulo to check if a number has any remainder.
So if I do three modulo two,
you can see that it has a remainder of one. But when I do six modular three,
that has no remainder because it can be cleanly divided.
So now that we've tested
if each number modulo two is equal to zero, well
then if that test passes,
then that particular number that passed the test
is going to be welcomed to this new list of results. So now when I hit run,
you can see the result that I get is the same as my expected results.
Now we've got one final list comprehension exercise for you.
So head over to the next lesson and complete the exercise.
All right. So we're now onto our final list comprehension exercise of the day.
And just a word of warning, this exercise is quite hard.
I decided that the previous two were a little bit easier and you've now kind of
warmed up and you've gotten going, it's time to test your knowledge on a number
of things that you've learned.
The first thing I want you to do is take a look at these two files and look at
the structure of the data in there,
and then have a read through the instruction and see if you can complete this
challenge.
This is the output that you are expecting when your new list called result is
printed. Pause the video and give this a go.
All right.
So we know that we've got two text files with a new piece of data on each line.
Essentially,
what we're trying to do here is we're trying to take the data in file1.
txt and compare it against the data in file2.txt,
and then we're trying to get a hold of the data which exists in both of these
files. So if file1 contained one, two, three, file2 contained two,
three, four,
then the result should be a list that contains the overlapping numbers.
Two and three exists in both files. Now,
in order to pass the test, the result must be a list that contains integers,
so whole numbers, not strings. So when you print it out,
if you see the numbers as they are, then that means they are integers.
But if you see quotation marks around each of the numbers,
then they are strings instead.
And our code checking is not going to allow that to pass.
The first thing we need to do is to use our read lines method that we've used
several times before to read the data from each of these files and create a list
from each line. Let's go ahead and do that.
So I'm going to use my with open and I'm going to tap into my file1.
txt, and I'm going to save this as file1.
And then this file is going to be read,
and I'm going to call file1.readlines,
and then I'm going to save this list to a new variable called file_1_data. And
notice how I've actually made a typo here
cause I want file1.txt instead of just file.text.
It's good that I spotted it.
And then we're going to do the same with file2 and change all of the places
where we have one.
So copying and pasting is always a little bit prone to error,
but hopefully we'll manage this time.
Now that I've got file_1_data and file_2_data which are both lists,
I can now think about how I can compare those two and create my new list
which is going to be called result.
Now result is a new list and I'm going to use my full list of keywords
inside this new list to create the list comprehension.
So new item for item in lists if test,
the list that I'm going to test is actually the first list.
I'm going to take the file_1_data which is a list of numbers,
and then I'm going to go through each of the numbers inside this list,
and then I'm going to do a check.
And the check is where this file2 is going to come into play.
So I'm going to check to see, well,
if this number that I'm looping through exists in,
remember the in keyword,
this file_2_data, this other list,
well then I'm going to include this number inside my new list.
So this number is going to go into the new list. At the moment when I hit run,
you can see them getting a whole bunch of strings. So in addition,
I have to modify this number so that I convert it into an integer.
So I end up with the same output as is expected here.
Did you remember all of the things that we've learned before
like the in and the with open and also the converting to int?
Did you manage to complete this challenge? If you had any trouble at all,
be sure to review the relevant parts, for example,
opening files or reading lines from the files which we covered in previous days.
Alternatively, if it's the list comprehension that's hard,
then be sure to review the list
comprehension lesson in today's course and make sure that you really understand
what's going on in the code before you continue.
Now the reason why we're learning about list comprehensions is because when we
created all US states game,
I realized that the code that we were writing could be a lot shorter if only we
knew about list comprehensions.
So I want you to head back over to your code for the US states game and open it
up. And I want you to look at this if statement.
So when the user types exit,
we create a new list of missing states in order to save it to a CSV file.
I want you to change this code
using your new knowledge of this comprehension and see if you can cut down this
code by three or four lines.
Pause the video and complete this challenge now.
All right. So instead of all of this, creating a new empty missing state
and then going through a for loop, we can simply do this in one line. So again,
it's going to be called missing_states and this is going to be a new list,
but this time it's going to be created using our list comprehension;
new item for item in list
if test.
The list in this case that we're looping through is all of our states.
So we're gonna replace that with all states. Now,
each of the items is basically a state in that list.
And the test that we're going to make is to see well if the state is not in the
guessed_states which has states added every time
the user makes a correct guess
so we can basically take this part of our previous code and put it here.
And in that case, then we're going to add this particular state
which pass this test into this new list.
This one line
basically will replace all four of these lines and it cuts down dramatically
on the amount of code.
And it reads relatively well as well. Add a state to this new list
if we loop through all the states in the list of states
and if that state is not in this list of guessed
states. List
comprehensions are super popular with Python developers and I hope through some
of these exercises
you can see why, just in terms of the sheer amount of code that it cuts down on
and how much it simplifies things. Now,
in addition to list comprehensions,
we can also do comprehensions with dictionaries. So in the next lesson,
that's what we're going to be looking at.
Now that you've seen how list comprehension works,
it's time to learn about another type of comprehension, dictionary
comprehensions.
This is also super useful because it allows us to create a new dictionary from
the values in a list or in a dictionary. For example,
we could write out our keywords like this.
We're going to create a new dictionary called new_dict,
and it's going to be created using this curly bracket now instead of square
brackets. And inside the comprehension, we get to set the new_key,
the new_value, and we get to loop through items in a list.
So any sort of iterable; a list, a range, a string, anything you want.
And this is the simplest form of dictionary comprehension.
Now remember that a dictionary comprehension is just a way of creating a
dictionary using this shortened syntax.
We could take this one step further.
We could also create a new dictionary based on the values in an existing
dictionary.
So we could take that dictionary and then get hold of all of the items inside
that dictionary, and then split it into a key and a value.
So now, we're looping through each of the keys and each of the values in all of
the items from the dictionary,
and we can use these key and value variables to create a new_key or a new_value.
And to go one step further for completion sake, we can, of course,
as always add our condition at the very end,
just like we did before with list comprehensions.
So let's see how this code works in practice.
I'm going to take my previous list of names
and then I'm going to click on this button to refresh my console so that all of
the previous variables get deleted.
So now I'm going to create a new list of names.
So I'm going to use the previous names I had before, and this is our list here.
Now, the next thing I'm going to do is I'm going to create a dictionary where I
generate a random score for each of these names.
So let's imagine we had a bunch of students and we wanted to create some random
scores for each of them so that they would get a random score between 1 and
100. Now for the teachers out there,
I really hope this is not what you do when you generate the students' scores.
But essentially we want to create a dictionary
which looks something like this. Each of the students in this list,
so let's start out with Alex. We want our dictionary to have a key,
which is the name of the student, and then a value,
which is their random score.
And we want to continue through that list of names until we've generated a
random score for each of them. That's the goal.
And now we have to use our dictionary comprehension.
Remember, when we're creating a new list using lists comprehension,
we're using square brackets. But now we're creating a dictionary
so we're going to use curly brackets. Now, inside these curly brackets,
I'm going to put down my usual list of keywords.
So it's going to be a new_key:
new_value that we're going to be adding to our new dictionary.
And then I'm going to do
a for item in list. In this case,
our list or our iterable is going to be all lists of names.
Now, even though in my keywords I always use lists,
it's just easier to imagine. But it's actually, in fact,
any sort of iterable like a range or a string or a tuple.
Once we've got our list of names,
we're going to name each of those names something,
and I'm just going to call it student.
So we're looping through all the students in our list of names here.
And for each of those students,
I'm going to create the student as the new key,
but the value is going to be a new, random number.
So in order to create a random number,
I'm going to have to first import the random module.
So I've cut out my previous code, imported random,
and let's paste that code back in.
So now we can replace the value for each of these dictionary entries with random
.randint,
and we can generate a random number between 1 and 100.
So now when I hit enter, you'll see our new students_scores
dictionary being created
and you can see we've got all of our students in our list of names, Alex, Beth,
Caroline, et cetera.
And each of them now have a new random score.
So it seems like everybody did pretty well other than Eleanor,
I guess. Random score generating seems to work. Now,
the next step,
we're going to take this a little bit further because this was quite simple.
We just did what we did before, which is looping through a list.
But now I want to loop through a dictionary. Luckily,
we've now created this brand, sparkling, new dictionary, our students_scores,
and I want to use that dictionary in my next dictionary comprehension.
So the next thing I want to do is to be able to create a dictionary called
passed_students. And this is going to be a dictionary
which looks through the dictionary of student_scores,
so imagine you have an entire high school where everybody's scores are logged
and you look at everybody who's got a score of 60 or over.
And then we're going to say, well,
those people have passed and everybody else has failed that year.
Essentially we should loop through this entire dictionary of items,
figure out which of these have a value that's equal to 60 or over 60,
and then we're gonna add those items back into this new dictionary
of passed_students.
So essentially, we'd probably end up with, um, Beth,
with Caroline, with Dave and with Freddy.
So it will still look pretty much the same as our students_scores dictionary.
So it would have something like Beth and then colon her score,
which is 72. But just the fact that she's included in this dictionary,
it means that she has passed.
And we will end up with this new dictionary where everybody is a passed student
and bear scores.
Have a think about how you might do this. And if you're up for the challenge,
try pausing the video and seeing if you can complete this.
As always, we know that we're going to create a new dictionary, so curly braces,
and then it's going to be our new_key: new_value.
And then it's going to be for, and now,
because we are looping through this dictionary and we want to get hold of each
of the values,
we're going to use the method that we saw in our previous slides.
So we're going to get hold of each of the keys and the value from our
dictionary. And then after the in keyword,
it's the thing that we actually want to loop through, which is our dictionary.
Once we've got our dictionary,
then we need to call the items method on that dictionary.
So it's items with a set of parentheses,
not just the items as an attribute.
So now that we've got our keywords down,
let's convert it to our particular case.
So our dictionary is called students_scores,
let's make sure I spell it correctly.
So students_scores.items gets all of the items in that dictionary.
And then for each of the keys
which is going to be students, and for each of the values
which is going to be their score, we're going to loop through this dictionary.
The new key is just going to be the student's name and the new value is just
going to be their score.
But what we need to do is we need to check using an if statement,
if the student that we're currently looping through has passed.
So the test is basically looking at the score and seeing if it is greater than
or equal to 60. And if that is the case,
then we're going to take this student as the new key,
their score as the new value, and place it inside this new dictionary.
So now if I go ahead and hit enter,
then you can see we've got our new dictionary being created,
which only contains all the students who have passed. So it's Beth, Caroline,
Dave, and Freddy, and we've lost Alex and Eleanor.
So in order to get more practice at this,
I've prepared some more coding exercises for you on dictionary comprehension.
So head over to the next lesson and we'll get started.
All right.
It's time to put what you've learned to practice and see if you can complete
these challenges on dictionary comprehension.
So I want you to find the exercise that is day 26.4.
Now, once you've found day 26.4 dictionary comprehension one,
you'll see that this is the starting code I have for you.
I've got a sentence here
which is a string and your job is to count
how many letters there are in each word and create a dictionary that looks like
this.
So your final dictionary is going to be saved as this variable called
result and it's going to be printed to the console.
Have a read of the instructions,
especially be aware that you might need to do some Googling to figure out how to
convert a sentence into a list of words and use the hints if you need them.
So pause the video and give that a go now.
Okay.
The biggest hurdle of this challenge is not actually the dictionary
comprehension.
It's the figuring of out how to convert a sentence, a string, into a list of words.
So I've basically just typed out the entire query with Python at the end into
Google. And if I click on the first Stack Overflow answer,
you can see that they're telling you that you should probably investigate the split
method.
The split method basically splits a string by space and converts it into a list.
That's exactly what we need in order to solve this challenge.
And also in the hints, you can see that I've linked it to a page in the W3
Schools documentation for Python.
And I like looking to the W3Schools just because you have the
try-it-yourself section
where you can actually run the code and see what is the result of running this
method. So if you have a sentence, Welcome to the jungle,
once you call split on it,
it creates a list with each word as a separate item in the list.
Now we're basically ready to tackle our challenge.
We're going to create our result which is going to be a dictionary.
So let's start out with the keyword methods. So we'll say new_key:
new_value for item in list.
Now, in this case,
we're not actually iterating through a dictionary and we're only iterating
through a string, which is just a sequence.
So we can replace this list with our sentence, but we can't leave it at
just the sentence, because then it's going to loop through each of the letters.
So instead of having it as just the sentence string,
we're going to use the split method to convert it into a list of words.
And once we've done that, then every time we loop through it,
we're actually looping through each word in this list.
And it's usually a good idea to test out the code.
So let's comment out these last two lines of code,
and then let's take our sentence and let's say for word in sentence.split.
And now let's print out each of the words. And when I run this,
you can see it has split our entire sentence by the spaces to create a list of
words. And each time it iterates through it using for word in sentence.split
just like we have here,
it's going to go through each word in turn and then check each of them.
So now let's reactivate our code. And we wanna fix the very last part.
So the new key is going to be the actual word
because we want each of the words in our dictionary as the key, and the new value
is going to be the length of the word. So now when I hit run,
you can see we've got a dictionary where each word is the key and the number of
characters in each word is the value.
And now I've completed the challenge.
All right. So now we're on to the next dictionary comprehension exercise,
which is day 26.5 dictionary comprehension two.
And in this challenge,
you are going to be converting a dictionary of temperatures in Celsius to their
corresponding temperature in Fahrenheit.
So this is how you convert a Celsius temperature to Fahrenheit.
So the temperature multiplied by nine divided by five and then plus 32.
So you saw this in a previous lesson as well. So pause the video,
have a read of the instructions, take a look at the hints
if you get stuck and see if you can complete this challenge.
So in this case,
we have a slightly different exercise from before because we're now going to be
working with a dictionary to create a new dictionary.
Let's write our code here and let's create our new variable
which needs to be called weather_f. And this
weather_f is going to be a new dictionary.
Let's put in our keyword method to
create a new dictionary from a dictionary.
So new_key:new_value for,
and then it's parentheses key,
value. So, be really careful here.
I've seen a lot of students just use the colon in this case,
but it's actually a tuple. So it should be key, value.
And then we specify the dictionary that we want to loop through.
And then we call .items on it. And remember, this is a method,
so it needs the parentheses at the end.
So now let's replace the relevant parts of this line.
So our dictionary is going to be this one,
our weather_c. That's the dictionary we're looping through.
And we're gonna get a hold of all of the items in that dictionary
and then get each of the keys which I'll call day, and value
which I'll call temp_c because it will be the temperature in Celsius.
So now that I'm looping through each of the days and the temperatures in our
weather dictionary, then we're going to create our new key and new value.
So the new key is actually still going to be the same day.
It's going to be unchanged because we want this as our output
and it looks pretty much the same as this one,
other than the fact that we've converted the value.
So the new value though is going to be calculated using this formula.
So we're going to take our temp_c and then we're going to multiply it by nine
divided by five. And then we're going to add 32. If you want,
you can add the parentheses around this line,
but because we're doing math and we're going from left to right,
and we're first doing multiply divide, then we do add and subtract,
then it's actually completely optional in this case.
But we'll just include it in there for completion sake. So now when I hit run,
you'll see that
I've got a dictionary that's being generated with each of the days in the week
from this dictionary
and each of the temperatures have been converted to Fahrenheit.
So this is super useful
and you often find yourself needing to work with values in a dictionary.
In this lesson,
I want to show you how you can use loops with pandas dataframes and how to
iterate over a pandas data frame. So here, I've got a simple dictionary,
I've got two keys, student and score, and under student
I've got a list of student names, and under score
I've got a list of their corresponding scores.
Now we know that we can loop through a dictionary very simply by creating a for
loop and then we say, well,
we're going to go through each of the key and values inside this student
dictionary.
And then we're going to get all of the items in order to be able to loop through
it. So now when I print each of the keys,
you can see that it goes through the dictionary and prints both of the keys.
And similarly, I can get it to loop through both of the values.
So this is how we've been looping through dictionaries
and we've been using it in our dictionary comprehension.
Now you can loop through a data frame in the same way that you loop through a
dictionary. In a lot of ways,
you can consider a data frame pretty much as if you're working with a Python
dictionary. So I'm going to go ahead and import pandas
and I'm going to use pandas to create a new data frame,
and it's going to be created from our student dictionary.
So you've seen all of this before,
and I'll just call this the student_data_frame and I can print it for you to see
what it looks like.
Okay.
This is our data frame.
It looks like a pretty standard table with the first column being all of the
indices. So at zero index is this first row,
and that basically denotes the index of each row.
Now working with this data frame,
we can actually loop through a data frame using the same method as before.
So we can say for key, value in our student_data_frame .items.
So if I print each of the keys,
you can see it's just going to give me the titles of each column.
But if I print each of the values,
then it's going to give me the data in each of the columns.
Now this is not particularly useful because it's basically just looping through
the names of our columns and then the data inside each column.
This is why pandas has a inbuilt  loop
and it's a method called iterrows.
And it allows us to loop through each of the rows of the data frame rather than
each of the columns.
And the way that we do that is we again use a for loop and then we can get hold
of each of the index inside each row,
so that corresponds to the number in that first column.
And then we can get hold of the data in the row.
And then we can say for index row in data frame,
which is student_data_frame, and then its that method.iter
rows.
And now I can loop through each of those rows and print out either the index for
each of those rows.
So you can see that this is going to print out our data frame here,
And then in order to print out each of the index at 0, 1, 2.
But I can also print out each of the rows.
So now I get the first row has a student and a score,
the second row has a student and a score, and the third row has a student and
score.
So each of these rows is a pandas series object. So that means we can tap into the
row and then get hold of the value under a particular column by using the dot
notation. So we can say row.student
and now when it goes through the loop,
you can see first, it's going to print out our entire data frame,
and then it's going to print out each of the students inside that data frame.
Now I can also say row.score,
and now it's going to give me each of the scores inside the data frame.
And I can even do something like this where I say
if the row.student is equal to Angela,
well then we can print that particular row that we're currently looping on,
.score. And this way we would get the student, Angela's score
which happens to be 56, as you can verify here.
Now we're finally ready to tackle our project,
and this project is based on a real-life struggle that I have. Often when I'm
calling a company and over the phone I have to give some sort of details
right? They'll ask me, what is your name, and can you spell it?
So I'll have to be like A-N-G-E-L-A. And they're like, wait, was that an E?
Was that a B, what did you say? In these cases
often I have to sort of default to some sort of Naval alphabet. where
I say A is the alfa, N for November, G for golf.
And then at some point I forget what E stands for and I'm like E for.. elephant?
And there have been times where I've just completely taken the MIG and said
things like M for mnemonic, P for pneumonia, W for wrench,
which doesn't make any sense at all
because these are silent letters. And I've had some very angry people,
um, but it was quite fun.
So now what we want to create is we want to create a tool that takes the NATO
phonetic alphabet which was generated because it's often really,
really important for the other side to know exactly what it is that you said and
which letters you're spelling out so that they don't mistaken your E for a B or
your T for a C
cause it all sounds really similar. Head over to the course resources page
where you can find the starting files for the NATO alphabet project.
I want you to practice with list comprehension and with dictionary
comprehension. But in this case,
we're not going through a dictionary per se,
but we're actually going through a data frame because our data lives inside a
CSV. So we're going to be reading it using pandas.
and then we're going to end up with a data frame. Instead of having a bog
standard dictionary comprehension where our keywords were new_key:
new_value for key, value in dict.items.
Now we're going to change this for-loop
so instead of using the simple for loop where
we're just looping through a dictionary,
we're going to use this particular loop. So then in this case,
we're saying for index row in our data frame,
and then it's .iterrows as the method.
So basically I want you to use this different loop in order to loop through our
data frame and then create a new dictionary using a new key and new value.
So what exactly is it that I want you to do with this? Well,
I want you to be able to take the CSV of NATO phonetic alphabet,
and I want you to do two things to it.
The first thing is for you to create a dictionary in this format.
The format is basically the key is going to be the actual letter,
so maybe A. And then the value is going to be the corresponding code for the NATO
phonetic alphabet. So A actually is for alpha.
And then the next one is B, which stands for Bravo.
Essentially,
we're going to take the CSV and we're going to convert it into a dictionary in
this particular format where the keys
are the letters inside the CSV, so that first column,
and then the values are the corresponding code words for each of those letters.
And the reason why we're talking about iterrows and had to loop through rows of a
data frame instead of just getting you to get hold of the data frame
and then just say to_dict
like what we did before, is because it's not going to give it to you in this
particular format.
So you're going to have to use what you've learned about dictionary
comprehension in order to create a dictionary in this particular format.
And then once you've created a dictionary in this format,
then the next step is a lot easier.
You are going to create a list of the phonetic code words from a word that the
user inputs.
That way the user can use the input to type a word.
So for example, Thomas, and then when they hit enter,
they get a list printed out
that is the phonetic alphabet code word for each of the letters in their input.
So Tango, Hotel, Oscar Mike, Alpha Sierra,
which they can then read back using our little tool.
I would say that to do step 1 is a lot harder than to do step 2.
But essentially, to do step 1 is a dictionary comprehension,
creating a dictionary in this format from the CSV, and to do
number 2 is basically completing the project and being able to create and
print out a list of the code words based on the word that the user inputs.
So I want you to pause the video, have a think about how you might solve this,
and then go ahead to the course resources and download this starting zip file so
that you can open it up inside PyCharm and create your project.
Pause the video and give that a go now.
Once you've unzipped and opened up the starting file inside PyCharm,
this is what you'd see.
There is a CSV file that contains each of the letters and the code word,
and there's also our main.py with some of the example code that I showed you
in the last lesson. Now,
if you don't know how to complete this challenge, especially step 1,
I really urge you to go through this example code and just go through each of
the different types of loops and see what it is that you get when you print the
key or the value. And in this case, when you print the index
or when you print the row. And then see what happens when you get hold of some of
the items in the row. And seeing how maybe the row.student or the row.
score works. Once you fully understood this,
then it should be relatively easy to complete step 1.
So essentially the goal is that we want to create a dictionary that looks like
this from the CSV.
The first thing we have to do is to go ahead and import pandas.
And if you need to install it, there should be a squiggly line
and then you can click on it
and the light bulb will help you install the pandas module.
But once we've gotten hold of the pandas,
we can go ahead and use it to read CSV from our file
which is this file. It's under the file path of just nato_phonetic_
alphabet.csv. So it will save this as our data
which is basically going to be our data frame. Now,
once we've got hold of our data,
then you can see that if we print this out,
it looks like this.
But if we use that method, to_dict, and then we try to print it out,
you can see that it's not organized the dictionary in the format that we want it
to, which is to have the letter as the key,
the corresponding code as the value. In order to complete step 1
as I mentioned, we're going to have to use dictionary comprehension.
And the method is going to be using the iterrows to iterate through each of the
rows inside that data frame. So I'm going to copy that line here,
and I'm going to paste it in here.
Now, this is the format, so let's go ahead and replace each of the keywords.
Our data frame, in our case, is just called data.
And then we're going to say data iterate through each of the rows,
and then for each of the index and the row,
we're going to do something with it.
Now the new key is going to be the row.letter and the new value is going to
come from that row as well and it's going to be row.code.
So this is the code that will create our new dictionary
and I'm going to call this our phonetic_dictionary.
Now, if I print that out,
you can see that this is the straight up data.to_dict
and then the second line is the one where we've actually formatted it
using what we've learned about dictionary comprehension.
Once we've gotten hold of this phonetic dictionary,
then to do step 2 is incredibly easy because all we have to do is to create
some sort of inputs, ask the user to enter a word,
and then we can save this input to a variable. Now,
once they've entered the word,
we have to check it against each of the keys inside this phonetic dictionary.
So notice how each of the keys all uppercased.
So we're going to have to change whatever it is that the user has inputted all
to upper. So that way, if they entered a lowercase or an uppercase,
it doesn't really matter because we're going to convert the whole string to
uppercase. And then we're going to use our list comprehension.
The way we create our list comprehension is going to be new item for item in
list. So in this case,
our list or the thing that we're going to iterate through is going to be our
word.
And then we're going to go through each of the letters in the word.
And once we have each of the letters,
we're going to go through our phonetic dictionary, this one right here,
and pick out the value that corresponds to the particular letter that we're
iterating on.
So we're going to use the square brackets and then pass in the letter like this.
Now we've created our output list and we can go ahead and print it out.
Now let's go ahead and comment out this line and run our code.
So it's going to ask me to enter a word, I'm going to enter my name.
And now it's managed to convert that into a list of phonetic alphabets that
corresponds to each of the letters in that word.
Did you manage to complete this challenge? And if not,
which part did you stumble on?
Was it the part where you were using the iterrows? If so,
then go back to the starting file for this project and go through each of the
different ways that we're looping through it and use print statements to really
understand how the loop is actually going through and looking through the data.
Now,
if on the other hand, it was the dictionary comprehension or the list
comprehension,
then be sure to go back to the relevant lesson and just make sure that you
review it and you write out the code in the lesson for yourself
just to be sure that you understand what's going on before you continue to the
next day.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 27 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be diving into a Graphical User Interfaces using TKinter,
and we're also going to be learning more about function arguments.
So we've already seen a little bit of graphical user interfaces when we use our
turtle module, but I wanna go a little bit more in depth,
and I want to show you one of the most popular ways of creating a graphical user
interface. For example, a program like this in a separate window,
and we're going to be using the inbuilt TKinter module to do this.
So we're going to learn how to create labels, how to create buttons,
how to respond to those button clicks as well as things like text inputs and how
to lay out and design your programs.
And while we're doing all of this,
we're going to be looking at more advanced features of Python functions,
including things such as how to set default arguments and what these Args and
Kwargs are.
So a way of being able to pass an undefined amount of inputs into a function,
and we'll apply these advanced concepts to build a unit converter program using
TKinter. This program is going to help us convert miles to kilometers or liters
to gallons, or whatever little conversion that you might often use. For example,
let's say that I ran 10 miles and I want to know how many kilometers that is.
If I go ahead and click calculate,
you can see it generates the equivalent value in kilometers,
and you can see that our whole program is nicely laid out.
So it says 10 miles is equal to 16 in kilometers,
and it's fully responsive to our inputs.
This is what we're going to be making as our project,
a fully-fledged Python graphical user interface program that uses our Python
code. So once you are ready, head over to the next lesson and let's get started by
learning a bit more about TKinter.
All right.
So our main goal in today's lessons is to learn about the Tkinter module and see
how we can use it to create graphical user interfaces,
also known as a, a gui or a GUI. Now,
GUIs were a huge deal back in the nineties because previously,
in order to interact with a computer,
you had to use a command line operating system such as MS-DOS.
So this is kind of similar to our Python console,
where everything we wanted the computer to do
we had to tell it by writing a piece of text.
So if we wanted Python to print hello, we have to write out the text.
But GUIs were different.
GUIs are graphical, and accompanied with a mouse,
they allow a user with very little training in computers
to be able to just point and click on the thing that they want to do on the
screen.
And one of the earliest computers that incorporated this type of
GUI operating system was the Mac Lisa.
It had these little windows
which you can click on and it launches programs,
which you can interact with by pointing and clicking. Now,
I mentioned that the Mac had these windows and in fact,
the Mac had programmed windows before Windows actually existed.
So Windows was Microsoft's version of the graphical user interface operating
system. And when it first came out,
it created quite a bit of controversy because it seemed like it might've stolen
this idea from Apple because after all, the Mac
Lisa came out way before even Windows one
let alone windows 95 or the later version that you might be familiar with.
And this even led Apple to Sue Microsoft for infringing on their intellectual
rights for using this graphical user interface to interact with the computer.
This is how big a deal GUIs were a back in the nineties.
There was such a big breakthrough in interacting with computers and that made it
so important to both Apple and Microsoft that they ended up battling in court.
Now, even to this day,
Bill Gates gets asked whether if he actually copied the graphical user interface
idea of an operating system from Steve jobs and Apple.
And I read on a recent Reddit AMA where somebody asked him this question,
he actually responded by saying that the copying wasn't really copying.
It was just that they hired some people from another company, Xerox
PARC, and it just happened that they were continuing on the work that they were
working on before.
But the more colorful piece of history actually comes from the biography of
Steve jobs by Walter Isaacson and in there,
there is this brilliant depiction of the scene where Steve Jobs, surrounded
by his employees, is basically just going off on bill Gates,
telling him that you're of ripping us off. I trusted you
and now you're stealing from us.
You saw the earlier versions of our operating system,
and you're now using it in your Microsoft software.
And to his credit, Bill Gates actually managed to come up with a pretty good
response on the spot where he said, "Well, Steve,
I think there's more than one way of looking at it.
I think it's more like we both have this rich neighbor named Xerox and I broke
into his house to steal the TV set and found out that you had already stolen it.
That was a pretty good comeback from Bill Gates. And the Xerox that they are
referring to is Xerox parc.
It's the Palo Alto right search center that was creating loads of breakthroughs,
um, in terms of the computing industry. And in fact,
they created the first graphical user interface that was actually put into use
in a computer before Apple or Microsoft even thought about it.
They also created other things like the Ethernet or the first Object-Oriented
Programming language. And most importantly,
they also created the first graphical user interface that
allowed a user to interact with the computer by pointing and clicking.
And they even developed the first mouse to allow people to do this.
So this is a little bit of Silicon Valley history
that is particularly fascinating. If you're interested,
there is a movie called Pirates of Silicon Valley that goes into this story
in more detail and this is where I first found out about it.
But coming back to what we're doing,
I just wanted to show you just how important the graphical user interface was
when it first came about. So we're going to learn how to use Tkinter
to create our very own graphical interface programs so that we're no longer
reliant on these console based or text based programs,
and we're also not working within the playpen of the turtle module.
We're going to be building some big boy and big girl programs now.
So let's get started.
Let's get started by, as usual, importing the relevant library. Tkinter, like the
turtle module, is already pre-installed with every installation of Python.
As long as you've got Python running,
then you should be able to simply import Tkinter as the module
and then you'll be able to use all of the classes and properties and methods
inside. So for example,
we could start off by creating a new window,
and this is sort of equivalent to the screens that we've been working with
in turtle . So in order to do this,
we have to dig into the Tkinter module and then find a class called Tk.
And then once we initialize a new object from that class,
then we have ourselves a window. But if I run this as it is,
you'll see absolutely nothing happen
and it will just go straight away to exit code zero.
And the reason for this is because we need a way of keeping the window on the
screen. What Tkinter has done here is it's gone ahead,
created the window, sees that there's no more instructions
and then it basically ended the program. Now,
what we want instead is to sort of have a while loop that basically just keeps
on running, so something like a while true. And inside this while loop,
it holds onto this window and keeps on listening to see if there's anything else
that the user is going to do to interact with that window so that it can
respond when that happens.
So this loop is included inside Tkinter
and all you have to do is get your window to simply call the main loop.
This main loop is the thing that will keep the window on screen like this.
So now here is our window and here's the line of code that keeps it on the screen and
listens for what the user will do to interact with it. For example,
click on a button or type something.
Now this line of code always has to be at the very end of your program and all
the rest of the things that you're going to write
go in between creating the window and getting the window to run.
The next thing we can do is we can change the title of that program.
And we've done this before using turtle.
We just call the title method and we give a string as the input.
So 'My first GUI program',
and now if I rerun my code,
then you can see that this is what's showing up at the very top bar of my
program. Now,
other things that we might want to change with the window is the sizing of it.
So there is a default size and there's also a way of changing the size.
And we can do that by tapping into a method called a minimum size.
The window is going to scale to include all of the components that you put
inside. If you put a hundred buttons inside,
it's going to make the window massive.
But if you don't have a lot of things in the window,
then you might want to define a minimum size so that you can specify that, by
default, I want my width to be, let's say, I don't know,
500 and the height to be 300,
unless the user wants to resize the window,
or there's a lot of components that makes the window a lot bigger.
So when we run our code
now you can see this is a 500-pixel by 300-pixel window that we've just created
with our own custom title.
In addition to creating windows,
we can, of course, create some components to put inside the window.
So I want to show you firstly
how you would create a label. Just as our window was created from the tkinker
module and it's the Tk class that was used,
there's also a class inside Tkinter called
a label. So that we initialize a label class,
and we can save that to a variable called
my_label or anything else for that matter.
Now this label has quite a few things that we can change about it.
It might not be obvious from the documentation or from the prompt that PyCharm
gives us,
but we can, in fact, change a property called text so we can change what is
displayed inside the label. Let's just write some text called 'I am a label'
Unfortunately, that's actually not enough to get the label to display.
So when I run my program as it is, you don't actually see a label anywhere
on the screen. When we're working with Tkinter
what we have to do is we first have to create a component like a
label.
And then we have to specify how that component is going to be laid out on the
screen before it will show up.
And one of the easiest ways of laying out any component is just to get hold of
that component and then call the method called pack.
And this is going to place it into the screen and it's going to automatically
center it on the screen. So now
if I run the code with this modification,
you can see our label is now finally showing up and it's packed so that it's in
the center of the program.
Now there's other properties that we can modify about our label.
So we could initialize our label with a piece of text,
but we can also specify a font. The font is again,
going to be a tuple,
and that tuple is first going to take the name of the font,
so let's say I want to use Arial,
and then it's going to take the size of the font.
So let's make it a little bit bigger, maybe a 24 size font. And finally,
it's going to take whether, if it's bold or italic or, um,
let's just set it to bold. And now if I run my code again,
you can see I've now got a Arial font, size 24
and it's bold.
You can also change this to italic or you can simply just ignore it and leave
out that last item and it will just give you a regular piece of text.
But none of this would show up unless you have this line of code where you
actually use the packer to pack our label onto the screen. Now
in the course resources,
I've linked to the Tkinter documentation on the Python docs and they talk
about the packer in a lot more detail.
It's basically a geometry management system.
It's just a simple way to lay out the components that you're building.
And this packer has a number of options. So if we scroll down,
you can see that we can change the expand to a boolean, so true or false.
And that tells it whether if it should expand to take up the entire space or
stay as small as it can be. Alternatively,
you have things like side which changes
which side should it be packed to, on the left, right, top, or bottom?
So we know that currently our label is bang in the middle,
but if I change the side to equal left,
now when I run the code,
you can see it's now been packed to the left of the screen.
And if I say bottom,
then it's going to go to the bottom and right and top. All of those will work.
And if I change expand to true,
you can see it's now trying to take up the entire height and width of the
available screen size. Now,
when you're writing this pack function here,
as soon as I type pack and I open up my parentheses,
normally we're used to a whole bunch of properties being listed in here for us,
and we can specify each one and pick and choose basically.
But in this case, this is all that we see.
So what's going on here? Compare this to when we used our turtle module and I'm
going to build a turtle Tim turtle.turtle.
And then I say, tim.write. Look at how,
when I opened up the parentheses here, you can see there's the argument
which is the Object that's going to be written, and then whether
if the writing should be moved to the bottom corner,
which direction it should be aligned,
what's the font and all of the available inputs that we can give to this write
function. Now compare that to our pack function here.
This, you'll notice, is really different. Now,
if you actually look in the documentation for pack,
you can see it actually has a number of things that we can change; before,
expand, fill, in, side, and all of these things
which are modifiable and do various things.
But how is it that it doesn't seem to exist as one of the arguments that we can
use? The secret lies in this last part here,
the **kw. And in the next lesson,
we're going to talk about some more advanced features of Python arguments.
And we're going to look at how we can provide default argument values,
how we can define unlimited positional arguments and unlimited keyword arguments.
To understand this better, head over to the next lesson
and we'll do a deep dive on Python arguments.
In the last lesson, we saw how different it was when we tried to use the turtle's
write function
and we saw all of the arguments available listed, versus when we tried to use the
Tkinter label's pack method,
and notice how there's actually very few arguments that are listed.
And yet, somehow there's all of these parameters that we can change
when we look at the documentation, like expand or side.
So let's set that side to equal left,
and I'm going to delete the rest of the turtle code.
And now you can see our label is placed on the left side of our screen.
How is it that these parameters,
even though they're not listed in the list of properties,
how is it that we're able to use them just by typing them in? Well,
to understand this, we have to learn a bit more about advanced arguments.
Not how to argue better,
but how to use advanced Python arguments in order to specify a wider
range of inputs.
We've already seen how keyword arguments work. For example,
here I have a function and I have three keyword arguments,
a, b, and c. And when I call the function,
I can provide those inputs, a, b, and c in any order I want
as long as I've got the keyword in front.
So c = 3, a = 1, and b = 2.
Now what if when I use this function,
it's nine out of ten times, a is going to be equal to 1, b is 2 and c as 3.
Why is it that when I call the function, I always have to put in these values?
That seems a bit of a wasted effort, right?
Python has a very neat way of solving this by creating arguments that have
default values.
We can do this by simply changing the function declaration.
So when we create our function,
we can already give it some values to start off with. So we can say that a
should be equal to 1, b = 2 and c = 3, and these
are the default values.
So that means when I call this function and I want to use the default values,
I don't actually have to provide any inputs and it will just go along as it
would before. Now,
if, however, I wanted to modify one of those inputs,
let's say I wanted to give a custom value for b
rather than let it be equal to the default value of 2, well,
then I can just change the value of b, b = 5. And the rest,
so a and c, will still take on their default values.
Notice when I called tim.write,
this write method takes five inputs; self,
because it's a method and associated with the turtle class,
it takes an argument which is what it is going to write,
move, align and font. Now,
if I wanted to use tim.turtle to just write
some sort of text,
I can actually just put in this. And when I run this code,
you'll see that I've got some piece of text being written.
But how is it that I've got all of these other inputs
which I've just basically completely ignored? What about move?
What about align? What about fonts? Well, as you can see,
they have the =...,
which is trying to tell you that they've already got a default value.
And in fact, if I hover over this write function,
you can see that in the quick docs that pops up,
it tells me that the argument,
or the arg,
which is what it is to be written to the screen, move
which is optional which can be set as true or false, align
which is optional, font which is optional.
The reason why they're optional is because all of these actually have a default
value. For example,
move, by default, is false; align by default is centered,
and there's also a default font.
So that means that all we have to do is just to provide the required arguments.
If I don't add anything at all when I call this write method, you can see
I do in fact get an error here.
And it says write is missing one required positional argument,
which is that first arg
which is the thing that it's expecting to write. I mean,
if you're calling turtle to do some writing and you not telling it what to write,
that's a bit of a problem.
So this ARG is a required argument because it doesn't have that =... at
the end. So this you have to provide. But once you've done that,
then the rest of them all have default values.
They already know how to behave and what to do
even if you don't tell them anything extra. Now, however,
if you wanted to modify one of those arguments,
let's say I decide to change the font to something completely different
like Times New Roman, and make the font super large
80 size font and change it to bold,
then you can see that that optional setting gets implemented and it's now
changed the font and its changed the size and also made it bold.
But this was completely
optional.
And this is all down to creating the function with default values.
In the last lesson,
we looked at how to provide default values for optional arguments.
In this lesson, we'll discuss how to create functions
that can take any number of arguments.
Let's say that we had a function called add,
which adds n1 and n2 and it just returns the sum of those numbers.
That's very well and good, but what if I wanted to add more than two numbers?
Well, I would have to add n1, n2, n3, n4,
but then I would have to add four numbers every single time.
So what if I wanted to make this function more flexible and to allow any number
of arguments to be used as the input? Well,
what I can do is to simply change the code to use this asterix
and then the name of my parameter.
That name args is by convention
what most Python developers will use. And it simply stands for arguments.
But you don't have to stick with that naming if you don't want to.
But what you do need is that asterix. That's the really important part.
What that tells Python is this function add can accept any number of arguments.
And once inside the function,
you can actually loop through all of the arguments
which is going to be in the form of a tuple and you can do whatever it is you
want with each of those arguments.
Instead of now passing in only two arguments because that was fixed
when we created the function, we can now pass in any number of values
like four values or seven values,
and we can do whatever it is we want with them. Let's try this code out.
I'm going to delete the code related to Python turtle,
and I'm going to create a new file called playground.py.
And we're going to use this playground.py to test out what we've just learned.
I want you to have a think about what you just saw in the slides and see if you
can create a function called add where you can pass in as many numbers as you
want
and it will always add together all of the numbers that are being passed into
the function as the input, and then return the total
sum. Pause the video and see if you can give that a go.
All right.
So what we want to do is to be able to call this method add, for example
down here and pass in any number of values, right?
Let's just go with three to begin with.
And then we want to receive all of those values inside this function and then
add them all together. So we're going to use that asterix trick.
So one * and then we can give a name to the arguments that we receive,
which normally is just called args.
Now that we've got these args,
if I actually go ahead and print it out and we go to run and then run and change
this to our playground, you can see it's basically just printing out a tuple.
And that tuple represents all the inputs that were passed in when this function
was called. And in fact,
if I do a time check on this args, you can see it
is indeed a tuple. Now,
once we've got hold of this args tuple, we can actually loop through it.
So we can say for n in args, for
each of the numbers in that tuple, let's go ahead and print each of them.
You can see it's now separated them all out; three, five, and six.
So that makes it easy enough for us to create the sum.
So let's create a sum which is equal to zero.
And then instead of printing out each of the n,
we can just add the n to sum, and finally outside the loop
we'll return our sum.
So now when we print this final results by calling add three, five,
six, you can see it's now added three, five, and six,
and we can call this method in different ways. We can add more values to it,
two and one, and you can see it's now equal to 17.
And you can basically keep going because it can take any number of values.
This is all done by this asterix keyword.
And it basically packs all of these numbers that you've put in as the input into
a tuple called whatever it is you want it to be called.
So you can call it numbers if you want, or you can stick to the default,
which is just args. And then once we've got that args inside the function,
we loop through it and we can do whatever we want to each of the values. Now,
in addition to looping through it,
you can also access them by index because it's a tuple after all.
So we can say args at position zero like this.
And if I print that out,
you'll see that the value is three because the first one is three.
So that's why these unlimited arguments using this *
args is also known as unlimited positional arguments,
because the position of your arguments which you pass into the function
matters' a huge deal because if I fetched the one at position one,
it will no longer be three, and it'll now be five.
So this is a way for us to be able to define a function and specify a unlimited
or unspecified number of inputs. In other words,
the number of arguments for the function can vary because the asterix operator
collects all of the arguments into a tuple. However,
what if we wanted to refer to our arguments by name rather than by position?
Well, that is exactly what we'll talk about in the next lesson.
So I'll see you there.
In the last lesson we saw how the asterix operator
could be used to provide any number of positional arguments to a function
because it collected them into a tuple. In this lesson,
we'll take a look at the double asterix operator,
and this is going to allow us to work with an arbitrary number of keyword
arguments. Let's see this in action.
So let's say I create another function called calculate,
and this time I'm going to add two asteriks. And in this case,
I'm going to call my argument **kwargs or keyword arguments.
What we've done now is we've added two asterisks signs in front of this parameter
name,
and we've now created unlimited keyword arguments.
What this allows me to do is I could basically now call this calculate function,
I could pass in a keyword argument, for example,
add, and let's give it a value, maybe three,
and then let's add another keyword argument which I'll call multiply,
set that to equal five. And effectively
what this has been turned into is these **kwargs,
which is basically a dictionary. So if I print these **kwargs,
you can see what gets printed is basically a bog-standard dictionary.
And in fact, if we do that type check thing again, so type,
you can see it is in fact, a dictionary.
This dictionary basically represents each of the keyword arguments and their
values.
So add is now a key and three is now it's value, multiply's
the second key and five is its value.
What I can do here is I could do the standard way of looping through dictionary.
So I could say for key, value in **kwargs .items,
and then I can get access to each of the keys and their values as I loop through
the dictionary like this.
So add three multiplied by five. Alternatively,
I can simply use the names of the keys.
So I could just simply print my **kwargs and then use the square brackets and then
provide the name of the key, so add for example.
And that will give me the value which is three as you can see here.
Now,
what this allows me to do is it basically lets me look through all of the inputs
and find the ones that I want and use them to do something.
So for example, in this case, it's a calculate function, right?
So we could let's say start off with a normal positional argument,
so let's call it n and let's pass in that n at the very beginning.
So let's say we start out with the number 2, n is now equal to 2,
and then the **kwargs is a dictionary of the remainder arguments.
Let's say that I wanted to do some calculations.
I wanted to say n+= kwargs,
and I'm going to get hold of the value under add.
And then I'm going to say, n*= the kwargs,
and I'm going to get hold of value of multiply.
So now when I go ahead and print
my n, you can see that what happens is it takes the first value 2 as equal to n,
and then n, this 2, is going to be added to the number I wanted to add
which is 3. So 2 + 3 is 5,
and then it multiplied that 5 by whatever it is I had stored in multiply.
So 5 plus 5, and we get 25.
This gives us a more flexible way of working with these arguments.
And it gives us a way to name the values that we're passing in to this function.
Now, coming back to what they've done in the Tkinter module,
basically this Tkinter module is actually ported from another technology called
TK.
And TK actually has a very different syntax from Python.
In order for it to work, they basically took all of the Tk commands,
like creating a label or packing some sort of item,
and took all of the options and turn them into these **kwargs or optional keyword
arguments.
And that is why when we create a new label from the Tkinter module
or when we call the pack method,
you can see that it doesn't actually come up with any properties that we can
modify other than this **kw,
which is the same as our **kwargs.
So we could actually create a class like that as well,
because this is done at initialization, right?
This is done when they're creating that label class.
Let's say that we create a class like this which I'll car,
and in the init,
what I'll include in addition to self is **
kw, or **kwargs, or however you want to spell it.
This kw are going to be all of the optional arguments that I'll pass in
when I'm initializing a new object from this class. I can say,
for example, self.
make of the car equals kw.
And then from kw, I'm going to get the make.
And then I'm going to have self.model
which is going to be equal to kw and then model. And of course,
all of the spelling matters so make sure you don't make any typos.
And then I decide to create my car
which is going to be the object created from this class. Now notice how
when I open up the parentheses here,
you don't actually see any of the properties like make and model show up
when I'm initializing. All you see is **
kw, just in the same way as you see it here,
**kw.
And that of course refers to our optional keyword arguments.
Let's add some values. Let's set the make to a Nissan,
and lets set the model to a-- let's set it to a GT-R. And now I can use my object
just as I would any other object. I can say my_car.model.
And when I hit run, you can see I've got GT-R being printed here.
And if I decided to print make, you can see
it gets hold off the make.
Now, what if I didn't actually specify one of these arguments.
Notice how it's now actually going to crash.
It tells me that keyError model.
So when it was initializing this car object, it fell on this line. And it
couldn't get hold of a value called model from this kw argument dictionary.
In fact, with dictionaries,
we can get hold of the values through the square bracket method,
but we can also use a function called get. And we use get in a very similar way
to the way that we use the square brackets.
We just pass in the name of the key and we want to get hold of the value.
But the benefit of get is that if this key doesn't exist in the dictionary,
then it will just return none and it won't give us an error.
So now if I run this code again, you can see that everything works,
but my car.model is now equal to none.
So this is how we can actually create a class with lots of optional keyword
arguments.
So we could have a self.color or self.seats.
And depending on what it is we want to initialize this car object to,
then we can simply go ahead and add whatever it is we want to set as the make
and the model or the color and the seats. And in the same way
that way using this label class,
we can set the text or we can set the font.
We can set all of the options or we can leave them as the default values. That
should help you understand how this code works a little bit better.
And the reason why it works like this is, as I say,
mostly because this module was converted from another language and this just
happened to be the most efficient way for them to do this. Now with other more
Pythonic modules or things that have been created in Python
like the turtle module, then you'll see more bog-standard kind of code
like what we've been working with. So when we initialize a new turtle,
you can see that it has a default shape,
it has a visible boolean,
and we can set all of those properties that we can see in this prompt.
Now in the next lesson,
I want to dive deeper into the TKinter documentation
and I want to show you how we can create other components, not just the label,
but things like buttons and text inputs
and a whole range of things that will bring our GUI program to life.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.
In the last lesson, we saw how we could set a lot of the properties for the
methods associated with Tkinter,
or for initializing the components like our labels.
Now in the documentation,
they tell us that there's a number of ways that we can set these options.
We can either do it when we initialize a new object or we can access the
properties like as if they are keys in a dictionary and then setting the value.
And finally,
we can set multiple properties by using the config method and passing in the
value for each of the things that we want to change,
I recommend taking a look at the Tcl tk documentation
which lists all of the options. Like for example, here,
I've got my label chosen and there are standard options like background color,
or text. And there are widget-specific options,
so specific to the label, you can change its height, you can change its width.
Coming back to my label in my main.py,
if I wanted to change my label's property, so for example,
if I want to change the text that's inside and I want to make it different from
the initial text that it displays,
then I can do simply this by changing it as if it were a dictionary.
And I can set that to the new value, so new text.
Now I could also do it by doing my_label.config and then passing in the
text as a keyword argument. Either way
when I run this main.py, remember previously,
we were running our playground.
So go back to run and then click this and then change it to our main.py.
And now you should see the new text show up instead of the original text,
which is I am a label.
So this is how we configure and change or update the properties of a particular
component that we've created.
In addition to labels, we can also create buttons.
Let's create a button, which again, is going to come from the Tkinter module
and it's going to be the button class from that module
as you can see right here. Now,
all of the components that we're going to be using
come from this class. Very often
you'll see people instead of importing Tkinter, they'll say from tkinter
import,
and then the asterisk to denote import every single class.
This means that we can basically get rid of all the module mentions
and we can just initialize a window as tk,
our label as a label and our button as simply button, like this. Saves a little
bit of typing, depends on how many of the classes you're gonna use.
If you're just going to use one,
I recommend keeping the module so that you know, where it comes from.
But if you're going to use loads of them
like we are here, then it does make it a lot quicker to type.
So let's create our button. And again,
it has a whole bunch of optional keyword arguments. And some of those are
standard. So for example,
we can change the button text in the same way that we changed the label text.
So let's make it to say click me. And remember that in order to make anything appear
on screen, it needs to have some sort of layout.
So let's call pack again to get it to be packed onto the screen.
So now if I run this code as it is,
you can see that my button has been placed in the middle of the screen and my
label is packed to the left.
Let's go ahead and get rid of that left
so that it actually goes in order so that the first thing gets created,
it gets put on screen first and then the next thing is the button
and then this is all centered by default.
The next obvious question is how can we get this button to actually work?
Because at the moment clicking on it does absolutely nothing. As you remember
when we used our turtle module,
we could have an event listener. So we can create some sort of a function,
let's call it say button_clicked.
And then this function could do something say, for example,
I got clicked.
And when this button detects an event,
say a click event, then it could call this function.
So in the tkinter world, there is a property called command,
which you can set to equal the name of a function. So remember,
it's the name of the function, not calling the function.
So we don't actually need the parentheses at the end.
Now when we run our code, when this button detects a command
which is basically a click event,
then it's going to trigger this method and it's going to print this hopefully
into the console. So let's hit run. Now,
I'm going to click on this button and you can see it says I got clicked and it
does that every time I click on it.
So here's a challenge for you.
How can you make the label,
my_label, instead of reading new text, for it to say
button got clicked when I click this button?
So this button click should now change the text. Pause the video,
give that a go. All right.
So we know that we can change our label's text by using either of these methods.
So you can basically pick one of these and add it to this function.
So I'm going to use the
my_label.config just because it kind of makes a little bit more sense when I
read that line of code.
So I'm going to configure the text property to read button
got clicked.
And now when I hit run,
what you'll see is when I click this button, it's going to change the text.
So we're now getting a little bit more interactivity.
The next thing I want to show you is even more interactivity.
I want to show you a component called the entry component,
and this is basically just a input effectively.
So let's create a new object which I'll call input,
and it's created from the entry class
which comes from our tkinter module. Now again,
if we want something to appear on screen,
we have to give it a layout and we can use the automatic pack to do that.
So now when I run this code, you can see I've now got a input field. Now,
if I want to look at the options for my entry,
I can simply go to this tk documentation, find my entry,
click on it,
and you can see I've got standard options and widget-specific options. Now,
one of the things I want to change is the width. For example,
I could change the width of this input by simply using the width keyword
argument.
And I can specify an integer to indicate the desired width of the entry window.
So at the moment, if I think it's a little bit too wide,
then let's try modifying our input so that has a slightly lower width.
Let's change it to maybe 10
and you can see it's now a lot smaller than before. Now
what if I want to get hold of the value that came from that entry?
Well, in that case, I have to use the get
which basically just returns the entry's string.
So I could say input.get
and then this method is going to return the input as a string.
So I could, for example, print it out.
But unfortunately, the point when this line of code is run,
there's actually no input inside this entry.
So we would actually print absolutely nothing.
Here's a challenge for you.
Can you figure out how to get whatever is written in here
to be the text in the label
the moment when I click on this button?
Given that I've typed something in here, when I click this button,
I want that something to be displayed in the label instead of 'button got
clicked.' Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right.
So we know that the trigger for the button is the button_clicked function.
So it's here where we're actually configuring our label. If instead,
we're going to get hold of our input here and call input.
get to get the new_text, well,
then we can actually use this new text and populate the label.
So we can say text = new_text.
And now when I hit run,
you can see that I can type whatever it is I want in here.
And then when I click 'click me',
it gets the text inside the entry and puts it in the label.
This is how we would work with some of the most basic components of tkinter like
label, button, entry,
and we've also seen the pack method. Now, as you can see,
they're all other things that you can do with tkinter.
So in the next lesson,
we're going to be working on top of what we've done so far
and I want to show you some of the other widgets that you can work with and add
to your tkinter program.
Now in the last lesson,
we saw a couple of different ways of working with tkinter widgets.
We've already seen how we can create labels,
so something like this, and also buttons that can be clicked and do some sort of
action. Then we've also seen entries,
which is basically some sort of textbox.
And now I want to show you some of the other widgets that you can work with.
For example, the text entry box
which allows you to use multiple lines of text, or something like the spin box
which is basically a sort of counter
which lets you go up and down, and then a scale
which is a slider
basically that you can move along its axis and change its value.
Then there's a check box which can be on or off basically just a tick box,
radio buttons, and finally a list box of choices
which you can pick from.
So these are pretty much all the widgets that you can work with. To save you from
typing a lot of this example
code, I've created a tkinter widget demo Repl.it for you
which you can go to and you can see some of the existing code that we've already
created
like how to create a window or how to create a label and how to create a button.
But I want to show you some of the other features by just looking at the code.
For example, with the entry
we can actually insert some text for the entries to start off with.
So notice how here we can click on it to edit it,
but it's really got some starting text in there. So for example,
if you wanted to create an email box,
maybe you would write the word email to give the user a bit of a hint.
Now you've also got a text box
which is a large area where the user can edit.
And this is simply created with the text widget.
You can set the number of lines as height and the width as the width of the box.
And you can set the text to be focused so that the cursor starts out in that
textbox.
And then we can insert some piece of text to begin with and we can also get hold
of the text inside the text box using the get method. Now notice
there's something a little bit weird
like the end here and the end here.
This is just an index to allow tkinter
to figure out which particular item you're referring to and you don't have to
change it ever. This is just the code that you use.
You can keep the code exactly as it is here and just modify the test that you
want to insert.
And this 1.0 basically refers to getting hold of the text
starting from the first line at the character zero.
And then we've got a new widget that we've never really seen before, a spin box,
which looks something like this.
So you can click on the up and down to change its value and we can print out the
value that's being changed in there by simply getting the spin box to be tied to
a function which is called spinbox_used.
And then we just get the value each time.
Now a scale is also pretty self explanatory.
You can move it up and down, and we're getting hold of the value that would
the user is landing on by simply packing, again,
another command into that scale when we're creating it.
And then when that function is called,
it actually passes over the value that the scale is currently on and that is
what's getting printed. Next
we've got a checkbox and we can click it on or off.
And we can print one or zero by simply tying that checkbox to a variable.
And this variable is something that's defined by the tkinter module as a IntVar.
So this is actually a class.
And once we create that object from the class,
then we can add it to our check button when we create it,
and that variable will keep track of the value of that checkbox. 1 for on and
0 for off. And then we can print it out
when that check button is used.
Now radio buttons are useful to pick between different options.
So normally you'd have a number of options and only one of them can be selected
at any one time. So in this case what we do is, again,
we create a IntVar and we tie that var to
each of the radio buttons that we create,
and then we give each of the radio button a value. So this one has value 1,
this one has value 2, and they're both tied to that radio state IntVar.
And then when that button gets changed,
then we can actually get hold of the radio state by calling radio_state.
get and when you get whichever value it is that's currently selected,
so option1 or option2. Now finally,
we've got a list box
which is just a list of options created from a Python list.
We'd loop through each of the items,
insert it to our listbox and then once the list box is used,
we use this bind function to call this particular call back. This way
whenever we select any of the items in here,
it will print out and get the current selection. Now,
a lot of this code is pretty much going to be used the same each time.
So it doesn't really matter if you don't understand fully exactly what some of
these weird components are.
It's just a factor of how this tkinter library has taken this tk module and
turned it into a Python format for us to be able to interact with it using
Python.
So there's a few weird bits like this listbox select or this,
um, end being used here,
but you can see that each line is commented and it tells you what it does.
So you'll be able to figure out what line of code you need to write
in order to add some text or to get some texts or how to bind a function to the
list box and how to get hold of the value that's currently being selected.
I recommend heading over to this link here and either downloading the code and
opening it in PyCharm if you prefer,
because then you can actually get a much larger version of the running program
or alternatively,
just have a play around with the code in here so that you understand how these
widgets work and how you can use it basically as a pallet
if you wanted a couple of checkboxes,
or if you wanted a couple of a spin boxes,
then you can just pick and choose them from this cookbook essentially
and then you can put them into your programs when and as needed.
Now coming back to our main.py
our previous program had a label,
a button and an entry, and it was relatively simple.
So I'm going to head back to this main.py file
where we've got only three widgets so that I can show you how we can define the
layout and positioning of each of our widgets.
Firstly, I've reconfigured the file a little bit. So I've moved the button
_clicked function to the top,
and I've made sure that each of the pack methods are at the very end of each
widget. That way we'll be able to work with it quite easily. Now,
as I mentioned before, tkinter has a whole bunch of different layout
managers that define how to position each of the widgets in your GUI program.
Now there's three that you should know about, pack, place and grid.
Now, firstly,
we've already seen pack and all that pack does is it basically packs each of the
widgets next to each other in a vaguely logical format.
And by default, pack
will always start from the top and then pack every other widget just below the
previous one. As I mentioned,
you can change this by adding a side parameter and you can change it to for
example, side = left.
And if you change this for all of the packs,
then it's going to pack everything starting from the left edge of the program
like this. And you can change that to bottom or right as well.
But the problem with pack is that it's actually quite difficult to specify a
precise position. So for example,
if you wanted this label to be a little bit up and then this button a little bit
down and this entry all the way to the right. It's very,
very complicated to do that using pack.
And that's why there's not just a single layout manager,
but there's lots of others. So let's take a look at the next one,
which is called place. Place is all about precise positioning.
So when you place something,
you can provide a X and Y value. So for example,
I can say my label.place, and then I can say, well,
the X value should equal 0 and the Y value should equal 0.
And this just places that label at the top left corner.
Now it's important to remember that if a widget gets created
but it doesn't have any layout specified it using pack, place or grid,
then it won't be shown as you can see here,
we've only got the label showing up. Now that we've placed our label to the top
left corner, we can try placing it in somewhere else.
So let's move it a little bit along the X axis.
So let's say place it on a (100, 0)
That moves it to the right a bit more, and if we want to move it down
we can change the Y position.
So now it's down at the bottom and then the X is 100. Now,
remember we've defined the width and height. So the width is 500 pixels,
the height is 300 pixels and anywhere along that screen,
you can define a X and Y value for a particular widget to place it at that
precise position.
The downside of place on the other hand is the fact that it is so specific and
we have to work out in our head the coordinate and where to put each widget.
It simple enough if you've only got three widgets like we have here,
but if you have a hundred or fifty,
then that becomes quickly a bit of a nightmare to manage the precise coordinates
of each widget.
So in addition to pack and place, there's also a final layout manager
which also happens to be my favorite one,
which is the grid. And the grid is a really simple concept.
It imagines that your entire program is a grid and you can divide it into any
number of columns and rows that you want to.
So just as a reminder, the rows are the ones that go along the horizontal and
the columns are the ones that go along the vertical.
If I remove my place and instead I use my grid,
I could say my_label.grid,
and then I can provide a column and a row number.
So let's say I'm going to put it at the first column and the first row.
So then starts from zero so that we could say column = 0, row =
0. And you can see that it gets placed in the top left corner.
Now the grid system is relative to other components.
So even if I change this column to, I dunno, five and the row to five,
you can see that it doesn't actually change the layout because there is no
widget in column four, three, two or one.
So it's still the first one in the grid.
So the easiest way of working with the grid
is starting with the things that you want it to be at the top left,
defining a starting column and rows, zero, zero,
and then for the next and subsequent widgets to just keep going through it and
define its position on the grid. For example,
if I wanted the button to be on column one and row one
and then I want my entry
which is called input to be on the grid in column two and row two,
now if you run this,
you can see it's now been laid out along our grid.
And this is effectively what it looks like.
Our label is in column zero row
zero, button in column one row
one and entry in column two row two.
This is one of the easiest ways of visualizing and creating the layout for your
tkinter programs. And it's really flexible
and it's really easy to imagine and understand.
So this is always my preferred way of working with the layout for
tkinter. Just a word of warning though.
You can't mix up grid and pack in the same program.
So for example, if I wanted my label and my button to be defined by the grid
but then I decide to use the pack method for my final entry,
then you can see I actually get a error when I run my code. It says,
cannot use geometry manager pack
which already has slaves managed by grid.
So these two are incompatible with each other.
You basically have to choose one or the other.
And often I will choose grid because it's just more flexible and more easy to
understand. So now here comes a challenge for you.
I want you to change the code that we've already written so that we end up with
this layout. So we've already got a label, a button and an entry.
I want you to add a new button and it should be positioned like this.
Have a think about how you might solve this challenge using the grid system that
you learned about just now. Pause the video and complete the challenge.
All right. So the first thing you notice is that the label is still at column
zero row zero, button is still at row one column one,
but this new button is now at row zero column two.
So let's go ahead and create it.
Now I'm just going to create a new button and I'm not going to worry about its
command or any of that.
I'll give it a piece of text just so that we can identify it and I'll call it
new button.
But then the most important thing is how we lay out this new button.
So I'm going to use the grid system and I'm going to give it a column of two
because it is zero, one, two,
the third column from the left and then row is going to be zero.
Now, when I run this code though, you'll notice something a little bit odd.
Why is the entry below the button? Because in our example,
the entry is actually over on the right of this new button in a new column.
By putting this new button in between the old button and the entry, we've
actually changed the positioning of that entry on the grid.
So we've actually had to move it along into the next column.
So to do that,
we have to change the grid of our entry instead of having column two,
to make it column three, just so that its on the right of this new button.
And now when I run it, this has the exact layout that we wanted
and we've now learned a little bit about how we can precisely position our
widgets in our program using the pack, place, and grid layout managers.
The very last thing I want to show you with relation to layout and design of our
GUI programs is how to add a little bit of padding around components.
The easiest way to add padding is actually to directly modify the widgets.
So for example,
if I wanted a bit of padding around all of the elements in my window,
so basically added around the edge of the window,
then I could simply say window.config and I can change the padding in the X
axis and the padding in the Y axis,
so padx and pady.
So now if I run this program as it is,
you can see that there's now more space being added around all four edges of our
program. Now I can make this a lot more extreme.
So let's say I add the padx to be 100 and the pady to be 200,
you can see just how much padding we've now added.
And this just means that you add more space around your program and it makes
things easier to see and looks a little bit nicer.
If you want to add padding around a specific widget not just the entire window,
then you can do the same with that widget. So we could get hold of my label and
again
using config to change the padx and the pady. So let's add, maybe I dunno,
50 pixels of padding in the X and in the Y.
Now you can see that around that label
there's a whole lot of space so that it pushes everything else away and actually
makes the entire program window a lot bigger.
So this is just a way for you to be able to add space around your widgets so
that they're not all crushed together
and it helps you with your layout and your design.
All right guys,
it's finally time to put everything you've learned so far today into practice
and build our miles to kilometer converter.
This is what the end outcome will look like.
This is our GUI  program where we've got a text entry,
we've got some labels and we've got a button.
So I should be able to type in some certain number of miles
and then when I hit calculate,
it should give me the equivalent number of kilometers. Now,
here, I've rounded it to the nearest whole number,
but feel free to decide however many decimal places you want.
But the important thing is for it to work, firstly,
but also for you to be able to use and put in all of these components and to
follow this layout. Just to break the layout down,
you can see I've got a entry widget
and then these are all label widgets. And finally,
I've got a button widget and they're divided along a grid that looks more or
less like this.
Have a think about how you might create the layout and the design first
and then go ahead and add the implementation and see if you can complete this
project. So pause the video now and give it a go.
Feel free to either create it inside
your main.py by commenting everything else out or as in my case,
I'm actually just going to create a new file,
which I'll call the mile_to_kilo_converter.py. Inside this new file is where
I'm going to create my project. And first of all,
I'm going to go ahead and import everything from the tkinter module.
So import *, and now I've got all of my classes.
The next thing I'm going to do is to, of course, create our window.
So that's going to be created from the tk class and my window is going to have a
title,
which I will call it miles to kilometer converter.
And finally,
we're going to get our window to be displayed and started off in the main loop.
Right now if I run this file miles to kilo converter,
you can see I've just got a blank window with the title miles to kilometer
converter. Afterwards,
the next thing to do is to create all of our widgets and lay it out on screen.
If we look at this break down,
you can see we've got one entry widget here and then four different label
widgets at each of these positions and then finally
I've got a calculate button down here.
So I'm going to create each of these widgets and then I'm going to lay them out
on screen. Firstly,
I've got a miles_inputs widget
which is going to be created from the entry class.
And then I've got a label which is the miles label,
and that's going to be created from a label class.
And the label is going to contain some text.
The text is just going to say Miles with a capital M, like this.
Now the next one we're going to create is our is equal to label.
So I'll just call it is_equal_label.
And this one is going to have, again, just some texts.
It's not really going to have much functionality.
And then we've got our label
which is actually going to be the kilometer value.
So I'm going to create that as the kilometer_result_label.
All right.
And that's going to start off just with a big fat zero. And then finally,
I've got the kilometer label.
okay,
ad , this is just going to say, uh, KM,
right?
And the final thing that I need to create is that calculate button
and then we will be done with our widgets
right?
And this is just going to have the text of calculate.
So now I've got all my widgets created.
If I go and try to run this code, as it is, you'll see
none of them get displayed because none of them have been laid out on the screen.
At this point
it's also good to mention that if you accidentally left out one of these keyword
argument names,
then you will actually get a error and the error will read something like this.
String object has no attribute tk, which seems a little bit confusing.
But basically if you see that, then just have a look,
make sure that you've actually got that text = in there rather than just the
actual string. That's a really common mistake that students make.
So the next thing I want to do is to use my grid layout method
to lay out all of these components in the correct positions.
So I'm basically going to have a grid with three columns and three rows.
So this will be column zero, one, two,
and then this will be row zero, one two.
So that should be relatively simple.
And let's start with our miles_input.grid,
and we're going to write a column number and a row number.
Now I'm just going to copy this because I'm going to need to use it quite a few
times.
And then I'm going to refer to the end result and you can see our entry is here.
So it's going to be on column one, row zero,
right?
And then let's define the miles label on the grid.
And this one I think is going to be column two, row zero.
And then I'm just going to go through all of these widgets and define them on
the grid,
right?
So they're you have it.
We've got all of the columns and rows that correspond to the positions of each
of these widgets in our final layout. Now, if I run my code
as it is, you should see this version show up.
Now we've got to do some refinements.
And the first thing you notice is that this entry is way too large.
So let's go ahead and change it's width,
and I'm going to change it to just five or seven,
basically not a very wide. That way it will be a lot smaller like this.
And then we're going to use the method that we learned previously to give our
window a little bit of padding by changing its config
to add a padx and a pady,
and you can pad it however much you like. But in my case,
I think 20 pixels should make it a little bit larger and a little bit easier
to see. So now that we're pretty much done with the layout,
let's go ahead and actually add the functionality.
We're going to need some sort of function
which converts miles to kilometers.
The miles is going to be inputted in the miles input.
We can get the miles by calling miles
_input.get,
and then we can convert that into km by using some sort of formula.
If we search in Google for miles to km,
you can see that the formula is pretty much multiplying the mile value by 1.609.
That's simple enough,
we'll say miles multiply by 1.609,
and we get the value in kilometers. Then we have the set
our kilometer_result_label to show this updated result.
So we're going to get hold of the kilometer_result_label
and I'm going to call config on it to change its text property
to this new value
which is going to be our value in kilometers.
Now we have to be careful with the data types here,
because when we get hold of the input from that miles input,
this is still going to be a string. But we want to multiply it by a number
so we have to change it to an actual number. Because people could type decimal
place numbers, I'm going to change it to a floating-point number like this.
Now I've got a floating-point number multiplied by a floating-point number
so that's perfectly valid. Now next,
when I actually want to put that number into a label I need it as a string.
Instead of simply just adding this kilometer in,
I'm actually going to use an f-string so that I wrap this kilometer variable
inside my f-string
and then I convert it into a string to put into this label.
Now,
all we have to do is to trigger this function miles_to_km when the user
presses the calculate button.
And if you remember, the way we do that is by tying it as a command.
So command = miles_to_km
but without the final parentheses
because we only want it to be called when it actually gets clicked.
Let's check our code and see if it actually works.
Let's check what 20 miles is in kilometers. So if I click calculate,
you can see it gets calculated and that label there,
that kilometer result label, gets changed. If you wanna leave it as this,
that's perfectly fine. If you want to,
you can also round this up so that it becomes a whole number
and you end up with something that looks a little bit more sleek
but maybe a little bit more imprecise.
That's how you complete this project. Now, of course,
the world really is your oyster.
You've learned about way more widgets than we've used here.
So you could incorporate anything else that you've seen,
like maybe add a radio button or checkbox,
and you can modify this to maybe not just do miles to kilos,
and you can try playing around with the code and creating your own version of
the program. If you create something fun,
be sure to share it with us in the Q/A below the lesson so that we can all
admire and congratulate you on your hard work.
So I hope you've had fun building your first GUI programs using tkinter. In
tomorrow's lesson, we're going to be diving deeper into tkinter and
we're going to be looking at how to create some more complex,
but more interesting programs as well. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you there.
Hey guys, welcome to day 28 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be building a Pomodora app completely from scratch
using tkinter and the knowledge that we gained from yesterday's lessons.
Now you've already heard me talk about the Pomodoro technique,
this famous book by Francesco Cirillo,
Cirillo. This
famous technique that helps people time-manage and to get more stuff done.
Now, if you didn't hear me talk about it,
this is basically a very simple breakdown. Essentially,
you figure out the task that you need to do something hard,
something that takes a while like writing your next book or coding up a project.
And then you want to set your timer to the 25 minutes and then work on the task
for 25 minutes. And then after that, you take a short five-minute break.
And after you've done four of these Pomodoros, basically four repetition,
then you get to take a 15 to 30 minute break.
So this basically really effectively utilizes the way that our brain works to
take short breaks often and to work for 25 minutes at a time,
which helps us with information retention and also keeping up the motivation.
This is the program that we're going to be building using tkinter. It's going to
be a timer with a tomato on it. And when you click start,
it's going to tell you to work for 25 minutes.
Then that window can go into the background
and while you're writing your code or doing whatever, when the timer's up,
it will pop to the very front of the screen above all of the other windows and
tell you to take a break.
So the first break is for five minutes and you'll notice here,
we've already achieved one check mark for our first Pomodoro completed.
And once you're done with the break,
then it's going to go back to work and it's going to continue until you reach
the longer break or until you click reset to stop and reset the timer.
Effectively,
it's going to help you do these Pomodoros where you have 25-minute work,
5-minute break. You do four of these 25-minute work sessions,
and then you get a 20-minute break. So hopefully by creating this program,
you're going to increase your productivity and you're going to have your own handy tool
to help you achieve more and do more.
So this is what we're going to be building. Once you're ready, head over to the
next lesson and let's get started.
The first thing I want you to do to get started is to head over
to the course resources and download the starting files for the Pomodoro
project. Once you've got that,
then you should be able to unzip this file and get hold of the starting folder.
Next, I want you to open up that folder using PyCharm.
So in my case, my folder's inside my downloads,
and then I'll just click open. And PyCharm should automatically configure the
latest version of Python you've got installed.
So if you take a look inside this folder, there's two files.
There is a image of a tomato which we're going to use in our project,
and there's also a main.py with a couple of sections already hashed out for
you. And we've also included some constants,
like some color hex codes or a font name or the number of minutes for working
short breaks in a long breaks. So that's already in the starting file.
The first thing we're going to do is to set up our UI.
So under the section UI set up,
we're going to create a new window using tkinter
and we're going to get the window to run and give it a background color,
pretty simple.
So let's go to the top of our file and import our tkinter module.
And then if we scroll down to our UI setup section,
let's go ahead and create a new window from the tk class.
Remember that our tk class is one of the classes from tkinter
so you can either tap into the tkinter module and then get hold of the tk class
like I have done here, or as in our case,
if we're going to be using a lot of classes from tkinter
then we can simply say from tkinter let's go ahead and import all of the
classes. So that way we can straight away refer to this tk class.
Now that we've created our window,
the next thing we can do is to set the title of the window,
which you can of course call it anything you want. But in my case,
I'm going to set it to just Pomodoro,
which just means tomato in Italian.
So now that we've got our Pomodoro,
then we're going to get our window to show up by using window.main loop as
usual.
And now if we run this, code our main, and you can see we've got a blank window,
a title, and we're ready to go to the next step.
The next step is to put an image into our program so that we can have this
tomato as the background of our program,
and then we can put some text on top
which is going to signify our countdown timer. This is what we're aiming for,
but to achieve this and to be able to put images onto the screen
which look like this,
we're going to have to learn about the tkinter canvas widget. A canvas
widget is a little bit like a real life canvas, really.
It allows you to layer things one on top of the others.
So you could draw something and then you can draw something on top of that.
And what it allows us to do in our case is to place an image onto our program
and then to place some text straight on top of that.
In between our window creation
and the window main loop is where we're going to create our canvas.
And our canvas is created using the canvas widget
of course.
One of the things that we can specify when we create our canvas is a width and
a height, and that will be a value in terms of pixels.
So we know that we want to display this tomato image inside that canvas.
And we can see that this has a,
roughly a width of 200 and a height of 223.
So let's create a canvas that's roughly about the same size as the image.
So we'll put a width of 200 and a height of 224 so that we work with some even
numbers. Once I've created my canvas
the next thing I want to do is to add my image to it.
And we can use a method that the canvas has it which is called create_image.
And as soon as I type create,
you can see there's actually a whole bunch of other methods like create the text
in the canvas, create a rectangle, create an oval.
And all of these things could be overlapped on each other inside the same
canvas. Now, when we create an image,
there's a couple of things which are required. The first thing is the X and Y
positions of this image in the canvas.
Given that we have a width of 200 and a height of 224,
I want my image to be bang in the center of the canvas. So I can provide the X
value as half of the width and the Y value as half of the height.
In addition to the X and Y values,
we also have to specify a image.
But I can't just simply just type the name of my image
which is tomato.png,
because that is not the type of data that this argument is expecting.
What it wants instead is something called a photo image
and this class comes from tkinter
and it's basically a way to read through a file and to get hold of a particular
image at a particular file location. In my case,
the file location is in fact tomato.png.
And if your image was stored in say another sub folder or a different place,
then you should provide the relative or absolute file path to get there from
where your code is, which is the main.py. But in our case
it's very easy, they're both in the same folder,
so we can simply specify our filename like
so. The next thing we're going to do is we're going to save this photo image in a
variable so we can refer to it later on.
I'm going to call this our tomato_img.
Feel free to call it anything you want.
And that is the data that goes into this image argument.
Now we've created our canvas, we've created our photo image,
we've told our canvas to create an image at this position,
and then we've put the image inside.
The final thing we need to do is to pack our canvas or use some other sort of
method to specify the layout of how the canvas is going to go on the screen.
And now we can hit run,
and we can see our image on the screen.
So now notice how the image is basically taking up the entire space of the
window. And in fact, the window is resizing itself to fit this image.
Wouldn't it be better if this screen was actually a little bit bigger?
So we don't just look at the image of a tomato.
We can do that by getting our window to be configured.
And the configuration that we want to change is the padding,
so I'm going to change the padx and pady. On the X-axis on the horizontal
I'm actually going to add a whole hundred pixels of padding on both sides.
And then on the Yaxis, pady,
I'm going to change that to 50 so that it's got 50 pixels of padding on the
top. That's looking pretty good other than one small defect.
You can see that our tomato image is a little bit cut off on the left
and I suspect this is because the actual image is a little bit shifted over to
the left.
So we can actually adjust this X position to be a little bit more to the right,
and that way our tomato
can be centered on screen without being cut off on either side.
So now that we've tweaked our image and we've displayed it on the screen,
the next thing to do is to display some text.
As you noticed before, in addition to canvas.create_image,
they will a whole bunch of other things we could create, including some texts.
This create_text method works very similarly to the create_image method.
Notice how the first thing that's getting highlighted is the *args.
And then we've got our **kw.
So remember from the lessons yesterday,
these arguments are the unlimited positional arguments and these arguments are
the unlimited keyword arguments. So the keyword arguments here
are for example the
image or the background color or anything else,
but these are the X and Y values.
So creating the text,
we also have to provide a X and Y value.
So I'm just going to try the same values as the image to see how that looks.
And now we can add some keyword arguments, for example, the text.
So I just want it to say 00:00,
which looks pretty much like the clock. Now,
if we run our code, you can see we've got a little bit of text showing up.
Now, notice how it's a little bit high up on the tomato,
because remember the tomato starts at the top here and ends here.
So that is the center of the tomato image,
but we can move it down a little bit so that it's actually centered in this red
part, the circular part. With a little bit of experimentation,
I think this, 103, 130, actually works quite well
and it's pretty much bang in the center of the tomato.
Let's modify this text in some other ways. We can change the fill
which is basically the color of the text and I'm going to change that to white,
that you can see here. And then I'm going to change the font as well.
And this is going to expect a tuple.
So it's going to be the font name and then the size, and then whether,
if it's bold or italic or whatever else you want to do. Now in the constants
here, I've already got the font name defined,
which is gonna be Courier that we're gonna be using. So that we can straight up
add our font name and then we'll add a font size as 35,
and it will say, yeah, make it bold. So there you have it.
We've got our tomato, we've got our text showing up as the countdown timer.
Now,
the final thing I want to do is just to change the background color to a slightly
nicer looking color. Now,
one of my favorite websites is this one called colorhunt.io,
which shows you a whole bunch of different color palettes that professional
designers have a created
and it makes it really easy for us to just snap up some of these hex codes and
use them straight away in our program. Now,
the one that really caught my eye is this one,
cause it has a bit of the tomato color palette.
So I've transferred all of these hex codes to the constants in the starting
file. So you can see I've got the pink, the red, the green, the yellow,
and we're going to be using that across our program to give it that consistent
color theme and make it look like it's been professionally designed.
So what I want to do is I want to change the window's background color,
and I can do that through the keyword argument called at bg for background,
and I can set it to a hex code.
So a hex code starts out with the pound sign and then it's some numbers and some
letters. Now I've already got all of that for you
and all you have to do is just to put down the name of the constant.
So this should not be in quotation marks because it's not the word. It is
in fact,
referring to that particular variable and the string that's held inside.
So now if we check our screen,
you can see the background has been changed to that nice yellow color, sort of
rice or hay color, but the tomato,
namely the canvas, still has that white background.
So let's change the background color of the canvas as well. And again,
it's using the bg.
So some of these, you'll notice, are standard attributes that we can change like
the width and the height and the background color,
which is standard across all of the widgets. And some other things like file
here are some of the more specific keyword arguments.
So let's apply this yellow to the background of the canvas,
and you can see that the canvas is now yellow as well.
But it's still got this little white border
which denotes the edges of our canvas. To get rid of that
I found a specific keyword argument that would actually help
and it took quite a bit of digging around, quite a bit of Stack Overflow
searching and googling in order to find this.
It wasn't very straightforward because tkinter is not well-documented
unfortunately. But thankfully for you,
all you have to do is find your canvas and on the line where you've created it,
go ahead and add this keyword argument.
It's called a highlightthickness,
and be sure that you spell it right, because it's really long.
And remember that there's two Ts cause it's highlight and thickness and there's
nothing in between, no underscore, no nothing to separate it.
I think that the tkinter team could have really done a little bit better here,
but hey.
If we set the highlightthickness to zero and we rerun our code,
then you should see that it now looks pretty good.
And our canvas is now completely the same color as the background of the window.
And you can't tell it where the window begins and the canvas ends. Now,
the only problem is once we've removed that border around the canvas,
our tomato is once again, shifted a little bit.
So we can actually adjust this and we can change this back to 100 and I'm going
to change it both for the text and the image.
And we can make that tomato image perfectly round
once more. With tkinter I've found that you have to do quite a bit of tweaking
around especially with these positions.
And you'll spend some time judging it by eye
in terms of the size and the width and where to place it.
But we have now successfully managed to place an image onto the screen,
changed the background of the window,
keep it consistent and add a little bit of text onto our tomato.
So now we're ready for the next step. In the next lesson,
we're going to create the rest of the user interface.
And that is mostly going to be up to you. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you in the next lesson.
In the last lesson,
we started setting up our user interface and we created this canvas,
placed our image onto it, and also on top of that, put some text.
This is how far we've gotten,
and we want to now complete setting up the user interface,
so adding in some more components.
And we wanted to end up looking a bit like this with a label at the top, a big
bit of text, some buttons at the bottom,
and also a label that keeps track of how many Pomodoros we've done.
So each 25 minute work session gets us a
check mark. So you are
going to be using a lot of the stuff that you learned in yesterday's lessons in terms of
which tkinter widgets to use and how to set them up in order to create this.
So it's going to be a challenge for you, but before we get started,
there's just a couple of things I want to point out. So,
one thing to note is that we've got this bg
which stands for background color,
and we've used our constants up here to set those background colors.
Now you can see that here
I've got the label and also the check mark in a green color.
And that color comes from our constant right here.
So you'll be able to color a piece of text in a label,
not by using bg, but by using fg
which stands for a foreground. And that you can basically set to equal the green
color that we've got. And as long as that's added to the label,
then you should be able to see that show up. Now,
the other thing I want to show you is if you don't know how to get hold of a
check mark,
the easiest way is just to go onto Wikipedia and find the particular checkmark
that you like.
And then just copy it and paste it into here as the text.
So for example, if we had a label which had a text argument,
and I copy that a checkmark and I paste it here,
then that checkmark is what's going to show up on screen. Now,
the final thing I want to mention before I let you get on with the challenge is
that we've packed our canvas onto the screen.
But as we've got quite a few things that we need to lay out on the screen,
it's much easier to do this using the grid.
So I want you to change the canvas to using the grid system.
And here I've created a more or less sort of breakdown of how that grid might
look like. So you probably will end up with one, two, three,
four rows and three columns,
and have a think about how you might lay out the labels and the buttons and the
check marks relative to those rows and columns.
Keeping this page on screen,
I want you to pause the video and give this challenge it go.
And if you don't know the sizes for things or the fonts, don't worry,
just guess them. It doesn't really matter.
As long as you've got the rough layout and the correct widgets,
then that would be considered a win. Pause the video now and give it a go.
All right.
So I'm going to get started by creating this top label here and that I'm going
to call the title_label and that's going to be created from the label class.
Now, the text in this is just going to read timer for now,
and I want to change its color by using the foreground keyword argument.
And I'm going to change it to that green color that we've got up here.
Now, I want to be able to show that label on screen,
so I have to give it some form of layout. And as we mentioned,
we're going to use the grid system. So I'm going to change the grid.
And if we refer to this image, you can see there's going to be three columns.
This is going to be in the middle column,
and then it's going to be on the first row.
So that we're going to start from zero.
So I'm going to say column = 1 and row = 0.
Now I have to change this canvas pack because otherwise it's going to give me an
error. And in terms of where the canvas is,
it's going to be again in the same column as that label,
but it's going to be on the next row.
So column 1, row 1. And now when I run it,
you can see our label shows up and then our canvas shows up and it's all
correctly positioned.
Now I want to change this label so that it looks a little bit more like the demo
that I showed you, like this.
So I have to change the font and the text to make it a lot bigger.
As we've seen before, we can simply add the font when we create the label.
So we can set that to a tuple.
And first I'm going to use my font name that I've got as a constant
which I've used when I created the text, it's just going to be Courier.
And then in terms of the size,
you can simply just make a guess. It's going to be something pretty large.
So I'm going to go with 50 and I'm not going to have it bold or italic or
anything, so that's the end of that font. And now when I run it again,
you can see its a lot bigger and it looks a lot more like the example that we
had here.
But the only difference is that it actually still has a white background. Instead
of just changing the foreground,
I'm also going to change the background and I'm going to make it the same yellow
color that I have in the background of the window.
So now it looks like it's all blended in and it's all a part of the same
application. Let's move on to the next row,
which is going to be our buttons.
So I'm going to have a start button and I'm also going to have a reset button
and they're both going to be created from the button class.
The start button is just going to have the text start and the reset button is going
to have the word reset. The start
button is also going to be laid out on our grid and it's going to be column 0
row 2.
And the reset button is going to be column 2, row 2.
So now you can see the start and the reset buttons are now on the next row after
the canvas and it's either side of it. Now notice how there's a little
bit of a white background around each of the buttons. If that bothers you,
then you can actually fix that by doing the same thing that we did with the
canvas
which got rid of the border by changing that highlightthickness to zero.
And because that's really prone to typos,
I'm actually just going to paste it in.
So now you can see that whiteboard has pretty much all but disappeared.
Now we're onto our very final thing that we showed,
which is the checkmark right here.
So I'm going to call it check_marks because eventually there'll probably be
quite a few of them
hopefully if we do lots of good work, and our label is going to have to text
which is going to have the checkmark. Now, if you are on a Mac,
you can actually go into edit and go to emojis and symbols and pick a checkmark
from here.
But on Windows you can simply just use the trick that I showed you.
Go ahead and copy and paste it from a piece of text, say like Wikipedia.
Once we've got our texts, I'm going to change the foreground color of
that text again, and I'm going to change it to green.
And it's also going to require a background color of yellow
just so that we get rid of the white. And finally,
I'm going to add this on using the grid,
setting the column to 1 and the row to
3. So this is basically going to be in the last row.
So you can see after all of that work,
we finally managed to complete the user interface and we've now achieved the
final look.
And all we need to do now is to actually add the timer functionality,
which we'll do in the next lesson. Now,
if you found any of the tkinter widgets difficult to use
or you got stuck or you couldn't figure out certain things about it,
then be sure to have a review of yesterday's lessons
where we talked about the widgets in more detail.
In the last lesson,
we completed the user interface for our Pomodoro timer,
and we've managed to get all the components that we need onto our graphical user
interface. Now, the next step is to actually give it some functionality.
I want to be able to create some sort of countdown mechanism that just does
something really simple. For example,
if it was just able to count down from five, four, three, two,
one going down by one each time, that would be great.
That's what we're going to be working on in this lesson.
And we're going to go and see the countdown mechanism section to do that.
One of the ways that you might think about approaching this is to use our time
module
cause we've seen before that we can say time.sleep and we can tell it to
sleep for a second.
So then we could maybe set up a while loop and while something or other is true,
go ahead and sleep for one second. And then afterwards just,
you know,
subtract one from some sort of counter. So that we could start count at five
and then each time we subtract by one and then each time we just simply update
our label here,
which we created in the canvas to whatever value count might be.
Now, that sounds great in principle.
The only problem is that we're working within a graphical user interface
program.
The reason why that's relevant is because if we think about a command line
program, say for example,
if we were to get our console to do something, print
hello, well,
it's only going to do something when you actually give it an instruction and you
hit enter.
It doesn't really need to keep an eye out for what you might do in between.
But a graphical user interface is a little bit different.
It needs to keep watching the screen to see whether
if a user clicks on a button, for example.
So it's basically going to refresh and keep listening for events.
So every fraction of a second,
it's going to keep checking, did something happene, did
something happen, did something happen. And the moment when it does,
then it's got to react. It's got to react to that event.
In this case, we tend to call these types of GUI programs event-driven.
And the way that it's driven is through our main loop.
So when we set up our window and we start off the main loop,
it's basically looping through and every millisecond it's checking to see did
something happen, did something happen, did something happen?
So that means if we have another loop in our program,
it actually won't be able to reach the main loop. And in this case,
when you actually try to run it, nothing happens.
Our program doesn't even launch.
So we have to rethink this and we have to do it a little bit differently. In
order to create interactive and interesting programs,
you kind of need something to happen on screen, right?
Every so often. You need this timing mechanism. Luckily,
tkinter already thought of this.
And we can in fact use one of the builtin methods to every widget.
So if we tap into our window widget,
we can get hold of a method called after and after is quite simple.
It's a method that takes an amount of time that it should wait
and then after that amount of time,
it simply calls a particular function that you tell it to call passing in any
arguments that you want to give it. Here's how it works.
We call window.after, we first provide the amount of time to wait in
milliseconds. So if we want one second, then that's 1000 milliseconds.
Next we pass in a function to call.
So let's create a function up here. Let's just call it, say something,
and then we'll pass in the thing,
like this. And then all we do is we just print that thing.
So super simple function.
And then we give the name of this function as the function to call after 1000
milliseconds.
Now the final thing in this list of arguments,
if I just go ahead and cut that and show you again, when it gives me the prompt,
the last thing is actually a *args.
This, if you remember, allows us to put in an unlimited number
of positional arguments.
What that means is we can give as many arguments as we want
and those arguments, in this case, is simply going to be passed to the function
that we want to call. So in this case, it's going to be that thing.
So if I put hello here then I run my code,
you can see that after 1000 milliseconds, basically one second,
it calls this function,
say_something, and it passes this hello as the input
to that function. As I said,
you can have an infinite amount of positional arguments.
So let's put in some other arguments which we'll call a,
b, and c,
and then we'll print a, print b, and print c.
And now instead of passing in hello,
we're going to pass in lots of positional parameters. So we'll say 3, 5,
and 8. Now, when I hit run,
you will see it waits for one second
and then it passes all three of these parameters to say something
and it goes ahead and prints all of those out at once.
So this is how the after method works. But what we wanted to do though,
is we want it to repeat itself,
to essentially loop. One way of getting that behavior is to simply put this
method,
call somewhere inside a function and then call itself.
So here's what I mean. Let's create a function called a count_down,
and this is going to take a input in the form of the number to count down by.
And then inside this function, we call window.after.
And we say that after 1000 milliseconds,
call this function count_down and then pass in a count number.
If that count number started out as 5,
then we want to say count - 1.
Now all we have to do is to call this countdown method.
So let's call count_down and passing the starting count,
let's say 5 seconds. So now when I run the code,
it's going to call this method passing in 5 over here,
and then it's going to wait for one second,
and then it's going to call this function count_down passing in five minus one
so it becomes four. And then afterward it repeats again, becomes three,
two, one. So now if we catch that number
which we can print, then we'll be able to see it count down
when we run the code; five, four, three,
two, one. One every second,
and it basically keeps on going and it even continues to the negatives.
So if we don't want it to go to negative time,
then all we have to do is add an if statement.
If count is greater than zero, then go ahead and execute this line of code.
So now it'll go from five, four, three, two,
one, zero, and then it will stop.
This is the kind of behavior that we would need if we want to update our
countdown in our Pomodoro timer.
So how can we instead of printing
the count actually change this text on our canvas? We'll,
the way that we do that is by assigning this text a variable.
So I'm going to call it timer_text
and now that we've got timer_text being a set as the text that was created in
the canvas, then we can access it right here.
And the way that we'd change a piece of text or anything for that matter in a
canvas is slightly different from how we would do for a label.
If it was just the title label that we wanted to change, we would say title_
label.config, and then let's change the text to something new.
But to change a canvas element,
you actually have to tap into the particular canvas you want to change and
Then you call a method called itemconfig. And then in this method,
you pass in the particular item that you actually want to configure,
so in our case it's the timer_text,
and then you pass in the thing about it that you actually want to change in
terms of a kwarg, so this is a keyword argument.
We're going to change the text to the current count.
Now notice how this is not the string count,
because then it would just show that word,
but its actually the live countdown time. At this point in time
if I run the code,
I actually get a error and it tells us that the name canvas is not defined
and that's because I'm calling this method countdown before I actually created
the canvas.
So if I move that to below this line and I run it again,
then you'll see it actually work.
And you see it starts out from five and it counts down to zero.
Now how can we tie that behavior to the start button so that I can press the
start button and then and only then does it start counting down from five,
four, three, two, one? Well, let's go ahead and add
another function and I'm gonna add it in the timer mechanism section and I'm
going to call it start_timer.
Now this function is super simple.
All it's going to do is it's going to be responsible for calling that function
countdown and it's going to count down from five seconds.
So I'll move that inside the start_timer.
And now the start timer is going to be the function that needs to be triggered
when the start button gets pressed.
Do you remember how to tie a function to a button in
tkinter? Pause the video and see if you can solve this challenge so that you'll
be able to run the code, hit start and the timer to start counting down.
So the keyword argument is command and all we have to do is to tie it to the
start_timer function, but without the parentheses.
So now when I hit run and I click start,
it starts the timer setting that text from five, four, three,
two, one.
So the main loop is listening and when the user interacts with the start button
it actually calls the start_timer function which calls the count_down function
and get it to count down from five seconds.
Now we don't actually want to count down from five seconds.
We want to count down in minutes because we're probably not going to be working
for five seconds at a time.
We're going to be working for 25 minutes or having a minute break.
So how can I change this countdown to interpret this instead of as five seconds
to five minutes? Well, let's have a think about that.
If we wanted to count down, let's say one minute,
then that in terms of seconds would be 60 seconds.
All we have to do is to take the number of minutes that we want to count down
by and multiply it by 60. In this case,
if we wanted to count down it by five minutes instead of five seconds,
all we have to do is multiply by 60.
So then when we call this function count_down,
instead of getting five seconds to count down,
we get 300 seconds to count from.
But now if we run our code, you can see it's going to start from 300.
It's going to go down all the way down to zero. Now in terms of time,
that is five minutes, but this is not a very good way to visualize it.
Nobody thinks in terms of 288 seconds remaining, right?
So we have to format this count so that we can display it in the format of
00:00 like the usual kind of time, where for example,
you have one minute and 35 seconds remaining or something like that.
So how can we create something like this? If we have the count in terms of
seconds,
so let's say we have 300, and we wanted to know how many minutes where in that
then all we have to do is take 300 and then divide it by 60 and we would get
5, so that's 5 minutes. But what if the countdown has already been going
and instead we had 245 seconds remaining?
Well,
we can actually get hold of how many minutes and seconds that is equivalent to.
And the way we would do that is by taking that number, say 245,
dividing it by 60 seconds
and we would get a number 245 / 60 is 4.08,
3 recurring.
If we rounded that number down to get rid of all of the decimal places,
then that would be equal to 4 minutes.
And then if we want to get hold of how many seconds there are after we've gotten
hold of the four minutes,
then the way we do that is to use the modular because remember the modular
divides a number by another number, so 245 divided by 60,
and then it will give us the remainder.
How much is left after it's cleanly divided. And in this case,
this would actually be the number of seconds remaining after the four minutes
has been taken away. So let's write this code out.
The count minutes would be the count divided by 60,
but then we have to round it down so that we get rid of all of the remainder.
Now we don't want to round it so that if it was something like 3.6
it becomes 4.
We actually just want to get rid of everything after the decimal place. To do
that,
the easiest way is to import the math module and then use a function called math
.floor and this math.floor,
if I hover over it, is going to return the largest whole number that is less than
or equal to x.
If this was a 4.8, then the largest hole number less than 4.8 is 4.
So that's basically what this is going to do.
And this is going to give us the number of minutes. Now,
the next thing we want to do is to know, well,
how many seconds is left after we've taken away the minutes. To do this,
we're going to do counts
and then we're going to use the modulo to divide it by 60.
So the modulo is going to give us the remainder number of seconds after we've
cleanly divided it by 600. For example,
if we had 100 seconds and we divide that by 60, well,
that's going to be equal to one.
So we can minus 60 from 100 and we get 40 as the remainder.
That is what we will get after doing the modulo.
So that's basically the number of seconds that remains.
So now that we've got the minute and the second, we can actually change this
count to use an f-string and we can format it so that we add the count minute
first,
and then we add a colon and then we add our count in seconds.
Now look at what happens. We're going to try and count down five minutes.
So we get hold of the number of seconds, we pass it over to this function,
we work out what the count is equivalent to in minutes and seconds
and then afterwards we subtract one second each time.
So now when I run the code and I hit start,
notice how it starts from 5 minutes, goes down to 4 minutes,
50, 59,
and then it keeps ongoing like a real timer.
That's pretty cool.
The only thing left to figure out is how can we get it to not display 5:0?
How can we get it to display 5:00
like you would see on a clock? To find out how to do that
we have to learn about Python dynamic typing.
We have to understand how that works and that is what we're going to be talking
about in the next lesson. So I'll see you there.
In the last lesson, we managed to get our countdown mechanism to work,
and we got it to count down from five minutes to zero. Now, everything works,
but there's just something a little bit niggling and you'll see it when I hit
start. Notice how it says 5:0.
Wouldn't it be so much better if it said 5:00?
So how would we do that? Well,
that is the zero comes from this count_sec because it's taking the count in
seconds, dividing it by 60 and finding the remainder using the modulo.
Now, when there is no remainder, it's just going to be equal to zero.
So we could use an if statement and check well
if the count_sec is equal to zero,
then instead of making it zero, let's set it to equal a string
which is "00".
Now this actually, believe it or not, works.
And you'll see it when I run it.
When I hit start, doesn't that look so much better?
But some of you might've realized that there's something a little bit crazy going on
here in these two lines of code.
We're checking to see if this variable holds data that is equal to the integer,
the whole number zero,
and then we're setting it to a string.
So these are completely two different data types.
That's an int and that is a string.
So how is it that we're able to do this?
So let me pull up the Python console.
We know that if we took a integer,
say 3, and we try to add it to a string, say a 4,
this is not going to work
and we get a type error because this is type int
and this is type string.
So you can't actually add these two together because there's a mismatch.
Now here's the crazy thing.
Let's create a variable a and let's make it hold the integer with 3.
And at this point, you can see that this a variable has a data type of int.
If I decide to change that variable and make it hold a different type of data,
let's say the number 4, or let's make it simpler,
let's make it hold the piece of text, Hello. As soon as that goes through,
you can see that a is now of data type string.
And the very fact that I'm able to do that,
change a variable's data type by changing the content in that variable,
this is what's known as dynamic typing. In this sense,
Python is a language that's quite unique because on one hand it is strongly
typed, in the sense that it holds on to the data type of the variable,
so this a is a string and it knows that it's a string
and if you do something that is not meant for a string,
say if you try to raise a to the power of 2,
then that is going to be a type error. Types matter
and when you call a function that's expecting a particular type,
say if you use the power function
which is expecting a integer and you pass in something
that's obviously not an integer say, our string here
and you try to get it to do some things, say raise it to the power of 3,
then again, we get type error.
It knows what type is supposed to go into that function
and it makes sure that you comply with that.
This is where the language is strongly typed.
But the part where the language is dynamically typed is that even though it
knows what type a variable is,
it knows what type a function expects,
you can also dynamically change the data type of any variable like this.
That is basically what we're using here. We're using dynamic
typing to change
the data type of count_sec from a integer to a string.
And then we use that string to display inside this canvas text.
Now there is however,
still a bit of a bug with this and you'll see it once it dips below 10 seconds.
Notice that as soon as it goes to 9 seconds,
instead of saying 09, which is what you would want or 08,
06,
it just lists the number of seconds until it reaches 00.
So how can we fix this?
The key lies in these two lines of code.
See if you can do this as a challenge,
pause the video and see if you can make it so that when it's nine seconds
remaining,
it says 09 or 08 or 07 and also 00 of course.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge. All right.
So basically what we want to check for is when the count in seconds is less
than 10, because now it's going to be in the single digits
and instead of having just one digit,
we wanna add a zero in front of it.
So the way we can do this is through just an f-string.
We can use an f-string to add the zero in front and then add the count in
seconds afterwards,
formatting that into the standard kind of time format.
Now that we fixed that if we run our app again
it goes down to 10 seconds
you can see it now says 09, 08, 07
and it's nicely formatted using our f-string.
And we're able to do because of the flexibility of the data types in Python,
checking it as a number,
making sure it's less than 10 and then formatting it as a string and using the
f-string.
Now, this is not a feature that's available in all programming languages.
For example, languages like C or Java or Swift,
you won't be able to do this.
Once you create a variable and you give it a certain type of data,
then it must forever hold on to that type of data.
But Python allows you to change the data type of a variable just by assigning it
to a different type of value.
There's a really well-worded Stack Overflow answer that addresses this exact
thing
I'm talking about, talking about the fact that Python is a strongly dynamically
typed language. And I recommend that if you want to dig more into this,
to have a read of this answer and I'll link to this in the course resources.
Now we're almost there. When we hit start,
our countdown works and it starts counting down from however minutes we tell it
to. Here's a challenge for you.
We know that the Pomodoro technique requires us to work for 25 minutes and then
after 25 minutes to take a short break,
and then it goes back to 25 and this repeats until we've done four sets of 25
minutes, and then we get a long break.
So I want you to have a think about how you could create a variable called reps,
which is going to be a global variable, and you can access it inside
start_timer by tapping into this global reps. Now using the modulo or some other
sort of mechanism that you can think of see if you can figure out how to get our
countdown timer to count down a different number of minutes.
For example, we would start out with work_seconds
which is going to be the work in minutes times 60,
and then we have our short_break_sec
and our long break seconds.
Now, how can we call this countdown timer
so that if it's the first third,
fifth,
seventh, rep that we're actually doing our countdown,
then we want this countdown to do our 25 minutes in terms of work seconds.
But on the other hand, if it is, um,
the eighth rep,
then we want the countdown to work on our long break seconds.
But if it's the second or fourth or sixth rep then it should count down to our
short break seconds.
Essentially what we're trying to achieve is for our countdown timer to do 25
minutes, then 5 minutes, then 25, 5,
and until we've done four sets of 25,
then do we get a 20 minute break.
So have a think about what you've done before using the modulo and see if you
can figure out how to get this to work in your code.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right.
So what we want to do is first when we start the timer to increase the reps.
So we're going to increase it by one.
So now it starts out at the first rep or the first repetition.
Now on this first repetition,
it's going to need to run this particular line of code.
And then when it gets to the second repetition,
it needs to run this line of code. And finally,
when it gets to the eighth repetition then it needs to run this line of code.
So we can actually use a if statement to check for all of these things.
So here we can check to see if the reps modulo by 8 is equal to zero.
If the number of reps divided by 8 has no remainder,
then that means it's actually the time for a long break.
Now, Elif though,
or else if the reps is actually even,
so if modulo 2 is equal to zero, then in this case
it should be time for a short break.
And finally,
if it's none of those conditions and we have an else statement,
then it's just a normal work time.
Now we might think that's all that's required,
but as usual we have to test it to be sure.
So let's go ahead and change our work minute down to one minute so that we can
run it and have a reasonable chance of seeing when it actually finally reaches
zero.
Once our timer counter goes down to zero,
we would expect it to go to a five minute break,
but it doesn't. It actually just stops.
And this is why we need to test our code and test our programs as frequently as
we write code so that we can catch these bugs in terms of our logic.
So what's happening here? Well,
basically it's counting down to
the number of seconds that we told it to count down to.
And then once it's done that, well, that's kind of the end.
There's no other way of triggering start timer unless we press the button.
So what we actually need to do is to add a else statement here and catch when the
count goes to zero,
because it's in that moment that we want to actually call start timer
once again.
And this time it's going to increase the reps and figure out which countdown we
actually need to go to.
So if we run this code again and I fast forward through the timer,
you can see that now, once it hits zero,
it's going to go straight to our five minute break and it continues the timer.
Now, as the user though, it's quite hard to tell whether
if I'm in a work section or if I'm in a break section and what's actually
going on.
So we should improve the user experience by changing this title from saying
timer to whatever it is that the user should be doing.
So if they are in this long break countdown then it should say
break, if they're in a short break section it should say break,
and if they're in the work section then it should say work.
So the label that we need to change is this title label.
And I also want to change the color, the foreground color,
so that when it's work, it's green, when its a short break it's pink,
when it was a long break it's red. So of course,
I'm referring to these constants over here.
See if you can complete this as a challenge and get that label to change
to display to the user, what they should be doing each time.
Pause the video and complete this challenge. Okay.
So when they're on a long break,
we're going to get our title label to configure it and change the text to say
break.
And we're also going to configure the foreground color at the same time
and we're going to make this
the red color. Now for the next one,
which is the short break, it's also going to read break, but in this case,
the foreground color is going to be pink. And finally,
when they should be working,
the foreground color is going to be green and the label is going to read work.
So now when it's during a work session, it will say work.
And when it switches to the break time,
then it's going to say break. And because this is pink,
this is, of course, the short break where we can also see that we've got five
minutes and counting. And when it gets to the long break
after four sessions of work,
then the text would be red and the countdown would show 20 minutes.
We're pretty much almost there. There's just a couple of loose ends to tie off.
One is to change this part so that we actually get a checkmark for every
successful work session we complete, and also to make sure that our reset button
works so that when we click on it, the timer stops and goes back to zero.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.
Now we're at the final stretch. Our Pomodoro program is almost complete.
We've got this beautiful user interface,
we've got beautiful colors from our colorhunt.io color palette,
and we've got pretty much everything functioning other than just some loose
ends.
So the first thing I want to fix is the section with the check marks. So
we've created the checkmarks
which is a label that currently just contains a single checkmark.
Now I'm actually going to cut this checkmark and delete the text here because I
want that label to start out as empty. Now,
the only time when I want that label to get an extra check
mark is when the user has completed a work countdown.
So once they've completed their 25 minute session,
then they should get that checkmark. To do that
I'm going to write the code inside this else statement because every single time a
countdown completes,
it's going to go into this else statement because the count goes down to zero.
Now, currently we're just getting the timer to restart itself and go to the next
session.
But what we want to do here is we want to check to see how many reps we have, and
for every two reps
then that means we've completed one work session because it's work then rest,
then work, then rest. So for every two reps,
we've completed one 25 minute work session.
So here's a challenge for you.
So have a think about how you can use our variable reps to check so that for
every two reps we've completed,
we add a checkmark to this checkmark label.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge,
then test it out and see if you managed to get it right.
Okay.
All right.
So we know that the reps is equal to the number of sessions we've had.
So for example, if we've done for reps,
then that means we've had two work sessions and two breaks.
That means we can basically divide reps by two to get the total number of work
sessions we've done.
What I can do is I can create a temporary variable called mark,
which is just going to be in an empty string to start off.
And then I can create a for loop to loop through a range.
And the range is going to go from zero up to our reps divided by 2.
Now this is giving us a warning at the moment because reps divided by 2 or
anything divided by anything becomes a floating type number.
In our case we want to do is we want to use that math.floor again so that we
can floor this reps divided by 2 to a whole number
and that way we get the correct number of work sessions.
If you want to make this a little bit more clear
the next time you read your code,
you can actually create a work_sessions and we can move this part of our code
over to here.
So the total number of work sessions is equal to the reps divided by 2 and
then rounded down to the nearest integer.
And then we can use that number of work sessions to create our range.
When we've created our range,
we know that this loop is going to run for that many times.
So we can add to our mark. For every single time the loop runs,
I'm going to paste in a checkmark.
You should have that checkmark that you had from a previously,
and you can paste it into here. Now,
once we've completed that loop, then all we need to do is the update
our checkmarks label by calling config and then changing the text to equal our
mark. Now, in this case,
it probably makes sense for that to actually be plural.
So I'm gonna use my refactor -> rename
to just add an 's' to everywhere I'm using this.
Now let's test it out. When I hit start,
it should start counting down. And once that work session completes,
then you'll see the timer go to zero and our first checkmark show up.
And for every work session we complete, we get an extra checkmark
just to nudge us towards working a little bit harder.
The final thing that I want to address is our reset mechanism.
So we have this lovely reset button,
but it's not really doing anything at the moment.
What I'm going to do is create a new function here
which I'll call reset_timer.
And what this reset_timer is going to do is basically it's going to reset all
the checkmarks, reset the text inside the timer,
stop the timer and change this title back to the text that it originally had,
which is just the word timer. Now,
the hardest part about this is actually stopping the timer because what we have
to do is we actually need to tap into that window.after again.
But instead of calling after,
we actually want to call after_cancel. This way
we can actually cancel the timer that we had set up previously.
This is the thing that we want to cancel. And if we want to cancel it,
we have to give it a name and we have to put it inside a variable.
So I'm going to call this my timer.
But because this is going to be a local variable because it's created inside
this particular function, I actually have to bring it out.
I have to make it a global variable, so after create it up here,
but what value do I give it? Well, initially,
it's actually not going to have any value at all.
So it's going to start out as none. And then later on,
I'm going to tap into that global timer in order to get it to hold on to this.
Now, then once I want to reset my timer and cancel it, well
then I can actually tap into this global timer and stop the timer.
So now to actually activate this function, reset_timer,
we have to add it as a command to our reset button.
So where we create our button, I'm gonna add it as a command.
And remember, we have to get rid of the parentheses.
So now if I run my program and I start my timer,
you can see that as soon as I click this reset button,
it stops my timer and it doesn't continue.
So now all we have to do is the add
all of the things that we have to reset, for example, the text in here,
we want that to read 00.
So that was the timer_text from our canvas.
And then the other thing we want to do is the title label.
We want to set that to just read timer.
And finally,
we want to reset our check marks so that once you hit the reset button,
it resets this title label,
the timer text here stops the timer and gets rid of all the checkmarks, like
this. Pause the video and give that a go.
Alright. So the first thing we want to change is our timer text.
And because the timer text is created in the canvas,
we have a slightly different way of changing that.
So we call canvas.itemconfig,
and then pass in the thing that we want to change, which is the timer text.
And then the attribute that we want to change, which is it's text.
And then we change that to just say 00:00,
go back to the beginning. Now the title label is a lot easier to change.
We can say title_label.config,
and then we can configure its text to basically just read timer.
Finally, we're going to reset our checkmarks.
So we tap into our checkmarks' label again,
using config to change the text back to empty.
However, there's still a slight problem with our code.
What happens if while our timer is counting down
I hit the reset button and then hit the start button again?
Did you spot that? Our timer jumped from "Work" to "Break" because our reps are still increasing.
So far we haven't reset the number of reps to zero when we reset the timer.
So all we need to do to fix this bug is add: global reps
reps = 0  to the reset time function.
That's all there is to it! Now if we reset our WORK_MIN to 25, SHORT_BREAK 5, LONG_BREAK 20 or whatever
it is that you want it to be. Then once we hit run, we will end up with our final Pomodoro timer.
And it will be now ready for you to start practicing doing Pomodoros and improving your work and your
productivity.
So I hope you enjoyed making this fully functional tkinter application with me and that I hope you
will modify this, customize it, make it truly your own and be able to show off to us what it is that
you have done. Because this really is a useful application that you can use or you can get your friends
and your family to start using and show off your hard work.
Hey guys, welcome to 100 Days of Code. And today we are on day 29,
where we're going to be building a password manager.
So we're going to be doing this using tkinter.
And the real inspiration for this project came about because I was trying to
register
for a website where it asked for a password that was just insanely
complicated, something along these lines, or it has to be really long.
It has to include lots of different things,
it can't match your previous passwords. It just has a whole bunch of rules
and I really struggled coming up with a password that actually match all of their
requirements. And by the time that I came up with it,
I've already forgotten what the password was.
One of my favorite blogs is Coding Horror by a guy called Jeff Atwood.
And you might not know him by name,
but you will actually have used something that he's made.
He is one of the founders and original creators
Stack Overflow
which I'm sure by now you're well familiar with.
And even he was talking about how password rules are just really terrible.
They're so long and they're so complicated and they've even inspired
a really good XKCD comic,
which essentially tells the truth that through 20 years of effort,
we've successfully trained everyone to use passwords that are hard for humans to
remember but easy for computers to guess. This is the crazy state of things.
So we're going to be creating a program to combat that.
And it's going to be called MyPass, our password manager,
and we're going to use it to store and generate passwords.
For example, if I wanted to create an account on App Brewery,
then I enter the name of the website so that I know what this password is for,
I put in my email, and username is already prepopulated in my password
manager. And then all I have to do is to either come up with a password
that is hopefully not terrible, but I can obviously never remember,
or I can use the builtin generate password to just generate me a very complex,
very long password with all of the required numbers and symbols and all of that.
And once I'm done with that, then I can click add,
and I get a popup asking me if this is okay.
And if that all looks good, then I click Yes
and that data gets added to a text file,
which I have on my computer.
So this is not an internet-based service and you keep everything locally on your
computer,
which some people feel is a lot safer than using a third-party service
like LastPass or whatever else.
So this is what we're trying to build and it's got some really neat features.
For example, it's got some basic validations. So if you, for example,
leave one of the fields empty and you click add, you get a popup that tells you,
please don't leave any of the fields empty. Or if you generate a password,
then you can actually immediately use it by pasting it. What's happening behind
the scenes is as soon as I click on generate password,
then my password is saved onto my clipboard and I can paste it into the password
field on the website I'm trying to sign up for.
This is what we're going to be building today.
And it's going to use everything you've learned about tkinter
and we're going to be learning some new things that you can do with
tkinter as well. Once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and let's get started.
To begin, as always, head over
to the course resources and download the starting project as a zip file.
Now, once you've unzipped it, open it using PyCharm
and go ahead and take a look inside the starting files.
I've included a logo image
which is going to be used in our project.
And I've got also a very, very blank looking at main.py.
Now here comes a challenge already. To start out,
we're going to create a window using tkinter that has a title of Password
Manager.
And the only thing that it's going to have is just a canvas widget displaying
that logo image.
So the canvas is going to have a width and height of 200 pixels,
and the canvas is going to be padded from the edge of the window by 20 pixels on
all four sides
so that way it could look quite centered like this. And this image finally is
going to be bang in the center of the canvas.
So I want you to think back to what you learned yesterday about the canvas
widget and in the course resources,
I've linked to this page on the canvas documentation
including that all important create_image method.
Have a look through this for what the expected inputs are
and you can also scroll up to see more of the references on other things that
you can do with the canvas.
Or just have a quick look through yesterday's code if you need to.
But I want you to be able to create a tkinter program using all the things
that you've learned and when you run it,
it should look pretty much the same as this. Pause
the video and complete this challenge,
Okay.
So to begin, we're going to go to the very top of our file,
and I'm going to import all of the classes inside tkinter
and I'm going to use that to do my UI setup. As always,
I start out creating a window
and then give it a title.
And then I'm going to get my window to start out with my main loop.
Now in between, I'm going to create my canvas.
And this is from the canvas widget. Now this canvas widget, as I mentioned,
is going to have a height of 200 and a width of 200.
And in addition,
it's going to display this logo.png inside as the image.
So I'm going to create our logo image from the photo image class,
and then I have to provide the filename.
So the filename is just simply logo.png in this case
because they're both inside the same folder. So once I've created my image,
I can tell my canvas to create a image inside the canvas
and then I can specify the image name
and that is of course going to be my logo image. Now,
the other thing that I have to do before I can actually run my code,
because at the moment it's actually going to give me an error and the error
says tuple index out of range.
It's basically expecting some sort of a tuple to work on
and that tuple is the define what the X and Y position is of this image on
the canvas. So we do that by simply just adding the raw numbers.
So the X position of the center of the image is going to be 100,
because remember that the width is 200 so half of that is 100.
And similarly for the Y position, it's also going to be 100.
So this way we've got the X and Y position to find,
and we've created the canvas size. Now,
all we need to do is to get our canvas to have some sort of layout dimension.
I'm just going to start out by packing my canvas onto the screen because later
on, once we have more components, then we can think about using more fancy things
like the grid. Now, if I run this as it is,
then you can see that I've created my password manager window and I've created
my 200 by 200 canvas.
The only requirement I haven't yet satisfied is adding some padding between the
window and that canvas.
So let's do that using our window.config,
and I'm going to set the padding using the padx and pady.
And as we mentioned,
I'm going to set that to 20 on the X and 20 on the Y.
So now we get pretty much exactly the image that you saw in the demonstration,
and this is the end result we were looking for.
Did you manage to complete this challenge?
If not, be sure to review some of the lessons that we learned yesterday
where we went through the canvas widget in great detail.
But if you're happy with all of this code, then in the next lesson,
we're going to be learning more about the grid system and how to lay out a
complex user interface like this one. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you there.
To go from this to this will require not only some widgets to be added,
but a little bit more knowledge about how to lay out our widgets on the grid.
Because notice how here we've got a single entry that is spread across the right
side of the screen. But then down here,
we've got an entry that's only taking up a part of that space. Effectively
if we think about our grid,
this particular entry is actually taking up two columns.
So, how can we do this? To demonstrate this I've created a sandbox app.
So it's super simple,
all it has is a red label and a green label.
And you can see that the red label has a width of 20,
a height of 5 as does the green,
but the red is on row 0 column 0
whereas the green is on row 1 column 1.
So we get this kind of checkered kind of look.
If I decide to go and add another label,
let's call it b for blue and I give it a background of blue.
And then I give it the same width and height. Now,
if I put this new label onto the grid and I put it onto the next row,
so row 2, but the column I'm going to put it on column 0. Now,
I think at this point you can probably all predict where that label is going to
go.
And indeed it goes onto the very first left-most column and its on the third
row.
Now what if I wanted that blue label to go across the entire width so that it's
below the red and also below the green? Well,
you might think that I could simply just double the width, right?
Instead of a width of 20,
let's change it to 40. Surely that's going to stretch this label so that it goes
across the entire red and green label.
But unfortunately when I run this, you'll see instead, this happens.
The blue label is still within the first column.
And in fact it stretched that column to a 40 width and that red column is now
centered again in the leftmost or the first column.
And that blue is nowhere near the green label because it's not allowed to go
into that second column. So how can we solve this situation?
Well, the actual answer is
another attribute that the grid has,
which is something called a column span.
Now the column span is exactly what it sounds like
really. It's basically how many columns is this particular thing going to span?
So in our case, we want it to go across two columns,
column 0 and column 1.
So it should start out at column 0
but then span a whole two columns. And now when I run this code,
you can see we get our desired effect.
The blue label is now across the red and the green and it's spanning two
columns.
The link to this playground is in the course resources,
so feel free to head over there and give it a go
if you want to play around with this example. Now in our case,
if we break down the final layout we're looking for,
it's effectively a 3-column and 5-row layout.
So we've already got our canvas
which is actually going to go in the middle, so it probably the second column.
And then we've got the website, the email/username, the password,
and finally our two buttons.
Now I've laid out this entire user interface and I've specified the width of
some of these entries and buttons just because you'll need to do a bit of
tweaking around just to make sure that everything lines up with each other.
I've really done that ahead of time
and I've already worked out the sort of near-optimal width.
So what I want you to do is to use what we've learned about the grid column
span. So if we have our label, a button, new button and entry,
if I want this particular button to go across two columns,
then I have to change that columnspan
attribute to 2 and I have to specify which column it starts out in and how
many columns it's going to go across. Using everything you've learned so far
I want you to recreate this user interface.
Have a look at what's on-screen; these are labels, these are entries
and these two are buttons. Have a look at where they lie within the grid system and
how many columns they go across and also the width of some of these widgets
and see if you can recreate this user interface in your project.
So pause the video and give that a go.
Did you have a go at the challenge? Here's what we currently have,
and this is what you should have created upon completing the challenge.
If you haven't had a go at attempting to recreate this user interface,
pause the video now because I'm about to walk you through the solution. Again,
we're going to be within the UI setup section,
and I'm going to write my code below where I've got my canvas. Now,
the first thing I'm going to create
are actually all of these labels because they're relatively simple to layout
and they'll be a quick and easy job.
Okay.
Now
I've created three labels and it's time to actually put them onto the screen. Now,
because I'm going to be using grids I can't use pack in addition.
So I also have to put my canvas onto the grid.
The canvas is going to go onto the grid in row 0,
the first row at the very top.
And in terms of column it's actually going to be column 1,
the middle column. And then going down the list,
my website label and my email label and my password label,
they're all going to be on subsequent rows.
So row 1 and then row 2
and row 3.
And they're all going to be in the same column,
which is going to be column 0, the very first column.
Now, if I run this code and we take a look,
you can see that it looks a little bit weird just because this canvas is in
column 1 while these labels are in column 0. But that's fine.
It's gonna even out once we add the other components.
That's all the labels done. The next thing are the entries.
Now, as I showed you in the slide, these entries will have different widths.
So the website entry,
this one here, and the email entry are both going to have a width of 35.
While the password entry is only going to have a width of 21.
Now remember that the width is a property of the entry class.
It's not something that's related to the grid.
So if inside this grid method, you add something like width,
then this is not going to work and it's going to give you an error.
So that's a common source of error for students so be aware.
Once we've created our entries, it's time to lay them out using our grid.
Now, the first website entry is going to go into the same row as the website
label, so that row 1, but the column is going to be column 1
so it's the next one over.
Okay.
And the email entry is going to be in exactly the same column,
but just shifted one row down.
And finally
the password entry is going to be on the next row, so row 3,
and it's going to be in column 1  as well. Right now,
this is what it looks like.
And you can see that this doesn't look terribly bad
other than maybe I need to change this to
a capital P and I could probably add a colon to the end of each of these lines,
like this. Now the final step to do is to add the two buttons.
So one button has to go over here to the right of the password field
and one has to go at the bottom.
Okay.
Now, this generate password button is going to be on the grid
but it's going to be in the third column.
And in terms of row, it's going to be on the same row as the password,
which is row 3.
Okay.
While the add button is simply going to be in the last row,
right?
And this should be a button rather than a radio button.
So this is what we have so far.
This is clearly not what we wanted to have, which looks more like this.
And if I put it side by side,
you can see that the add button is far too small. Referring back to this,
we need to set the width to 36. So let's go ahead and add that.
Okay.
Now, that makes the button a lot wider, but it still doesn't solve
the fact that this generate password is actually in a completely different
column while we actually ideally want that button to cover the entire password
entry and also the generate password.
So we need this button basically to have a column span of 2
so that it spans both of these columns. And in fact,
so does the website entry and the email/username entry.
So let's fix that.
The website entry grid is going to have a additional keyword argument
which is the column span, and this is going to be set to 2.
And we're gonna add that to the email entry when it's on the grid as well,
and finally the add button.
So now you can see that we're getting pretty close, right?
Once we put in those columnspans,
you can see our layout has dramatically changed and everything
now looks a lot more aligned.
Now the alignment is not perfect because the generate password button is
actually just allowed to be the size that it needs to be.
And I've tinkered around with some of the widths and you can, of course,
try out your own widths and nudge it around a bit to see if you can change it.
But I think in terms of overall look, this is not bad.
The only thing I would add is maybe our padding of 20 around the side of the
window is actually not enough. Maybe we need to increase it a little bit.
If you want to,
you can actually change the padding to 50 so that you get a little bit more
white space and it looks a little bit less busy.
So this is the final design that we're trying to get to.
And now that we've set up all of our UI,
all that's left to do is to add the functionality.
And that is what we're going to do in coming lessons.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.
Now that the UI is all set up, it's time to go onto the next step
where we actually can start saving some of this data that the user is entering.
So that there's a couple of things I want to show you before we get started.
Firstly, notice how when we run our code at the moment,
it just launches our app.
But wouldn't it be nice if the cursor was already within the first textbox? That
means the user can start typing straight away when they launched the password
manager. To do that, you can of course dig through the docs,
but the easiest way is to get hold of that website entry and then call a method
on it called a focus.
And this will focus the cursor into that particular entry.
And you can see that right there.
Now the next thing that would be nice is when you're signing up for lots of
websites, at least in my case,
I often use just one email to sign up.
So wouldn't it be nice if when we launch our password manager that this email
field is already pre-populated with our most commonly used email?
Well,
we can do that by simply adding a starting value to that email entry.
And the way that we do that is through a method called insert.
Now insert it takes two parameters. And in fact,
you can actually scroll down to the insert method and you can see it describes
in detail that it takes an index
and also the string that you want to insert. The way that the index works is it's
basically where the cursor is.
If you wanted to insert it at the very beginning of that email entry,
then you could just put in zero.
That basically inserts this piece of text at the first zeroth character.
Alternatively, there's another useful index which is called end.
And this end comes from tkinter constants and its just a constant
that's gonna represent the very last character that's inside that entry.
For example, if inside your entry
you already had some text and you want to insert it after your text here,
then you would use the index as end.
But if you want to insert it at the very beginning,
then you would use the index as zero. Now in our case,
it shouldn't actually matter because our email entry will start out being
completely empty.
So I'm going to choose to insert this piece of text at the very beginning
and the text that I'm going to insert is just a example dummy email.
This is not my real email, but in your case,
if you were creating your own password manager,
then you could put down your own email so that every time you run the app,
it already starts out being pre-populated when that email that you've got.
So now the rest of the challenge is pretty much going to be up to you. Inside
this save password section,
what I want you to do is to be able to take the inputs that are put into the
website entry, the email entry and the password entry,
and when the user clicks on this add button,
I want you to somehow figure out how to save that data into a file called data
.txt.
This data.txt is going to take the website that the user entered,
the email that they entered and the password that they entered
and it's going to put it in here with a space in between and a pipe symbol that
you can find on your keyboard. Or in fact, you can format this however you like
because at the end of the day,
you're going to be the one looking at this file to find your emails and
passwords. So format it in a way that's comfortable for you.
But essentially, what we want to do is to transport things that the user types
into here,
the website that this password is for, their email and their password and the
moment that they press this add button to trigger some sort of function that
saves this information into a data.txt file.
And that format is the information like this.
And every time the user adds another entry,
it's going to be added on a new line and it's going to be appended to the end of
the previous entry.
So I know that it's been a little while since we last dealt with writing to
file. So I'll link to the documentation that's relevant to this challenge.
One is how to write to file using Python and you can see the demo code
which you can run and you can try out,
and then you're going to format that to work for your particular case. Now,
the other thing is the tkinter entry widget.
So there is the insert method that's going to be pretty useful.
But the other thing that you want to happen is once you press the add button,
you want all of this information other than the email to be cleared out.
So you're probably also going to have to take a look at the delete function.
And at the very top,
you can see it even shows you how to delete something entirely from an entry.
Using these two pieces of documentation.
I want you to be able to take this information,
put it into a data.txt file
and afterward, wipe clear this website entry and the password entry.
So that's all there is to it. There's going to be quite a bit of code writing.
So you have a think about it and go ahead and complete this challenge.
I'll wait for you and we'll go through the solution afterward together.
So the first thing I need to happen is when the user presses on the add button,
I need to trigger a function. So in this add_button,
I'm also going to add a command and I'm going to call my function save.
So I'm going to put that function inside the section save password.
Now this save function is going to write to a file
which is called data.txt,
or in fact, you can call it anything you want. Inside the save function
we want to be able to write to a particular file.
So we need to open the file and then we need to write to it.
And we can use the option a, to append to the end of the file.
Or write, which overrides any existing content or read,
which just reads the actual file. Now in our case,
every time we add a new password, we wanna add it to the previous passwords.
So we're going to need this append.
So let's go ahead and open a file
which we're going to call data.txt and we're going to open it using the
append mode. Now,
remember that when you're opening a file using the append mode or the write mode,
and that file doesn't exist, it's simply going to create it.
We are gonna open this and you can either save it to a file name,
so you could do it like this data_file = open,
or you might have remembered that previously we spoke about the with keyword.
So we can say with open this particular data file as our data file.
And what this allows us to do is it will close this file automatically without
us having to later write file.close.
So it's a much better way of working with files.
But if you didn't remember the with keyword,
don't worry. Using the open will still work. Now,
once we've opened our data.txt in append mode,
the next step is to actually add the pieces of data. Now,
how do we get hold of data from our entries? Well,
that's where the entry documentation comes in handy.
And you can see even at the very top,
it tells you that to fetch the current entry text, use the get method,
so the entry.get.
We can get hold of our website by getting hold of the website entry and then
calling .get.
And then we can do the same for email and password.
Once we've gotten all of these pieces of text,
then we're going to be writing it into our file.
So our data_file.write
and what we're going to write is a string
which I'm going to format using an f-string.
And I'm first going to put in the website and then space and pipe symbol,
space and then it's going to be the email
and finally, it's going to be the password. Let's check this out,
let's run it and see if it works
right?
Say we're signing up for Amazon, I'm going to use my normal username
and I'm going to create a password which is super insecure,
which you should never use.
But now I'm going to click on add. And after I've clicked it,
even though nothing has happened so far,
if we take a look inside our project folder,
you can see we've now magically created this data.txt file. And you can see
it's formatted our website, email, and password, all into that file.
So that's pretty much a success. Now,
the other thing I mentioned is that it would be nice to get some sort of
indication that it worked right? And for our application to be prepped and ready
for the next piece of data to be entered.
So we wanted to delete whatever text there's inside the website entry and the
password entry. If you take a look again at the documentation,
you can see that you can delete whatever is inside the entry by calling delete
and telling it to delete from a particular index to another index.
Now, there's more detailed if you actually scroll down to the actual method and
it tells you that it takes two parameters; first and last. First is the start of
the range and last is the end of the range.
And it tells you that if you omit it, it's only going to remove one character.
So that's not what we want.
We want it to remove all of the characters in a particular entry.
So let's start out with our website entry, call delete on it,
and we're going to start from index zero and go all the way to the end. In the
same way that we used our index
when we inserted our email to the email entry,
we moved the cursor to the very start, the zeroth character in that entry.
In this case, we're deleting from the zeroth character to
the end of the entry.
And then we can do the same for our password entry,
right?
And now if we run this code,
you can see that once I type something in and let's just generate another bad
password Qwerty. And by the way,
if I've called out any of your passwords, just for my sake, um,
and definitely for your own security, go ahead and change it.
These are really bad passwords. But either way,
I'm going to click add and you can see the moment that I've clicked that my
website and my password entries have now cleared out and it's now ready to take
the next entry. And back in my data.txt, I've now got
another entry.
But notice this, it's been added to the end of the previous entry,
but its on the same line. That's a little bit confusing.
Now you might remember this special character which is \n,
and that allows us to enter things onto a new line.
Let's delete everything that we've got in here so far and let's hit save so that
we can start from scratch.
Now let's run our program with that new line inserted.
And if I go ahead and add the website and let me think of another bad password,
um, password is a really terrible password. Now,
if I click add,
you'll notice that those fields disappear and that the password gets added into
here. Now, if I try and add another value in here,
so let's say-- then you can see that the next value got added in on the next line,
which is a lot better in terms of formatting.
These are just small things that make things look tidy and neat.
But the big part was remembering how to save things into a file and using the
documentation to get hold of the values inside our entries and putting it into
our data file.
One of the things you might have realized is that it's a terrible user
experience when the user enters a piece of data,
say a website and a password and they click add. Things sort of disappear,
but they don't really have a confirmation that this, in fact, did work.
So in the next lesson,
we're going to look at how we can create some popups so that we can show the
user what the result was of their action.
We can tell them if it was successful or if it was not, ask them to confirm
whether if they're happy with that data entry. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you in the next lesson.
Now in the last lesson,
we managed to get our password manager to start saving the data that we're
entering inside the password manager.
And we formatted it and put it inside our data.txt.
Now,
one of the things that was a bit of an issue in terms of user experience is
whenever the user actually enters their details into this password manager at the
moment,
it doesn't actually give you some sort of way of knowing that it was successful
or if it was not,
or actually getting them to check and verify that the data that they've entered
is definitely the one that they want to save into the file.
In order to do this,
we're going to learn about something else that you can do with tkinter
which is something called standard dialogs.
These are basically popups that your tkinter program can generate.
And one of the most popular standard dialogs are the message boxes.
And it's really, really easy to create these popups.
You can simply just import the message box module
and you can tap into methods like show info or show warning, show error,
or you can ask the user yes no, or OK
or cancel, ask a question yes or no,
ask to retry or cancel.
Now the screenshots where made in a Swedish version of Windows,
but we can actually try these out ourselves and start putting in some standard
dialogs so that we can give the user some feedback.
The thing that we really want to tell the user is the moment that the save
function is called it's because they pressed on the add button here.
But before we actually commit all of the current information to the file,
we want to check and make sure that they're actually happy with what they've
written.
So we can create a message box here and get them to check the details that
they've entered and then hit yes or no as to whether
if they want to save it. In order to use the message box,
we actually have to import the message box. Again,
it's from the tkinter module that we're going to import the message box module.
Now notice how this is not actually a class. So that's why,
even though we've said * which means import everything,
it actually only imports all of the classes, the constants,
but it doesn't import things like the message box,
which is simply just another module of code. And in fact,
if you right-click on it and go to implementation here,
then you can actually see this messagebox.py file and how it's implemented.
The thing that's important though is to actually put it into use. So we can use the
message box and call a method to show a popup.
The simplest type is just showinfo
which you only need to think about two things
really; a title and also a message.
So I'm just going to put title as title and message as message.
And you can see when I press add,
I get this up and it's just got the title and the message and you can't do
anything other than click OK.
In addition to showinfo,
there is actually a lot of other methods; you can ask yes or no,
ask retry or cancel. You can show an error or you can show a warning.
Now in addition, you can actually ask the user something.
So this generates two buttons, yes or no, retry or cancel,
OK or cancel, ask question is also yes and no, and we've also got yes,
no and cancel here. What I'm going to do is I'm going to ask OK
or cancel.
And what I want to ask the user is I'm going to set the title as the website
that they've entered
so that's going to come from here, and then I'm going to set the message as a
f-string.
So I'm going to say these are the details entered:\n.
And then I'll give them the email that they entered
and then a new line and the password that they entered.
And then after new line, I'm going to ask them, is it okay to
save?
If I go ahead and run this code,
you can see that when I type a website
say Amaazon
and I type in my password and I click add,
I get my popup and it says these are the details entered. This is email,
this is the password, is it okay to save?
Now what I want to do is when they click OK
then for that action to go through and for us to write to our data file.
But if they click cancel,
I want them to be able to go back to the screen and edit it if necessary.
In order to do that,
we have to receive the output from this method call,
which is going to be a boolean. It's going to be either true or false.
So I'm going to set that to is_ok.
Now if this is_ok  is true, well, in that case,
we're going to go ahead and do all of this. So write
to file and delete everything that's inside the entry.
But if it's not okay, then we're simply just going to do nothing
and the popup box will dismiss itself. Now,
if I run this code again and I type in some ### and I click add,
you can see if I click cancel, nothing happens, and I go back. But if I click
OK,
then all of that information is going to be to my data.txt like here.
Now it's time for you to have a go with the message boxes and these standard
dialogs.
But your job is to figure out how can we get our app to have a little bit of
validation because when they have an empty website and an empty password and
they click add,
you shouldn't really let them save an empty password and an empty website,
right? That's not right.
So we want to check to see if the length of the entries in the website or the
password is zero. And in that case,
we're going to bring up a message box
that's just going to tell them basically that, Hey,
you've left some fields empty. So this is what you're aiming for.
Let's say that you've left the website or the password empty and you click add,
you should get a popup that tells you, Hey, don't leave any of the fields empty.
And this should trigger when either the website or the password is empty.
So have a think about how you might solve that challenge and give it a go.
Okay.
All right. So here's where we get all of the information from our entries.
And this is also a good time to do this validation.
We can use an if statement to check, well,
if this website string has a length of zero,
then that means the user didn't type anything in there.
And we can use an or statement to check well,
if the password also has a length of 0, well,
in that case, they didn't type anything in there either.
Now you can also add validation for the email,
but because we have the email already pre-populated,
there's actually not much point here.
So if either they've left the website blank or the password blank,
then we're going to generate a message box and we're going to use the showinfo
message box. The title is just going to say
Oops, and the message is going to say
Please make sure you haven't left any fields empty.
And now when you run this code, if you've left either of these two empty,
then you are going to get a popup that tells you this.
Now we don't actually want the rest of this code to happen if this is true.
So let's go ahead and add an else statement as well so that we can indent all of
this so that we only continue forward
if in fact, the length of the website or the password is not equal to zero.
So in this case, when they leave it empty, you can say OK
and it just goes back to let you continue entering more details.
Now in the next lesson,
we're going to add another piece of functionality to our application
which is the generate password.
We've already seen how terrible the passwords are that we come up with from our
own heads.
So we're going to be using the generate password code that we created many,
many moons ago as one of our projects
and we're going to be embedding that into this application.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now what may seem like a long time ago,
we created a password generator project.
So this was in fact on day 5 where we took three lists,
letters, numbers, and symbols,
and we used it to generate a random list of letters, symbols,
and numbers
and then we shuffled all of those together and we turned it into a string to
create a very secure password.
Now I've modified the code a little bit,
just so that we don't need to use any inputs.
So we don't have to type anything in the console. Instead,
I've created a random number between 8 and 10 to pick 8 or 10 letters
and then 2 to 4 numbers and 2 to 4 symbols.
So what I want you to do is the head over to this link
which is in the course resources,
and simply just copy everything that's in there into your password generator
section,
because we're going to be using this code in our password manager so that when
the user clicks on this button,
we can generate them a random password and already pre-populate that field.
So they don't have to type anything
and they don't have to come up with a really complex password like this.
Once we've put our password generator code into the password generator section,
let's go ahead and reformat it. So let's put our imports at the top.
And as a challenge, I want you to take a look at these three lines,
look at what they're doing.
We've created an empty list and we're adding a random letter from this list of
letters. And then we have this for-loop
which basically creates a range from this random number,
so anywhere between 8 to 10,
and then we add a random letter to that password list. So this is a really
good opportunity for using list comprehensions instead,
because we can get rid of a lot of these for loops and do each of these things
in just one single line of code. It's also a good point for
a bit of revision.
I want you to have a think about how these things work and see if you can do the
same thing by changing these three sections into three list comprehensions.
If you're successful, once you run the code,
it should still work exactly the same way
and you should see a random password being generated and printed down here.
Pause the video and give that a go.
All right.
All right. So what I'm going to do is instead of creating an empty list,
I'm going to create three new lists.
One is going to be the password_letters and this list is going to be created,
of course,
using less comprehension and replacing these two lines of code.
Remember our keyword formats.
We have our new item for item in list.
Now, in this case, our list is actually not a list.
It's actually going to be a range because we're going to create a range using
this random number. So we generate a range between zero and this number minus
one. So we can pass in our number letters into here.
Each of the items is actually not important.
We don't actually need to use it so we can just use an underscore to replace it.
But what is important is what the new item is going to be,
because this is going to be created from random.choice
and we're going to be passing in our list of letters up here so that we pick a
random letter and we put it into our new list, password_letters.
And then we're going to check to see how many times we need to do this by
looking at the range. That line will replace these two lines of code,
and we can go ahead and do the same thing for the other two sections.
Yeah.
These three lines of code uses list comprehension to replace these for loops. So
we can delete those for loops and now we end up with three lists.
Now we want to combine these three lists into one list so that we can actually
shuffle it. So I'm going to create, again, this password_list,
and it's going to be created by adding our password_letters to our password_
symbols and our password_numbers.
So we're basically adding all these three lists together and putting it into one
big list, and then we're shuffling it up in order to get the final random list.
Now we can actually cut down on this code even further if we wanted to.
For example, instead of creating a separate variable here,
we could actually put it straight in like this.
And instead of calling random.randint,
we can actually say from random import the methods that we need,
which is choice and randint and also down here we're using the shuffle function
as well.
So now we can delete all the places where we have random and we can replace
these with just simply the randint,
and we can delete these three lines of code. And finally,
it's simply just shuffle and we shuffle our password_list. Now,
one last thing that I think is a good thing to point out is here
we've created an empty string called password
and then for each of the characters in our list,
we've basically added it to this password. Now that's easy enough,
but these three lines could actually be done in a more Pythonic way. In
Python there is a method called join
which is available on every single string.
So you could take a string like the pound sign and you could call the join
method on it.
And what it does is it will create a new string that combines all of the
elements in this iterable, John, Peter, and Vicky,
and it will separate them by whatever character you put here. Now,
this doesn't actually have to be a tuple.
It could be a dictionary and it could also be a list.
Let me convert this into a list.
And now if I go ahead and use the pound sign to join my list and run this code,
ou can see,
I end up with the same results. Now,
what if I actually delete this pound sign and I just have an empty string?
Well, this will work as well. And what it does,
it will join all of the elements in that list with no separation.
That's basically what we're trying to do here, right? So instead of all of this,
I can simply just write
" ".join,
and then pass in my list which is my password_list.
And this would be equal to my password.
And that replaces all of these lines of code. Right now
if I run my code as it is, you can see
I still generate my password and it still is super secure and super long
and in fact, you can modify that by changing how many password letters you want,
how many symbols, how many numbers,
and you can change these up to make it even more secure.
But we've greatly shortened this code from our day 5's work because we now
know things like list comprehensions,
and we've now learned the join method as well.
So this entire section is our password generator mechanism.
If we embed all of this inside a function
so we could call it generate_password
which is what it's pretty much going to do,
then we can call this function when the user presses on that generate password
button.
So let's add another command and add in our generate_password function here.
Now, what we don't want though is we don't want to print out the password,
that's not very useful for the user who's using a graphical user interface.
Instead, we want to populate this entry with the password.
Do you remember how to do that?
If you do, pause the video and complete this as a challenge.
If you don't, I'm to show you how to do it.
So it's the same way as what we did with our email.
Remember how we wanted our email entry to have a starting value,
the user's email. Well, we'll do the same thing here.
So we can tap into our password entry and we call the method insert.
Now the position that we want to insert our text is going to be at the very
start,
so the zeroth character, and the text that we want to insert into it is of course
our newly created password. So now
if I run my code, you can see as soon as I click on this button,
a random and beautifully complex password gets generated and populated in here.
Now, whenever I sign up for a new website,
then I can simply just type in the name of the website,
generate my password and hit add, and I'm already done.
Now we've incorporated our generate password functionality,
we're able to save all data to our data file.
The very last thing I want to show you
which is a really neat trick that you can do with Python is the ability to put
strings into the clipboard so that once we click generate_password,
this entire string,
I don't actually have to go ahead and highlight it and then copy it and then get
hold of it. Because in most cases, once I've generated my password,
I want to be able to immediately paste it into somewhere where I'm signing up
for, right? I want to be able to just simply hit
paste.
So how can we do that? Well, we can use a Python project
which is called pyperclip. And this is a cross-platform Python module
that just makes it so easy to work with copy and pasting for clipboard
functions. All we have to do is import it
and then we say, copy, and we pass in the text to be copied.
Or you can hit paste and it'll paste whatever is in the clipboard.
We're only really interested in these two parts.
So two lines of code gets us that functionality. Going back to our code,
scrolling to the very top,
let's go ahead and import our pyperclip.
Make sure that you spelled it right. You can check it against this link
which I've got in the course resources.
And once we type that you can see that PyCharm is already telling us you don't
have this package. So go ahead and install it.
Once it's been successfully installed (it's a very small module)
then we can use it.
And the part where we're going to use it is when we generate our password.
So once we've generated our password, we're going to call pyperclip
and we're going to call the copy method. Now, inside here,
we have to put the text that we want to copy into the clipboard,
which is going to be the password.
So now when we run and I generate a new password, right now
that password is already in my clipboard
and I can show you just by pasting it into here with command + v. That makes
it so much easier to work with our password manager
because all we have to do when we want to sign up to a new account is to simply
specify the website name
and then we've already got our email saved and we've got our password generated,
ready to paste into here.
So that should make it a lot easier to have very secure passwords and also a
place to check on what those passwords are when you forget.
I hope you enjoyed building this project with me today
and that you are going to put this into good use and make sure that all of your
websites and all of your data and all of your accounts are secured with a good
quality password.
All right.
Hey guys, welcome back to
100 Days of Code. Today is day 30
and to mark this milestone,
we're going to be learning about some more advanced Python topics,
such as errors, exceptions,
and also we're going to be learning how to save and load JSON data.
So that's all yet to come. First, we're going to be taking look at some of
the errors we've been getting and how to avoid crashing our app by handling those
errors.
Then we're going to take a look at this particular data format called
JSON
and this is probably one of the most widely used data formats for transferring
data across the internet between applications.
And this is going to be something that's going to be helpful,
not just in Python, but in a lot of other programming languages as well.
And once we've understood all of that, then we're going to put it together,
we're going to use it to improve our existing password manager.
By the end of today, not only will we be able to save websites,
generate passwords and add it to our database of passwords,
but we're also going to be able to search through that database.
So we could type in the name of a website, hit search,
and it'll tell us what the email and password is that we need to use to log onto
that website. Plus,
we're going to make this a lot safer by handling some of the exceptions that
could happen and make sure that in all circumstances,
our app will work exactly as expected.
So all of that and more is coming up.
Head over to the next lesson and we'll get started by learning about errors and
exceptions.
In this lesson, we're going to talk about errors and exceptions.
I'll show you what happens when a program encounters
different types of errors and how you can write code to handle these situations.
To begin, I've created a brand new project called day-30
and I've created my main.py file. Now notice how inside my project,
there is only one code file at the moment. There is no data files,
no text files, nothing. In this situation
if I was to try and open up a particular file that doesn't exist and I tried to
read it, what do you think would happen?
So we're going to use our normal syntax with open,
and let's just make up a file name. So a_file.txt.
And I'm going to save that as file
and I'm going to take this file and try to read from it. Right now
if I run this code, then this is what happens.
I get a trace back and I get a error
which is the file not found error, which kind of makes sense
given that there really is no such file existing inside our folder where we're
telling it to search. That's not great.
And if this happens somewhere within our actual program, so here
I've got the password manager completed project from yesterday.
If in this case, I made a typo in this word
so instead of data.txt, I wrote daata.txt.
And instead of the append mode, I had the read mode. Well,
in this case, what would happen is exactly the same thing.
So I could have a website, have a password,
but as soon as I hit add, then we get our file
not found error. And notice how as soon as that error happens,
it actually doesn't continue because on the next few lines,
we've actually got these two lines of code
which deletes the entry inside the website entry and also the password entry.
But those lines of code are not being carried out because it's hit a stumbling
block.
It has not found the file that we're trying to open and we're trying to read.
So I'm going to restore the code to how it was previously,
but this is a good point to start thinking about errors because we've come
across a lot of errors, right? Including errors like key error.
So for example,
if we have a dictionary that has just one key-value pair and we somehow try to
get a value from that dictionary
by tapping into a key that doesn't exist,
then when we run this code, we will get a key error, right?
It can't actually pick out the value from this dictionary because this key that
we provided does not exist in that dictionary. Now,
some of the other popular ones that you've seen are the index error.
So in this case
we have a list and we basically are trying to get hold of an item from this list
at an index that doesn't exist. So remember the index starts at 0, 1,
2, and 3. There is nothing at 3. So again, when I run this,
we get an error and this is an index error.
And the final error that we've probably been used to seeing is the type error
where we're trying to do something with a particular piece of data,
but we cannot do that thing with a particular data type.
Let's say we have a piece of text abc
and we try to print it this text plus the number five,
so a string plus an integer. And again,
when I hit run it, again we get a type error.
All of these types of errors we've actually come across already and
all that we've done so far is
we've just used it as an indicator to tell us, wait a minute,
something's not quite right. We got to go and fix our code.
But life doesn't really work out
so neatly most of the time. In a lot of cases, it actually follows Morphy's law
which states that anything that can go wrong probably will, eventually at some
point, go wrong.
So we have to plan for these eventualities just as, you know,
your car is probably not going to break down,
but you need breakdown cover just in case that it does happen. In programming
what we can do is we can catch these exceptions. When something goes wrong
and in that moment we catch that exception,
then it doesn't have to fail catastrophically.
We can actually fail more gracefully or we can decide that something else should
happen.
Here's what the code looks like when we're dealing with these exceptions.
We have try, except, else and finally.
These are the four keywords that are really important when it comes to handling
exceptions.
Now the first keyword try comes for a block of code where you're executing
something that might cause an exception.
So basically you're trying to execute a piece of line. In most cases,
it probably will work, but sometimes it just might not.
Now the next step is to define the except block.
So this is the block of code that you want the computer to execute
if there were more was an exception.
If something went catastrophically wrong and it was not the way that you
expected it to go, then carry out this piece of code.
Now the else keyword allows you to find some code to execute
if there were no exceptions. If you tried this thing that might fail
but actually it didn't fail. You succeeded and there were no problems.
Well then, in this case, you're going to do whatever is inside the else block.
And then finally, we have the finally keyword
which basically is just the block of code to carry out
no matter what happens. If this thing that you tried failed
or if it succeeded, Honeybadger, I mean, finally doesn't actually care.
So no matter what happens with trying this line of code,
this finally block is always going to be executed
and it's usually used for cleaning things up or tidying things up at the end of
some sort of code execution. Let's take our file not found exception
and let's see how we can make this a lot safer by catching that exception.
The thing that we're going to try is to open up this file. Instead of using the
with format,
I'm actually just gonna straight up create a file and set it to open this
particular file path. So a_file.txt.
Now this is the line of code that can cause an error and it will cause an error
in our case because we don't have a file called a_file.txt.
So this line of code is going to go inside a try block.
So let's indent that. So this is the line of code that we're going to try. Now,
the next thing we'll define is the except block. Basically,
once we've tried running this line of code,
and if there was an exception that was thrown when we were running it like the
type error or in this case, it would be a file not found error,
well then, in that case, we're going to do something different.
We're going to let's say print, there was an error.
So now let's run this code and you can see straight away,
there was an error because this file doesn't exist.
So this failed and therefore this line of code was executed.
It's almost a little bit like we have an if statement and the
if statement is checking to see if something fails, well,
in that case, this is where it looks to see what it should do next.
Now just printing there was an error is kind of pointless.
What we actually want to do is to make sure that we don't actually fail so that
whatever happens, we succeed. So if there is a good alternative,
then that's what we're going to put inside the except block.
What we're going to do instead
if this file doesn't exist and we can't open it is we're just simply going to
create it. To create a new file,
remember that you can open up the file
and you can open it using the write mode because when you're inside write mode,
then what this open method is going to do is it's going to try and find this
file and open it. But if it doesn't exist,
it's just going to create it. Right now if I run this code again,
I want you to watch inside the day-30 folder because as soon as I hit run,
you'll notice that a_file.txt gets created because we tried opening it.
It didn't exist.
So it went into the except block and it actually just went ahead and created this
file from scratch.
Now this file is of course completely empty because we haven't told it to do
anything, but we could, in fact, get our file and write something to it.
We can put all of that inside the except block if we want to. Now,
one of the things that's giving us a warning here with the except keyword is if
you hover over it, it tells you that this is too broad an exception clause.
And according to the PEP 8 recommendations,
it tells us you should never use a bare except
and the reason for this is because when you have an except  clause,
then it's actually going to ignore all errors. For example,
if inside here
let's say I decided to do something that was also going to create an error,
but not the same kind of error.
So now I have a dictionary with a key and a value,
but let's say I tried to print some sort of value from that dictionary
and I use a non-existent key.
So you can see that this dictionary does not have a key that is named this
so this line is going to actually give us a key error.
But now, notice what happens when I hit run.
Absolutely nothing. I don't get any errors.
And the reason for this is because inside the try block
it's first trying to open up this file and indeed that file exists.
So it moves on to the next line. It creates a dictionary called a_dictionary
and that it tries to get hold of this value with this key
from that dictionary.
Now this line actually fails and creates an exception,
but that exception is caught right here
and it simply tells it to go ahead and create a file called a_file.txt
which it will go ahead and do. So this is not what we want at all.
Instead,
we want our exception to catch a specific situation.
We want to say that in the exception that we have a file not found error,
then this is what we want to do. And now if I run the code again,
you can see when now getting that key error
and it's telling us that this thing worked, so it didn't generate a file
not found error.
But the next thing that it tried when it tried to print this value,
it got a key error.
So we can actually have multiple exceptions. Instead of just except file
not found I can also say except key error and in this case,
I'm just going to print that key does not exist. Now, if I hit run,
I get no errors, but I do catch that exception
and I have this print statement executing. In addition to simply catching an
exception using
except, you can also get hold of the error message that would have normally
printed had we not had the exception called.
Normally, you would get key error and it would give you a message that tells you
which key was the problem.
If we catch our exception and we still want to get hold of that error message,
then we can say
except key error as error message.
And this means we can get hold of the error message that was generated from this
exception if it does occur. Instead of saying that key does not exist,
we can now take this as an f-string and we can say, the key, and we pass in the
error message right here.
So now I hit run again and it tells me the key 'sdfsdf' does not exist,
which is a lot more useful than simply saying the key does not exist.
So you can try, you can catch exceptions, you can catch other exceptions,
you can also get hold of the error message and use it when you catch the
exception. Now, the next keyword we mentioned was the else keyword
and this block of code is going to execute when the thing that you're trying all
succeeds. So if it managed to open up the file,
it managed to print this item from the dictionary
and there were no exceptions that were thrown from this block of code,
then it's going to jump to the else block. So what else do you want to do?
Well, maybe I actually want to read from this file,
so file.read,
and we save this as our content.
And then we go ahead and print our content. Now,
remember, if this file doesn't actually exist,
this else block is never going to be triggered.
So if I go ahead and simply delete this file
and I hit run,
you can see that this else block does not occur because it tried to do this,
it failed
and so it ended up jumping into the except block and it generated that file.
But now that that file has been created, the next time I hit run,
then this line of code is going to succeed and now it catches the next error in
that try block. So if I change this to a key
that it actually will recognize, then that next line also succeeds
and finally it gets to this block and it actually prints out the thing that's
inside a_file.txt which is just the word something.
So we've now got try, except, else,
and the last thing I want to show you is the keyword finally.
So this finally is basically some code that's gonna run no matter what happens.
And in our case,
the most appropriate thing to do here is actually to close down the file because
we're not using the with keyword
so our file would actually stay open if we actually had an exception. And I'm
going to go ahead and print
File was closed.
Now our code basically will open up this file
and no matter if it succeeded or if it failed,
it's going to close down that file so that we don't end up with an open file
that we're not doing anything with. So finally is not often used,
but sometimes it can be useful when you want some code to execute
no matter if the code you are trying is succeeded or failed. In the next lesson,
I'll show you how you can raise your own exceptions.
In this lesson, I'll show you how you can generate your own exceptions
in case your code encounters unexpected situations.
So these are the four keywords are most important when it comes to error
handling and catching exceptions.
The final keyword that is related is one called raise.
And what this allows us to do is to raise our own exceptions.
For example,
let's say I decide that at the very end of all of our file,
no matter if this file went through or if it didn't, if there were an error
if there wasn't error,
I'm still going to raise an exception. And to raise an exception
all you have to do is tap into one of the known exception classes.
So let's say I just decided to raise a key error. Now, when I hit run
you can see no matter what happened, and in fact, there is no error.
I decided to raise this error and that's what I see right here.
I could change that to a type error,
and that is what will crash my code.
And I can even specify a message along with this error.
So I could say raise a type error and let's just say the message is,
and you can see now when it runs, it hits that type error. And it says,
this is an error that I made up. So when might you want to raise errors?
Well,
let's comment out all the code that we have because we have that type error at
the end so it's always going to crash the code no matter what.
So let's comment it out and let's start from scratch.
Let's say that I decided to calculate the body mass index or the BMI of
somebody's and I'm getting them to input their height as a float.
So this is going to be their height in meters and their weight as an integer.
Now I can calculate the BMI by taking the weight / height * height.
And you can either do this and wrap it inside some parentheses,
or you can use the power function or even better
you can actually use the builtin exponent, so height to the power of 2.
No matter which way we use, we can print out the BMI.
But if I provide a height that is just an unrealistic non-human height,
lets say there were 45 meters tall,
like some sort of four storey building.
And then I gave them a weight, so let's say they are 67 kilos.
Then obviously a mistake has been made somewhere in the height, right?
Because this is just not within the normal human range.
This is like Godzilla's height. If I go ahead and hit enter,
you can see that we get at BMI and it is calculated correctly
and there are no errors because everything is perfectly valid other than the
fact that this height should not really ever go over 3 meters.
In this case, we might want to raise our own exception.
So we can go ahead and say that if the height is greater than 3 meters,
well, in that case, it's probably not a valid height.
So we can go ahead and raise a value error.
So this is an error that says that whatever value was entered
as the argument is probably wrong.
And we can accompany that with a message.
Human height should not be over 3 meters.
Now, when we run our code and the user mistakenly types
a wrong height, then it's going to actually give us this error
and it won't proceed to give them an inaccurate BMI.
So this is how you might raise your own exceptions
when there are certain things that are not caught by the code because it's
perfectly valid code, but it's in fact going to generate the wrong results.
Now that we've seen all of these aspects of exceptions,
I want you to have a go at catching some exceptions that can commonly occur.
So head over to the next lesson where I've got an exercise for you.
Now that you've learned some of the theory around error handling and catching
these exceptions and handling them,
then we're going to put all of that knowledge to practice by completing a couple
of code exercises. So you're going to hand over to the Repl.it coding exercises
which you'll find in the course resources,
and the one that I want you to complete is day 30.1 index error handling.
So this is the starting code. And if we hit run, you can see that immediately
we get a error, and it is the index error telling us that list index is out of
range.
Your job is to fix this code and catch the errors so that it no longer causes a
crash like this. Have a look through the instructions,
pause the video and complete the
challenge.
The problem here is that we're calling this function, make_pie,
which takes a index number
which is used to pick out a particular item from our list of fruits. Now,
if we try to get hold of the item at index four
which is way beyond the number of items that's in this list,
then we're going to get this index error.
What we're going to do instead is when this happens and we try to pick something
out of the list that doesn't exist,
we're just going to print out the default output, which is just
Fruit pie. The part of our
code that is prone to errors is this line right here.
So that is what we're going to trap inside a
try block. So the idea is
try this, and if it fails, so in the case where there's an exception,
then do something else. Now,
except the fact that we're not just going to use a broad stroke
except because that means it's going to catch all errors and it's going to do
this no matter what type of error. Instead, we want to be more specific
and we want to say, except in the case of an index error,
same as what we see being thrown right here, well then in that case,
we're going to do something a little bit different.
We're just going to print the words fruit
pie. However,
if this thing that we tried succeeded,
then we go into the else block. And in that case,
we're going to get a hold of the fruit and we're going to add pie to the end of
it. So now if I hit run,
you can see that we get fruit pie being printed and there's no more errors.
And our program is no longer crashing.
So did you manage to complete this coding challenge?
If not, be sure to go back to the last lesson and review some of these key words
and what they're used for. Otherwise, head over to the next lesson where there's
another coding challenge waiting for you.
Now that you've handled index errors,
we're gonna handle a different type of error in this coding exercise.
We're going to look at key errors. So in this case, again, when I hit run,
my code is going to crash and I get a key error.
And the reason is because I am looping through this list of dictionary objects
and what I'm trying to do is I'm trying to get a hold of all of the likes from
each of these Facebook posts.
So imagine you have a whole bunch of Facebook posts and you want to know how
many likes did you get in total this month? Well,
you might get some piece of data that looks a bit like this,
a list of dictionaries.
And what you're essentially trying to do is you're trying to loop through every
post inside that list
and you're trying to get a hold of the total likes by adding the existing number
to the number of likes for each post.
The key error occurs because some of these posts actually have no likes.
So that key doesn't actually exist. And that's why we get this error.
So I want you to have a look through the instructions and see if you can fix
this code so that we no longer have these errors. Essentially, if a post
doesn't have many likes, you're gonna treat it as zero likes.
Pause the video and complete this challenge.
Okay, so the key part that we need to fix is inside here.
Now, what we're going to do is inside this for loop,
we're going to add a try statement so that this line of code is inside the try
block. This is the thing that we're going to try,
and this is the particular part that might fail. Now, if it does fail,
we can catch it using an except.
But we're going to be more specific than just except. We're going to say,
except in the case of a key error
which is the problem that we're coming up against right now. Basically,
if we try to fetch a particular value from this dictionary
using a key that doesn't exist,
then this is the block that we're going to enter. And so inside this block,
we're going to either add a zero to our total likes or alternatively,
an even easier way is we can just say pass.
So in the case where we generate a key error,
we're just going to skip and then the code is going to continue running,
which means it's going to get to the end and it's going to loop back to the next
post in our list of posts. So now if I hit run,
you can see that I actually get the total number of likes being printed because
it's looping through all the posts in our list, and for the ones which have
that key
likes, it adds the number from the value of that key to our total number of likes.
But if we get a key error,
then we simply pass and we don't add any numbers at all.
This is how we can solve this particular situation. In this solution
it doesn't matter if you pass or if you simply said total likes plus equals
zero. It doesn't actually matter what you do,
as long as you handle this particular exception
and you do something to address the fact that some of these posts don't have a
like key.
Have a look through the solution code if you want to on Repl.it.
But otherwise, head over to the next lesson
and we've got a final coding challenge for you to try out exception handling.
I'll see you there.
Now for the final coding exercise,
we're actually going to jump into a previous project that we created.
This is the NATO alphabet project that we created a few days ago.
And it's pretty simple.
All it does is it takes the data that's inside this nato_phonetic_alphabet.
csv,
and it uses that to create a dictionary so that we have each letter as the key
and the actual phonetic alphabet as the value for each of those keys.
Now, if I go ahead and hit run,
you can see that the entire phonetic alphabet dictionary is printed here
and this is the structure of that dictionary. Now,
the next thing it asks us is to enter a word and it takes that word and creates
a new list using list comprehension that matches each of the letters to the
correct phonetic alphabet. So Angela becomes Alpha November Golf Echo
Lima Alpha.
So you should remember all of this from creating this project a few days ago.
Now,
what we're going to do is we're going to update and refresh this project so that
it's even better than before. Now,
if you don't have access to the final project of this NATO alphabet project,
then don't worry. Just head over to the course resources for today's lessons
and you'll find a starting file that matches what you see here precisely.
Now your job is to address a particular situation because we're relying on the
user to enter a word.
Then if they enter something that is actually not in this dictionary,
let's say they entered just a number, 1234,
then we will get a crash and we get a key error in this case.
Now what we want to happen instead is for us to enter a word and we enter
something that's complete nonsense. We hit enter.
And it tells us that the sorry, only letters in the alphabet please.
And then it goes back to give us that same prompt again.
And if we keep refusing and we keep typing numbers,
then it's going to continuously give us this feedback until we actually end up
typing something that contains only letters in the alphabet
and it actually generates the phonetic alphabet for us.
This is the goal that we're trying to achieve. And in order to do this,
you're going to have to use your skills of exception handling.
Have a think about how you might achieve this,
pause the video and complete this challenge.
Now that we know what we're aiming for, the next step is to actually try to get
there. Now we know that the part of the code that is prone to error
or can occasionally be problematic is this line right here,
because we're going through this phonetic dictionary and we're passing it a key and
that key depends entirely on what the user puts into this input.
So that means if they put something that is a number and it doesn't exist inside
the phonetic dictionary, that's when we get our key error.
So this is the line that we want to put behind a try block.
Like this.
And when we try out this line and if it actually fails and we end up with an
exception, then we want to catch that exception.
But we want to catch the specific exception, which is the key error. Now,
what do we want to do when we actually have an exception when that key doesn't
exist? Well, it means that the user entered something into the input
that was not a letter from the alphabet.
So we're going to give them some feedback.
We're simply going to use a print statement to print 'Sorry,
only letters in the alphabet please.' Hopefully that way they will learn
and they will only write letters instead of trying to type other things like
symbols or numbers. Now,
if everything went well, so in the else case,
then we actually want to print out the output list.
Because if this line succeeded,
then we will have that to print out to the user. Now,
the only problem here is if we run the code as it is right now,
we can enter a word, so let's try something that's not a word,
and we get that feedback, but our code ends.
So if we want our code to repeat so that we ask the user for a word again,
then we're going to have to have some sort of mechanism like a loop or a
function. So I think in this case,
the best thing to do is actually to create a function which I'll call generate_
phonetic.
And this function is going to contain all of this code.
So in order to run this function,
we of course have to call it outside of the function.
So once the code runs down to here,
it sees this line and it will run all the code inside this function.
But what we also want to do is if there was the case of a key error where the user
typed in something wrong,
then we want to give them the opportunity to type in something again.
So we want to be able to run this line of code again.
The easiest way of doing that is to simply call this function right here.
So that way, if they typed in something wrong, we give them some feedback
and then we go to the very start of this function once again,
and we get them to type in a new word using this input.
And then we can see if that was valid or if it was not and deal with that
accordingly. So now when we run our code,
it won't generate any errors,
but instead it gives me some feedback and tells me to enter another word.
So this is more of a real-life implementation of error handling,
making sure that we are validating and checking the user's inputs and addressing
these situations ahead of time using exception handling.
Now that we've taken a good look at exception handling, in the next lesson
we're going to go back to our password manager project and use the skills that
we've learned to improve it even further.
So, for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
The goal is to take our password manager to the next level.
And in order to do that, we need to add a search functionality.
It's not good enough just to look through the data file anymore.
What we want to be able to do is the type a website into the website entry,
and then hit search
and we get a pop up showing us our email and the password that was saved for
that website. So this is the goal.
But where we're currently at is we have a text file
which contains the name of the website, the email and the password.
This is very difficult to search
and this is a really terrible format to work with.
So we're going to be leveling up our data storage in our password manager
and we're going to switch from saving data straight to a text file to a fancier
data format, which is called JSON. Nope,
this is not the latest hottest DJ on the block.
It's actually JSON,
which stands for JavaScript Object Notation.
This was something that was designed originally for JavaScript
but because it has such a simple structure and it's so easy to understand and
work with that it's been adopted by many, many different fields,
including Python.
This is probably one of the most popular ways of transferring data,
especially when you're transferring data across the internet.
So this is what we're going to be learning about.
And for those of you looking at this slide,
you might've already realized that it's kind of similar to the dictionaries
that we've been working with in Python, right?
A JSON is essentially composed of a bunch of nested lists and dictionaries,
and it has that key value pair data structure.
This is essentially what we're aiming for so that we can store our data in this
format
and we'll be able to easily load up this data and search through it for the
particular website that we want the information for. To work with JSON data in
Python, we can use the inbuilt JSON library,
and we're going to use it to write, read,
and update data to a JSON file. To begin.
I'm going to simplify our code a little bit.
I'm going to get rid of this message box, which asked the user OK
or cancel. We're just going to assume that once they click add,
then they're happy with email and password.
So now that we've cut down that little bit of code,
it makes this a little bit easier to understand.
All that we're doing here is we're checking to make sure that the length of the
website entry and the length of the password entry is equal to zero.
And you might still have the length checking for the email entry,
but remember that at the end of previous lessons,
we actually inserted a default value.
So we can actually skip that check as well if you wanted to.
The reason why we want our code as simple as possible is so that when we're
working with the JSON and we're learning about how to work with it,
as long as everything else is simple,
then we can focus on the new things that we're learning. In this case,
instead of opening a data.txt file,
I'm going to change the data format to a .json.
And instead of using the append mode,
I'm going to use the write mode because I'm going to be writing to this data.
json file. Now, in order to write to a JSON file,
we don't use this line of code. Instead,
we use a method called json.dump,
and that, of course, requires us to import the JSON module
which should be inbuilt to Python so you don't actually have to install it.
Now, once we've imported our JSON module,
we can say json.dump.
And this takes a number of inputs, but the most important
are the things you want to dump and the file that you want to dump it to.
The data that we want to put in here should go in as a dictionary.
Essentially, what we want to create is a new dictionary
which I'll call new_data and it's going to be a nested dictionary.
So the first level key is going to be the website,
because this is what we're going to be searching through eventually.
And the website is going to, itself, contain a dictionary.
Now this dictionary contains two keys, the email,
and also the password.
The values for each of these are pretty self-explanatory,
it's the email that we got from this line of code and the password is the
password that we got from this line of code.
Now that we've created this new dictionary called new_data,
well that is what we're going to use to dump into our JSON file.
Let's go ahead and dump our new data. So that's the first input. Now,
the next input is going to be the data file that we want to put it into.
So that is going to be the file that we opened up inside this line.
Let's provide our data file as the location to dump this data.
And now if I go ahead and hit run
and I create a new entry for my Amazon website password, generate the password,
hit add,
then you can see that we've got our brand new data.json file
that's just been created. So just as a quick reminder,
when you open a file in write mode, if that file doesn't exist,
it will actually create it. So we've created this new file, data.json,
and we've dumped the data that we entered into that file.
So now if I open this up,
you can see we've got a JSON format in here and we've got our Amazon website
and all of its associated data.
Notice how this data is not very easy to read for a human.
So we can actually improve that by adding one other argument.
And it's an argument called indent. This,
we can provide the number of spaces to indent all the JSON data so that it
becomes much easier to read.
So I'm going to go ahead and delete everything that's in here and I'm gonna run
the code again. And this time,
once I save this data into my data.json,
you can see everything is all indented and it's much easier for the human to
read.
Now that we've seen how we can write data to a JSON file,
the next step I want to show you is how you can load data from the JSON file or
how to read from it. To read JSON data
te use the JSON module and we call the load method.
So I'm going to go ahead and comment out this line of code.
And now that I've actually got some data in my data.json file,
I'm going to try and read from it.
We call the json.load method and we pass in the file path,
or you can see here the fp.
So that's the only required input.
The file that we're going to pass in is our data file
which we opened up over here
ad what we're going to do is we're going to change this from write mode to read
mode. Once we've loaded up the data,
we're gonna save it inside a variable called data
and then I'm just going to print it out. So when I hit run right now,
and I simply add any sort of gobbledy goop,
but as long as I can hit the add button,
it's going to trigger this part of the code.
And now if we take a look inside our console,
you can see that data is being printed down here,
but without any of these indentations or any of the formatting. Instead,
what that load method does is it essentially takes this JSON data and
converts it into a Python dictionary.
So this data,
if we actually do a type check on it,
you can see it has a type of dictionary.
This is just a normal Python dictionary.
So essentially we can use json.dump and json. load to serialize
and deserialize from JSON data to Python dictionaries.
And it allows us that free interchange of information.
We change it into a JSON to store it,
and then we take it out of storage and turn it into a Python dictionary to
easily work with it in our code.
Now that we've seen how to write,
how to read, the last thing I want to show you is how to update data.
Because if we have a new piece of data come in,
we want to add to this JSON but we don't want to overwrite it.
But we also don't want to just append to the end of it,
because as you can imagine if we had something that we just appended to the end,
that's not a valid data structure
and that's why we're getting all of these errors. Instead of doing it manually,
we're going to use the builtin method json.update.
And here's how it works. So we've already got some data inside our data.
json file and I'm going to change this from read again, back to write.
And what we want to do is we want to take that data and we want to update what's
existing in there with the new data that's being passed in. To do that
we first have to load up the data, so I'm going to uncomment this line,
and once we've gotten hold of the data,
we're going to say data.update.
And we update it with the new data. What's happened so far is we have our data
loaded up into a dictionary,
we use the update method to update that dictionary with some new piece of data.
Now,
the next thing we want to do is we want to actually write that data back into
this file.
So we have to use this line of code using json.dump.
But instead of dumping the new data,
we're going to dump that data that we updated right here.
Essentially what we're doing here is a three-step approach.
We're reading the old data, we're updating old data with new data,
and we're finally saving the updated data. Here
we've got two things happening. We've got reading and we've got writing.
So we can split this code into two sections. First,
we open the file in read mode, we get hold of the data,
we update the data and then we open up the file again.
But in this case, we open it in write mode.
This time we're going to dump the data that we've updated over here into that
data file using this particular indent format.
And once we written to file,
and we delete all the text from a website and password entries and these lines
of code now replace our previous functionality where we were saving just plain
text to our data.txt. Let's go ahead and run it and test it out.
Currently, we have a single entry inside our data.json.
So if we go ahead and add a new entry,
say for eBay, and we generate password, click add.
If we go back to our data.json, you can see how it's now been updated.
This entire JSON has now been updated to have two entries,
Amazon and eBay. It didn't just append it.
It actually added it into the dictionary
and that's all thanks to that update method.
And once it updated that data,
then we told it to save the updated data back into the data file and wipe all of
the previous data. So now that we're able to read,
write and update JSON data,
the next step is to think about what situations might this fail.
And one of the biggest problems we have at the moment is we're trying to open up
this file, load up the data and update it.
But if we actually had no data in here,
say the first time we ran our program, or indeed,
if we didn't actually have this data.json file,
then you can see that the first time I run it and I tried to save a password,
then it's going to crush and we get some exceptions being thrown.
But we know all about exceptions now. So in the next lesson,
that's what we're going to tackle. For all of that,
and more, head ever to the next lesson.
So in the last lesson,
we looked at how we can use this JSON format to save our data and to load
our data into our program.
But one of the problems that we have is if we run our program from scratch
where we don't have that data.json file created,
then the first thing that it's going to encounter once it lands inside here is
it's going to try and open a file that doesn't exist.
And what happens then? We get a file
not found error because there is no such file data.json.
So what can we do? Well,
we already learned about dealing with exceptions and handling them so that we
don't end up in these situations.
So now it's time to put your knowledge into practice inside a real project.
And I want you to think about how you can catch that particular exception,
how you can get it to work so that if this fails,
then we simply create a brand new data file.
But if it does work, then we can simply load up the data,
update the data and write the data.
So the actual implementation I'll leave up to you.
But what you want to be able to do is to not have a data.json file and run
your code, and it would not crash
and instead it would create a brand new data.json file with the new data.
But if you had already got some old data, then it should simply just update and
write it to file. Pause the video and see if you can complete this
as a challenge.
This always starts with analyzing which part of our code is the part that's
going to fail or likely to fail at some point. And in our case,
it's this line right here,
opening this line in read mode is dangerous because if this doesn't exist,
then we get that file not found error.
So what we can do is we can put this inside a try statement.
Try opening this file and try reading the data that's inside.
Now, if this fails, however, then we can catch it
and we're going to catch a very specific type of exception,
which is the file not found error exception. Now,
when this exception happens,
what we want to do is we want to create a new file
which is going to be our data.json. So at this point,
remember it doesn't yet exist. And we're going to open it in write mode.
And this data file is going to be used so that we can write to it
and we can dump our newly created data up here.
Remember, when the user hits the add button,
then everything they've typed in these entries gets aggregated into this
dictionary
and that dictionary is what we want to dump into this new data file.
So we'll get hold of that new data and we'll dump it into the data file.
And again,
we'll keep the indent to four spaces just so that we can read it more easily.
Now this is what should happen if the file's not found.
But if the file was found and it already exists,
then we're going to tap into the else statement. And in the else statement
what we're going to do is we're going to get hold of the data which we managed
to get because this block of code succeeded, and in the else block
what we're going to do is we're going to update the data with the new data. Now,
this else block is only going to be triggered
if everything inside the try block was successful.
So that means by the end of this block,
we have this data which holds onto all of the existing data from that data file
and we update that data with the new data which is this dictionary here.
Now, after we've updated that data,
we want to be able to open up data.jason in the write mode
and then dump this updated data from here into that data file.
And then once all of this is done,
no matter if there was an exception or if there was no issues,
we're going to still need to delete everything that's inside the website and
password entry.
So we can even add a finally keyword right here.
So this is the final code that deals with our exception.
We have our try block which can fail, we have our except block
which deals with any failures that occur, we have our else block
which has the code that needs to be run if there were no issues,
and finally, at the very end no matter if there was an issue or no issue,
we have a block of code which clears our website and password entries.
Now you might've noticed there's a little bit of repetition here with the
writing to file. So if you want to,
you could in fact create a separate method somewhere up here.
But I'm actually going to keep this as it is just because I think when you look
at this code, if you had any issues and you wanted to review it,
this is much easier to understand and reason about compared to a separate
function.
Feel free to refactor this code and make it as short as you want.
But this is the version I'm going to keep
just so that if you had any issues and you want to take a look at it,
it's there for you
and it's easy to see the try, except, else, and finally blocks with all of the
code together in one place.
Now in the next lesson,
we're going to be completing the functionality of our password manager.
We're gonna add that all important search functionality
which is going to look through our JSON, fetch the results for a particular
website, and then show it to us in a popup.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In the previous lessons today,
we looked at how we can use the JSON format to store and load data into our
program.
We also looked at how we can use the try, except, else, and finally keywords to
handle exceptions in our program to make sure that it doesn't fail and end up
crashing our program so the user ends up with a bad user experience.
Instead, we can anticipate the things that might happen. For example,
the first time when we run our program,
we might not have a data.json file and we deal with it accordingly.
Now, all that's left to do is to put in the last bit of functionality,
which is the search functionality, because after all,
we don't want to be digging through a JSON file to find out all email and
password combinations for the websites that we've stored.
So what we want to be able to do is to add a search button
and it's going to look very similar in size to the generate password button
and it's going to be in the same grid column. Now,
when we type in a website and we hit search,
it's going to look through our JSON, find that data,
load that data up and look through it for a key that matches the one the user
typed in. If they find it,
then we get a pop up showing up and it tells us the email and the password
that's associated with that account.
So you've actually done all of this before. Creating tkinter widgets,
laying out tkinter widgets,
creating message boxes or these popups and giving it a title,
giving it a message.
You've also seen how you can load JSON data and get the data in the format of a
Python dictionary. Now, once you have the Python dictionary,
then you can use your usual dictionary methods to try and get hold of the data
that's inside. And finally,
you also know how to deal with exceptions.
So remember, there might also be an exception in this case,
because if this was the first time that we were running this password manager,
and in fact,
we hadn't stored any websites or any emails or passwords in our database,
then if you hit search, it might actually just give you a file
not found error as well. So there's quite a few components involved,
but I'm pretty sure that you can actually get this to work.
So the end outcome you're looking for looks something like this in terms of
layout,
and you should be able to test this so that when you start out without a data
.json file and you hit search, it should tell you error,
No data file found.
But, if you had saved a password under that name and you added it to the
database, then you try to find it,
then it should find you the email and the password that you saved.
So this is what you're aiming for
and I'm pretty sure that you can do it with just a little bit of thought and
a little bit of time spent problem-solving. Once you're ready,
pause the video and give this final challenge a go to complete the password
manager
project. Good luck.
Alright, so I hope
you gave that a good go. And as I always say, if there's no struggle,
there's no learning.
So make sure that you've allocated at least 20 minutes to trying things out and
figuring things out and debugging and just messing with the code yourself before
you're coming to the solution. But all right,
I'm going to walk through the solution with you together.
And the first thing we're going to do is we're going to add a button next to our
website entry.
So right here. Now notice how we've got our three columns in our grid system.
So our search button is going to go in pretty much in the same column as our
generate password button. So let's go ahead and create our
search button.
This is going to be a button with the text that says
Search.
Now, once we've created that, let's go ahead and lay it out
uusing the grid system.
Now the search button is going to go onto the grid in the same row as the
website label and the website entry. So that is row 1.
So let's go ahead and add row equals 1 and column-wise,
it's going to go in the same column as the generate password.
So that is a column 2. Now, if we run our code, as it is
however,
you'll see that the search button seems to be sitting inside the entry.
And the reason is because initially when we created this entry,
we gave it a column span of 2
so that it spans this second and third column.
So we have to change that.
Let's go and find our website entry and delete this column span equals 2.
So now you can see that this has a column span of 1,
so it's only in this middle column,
but it's so large that it's pushing the rest of our layout out of the way.
So what we need to do is we need to make this entry
the same width as the password entry
so that it'll actually fit into our layout.
So our password entry has a width of 21.
So our website entry is also going to need to change down to a smaller size.
Now you can see the entry is now the same size and its looking a lot better. If
you want, and this is really not strictly necessary
but I think it's quite neat, is you can tweak and adjust the width of this search
button so that it's roughly the same as the generate password button.
Now this button is this width because it's what is needed to accommodate all of
the words in that button, but we can manually change the search button
so that it's about the same width.
And in this case, I'm literally just using trial and error to figure it out. Width as
10 looks maybe a little bit small, let's try width of 13
and it looks just about right. Now that I'm done with my layout,
it's onto the next part which is adding functionality.
Now the functionality is going to come when the search button is pressed.
So I'm going to add a command to this
and the command is going to call a method which I'll call find_password. We've
got generate_password and we'll now have find_password.
Now I'm going to go and create my find_password.
And just because we've got all these sections set up, I'm going to add
another section which I'll call find_password. Inside
the section is where we're going to be creating our
find_ password function. And this find_password,
let's just check to make sure there were no errors here
and we've spelled at the same way.
And this find_password function is going to need to get hold of the entry
that's inside the website entry.
So the website that we're looking for comes from the website_entry.get,
and then we'll be able to get the value of whatever the user typed inside this
entry.
And then we're going to use that to search through our data.json.
Now the easiest way for this to work is actually to first add a website.
So I'm just going to generate a website with my email and password and add it so
that it gets saved inside my data.json.
This way I'll be able to print things and I'll be able to work with the data a
little bit easier.
And then we'll address the exception catching a little bit later on.
What exactly are we looking for? Well,
we're looking to load up the data inside this JSON file.
So we're going to be opening up that file.
So with open and then the filename is data.json,
and then we'll save this as the data_file.
Now, once we've got our data file,
then we can use our JSON module to load up that file
and we're going to be getting hold of the data that's inside.
So we can save this to a variable called data.
Now this data, if I go ahead and print it,
you should remember is basically just a dictionary.
So as soon as I hit search, that should trigger this find_password
and now I've got my dictionary printed in here.
So what do we want to do with this dictionary? Well,
we want to look through it and check to see if this website that we're searching
for actually exists inside that dictionary.
The way we do that is we say if website in data,
well, in that case, it's actually success, right?
We've managed to find it inside the data
and we now just need to get hold of the email and password values.
So let's create a variable called email and we want to pick out this particular
value from this dictionary.
If this is the entire dictionary,
then we want to get hold of the dictionary and pick out the item with the key
that matches the website that we're searching for, like this.
Now, once we've gotten hold of this,
this is going to be a nested dictionary.
So it's equivalent to basically this part of the dictionary.
So this in itself is the dictionary,
which you could save to a separate variable,
but I think it's actually easy enough to understand that we can tag on another
key here
which is the word email in order to get hold of the value that's associated with
that key. So that way,
this email variable now saves this value here.
And in the same way, we can get the password from data
getting hold of the data under the website key and then passing in the password
key. Now that we've got the email and password,
we can go ahead and create our message box using show info. And we'll set the
title to be the website that the user is searching for
and the message is going to be a f-string,
which has the email listed.
And then on a new line,
it's also got the password that's going to be listed as well.
Like that.
Let's go ahead and run this code and make sure that it works.
Let's say that we have a couple more passwords that we save in here.
Now I should have three entries, Amazon, eBay, and Twitter,
and I want to go and search for my password for eBay.
Once I hit the search button, it goes into that find_password function
and if it finds that one of these has the key eBay,
then it's going to fetch all of these relevant pieces of data that I wanted from
that JSON file.
So now what we have to do is to make sure that we catch any exceptions that
might occur and you might already have realized that this works really well
right now because we have data
and because we have this data.json file.
But the first time that I run my program,
this is not going to exist.
So this is a more realistic version of what the program will look like
the first time we run it. And the first time that we go ahead and run this
and I search for something that is going to look for a file that doesn't exist
immediately, our program crashes, and we get the file not found error.
So what we need to do is we need to be aware enough that these things like
opening files can fail.
So what we have to do is we have to catch the exceptions and handle them.
Let's go ahead and indent this entire block and put it inside the try.
Now, the part that's most likely to fail in fact,
the first time the program starts, this is definitely going to fail.
But what we want to do is we want to catch the exception
that is file not found error. And in the situation,
what we want to do is we want to create a message box that tells the user
this data file doesn't exist.
This is just a simple showinfo
and we'll give it a title of error and we'll give it a message of no data file
found,
or you can put any other message you can think of. However,
if we were successful in opening this file,
then this is the part of the code that we want to implement.
So let's go ahead and bring it up to the right indentation.
And we searched through our data,
look for this website and then give the user a popup if it exists.
Now, if we run our code again and we search for something
even though we don't have a data file, we haven't saved anything yet,
then we get this error popup and it tells us no data files found.
And hopefully the user would realize, well,
actually I haven't actually saved any passwords.
So there's one other situation that we haven't yet addressed however.
If I had, um, let's say Amazon, um,
eBay and Twitter saved in my JSON file,
but I decided to search for something that I never saved.
Let's say my details for Facebook. Well in this situation, actually
nothing really happens. And it's a little bit confusing because for the user,
it seems like our program just doesn't work. But in fact, we
as the programmers know what the problem is. It's basically this
if statement is coming out as false. The website doesn't exist in the data.
So none of this gets carried out and the function ends.
That's probably not the best user experience. Instead,
we probably want to catch it with an else statement and we want to use a message
box to tell the that again,
there is a error in this situation
but the reason for this error is because
there are no details that currently exist for the website that they're searching
for. That way
they're not sitting there confused as to why searching for some sort of website
doesn't actually come up with anything.
It tells them that there are no details and they would have to add it
if they wanna find it in the database.
A lot of students might be wondering at this point, well,
why don't we catch this with some sort of exception?
And in fact, we could create an exception.
We could raise an exception here and then we could catch it somewhere else and
show this message box.
But the thing you want to keep in mind is that if you can do something with if
and else very easily, then you should stick to if and else.
If you can't do it with if and else very easily, and it's actually an error
that's going to be thrown that you don't have any other way of dealing with,
then you should be using the try, except, else, finally, keywords.
And in fact, if you think about this,
I don't have an easy way of checking to see if this data file ends up being not
found. But I do have this file not found error
which is going to be thrown every time that I try to open a file and that
doesn't exist.
The other way to think about it is that an exception is something that is
meant to be exceptional. It's something that happens very rarely.
Whereas if and else catches things that happen frequently.
It's pretty often that your user might search through the website
thinking that they saved some sort of details for a website. But in fact,
they didn't. Think about this when you're writing your code
and remember that only use exception handling when you don't have an easy
alternative. There you have it.
That's the completed code for our upgraded password manager.
If you want to take a look at any of this code,
then, as always, head over to the course resources
and you'll see a link to the completed code that you can review.
But in today's lessons,
we added a lot more knowledge regarding things like error handling and saving
data in JSON formats and handling and loading and updating and dealing with
all of that data in order to create this fully-fledged password manager project.
Now, I'm sure there's a lot more improvements you can add to this,
but it's going to go beyond the allocated time for today's lessons.
So if you want,
please continue messing around with the code and improving it and make your own
customizations and modifications.
If you create something that you thought was cool,
then be sure to share it with us in the Q/A below the lesson so that we can
all admire your hard work and maybe improve our own code as a result.
So have fun playing around with this program and I'll see you tomorrow.
Hey guys, welcome to day 31
of 100 Days of Code. And you've been learning quite a lot of things
now. We've been looking at handling exceptions,
using the JSON data format, passing and reading CSVs
using pandas, opening and writing to files and a whole lot more.
So it's time for your capstone project.
And in this capstone project,
we're going to be building a flashcard program to help you study.
And it's especially great with studying for languages. Now,
when I was in school,
I studied French and it was a lot of vocab that we had to learn for tests.
Pomme is Apple, and I would memorize all these words,
all of the grammar tables, and yet after four or five years,
I couldn't really speak much French.
So I decided to go for immersive language learning.
I went to France,
I hung out with friends and I tried to immerse myself in the language and
culture. But that also failed. I had a lot of fun,
but my French didn't seem to improve all that much.
But then I discovered a new way of learning languages and it all started with
looking at Chinese characters. There's a lot of Chinese characters out there.
There's something like 50,000 Chinese characters in total from history to now.
There's a lot of characters that you could learn. They each have a different
meaning and they each have a different pronunciation.
Imagine that. Trying to learn 50,000 characters. That's no easy feat.
But then a friend told me that actually you don't really need 50,000
characters. Your average professor, who is very eloquent,
can write a lot of the characters and use them with ease,
only knows about 10,000 and your average person probably only uses about 8,000
in their day to day lives. And if you basically just want to get by in life,
you can pretty much rely on the 3000 words that an average teenager would know.
And finally, if you actually just want to be able to watch some simple movies,
read some simple books,
then you could use the average kid vocabulary of about that the 1000 characters.
And at this point, I think to myself, 1000. That's quite doable.
I could do 1000. If I learn just 10 characters a day,
that will take me less than a year to learn all of these characters.
But it's not just 1000 random characters either.
There's such a thing as a frequency dictionary.
So a dictionary that's not listed here by A, B, C, D,
but it actually listed by the frequency that a particular word occurs in common
usage. For example,
if you take the first 1000 characters that are most commonly used,
then you can pretty much read most of the Newspapers,
you can watch most of the TV shows because these
are the words that are the bread and butter of the language. It's like in English,
the a, the, of, from, why, yes, no,
these are words that we use every day, again and again.
The crazy words like anti-establishment or glioblastoma.
These are not words that you need to really know for day to day life.
So let me show you the program that you'll build
where you can learn the most frequently used words in any language.
It's a flashcard program,
and it shows you the front and the back of the card. So for example,
French, demande. In English means request. After three seconds,
the card flips and I can check whether if I knew the right answer.
If I got it right I'll press the tick and if I got it wrong
I'll press the cross. So let's try another word.
Parti means left or to leave. Attendez
means to wait
and I think I knew that word. So I'm going to click the check mark.
And what that's going to do is it's going to take the flashcard out of all of
the list of flashcards so it doesn't show me the things I already know.
And instead it only shows me the things I don't know
so I can review it and say, Oh, I'm not sure what loin means
so I'll say cross,
and that will go back into the deck and it might come up again at some point.
So this beautiful piece of software is what we're going to be creating.
But more specifically,
you're going to be creating because after all, this is your capstone project.
But don't worry,
I've divided up into four steps and I've got some step by step instructions for
you in the next lesson. Now, if you're wondering,
how did you get the most frequent words for the flashcard app in the first
place? Well, let me show you.
There's a Wiki for the frequency list of different languages,
and it lists most of the common languages. If we go to French,
you can see that there are loads of different lists that people have compiled
that list the top, most frequently occurring words.
And one of the ones that I thought was really relevant is the words are based on
subtitles.
These subtitles come from all sorts of shows and movies that are relevant to modern
culture. And when you look at one of the subtitles,
this is one of my favorite shows by the way,
you can see that the subtitles are listed by language.
And if we pick out one which is in English and we take a look at it,
then you can see
it's basically just all the words that are spoken in the movie or in the show
and it's been transcribed into subtitles. Now
then if we take all of these words that are from the most commonly watched
movies and shows, we end up with these frequency lists.
So if we take a look here,
it shows the most frequent words from 1 to 5,000.
And at the very beginning,
it's your I, of, is, all of these things that are really common.
And then as you scroll down, you get to some longer words.
And if you scroll to the bottom,
you can see you're getting some more and more niche words.
These frequency lists are compiled by a user called Hermitd
and Hermitdis a Hermit Dave
And he has a GitHub repository where he's compiled all of the frequency words,
and you can see the latest version from 2018.
Now he's got all of the frequency words for many languages
and it's listed by the language code,
so French would be FR for example.
And here you can see the top 50,000 most frequent lists or the full entire list.
We're probably not gonna learn more than 1000,
and I'm certainly not going to get to 50,000.
But this data here lists all the words that he found in these subtitles and the
frequency that they occurred.
And once they've been sorted in order of frequency,
this is what you end up with.
So I've already studied some of the first 200 words.
So if I take a hundred words from this frequency dictionary
and I put it into a Google sheet, then I end up with something like this.
Now,
what I want to be able to do is to create a flashcard where the front of the
flashcard is the word in French,
and then on the back of the flashcard is the answer in English for what
that word means. Instead of having to flip through a dictionary
finding out the meaning of each of these words,
there's actually a really neat trick in Google sheets that I want to show you.
If you hit equals to
start a new formula and you type in Google translate,
you can see it expects some inputs.
First is the piece of text that you want to translate,
so I'm going to click on this cell, and then it's the source language.
So this is the language as a code. So for example,
Spanish is ES and French is FR. And then the final input.
it expects is the language code that you want to translate it to.
So in this case, I want to translate it to English. So I'm going to use en.
And then we can close off the parentheses, hit
enter and after a little while with good internet,
you'll see the English translation for this word. And of course,
because we're an Excel,
we can simply just drag this cross all the way down to all of our words.
And after a little while, bam!
It's translated all of those words into English.
So this is a really neat trick and I'll link to the docs for this particular
formula.
And also you can take a look at the language support that Google's translation
service has and you can see the language code for each of these languages.
So if you want to try learning Macedonian or Malay,
and this is going to be your best bet.
So now that I've created my Excel sheet
essentially of a French and English words,
I've got potentially a hundred flashcards with the front and back data already
saved inside this Google sheet. Now,
all I have to do is simply download it as a CSV
and we'll be able to work with it very easily. Now,
you don't have to worry about downloading this or getting hold of this because
I've already included the final CSV data in the starting project for you to be
able to use.
So head over to the next lesson and get started building your very own study
aid, the flashy flashcard app.
All right.
So hopefully you've headed over to the course resources and downloaded the
starting zip file for today's project. So go ahead and unzip it.
And then let's open up this folder using PyCharm.
Okay.
Here you've already got two folders, data and images.
We're going to be using all of these images inside the images folder to create
our project. So this is the front of the flashcard,
the back of the flashcard, the right button and the wrong button.
And we're going to be writing our code inside main.py. So notice here
we've already got the background color hex code defined.
So we'll be able to use it in our coding as well. This is what we're aiming for.
This is the user interface for this program.
It's going to have a window with a title and inside this window,
we're going to have the card front image here showing up.
And on that card, we're going to have two pieces of text,
a word that says title and a piece of text that just says word.
And these are going to be formatted according to the instructions,
so in terms of font and size, et cetera. Finally, at the bottom,
we've got two buttons, a cross, and a checkmark.
And they're basically buttons that have the images right and wrong inside them.
Let's get started. Inside main.py,
the first thing I'm going to do is to go ahead and import tkinter.
So I'm going to import all the classes from tkinter
and then I'll be able to use it to create my window.
All right.
I'm going to set a title for my window and I'm going to give it the name of our
app
which is going to be called Flashy or whatever it is you want to call it. Next,
I'm going to give this window, um,
a configuration and I'm going to set the padding of the window to 50 pixels in
the X and 50 pixels in the Y.
Now this window is also going to have a background color
which is going to be set to this BACKGROUND_COLOR
constant that we have up here.
So now that I'm done configuring my window,
I can go ahead and get my window to start off in the main loop.
And now I should be able to run this code and just check that it works.
Here's our window with the background color
and there's already some padding in it and making this window a little bit
bigger. Now,
the next thing to do is to somehow put this card front image onto our window.
I'm going to be using a canvas object.
And if you remember, canvas object allows us to layer lots of things on top
of each other. So here is an image and then on top of that,
we've got some text being created.
And as long as we specify the position for each of these items,
it can all be overlapped on top of each other.
So we're creating our canvas from the canvas class
and then I'm going to give my canvas a width and height.
So I'm going to set the width and height to be the same as the width and height
of my card.
So the width is 800 and the height is 526.
You should've seen these numbers in the instructions as well. Next,
we're going to create our image from the photo image class.
So let's call it card_front_img
and this is going to be created from the photo image class
where we have to specify a file name. Now, previously,
all we've done is we've just said the actual name of the file,
which in this case is card_front.png. But in our case,
this particular file is actually inside our images folder.
So we have to specify the full file path for this to work; images/card_
front.png.
And then we can get ahold of our canvas and create our image inside.
So the image is going to be set to our card_front_img
and then we have to specify the X and Y values of that image. Because it needs
to go into the center of the canvas,
we're just going to half the width for the X and half the height for the Y.
So this goes in as a tuple
so half of 526 is 263
and then I'm just going to put our canvas onto the grid and I'm going to set the
row to zero and the column to zero as well.
Now, just be careful when you're writing strings like this,
because it's pretty easy to make a typo like I have here. Instead,
I prefer using PyCharm's autofill.
So when you have a file path,
you can type in the name of the folder forwardslash and then the name of the
file. And we can just hit enter for it to insert it for us automatically.
Now, if I go ahead and hit run,
then I'll see that I've got a background which has the background color,
and then 50 pixels of padding on all four sides, in the middle
I've got my canvas displaying
this card_front.png. The only thing about this card is that it's still got
that white background. How do we get rid of that? Well,
we can change the background into the same color as everything else,
so this background color. Let's go ahead and get our canvas
and then let's config it to have a background color
that's set equal to our constant like this.
Now the background color is the same,
but we now have a line that is all around our canvas.
If you remember from previous lessons,
I told you that you can simply get rid of the highlight thickness and set it to
zero. And that basically just gets rid of that border.
So now we have a window with our flashcard showing up and the image has the
shadows which I created in illustrator
so that you'll be able to see it as a 3D card. Now,
inside the card, not only do we have an image,
but we also want to have some text.
So let's go ahead and create some text. And we can set the text to say Title.
So this is the first piece of text. In addition,
I'm going to set the font to a tuple
which is going to use the Arial font, and then it's going to be 40 size
and finally I'm going to make it italic. Now,
before we can hit run,
we also have to specify a X and Y position for our text.
So our image was created at 400 X, 263
Y, our text is going to be created at 400 X and 150 Y.
Now remember that these positions are relative to the canvas.
So 400 makes it halfway along the width
and then this 150 is going to make it a little bit towards the top
so that's a good position for the title. Next,
we're going to create another piece of text
and this piece of text is going to be the actual word, so that the French word or
the English word.
So we're going to set it at the center of our canvass
so exactly centered on the image,
and then we're going to say that the text is going to be equal to the word for
now anyways. Later on we'll probably change it.
And then the font is again also Arial.
And this time it's going to be a bit bigger and it's also going to be bold. So
there we have it. We've got our flashcard pretty much all laid out.
Now we just have to add our two buttons. Below our canvas
I'm going to create two buttons. First, there's going to be the unknown button.
This is going to be the X which the user presses
because they don't know what's on the back of the flashcard.
And this button is going to have a special attribute though,
the image attribute and that image is going to be a photo image.
So let's put this as the cross_image,
and it's going to be a photo image
which is going to be created from the images folder
and it is the wrong.png.
And that image is what's going to go inside our unknown button.
Let's go ahead and layout our unknown button on the grid so that it'll actually
show up. Row is going to be 1,
so below the canvas, and then column is going to be 0.
So now you can see our X button show up here.
Next, I'm going to create the check_image. This is going to be the checkmark.
And in this case, its again,
a photo image created from a file
which is in our images/right.png.
And of course, you can always just double click on each of these images and view
them and just make sure that they are the ones that you want to use.
So once we've got our image, we can create our known_button.
And this is going to now have a image attribute set to this check image.
And then we can place our known_button onto the grid as well.
So row = 1 and column is going to be equal to 1 as well.
So its on the same row as the unknown button,
but it's just shifted a little bit to the right. Now at this point
if I run the code,
you can see that our check button is all the way on the right while our canvas
and our cross button are in the left most column.
So you know what you need to do. You have to change
this canvas grid to have a column span of 2.
So it starts at column 0 but ends at column 1.
Now when you run it,
you can see it's nicely placed onto the screen in the way that we want it to
look. Now, if you want to get rid of the border around the buttons,
then the easiest way is to again,
change the highlight thickness to 0.
So lets add that here and here.
But both on Mac and Windows,
you'll see this fine line around the button and it's not easy to get rid of it
because it's their so that you can click on the button and you can see this
visible depression.
That way it lets the user know that the button press was actually successful.
But that's fine.
And we're now pretty much done with our user interface. In the next step
we're going to get rid of these placeholders, title and word, and we're going to
start picking out the words from this french_words.csv,
picking out random records like this or this so that we can put the French word
into right here and change the title to say French.
For all of that and more, head over to the next lesson and see the instructions.
Now that we've created the UI,
the next step or step 2 was to try and get the buttons to start working so
that when we press the cross or the tick button,
we get a new French word being shown in the middle here,
and the title switches to the word of French. So how do we do this?
Well, firstly, for both of these buttons
the unknown and the known button,
we're going to add a command. And remember the command links to a particular
function that is going to be called.
So we'll call that next_card and we'll add that to both the known and the
unknown buttons.
Now that we've got next_card added here,
now let's go ahead and create this function next_card.
What exactly is this function going to do? Well,
it's going to take the words from the french_words.csv
and it's going to get hold of some of these words and their translations.
So it basically,
you can imagine these as single rows that we want to get hold of.
Now, what we need to do first though
is we need to use pandas in order to read from that CSV.
So we're going to first import pandas and it should already be installed in
your project. If not, you'll see a red light bulb
and then you can just click on it and then install that module.
Once we've got pandas enabled though,
we're going to use panders to read from a CSV and the CSV is our french_words.csv
from the data folder.
Now we're going to set this as equal to the data.
So this is now going to be a data frame. And in fact,
if I go ahead and print it
now
you can see that pandas will nicely format our table with the column headings
and also record numbers
and each of these rows are basically the pieces of data that we're interested
in. Now that we've got a data frame,
we can convert that data frame into a dictionary.
Let's go ahead and create a dictionary which we'll call out to_learn,
so that's the word that we need to learn,
and this is going to be a dictionary that's created from this data
from this french_words.csv. But notice how at the moment,
if we just use the default method of creating a dictionary,
what our to_learn is going to look like is like this.
We've got French and then inside
we've got all of the French words and then we've got a key later on called
English and all of the corresponding English words.
Now, that's what we want. Instead, we want to change one of the parameters
which is orient,
so how do we want to orient the table to create this dictionary? Now in the hints
for step 2, I already showed you that you could use this
orient set to records and this way it'll give you each column's values as a
list. Let me show you what that looks like.
So let's change this parameter orient,
and we'll set it to equal the string records.
Remember that there's an 's' at the end.
And now we can compare the previous version of the dictionary
that's generated from the data to the new version.
So let me run the code again and you can see now we've basically got a list of
dictionaries and each dictionary has a key, French,
the French word, a key English,
and then the English word and so on and so forth. This is really,
really useful for us because we can basically pick a random entry from this list
and we'll be able to tap into the French value and the English value later on
when we flip our cards. That is our to_learn dictionary done.
So when the next_card function gets called,
then we're going to need to pick out some data from this dictionary and the way
that we're gonna pick it out is randomly.
So we're going to import the random module and we're going to use random.
choice in order to pick out a random item from this list of words to learn.
And once we've got a random choice which we'll call current_card,
then we can get hold of the data from this current_card by saying current_card
[French]. Remember that in this french_words.csv
we've got a capital F and a capital E.
So our keys must match that exactly.
So let's go ahead and print this
and you can see now that when I press on one of these buttons,
either the cross or the tick,
it's going to pick out a random French word from my list of words in this
french_words.csv. So now instead of printing it,
let's go ahead and put it into these pieces of text on our canvas.
In order to do that,
I'm going to create a variable called card_title to hold on to the title and
the card_word to hold on to the word text.
And now I can go ahead and tap into my canvas and say
itemconfig and the item that we want to configure is firstly
our card_title
and the thing we want to configure about it is to change the text to say French.
So that's the title remember, which is the part that's up here.
And then we're going to do the same thing using canvas.itemconfig
but this time we're going to configure the card_word,
and this is going to be set to exactly what we printed before,
which is the random card that was picked out and the value under the key French.
So now when I hit run again,
you can see that when I press either of these buttons,
I'm going to get a random French word showing up right here.
But notice how when I first run the app
you can see that it still has the placeholder title and word showing up.
Instead, we want it to show the next card.
So we have to call this function once we've created all of our UI
but before we get to our main loop.
So we'll call our next card. And this way,
once we've created all of our images and everything else,
then we can generate the next card,
get the data and put it into the card title and card word. So in fact,
if you want to,
you can actually delete these two pieces of text because they won't actually do
anything at the moment. And now as soon as we hit run,
you can see the first thing we see is already a French word
and it will keep going through all of the words that we have in our CSV.
There you have it. We've now managed to read from the CSV,
get a dictionary of all the records in the CSV and to randomly get the French
word showing up in our flashcard. Our flashcard currently,
doesn't actually flash. It doesn't change, right?
We need a way for us to be able to set some sort of a timer,
say a 3-second timer,
and then for our card to show us the opposite side or the backside and to show
us the English translation of the words.
That is what we're going to tackle on the next lesson.
So head over to step 3 and have a read of the instructions.
Now that we've got our words showing up in French,
it's time to see the other side of the card and see the English equivalent so
that we can check our knowledge. To do this
we're going to have to implement some sort of way of changing this card after a
set amount of time. So we're going to flip the card
after three seconds are up. To do that
we're going to use the window.after method.
Right after here where we've created a window,
we're going to say window.after.
And then we can specify the amount of time in milliseconds.
So I'm going to say three seconds or 3000 milliseconds.
And then the function that we're going to call is a function
that's going to be called flip_card. And if we want that to work,
then we're going to have to create it. So I'm going to create right here,
just above.
So I'll call it flip_card and this function is going to take care of changing the
card to show the English word for the current card,
and also going to change the image from the card_front to
the card_back, and also we're going to change the color of the text as well.
In our flip card,
we're going to get hold of the canvas and we're going to first item.config
the card_ title. So we're going to change the card_title to,
instead of saying French, we're going to say, well,
this is now the English translation,
and then we're going to config the card word,
and this is going to be still from the current card,
but we want to get ahold of the value under the key English instead.
Now at the moment, this current card is locked up inside next_card.
So we can't actually get hold of it without creating a new random choice.
So what we can do is we can create our current card
and we can set it to a empty dictionary.
And then we can change this to a global and tap into that current card to modify
it and save this random choice from our list of French and English pairs.
So once we've got that inside there,
then we can tap into it inside flip_card and we can say current card
get hold of the value under the English key.
And that way we update both of our texts. So right now if I hit run,
you can see that immediately after three seconds
we switched to the opposite side and we have our English and the English
equivalent of the same word showing up. So for example,
in French matin, in English means morning.
So that's how we can verify that we actually know the meaning of the card.
In addition to changing the words, I'm also going to change the image.
So notice how we saved the words with a variable.
We can do the same thing for this create image method.
We can say the card_background is equal to canvas create image.
And in addition to creating the card front image,
we can also create the card back image.
Now, you have to be really careful here
because if you create this card back image
which is a photo image created from file,
if you create it inside one of these functions, by the end of the function
call, that reference to that particular image will be gone.
And it won't work if you create this photo image inside flipcard and try to set
it inside this method. So you have to create it outside of any of the functions.
So let's change the file to images/card_back.png
and now we're going to get our canvas to again,
call itemconfig.
And this time we're configuring the card_background.
And the attribute that we want to configure is the image property.
So we're going to change that to the card_back_img
which we created right here.
So now let's just check that again.
Let's wait three seconds and then it's changed to
the back of the card. On the back of the card
we want these two pieces of text to actually have a different color.
We want it to be white, just so that it stands out from the background.
And to do that, we can add it along with our item config.
Not only are we changing the text,
but also changing the fill of the text to white.
Okay.
And now when our card flips over,
you can see its a green card with a white text.
Now,
one of the things we have to do is every time we click on one of these buttons,
it has the flip back to the front of the card, right?
That means changing the text color and changing that background image.
So that happens when we go to next card.
So in addition to configuring the text and the words,
we also again have to itemconfig the card_background so that we can change the
image back to the card front image.
In addition, we have to change these text colors to have a different fill,
so we're going to change it back to black.
Right.
This way, when the card flips, it goes to green,
white on green. And then when we go to the front of the card,
it goes to black on white.
Now notice how once we go to the next card,
that card flipping mechanism has gone because we only ever call this window
after the first time we create the window.
So we actually need this to happen a few times. In fact,
we need it to happen every single time we go to the next card.
So after we've configured all the things on our card,
we're gonna call a window.after, three seconds, flipcard.
So this way, even if we go to the next card and we wait three seconds,
it again goes to the back.
Now one of the bugs you might have encountered is if you clicked this button
many times and you go through lots of different words,
you see immediately, that card actually flipped.
And it's because that window.after three seconds is counting down in the
background, waiting, waiting, waiting until three seconds
at which point it's going to flip the card.
It doesn't care that you've actually just gone onto a new card and you want to
wait again, three seconds. In order to get this to work,
we actually have to give this line of code a variable so that we'll call it the
flip_timer. And this is now a global
which we can tap into and we can add it after a comma over here,
flip_timer. Alternatively,
you can also go onto a new line and say global flip_timer.
It doesn't really make a difference other than the fact that this probably takes
less lines of code. Now, once we've got access to our flip_timer,
we can say that every time we go to a new card,
when we click on one of these buttons, we're going to invalidate this timer.
So we can say window.after_
cancel and then pass in the ID of our flip_timer.
And then after we've set up this card,
we can set up a new flip_timer so that it waits for again three seconds.
And now once I've added that bit of code, it should fix this bug.
So now whenever I keep going or I press the check or the crossmark,
it doesn't really matter.
It's not going to flip until I land on a card and wait for three seconds
before it flips. There you have it. We've got our card
flipping technology added to our code.
Now all that's left is to get rid of the cards that the user says
they know
and to create a new CSV that is going to hold all the cards from this to_learn
dictionary and to remove the cards that the user says they know.
And then that way, the next time we run our app
it will remember which words we've learned and which words we haven't so that we
can load up only the words we have yet to learn.
So for that, head over to the next lesson where we've got the final step of the
flashcard project.
We are now within sight of the finish line. We're onto the last step.
So this is the solution for step 4. And in step 4
we want to be able to improve our program so that the words where the user
clicks the checkmark to means they already know that word.
They know what it means and they don't wanna see it again in this list.
So what we want to be able to do is to remove the words that the user knows from
this dictionary of words to_learn. And to do that,
we have to change this command. When the user clicks on the unknown button,
we're going to simply just give them the next card,
which is a random word from the list of words.
But when they use it clicks on the known button,
instead of clicking on next card, we're going to call a different function
which I'm going to call is_known. Now is_known
is going to be a function
that's going to remove the current card from the cards that are in the list of
words to learn.
So what we're going to do is we're going to get hold of our list to learn,
and then we're going to call the remove method.
And then we're going to remove a particular element from it.
And that happens to be the current card.
So remember, the current card is a dictionary
which we got by randomly choosing from our list to learn.
So now, when the user says is_known,
then the current card is going to be removed from the list of words to learn.
And then after we've done that,
then we're going to call next card from this particular method. At the moment,
if we run this code and I just keep clicking the check mark,
eventually, we're going to have a very small list of words that we're going to
pick from. In fact,
if I go ahead and print the length of my list, to_learn,
you can see that the first time I run this code and I click on the is_known
button, we have a hundred words. But if I keep clicking on this,
then you'll see that every single time,
I'm just reducing that list because I'm saying,
I already know what this word compris means
and that word is now taken out of my list of words to learn.
So now that list is smaller by one entry.
Now this works right now, but if I rerun the app,
then you can see it goes back right to the beginning
and it has a hundred words again.
So in order to keep hold of the words that I still need to learn,
I have to save this list to a new permanent file
each time the user clicks on this is_known button.
So the way that I'm going to do that is by using pandas again.
I'm going to use pandas to create a new data frame.
And that data frame is going to be created from our list to_learn.
Now, I'm going to save this as our data,
and then I can say data.to_csv in order to save it as a CSV file.
So I'll call this words_to_learn.csv.
So now, if I press my check mark
and I take a look within my files,
you can see that words_to_learn.csv is created.
And at the moment it's got 89 entries. But if I keep clicking this a few times,
it's going to reduce each time.
So this is now a permanent storage of all the words that I have yet to learn.
But I don't really want it randomly in the middle of my project.
I want it to be saved alongside my french_words.csv.
So I have to change this to a file path
which is going to be data/words_to_learn.csv.
So let's go ahead and delete this file and do refactor.
And then we're going to run this again.
And next time you'll see that it appears in the right place.
Now, in addition to saving it to CSV,
we also have to read from that CSV because instead of using the words from our
original list which is our french_words.csv,
I actually want to be able to read from my words_to_learn.csv instead,
because that way, every single time I rerun the app,
it's always going to give me all the words that I've yet to learn.
So currently we're on 87. If I run this again,
you can see that the first time I click on this,
it's going to go to 86 instead of going back to 100.
But there is a problem here though
because if I delete this file, words_to_learn.csv, and I go ahead and run this, the first
time this runs it's going to crash and we have that familiar file
not found error. So we know how to deal with that.
We need to catch this exception. The exception occurs right here.
It happens when we try to get hold of this piece of data
which may or may not exist. So if it does not exist,
so we're going to catch this except file not found error. Well,
in that case, we're going to be using the original data
which comes from the french_words.csv. So we'll say pandas.
read_csv
and then we're going to read this file, data/french_words.csv.
So this is always going to be there because it's preloaded with our project.
But if we do manage to find our words_to_learn.csv,
then that means this program has been run before and we've removed some of the
words we already know. So we can catch that with an else statement and we can say,
well, in this case,
we're going to set a global variable called to_learn
which starts out as an empty dictionary.
And we set it to the data that comes from this CSV.
However, if that file was not found,
then this to_learn is going to be set to the original data.to_dict
and we're going to orient according to records as well.
Okay.
Now, when we run our code, you can see we have no errors.
And the first time that it runs,
it's going to pick from our french_words.csv. Now,
once I've started saying I've learned this, I've learned this,
I've learned this, then it's going to generate a words_to_learn.csv.
And the next time I run this code,
it's gonna start using that words_to_learn.csv and start where I left off.
Now, there is one slight weird bug to this.
When you take a look at the words_to_learn.csv,
it adds the record number to the first column
every single time I run the code. So if I run this code again,
you can see now I have three columns of all of the records.
So basically when we read from this particular CSV,
we generate a data frame. And when I read from that data frame,
so let's delete this and run our code again,
you can see that pandas is automatically added in these record numbers.
So that gets then added back into our words_to_learn.csv when it saves it into
the file. If we want to get rid of these record numbers,
all we have to do is when we save it to the CSV,
we can set a property called index to false. This way
it just doesn't add the index numbers to our newly created list
and now if I rerun this code,
you can see that our words_to_learn.csv
doesn't actually include an index. It only includes the actual records or
the actual words and their English translations.
That's
basically it. That's all the solutions to our capstone project.
And you've now built a fully fleshed flashcard that you can use to learn
languages.
So you could have the front with whatever language you want, and the back with
English translations, or you can use it to learn Programming facts.
You could have the front with a Programming word and the back as the meaning of
the Programming word.
You could use it to study History or Geography.
And this program is going to help you manage all the things that you don't
remember and keep showing it to you until you do. Have fun modifying this
flashcard app and I hope it will be helpful in your studies as well.
If you've built something particularly interesting, again,
be sure to share with us in the Q/A so that we can all admire and
congratulate you on your hard work.
Hey there, welcome to day 32 of 100 Days of Code. Now,
today
we're going to be learning about email SMTP and the date time module.
Basically, we're going to learn how to send email using Python code.
And we're going to determine when we send the email using this daytime time
module. And once we've learned all of those skills,
we're going to be building a really interesting and possibly helpful tool where
we can automate a happy birthday email to all of our friends and family.
So, I probably only remember a handful of people's emails off by heart and the
rest of the time, I rely pretty much on Facebook telling me that it's so,
and so's birthday. And I end up writing on their timeline.
But if Facebook didn't tell me, I would probably not remember.
Now I know some friends of mine are really good at remembering everybody's
birthday,
even if they don't go on the Facebook and they'll send you a message every year
showing how good of a friend they are.
And it always makes me feel a little bit bad inside.
So what's our solution? To remember everybody's date of birth?
No. We're going to build a Python program.
And this Python program is going to be the automated birthday wisher.
All we have to do it is
create a spreadsheet of all of our friend's birthdays and then create a bunch of
emails
and we'll randomly pick an email to send to each of these friends.
And this program is going to teach us some skills in Python
helping us level up as a programmer.
But it also makes us better people because our friends will feel like we
remember their birthdays and help our friends feel more appreciated.
Email SMTP is a module that comes pre-bundled with Python
and it helps us send email using Python code.
And daytime is another Python module that helps us figure out what today's date
is or how to format a particular date and time. And in our case,
it's going to help us figure out if today happens to be the day of one of our
friend's birthdays, in which case we'll send them a birthday email.
So that's the plan. Head over to the next lesson
and we'll get started by learning how to send email.
The first thing we have to figure out is how exactly does email work?
We all know that we can log on to Gmail or Yahoo dot com and we can start filling out an email.
It's pretty much second nature to everybody by now.
But what actually happens behind the scenes?
Well, let's say that we have a sender Angela gmail.com and a recipient Timmy at Yahoo dot com.
Now in order to send this email from my Gmail account to another email account, what happens behind
the scene is that there's a Gmail mail server which will receive my message and then there's a Yahoo
Mail server which will store the message until Timmy logs on to his computer and logs on to Yahoo dot
com, which downloads the email from the Yahoo Mail server.
So this email is going to move between all of these steps.
And in order to do this, it relies on something called SMTP, the simple mail transfer protocol.
And this contains all of the rules that determine how an email is received by mail servers passed onto
the next mail server and how email can be sent around the Internet.
Now, a good analogy for SMTP is if you imagine these mail servers as a post office and Timmy's computer
being the mailbox, then SMTP is basically the postman who knows how to handle the email and take it
to various post offices and eventually put it into Timmy's computer.
So in Python there's a module called SMTP lib, which allows us to use SMTP to send our email to any
address on the internet.
To start, I recommend setting up two fresh email accounts, create a new email account with Gmail,
and also create a new email account with Yahoo!
These new email accounts will be perfect for testing your code and following along with the video tutorials.
Plus, we'll be making those email accounts a little bit less secure to test our code.
So that's another reason to set up some testing email addresses for now.
After you've set up your new email accounts, head over to the course resources and download the zip
file with the starting code for today's lessons.
And then we're going to open that up using PI charm.
Now, I want you to take a look inside the starting project.
There is a main PI file and there's also a quote text file.
Don't worry about this file for now.
We're going to come back to it when we explore the date time module.
For now, we're going to be working within the main PI.
And I want to show you how you can use this SMTP lib library to start sending emails straight from your
Python code.
As always, we import the module SMTP lib and then we can start using it once we've imported this SMTP
library.
Essentially, we can use it to create a new SMTP object.
So we're going to call that object a new connection because it's basically a way for us to be able to
connect to our email provider's SMTP email server.
We're going to do this by tapping into the SMTP lib and then creating a object from the SMTP class.
Now, when we create this object, one of the things that we should specify is the location of our email
provider's SMTP server.
Now, for Gmail, it's simply SMTP gmail.com.
But it's different for every email provider.
So that means if your email ends in at gmail.com, then this would be how you would connect to your
email server.
In our case, I've created a testing email called App Brewery Info at gmail.com.
And this part that's before the ADD sign is the identity of my email account and the part after the
ADD sign is the identity of my email provider.
So in my case I need to connect to SMTP gmail.com.
But if you have a different email provider, for example, if you're with Hotmail, it's SMTP, Mlive.com
and if you're with Yahoo, it's SMTP mail, yahoo.com.
And if you're with a completely different email provider, then simply just Google your email provider
and the SMTP information and you should find an article somewhere that describes a URL that looks something
like this.
Once I've created my connection, the next thing I need to do is to go ahead and call start TLS.
Now TLS stands for Transport Layer Security.
And it's a way of securing our connection to our email server.
So that way, when we're sending an email, if somebody else intercepts our email somewhere along the
line and they try to read it because this is enabled, that message will be encrypted and it'll be impossible
for them to read what is in the content of our email.
So this line basically will make this connection secure.
Now, once we've secured our connection, the next thing to do is to actually log in.
So we'll call connection, log in.
And here we have to provide a username and a password.
So the username is simply the email that we use to log on to our email service.
So in my case, it's just my email and the password.
I've just made up a new password.
So my made up password is ABCD.
One, two, three, four.
And then two brackets.
And once I've logged in to my email provider, the final thing I want to do is to actually send my mail.
Now the from address is my email and the to address is the person who I want to send the email to.
So I've set up a new dummy account called App Brewery testing at Yahoo dot com and make sure that you
haven't got any typos in your email, your password, the SMTP URL, or the recipient email address.
Now, finally, the last thing we want to add is the message.
So this is what we actually want to send in our email.
And just like we did with our file when we opened it at the very end, once we're done with it, we're
going to close it off as well.
So now we can go ahead and hit run.
And you might get a number of errors at this point.
Now, it's important that if you do get an error, then you first check to make sure that you haven't
got any typos here, here, here or here.
But once you've checked that through, then the next thing you can do is you can actually look at this
error code and follow the URL.
Now, in our case, the reason is because by default, Gmail doesn't just let anybody access your email
account.
And you have other ways of making your account even more secure in order to send email from a Gmail
account with Python.
The first thing you have to do is create a special password for your application.
This means you have to go to the security settings for your Google account.
So if you're inside Gmail, go ahead and click on your profile.
Go to manage your Google account and then go to security.
Now, while you're here, you first have to turn on to step verification.
Once you've confirmed using your phone, go ahead and turn on two step verification.
And then go back to the security page.
And now you should be able to see this section.
App passwords show up.
Go ahead and click on it and enter your password for your Google account again.
And then go ahead and create a other type of app and we'll name it Birthday Wisher.
And click generate.
Now, here's the really important part.
You're going to get your app password show up here.
I want you to select all of it and copy it.
And then you'll be able to paste it inside your code.
Once we've done all of this, then we can go back and hit run again.
And you'll see this time we see the process finish with exit code zero, which means all of the code
ran successfully.
And now if I take a look at my sent box, you can see that I've got this message that's been sent.
And if I take a look at the email address which the email was sent to, then you can see that in my
inbox there's actually nothing here.
But if you take a look inside spam, then there is our brilliant email that came from our Python code.
So first thing I'm going to do is change that to not spam, to make sure that it goes into the actual
inbox.
And the next thing we want to be able to do is how can we make our emails seem less like spam?
So an email without a subject headline is prime target for being filtered as spam.
So let's go into our email and see how we can add a subject line.
It's pretty simple.
It goes inside the message parameter and all we have to do is just write the word subject colon and
then we can put in whatever it is that we want to use as the subject of the email like this.
Now, how do you put in the content or the body of the email?
Well, you add two new lines using backslash and backslash n, and then you can put the content.
So this is the body of my email and let's just split this up so it's a little bit easier to read.
And now I can hit run again.
And once that's done, you can see that in my Gmail in the sent folder that this message now has a subject
line and a body.
And it's the same thing when I go to my.
And when I take a look at this new email that came through, you can see the subject line and the body
of the email being separated.
Now we can actually avoid having to write this line connection close if we do the same trick as we did
with file opening, we use the with keyword, so we can say that with SMTP, SMTP to create the connection,
and then we save that as the connection.
Then we can indent all of the rest of the code inside this block.
And once it's done with sending the email, it will close off that connection automatically.
So this is how you could send email using Python and SMTP lib.
Now, there's quite a few things here that are prone to errors, especially given that we're typing
a lot of things in plain text, like our email or password and a bunch of things.
So if you're getting errors when you're running your code or if it's not doing what you expect it to
make sure that you've checked against all of these strings and it's actually what you expected it to
be.
Secondly, make sure that whichever account you're sending from that, you actually go ahead into the
account and modify the security settings.
For example, let's say I wanted to send from this email address, so I'm going to put that in here.
And then in this case, the email server I need to connect to will be Yahoo's email server, which is
under the URL that I showed you before SMTP dot mail, dot, Yahoo dot com.
And that is actually not enough.
So let me just change my recipient.
And I hit run.
This is the error that you'll see.
It says SMTP server disconnected connection unexpectedly closed.
Now, this could be down to a number of reasons.
For example, a typo in this part, but also if your account doesn't actually allow less secure apps.
So on Yahoo!
The process is a little bit different.
You have to go into your account, go to account info, and then go to account security.
And you'll have to log in again.
And generate a new app password.
So we're going to create a new app and we're going to give it a custom name, Python code, and then
click generate.
And now we have a app password to use for our Python code.
So now back over here, we change this password to the one that we just copied over.
And now if I hit run, that error should go away and we should get processed, finished with exit code
zero.
And when I take a look over here in my inbox.
I've got my email from Apple testing at Yahoo.com.
So check your security settings.
Check your spam and check that you haven't made any typos.
And if none of that works, then just simply try doing everything I did in the video.
But with a new email account that you set up with Gmail.
Then you can use the same SMTP address and the same process that you saw in the video to try this out.
In this lesson, I want to talk to you about the Python datetime module.
This is a really useful module that helps us work with dates and time.
Going back to our day 32 start project,
I'm going to comment out everything that's there.
And then I'm going to import our datetime module. Now, again,
this is the module that comes preloaded with Python
so you don't have to install it. Now,
one of the most useful things to get with daytime is the current date and time.
And you can write Python code to get that from the computer. Inside this date
time module,
there is a class called datetime as denoted by the c here.
And this is how you get to that class. So to get to that class,
you tap into the datetime module
and then you get to the datetime class.
Now this is really confusing.
So I prefer to rename the datetime module and give it a as so we can shorten it
to just dt.
And that way we can say dt.datetime
and that looks a little bit more easier to understand than before. Nnow,
inside this datetime class, there is a method called now,
and this gets you the current date and time.
So if we save this into a variable called now, and we go ahead and print
now, then when I run this code,
you can see it prints a very long string showing you the current year, month,
day,
as well as time in my local time zone with a high degree of accuracy
here.
Working with that particular string is not very easy.
If you wanted to check something like if now is the year 2020,
then you can't really do that with just a string like that.
That's why once you've gotten the
now object out of this method because this method of course returns and it gets
saved inside here, then we can tap into some of its attributes.
So for example, we can tap into the year.
So let's save that has the year. And if I print that, you can see
it just gives us the year as a number.
And if I do a type check on that,
you can see that it has a class of integer
whereas if I do a type check on now
it has a class of a datetime object.
So this way, if we managed to get hold of the year as a number,
then we can say something like, well,
if the current year is equal to 2020,
then we will print something like,
and because this rings out as true, then that gets printed out.
In addition to the year, we've also got month, day,
hour, minutes. So you can basically tap into anything in that date
time string as you need. So when you write 'now.'
you can see that there's the year, day, month, hour, minutes,
microsecond, second,
and you can get to the specific part of that datetime that you need.
You can even call other methods like weekday. For example,
if we want to know which day of the week it is, so Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday,
then we can simply tap into now and call this weekday method.
And now if we print out this day of the week,
you can see that it gives us a number.
So it remember that computers start counting from zero so 1
means that its actually the second day of the week, which is Tuesday
as you can see up here.
So we've seen how we can get hold of the current day, year,
month and whichever property you're interested in for today.
But what if we wanted to create a daytime object of our own setting it to a
particular date of our choosing? Well,
let's say that I wanted to create a object that stored my date of birth.
Well then I would tap into the dt module and create a new datetime object
from that class. Now I get to specify, well,
what is the year? What is the month?
What is the day?
And I can even go even more specific like which hour was I born in?
And you'll notice that in here, when you look at the parameters,
the year requires an integer,
the month requires an interger and the day requires an integer.
But after the hour we've got this ... as does the minute and the second
and this is because they have default values. So if I delete this,
the only things I'm required to give when I'm creating a new datetime object is
the year, month and day.
Let's say that I was born in 1995 and I was born in December the 15th.
All right.
Now,
if I print this date of birth object you can see that we get 1995,
12, 15,
and the time in hour, minute and second are set to the default values of zero.
If I wanted to be more specific and I wanted to set my hour of birth,
let's say I was born at 4:00 AM,
then we can set the hour and that updates that default value.
So now we've seen how we can tap into the current date time and also create any
datetime object from scratch
then it's time to put this into practice and use it in our project.
Now let's put what you've learned into practice by creating a Monday
motivational quote email application. To get warmed up,
we're going to create a application that looks at the current date and time
and if it happens to be a particular day of the week,
let's say a Tuesday,
then we're going to email ourselves a motivational quote.
So I found 101 Monday motivational !uotes from a place called the positivity
blog and I'll link to this as well.
But the idea is that we all need a little bit of boost on Monday mornings and
getting an email from Albert Einstein might just be the little nudge that we
need in order to push us onto a successful week.
So that's the idea.
And if you take a look in the starting project that you've already downloaded
and opened up, that should be a quotes.txt file.
And here on each line,
I've placed the quote from the positivity blog,
and it's got the quote and person on the same line.
So you can use what you've learned before where we went into how to read files,
how to open files,
how to create a list of all of the lines inside a particular text file.
And you can use that along with what you've learned about sending emails to
check and make sure that the day of the week is your current day of the week
because obviously you need to test this. Instead of setting it to check for
Monday, I want you to check for the current day that you are on.
So if it happens to be Tuesday, then check for Tuesday, if it Saturday,
then check for a Saturday and I want your Python code to make that check
and if it matches today's weekday,
then to send an email with a random quote from the quotes
.txt. That's the goal.
So I want you to pause the video and give it a go.
Yeah.
All right. So in order to complete this mini project,
we first have to import those two modules we learned about; smtplib
and also the datetime module. And again,
I'm going to import it as dt, so give it an alias. Next
we're going to tap into the dt module and we're going to get today's date and
time. So we're going to use this now method.
If now is equal to this,
then today in terms of the weekday is equal to now.weekday.
And once we've gotten hold of that, then we can check well,
if the weekday is equal to say Monday
which would be zero,
then that means we're going to activate the rest of our code and send ourselves
the email. But of course, in order to test our code,
unless you have the patience to wait until next Monday and test your code once
every week,
then we probably want to set this to equal to the weekday that we're on
today. So in my case, I'm on Tuesday so I'm going to set that to equal to 1,
at least while I'm testing my code. And once I'm done with everything,
I can reset that to 0 for Monday.
If the weekday is equal to 1,
then we're going to initiate our email sending mission.
But first we have to figure out what we're going to send.
So we're going to open up our quotes.txt and I'm going to use the with
and then I'm going to use the open method to open the quotes.txt file that
I've got right here.
And I'm going to call this the quote_file. Iside this quote_file
I've got a bunch of quotes, one on each line.
So we can use the method called readlines in order to get a list of all of the
lines in this quote_file and I'm gonna save it into all_quotes.
Now we can import the random module and we can tap into a random quote.
So we'll use random.choice and we'll get a random quote from this list of
quotes.
Now that we've created our quote inside this with block,
we can actually go outside of the with block and we can still access our
quote. So if I go ahead and print our quote,
you can see we've picked out a random quote. If you want to make an easy job
seem mighty hard just keep putting off doing it by Olin Miller.
And this is what we're going to try and send to ourselves using the smtplib.
Again, inside the same if statement, we're going to create a new connection
which is created from the smtplib and the SMTP class.
Now, once we create this class, we have to provide a host.
So that's the URL of the email server that we're going to use.
Again, I'm going to use my email as my testing Gmail
that was appbreweryinfo@gmail.com.
And then I'm going to put in my password as well as a constant
so this was abcd1234, and then brackets.
And then we can add our SMTP URL. Because we know that we're sending it from the
Gmail email service
then I'm going to tap into the Gmail SMTP server so that's smtp.gmail.com.
And instead of saving this as a connection,
I'm going to use the width method with SMTP as the connection.
Then using this connection, I'm going to firstly secure it.
So I'm going to starttls
and then I'm going to get this connection to log me in.
So the username is my email and the password is my password.
Once I've logged in to this connection,
then I'm going to finally send my email. Now, in this case,
the from address is going to be my email
and the to address is also my email.
I'm just sending an email from myself to myself,
but it's going to have a different piece of content every time it sends it.
And that message is going to contain that content.
So I'm going to change this into an f-string because firstly,
I want to have a subject which I'll call Monday Motivation
and then we know that we can add the content by adding two line breaks.
So let's format this so that it's easier for you to see.
And I'm going to put it on two separate lines like this.
Now after these two new lines comes my content
which is basically going to be my f-string
that's going to insert my quote right here.
So now with all of that done and making sure that our weekday is set as the same
day as today, so weekday ==
1, that is Tuesday. weekday == 0 means it's Monday.
Then we can be sort of sure that this code is actually going to run.
So now if we run our code,
you can see the quote being printed out here by Bertrand Russell.
And if we go to our email,
you can see that email from ourselves. Monday motivation.
One of the symptoms of an approaching nervous breakdown is the belief that one's
work is terribly important.
So I guess today's motivation is to not take ourselves too seriously.
But this is essentially what we're looking to achieve.
So hopefully you managed to get that working. If not,
you can take a look at my finished code
including all of the previous actions on smtplib
sending the email as well as date
time in the day 32 ending code that you'll find on the course resources page.
Now we're pretty much ready to tackle our final project,
which is the automated birthday wisher. So for that,
and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now it's finally time to put all of our skills to use by creating our automated
birthday wisher
which is going to send our family or friends
a "Happy Birthday" email on their birthday automatically.
Now the idea for this project actually came from my mum. Well,
inadvertently.
Now I love my mom to death and she is my biggest source of motivation and
inspiration. But on her birthday,
she always expects me to send her some form of "Happy Birthday" by like 8:00 AM
And
if I send her a message at, like, 8:05,
or 9 o'clock, God forbid,
then I am deemed as a *bad child*.
I don't know if this is true for you. Um,
maybe other Asian kids out there can relate,
but my mom has this thing about being wished a "happy birthday" promptly on her
birthday. And you know, I always remember her birthday,
but I just might remember it at 10 o'clock or, you know, at lunchtime.
And I always panic, um, thinking that I've forgotten or missed
the crucial eight o'clock in the morning time slot.
So what did I decide to do?
Um,
I decided to use Python to create a automated way of wishing her a happy
birthday at 8:00 AM on the spot or even seven o'clock or five o'clock. That way
she'll think that I wake up really early and
I am working really hard in life. But
let me demonstrate to you what this app is going to do. This is the birthday
wisher demo,
and I'm not going to show you the code in my main.py cause that is what
you're going to create.
But what I've got here is a CSV file called birthdays.csv.
Now, here, I'm going to change one of these rows of data to test it.
And I'm going to change the month to the current month
which is July and the day to the current day, which has 14.
So I'll change this
which corresponds to this column of data to 7 and then the day to 14.
And then I'm going to hit save to save that data.
And now I'm going to run this code
and what it will do is it'll check against all of these dates inside my
birthdays.csv,
it'll find that one of these rows of data actually has a month and day that
matches today.
And it will pick a random letter from one of these text files and replace this
name
placeholder with the name of the row of data that actually matched today's
date. And then it's going to send that as an email to this email.
So now if I go ahead and hit run,
and once that process is finished, we can go and check our email.
And you can see that email show up here with a subject line of Happy Birthday!,
and it's replaced the name of the person whose birthday it is right here inside
that name placeholder, it sent the rest of the message
and this was all done automatically. As you can imagine,
if I change this back to a random date,
if our code was running in the background every single day
checking to see if today's date matched one of these dates,
then the day when it actually matches or on their birthday,
it's going to pick out their name, insert it into one of these letters randomly,
and then send it to them as an email.
And the reason why we have three letters is just because so that they don't
actually clock onto the fact that it's the same letter being sent every single
year.
The ethics of this whole project is really up to you to decide. Um,
I don't actually do this in reality. Um,
I just live with being told I'm a bad child by wishing my mom happy birthday at
10:00 AM instead of 8:00 AM. But in terms of Python Programming,
this is going to be a really interesting project because it's going to use a lot
of the things that you've learned before
like pandas to read CSVs or replacing texts,
doing mail merge, using built in Python
ways of opening and reading files, and also of course what we learned recently
which is the datetime module and the smtplib.
Now the starting project I've split into three difficulty levels.
So depending on how comfortable you feel with the things that you've learned in
all of these 32 days,
you can pick which level of starting project you want to use.
Obviously, if you go for the extra hard starting project,
it's not going to have a lot of hints in there.
It's going to tell you generally what the program needs to do
and it's your job to figure out how to actually implement it using maybe a
Google search or Stack Overflow or looking through some of the path lessons.
This is going to be the extra hard version.
And then there's the hard version with some hints, but not a lot.
And there's the normal version where I've put in a lot more hints that will make
it a little bit easier for you to write out all the code.
So depending on how confident you feel, head over to the course resources,
pic the difficulty level for your starting project
and then go ahead and try to complete this project.
Now I hope you've given this project a good go because I'm going to now go
through the solution for the normal starting project. Now,
the important thing to stress here is that if you used one of the hard starting
project or the extra hard starting project,
you might have ended up with a different method of doing the same thing.
And often I get students asking me,
what is the right way of doing things?
And this is not really the thing that you should focus on. Instead,
use your creativity, you use your skills
and make sure that your program does what you want it to.
There is no real right answer.
It really depends on your preferences or even what it is that you know how to
do.
If you can get this project to work using just your own skills and a bit of
Googling, a bit of Stack Overflow, as long as you managed to get it to work,
it's way more important than what is the right way of doing things.
So all of that, I'm trying to say that I'm going to go through the solution,
but don't view this as the ultimate solution. And if you did it a different way,
that's totally fine as long as it works. Alright, let's get started. So here,
I've got these starting files for the normal starting project,
and I'm going to go through each of the lines line by line to create our final
birthday wisher project.
The first thing the instruction tells us to do is to go into this birthdays
.csv and update this with some birthdays of our friends and family.
So I'm going to replace all the data that's currently in here,
and I'm going to add some data of my own. Now,
the thing that we have to do in order to test this code is to make sure that one
of these rows of data actually matches an email that we can access
and also today's month and day.
So today is July 14th
so I'm going to update those two numbers and the year doesn't matter so much in
this case. Once I've done that,
I'm going to hit save, command + s or just go to file and go to save all.
And you can also see the shortcut for your particular operating system there as
well. Now, inside my main.py,
I've now completed this step. So I'm going to go ahead and delete it.
Now, step 2 is the hardest.
And here we have to check if today's date matches a birthday in the birthday
CSV.
The first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to import datetime
because that's going to be crucial for me to be able to figure out what today's
date actually is. And in fact, that is what hint one says.
It says to create a tuple from today's month and day using the datetime
module. This is essentially what we want to create.
So how do we get hold of today's month? Well,
we can use the datetime module and then the datetime class,
and then we can call now and we can get hold of the month like this.
Now we can simplify this in a number of ways.
We can create a alias for datetime as dt.
So then we can shorten this by a little bit, or
you can shorten it even more just by saying, well, from the datetime module
let's go ahead and import just the datetime class.
That way you can actually set this to simply as datetime.now.month.
Then we have to get hold of today's day so we could copy this
and instead of getting the month we could get the day.
So now we've created today. Now you can of course split this into two parts
if you find it easier to understand.
You could say that today well is equal to datetime.now,
and then today_tuple is equal to a tuple
which is today.month, today.day.
So this is another variation and there's millions of variations out there
of course. So I think we're now done with hint 1 so let's go and delete it.
Now we're onto hint 2.
We're going to use pandas to read from the birthday CSV.
So we're going to import pandas. And once we've imported that,
we're going to use pandas to read CSV and then provide our file name
which is birthdays.csv.
So I'm going to save this as a variable called data. And remember,
this is now a pandas dataframe
which we can use to do a number of things with including using these
instructions to create a birthday dictionary.
So what we're going to do is we're going to create a dictionary comprehension,
and I provided the template here for you already. So you can use that
iterrows in order to iterate through our dataframe that was created here,
so data.iterrows,
and then we'll get hold of the index of each of those rows and also the data in
each of the rows.
And then we could create a new dictionary with a new key and a new value from
all of these things that we've iterated through.
What is that new key going to be? Well, it's going to look something like this,
right?
We're hoping to create this birthday dictionary using this particular format.
Now the key is going to be a tuple that consists of the birthday month and the
birthday day
so let's replace that new key with a tuple. And the birthday month is of course
going to come from our data row. So that we're going to say data_row
and then we can either use square brackets
or we can use the dot notation to get hold of the data in this month column.
So you can either say data_row.month or data_row square brackets
and then month, like this. So it's totally up to you.
And then the next item in the tuple which is still in the key,
so we're still before the colon here, is going to be the birthday_day.
So that's going to be the data_row
and then we have to pass in the name of the day column,
which is just the word day.
Now, once we've done that,
then we have to provide what is the value for each of these key value pairs in
our dictionary. Well, what we actually want is the data row,
so the entire row of data, and we want it to look a bit like this.
So we have our tuple with our month and our day as the key
and then the value is just the entire row of data.
So we can simply replace this value with our data row like this.
Now we're pretty much done with this part and we can delete all of these bits of
hints and comments, and I can delete this example code as well.
Now that we've got our birthday dictionary,
the next thing we want to do is we want to check to see if today matches a
birthday in the birthdays.csv.
So you wanna check if this tuple exists inside this birthday_dict
and if it matches one of the actual birthday month and days.
So we can do something like this; if today_month, today_
day is in our birthdays dictionary.
Now this today_month today_day is of course going to be our today_
tuple. And this way with this
if statement we can check to see if this today_tuple with the month and day
actually exists as one of our friends and family's birthdays inside this
birthdays_dict. And once we've done that,
then we can get rid of step 2 and move on to step 3. In step 3
we're saying, well, if there is a match, so if this if statement is true,
then we're gonna pick a random letter out of letter_1, 2,
3, from our letter templates inside here. To do that,
we're going to need to think about the relative file path.
So we have to access the letter template folder to get to
each of these files.
The file path will look something like this.
It will be letter_template/ one of these letters for example,
letter_1.txt or letter_2 or 3. In fact,
this particular number is going to be something that we're going to generate
randomly and we're going to put in there as a f-string.
So I need to now import the random module in addition to everything else.
And we can go ahead and call the random module and get a randint between one and
three.
Like this.
So now we've completed these two hints, and finally,
we're going to use the replace() method to replace the name placeholder inside each of
these letters right here with the actual name of the person whose birthday it is.
Here I've linked it to the documentation for the replace keyword
and this is what it looks like. For example, if we have a string like this,
then we can say text.replace, take the word that we want to take out
and then the word we want to put in. In our case,
we're going to have to read the text from this file with our
with open, and then the file path goes in here,
and then we'll call this the letter_file.
And then from this letter_file,
we're going to get the contents by reading from this letter_file.
Right.
Now, once we've gotten the contents, then we can say contents.replace
and the thing that we want to replace is that hard-coded name placeholder
and the thing we want to replace it with comes from the current matching
birthday.
If the today_tuple exists inside our birthday dictionary,
then we can get hold of the entire row of data
...
by taking our birthday dictionary and then getting hold of the item at the key
which matches today_tuple.
Remember that today_tuple is the month and day as a tuple and the birthday
dictionaries all have keys as the birthday month and birthday day as a tuple.
So we've checked that this tuple exists as a key inside the birthday
dictionary,
and then we use the square bracket to actually access the data row for that
particular match. And then we've got the birthday_person,
so from that birthday_person
we're going to get hold of their name.
And the name lives under the name column here.
As long as we put the name as a string,
then we should be able to get hold of their actual name right here.
And that is the end of step 3.
So now we're finally moving on to step 4
where we're going to send our letter
which was generated here in our contents,
and we're going to send it to that birthday person's email address.
So the first thing we're going to need is to create a connection and we're going
to use the smtplib library to do that.
So import smtplib. And then we're going to say with smtp
lib.SMTP, let's create an object from that
and we have to provide the host string. So as I mentioned before,
depending on which email provider you use, it will be different.
Now I'm going to put in my email and password at the top as constants.
Of course, this is not going to work for you
so you're going to have to use your own email and password.
And depending on which email provider you use,
you'll have to pick the correct SMTP. So I'm sending emails
using Gmail so I'm going to change this to smtp.gmail.com.
And I'm going to save this connection that I create as the connection.
Step 2 is to go ahead and call the starrttls.
So we'll get our connection and then call starttls.
And then step 3  is to log in to our connection by calling login.
And then we have to provide the email that we want to log into and the password
for that email account. Finally,
we're going to set up the subject and the content by calling connection.
sendmail. And the from address is MY_EMAIL,
the to address is going to be the email of the birthday person.
So we're going to get our birthday_person
and then we're going to get hold of their email by looking at the name of the
email column, which is just email actually like this.
And then finally, we can add in the actual message.
I'm going to again,
format this so that it's a little bit easier to read for you.
And then we're going to set up our message.
This is going to be an f-string and the subject is always going to be the same.
It's going to be happy birthday.
And then after two of these new lines, we can add the actual message body.
Now the message body is going to be the contents that we created because,
remember, that takes a random letter, reads it
and then replaces in the name placeholder with the birthday person's name.
So that's what we're going to put in here.
And now that's step 4 completed as well
and we can now go ahead and run this file.
And hopefully it will show us process finished with exit code zero,
which is the best thing we can see. That means everything went well.
And remember that the birthday
which I set to test was this row of data.
So it should have replaced a random letter's placeholder with the name of mum
and it should've sent that email to appbreweryinfo@gmail.com. So now
if I take a look at my appbreweryinfo@gmail.com,
you can see the email come through, but you might notice a bug here.
The name was actually never replaced. Instead,
we're still seeing this placeholder.
So this is a really common mistake that a lot of people make
and the reason is because the text replacement comes out as the output.
So it doesn't actually change the original text just by calling that method.
Instead,
you have to save it to a new variable in order to see the replaced text.
So in our case what that means is we can't just say content.replace.
We actually have to say contents = contents.replace.
So we replace the contents and then we save it back to the original variable.
So now if I run this again, you can see that this time
our message actually has the name replaced in here,
it has a random letter that it's generated and it has sent it to the correct
email address. If you want to take a look at the completed code,
then you'll find it in the course resources as the end code for the birthday
wisher project
and this contains a lot of things that we've talked about so far,
including dictionary comprehension, reading CSVs,
creating dataframes from pandas, using and creating tuples,
working with dictionaries, file paths, opening files,
replacing files, reading them, and of course,
writing and sending email as well as the datetime module.
So if you got stuck on any of these aspects,
then be sure to take a look at the previous lesson where we covered them
because we covered all of these concepts in a lot of detail in previous lessons.
So make sure that you don't just skip ahead if you actually got stuck.
It probably is an indicator that it's a good time to revisit and review some of
these concepts. For example, if you got stuck on dictionary comprehension,
then go back to the lessons where we did list and dictionary comprehensions
and try out some of the exercises again, just to refresh your mind. Now,
if you got stuck on working with the iterrows or the data that comes from our
pandas dataframes, then go back to those lessons where we talked about CSVs,
and we talked about pandas because nothing here is new,
but it does require your understanding and your ability to know how to apply the
knowledge that you've learned before. Now,
the final thing I want to show you in the next lesson is how to get this code to
actually run every day so it can actually check every single day to see if it
needs to send out a birthday email.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In previous lessons,
we completed our automated birthday wisher Python project
and also the motivational quotes on Monday's Python project.
But at the moment,
you'll notice that this code is only going to work to continuously check to see
which day it is currently, compare it against the birthdays,
and then run the code
if this code is actually running constantly in the background.
Now you could of course, open up your project in PyCharm,
hit run every single day and make sure that it works,
but that's actually more effort than wishing somebody happy birthday manually.
So what do we do instead? Well,
we want some sort of way where we can host our code in the cloud and run our code
every single day.
So one way of doing that is using a service called Python anywhere,
and they have a free tier where we can do exactly that without having to pay
anything. Head over to python
anywhere.com and go ahead and sign up for a new account.
Now, once you've signed up and signed in,
then you want to go ahead and start adding some files.
Head over to the files tab right here
and we're going to upload the files that's currently inside our birthday wisher
project. So that's our main.y, our birthdays.csv,
and also our letter templates.
Now we want our letter templates to be inside a folder, so we're going to
create a new directory called letter_templates.
Make sure there's no typos there.
And then inside this directory is where we're going to upload these three files.
So letter 1, 2 and 3.
So now we've got our letters inside hom/AppBrewery/letter_
templates, and inside AppBrewery
we've got our birthdays.csv and our main.py.
So now we're going to go into our console and we're going to create a new bash
console. So we're going to click on this link right here,
and then once all of that's loaded and you see this dollar sign right here,
we're going to type python3 main.py.
Now you might see this error right here, the SMTP authentication error.
And this is something that happens because our Python program is trying to log
into our email, and our email provider in this case,
it's Google, is actually blocking it. So we can copy this URL and you can see it
ends right here
cause there's a space there, and we can paste it into the address bar and it
takes us to this problem.
I can't sign into my email client, and this is essentially what our Python code
is trying to do.
So what we need to do is click on this link to display the unlock capture, we
click continue, and it's now enabled our code to sign in again.
So we have to go back and type in exactly the same as we did before, python3
main.py.
But this time it should complete without giving us any errors
and it does that by showing us the dollar sign again and our prompt.
And now if I head back into my email,
you can see that this email was actually sent because the code was initiated
inside Pythonanywhere. So going back to our Python
anywhere dashboard,
we can go to the task section to actually schedule
a task to run. Now to set up a scheduled task,
we're going to type the same command that we did in the console
which is python3 main.py.
And then we're going to schedule this at a particular time.
And the server time is based on UTC.
So you can take a look at the current time in UTC
by typing in UTC now into Google
and you can see right now it's 12:09.
So if I go ahead and schedule this for 12:10
and I hit create,
then at the time when this particular time hits,
when it becomes 12:10, then our command should be run
and we should see a happy birthday email show up in our testing Gmail account.
So right now UTC has just gone to 12:10.
And so if we wait for this schedule task,
we can click on this button to view the task log and you do have to be quite
patient because sometimes it might take a while before that task actually gets
executed. So just keep checking the task log until you see this happen.
Completed task at 12:10:56, o at the end of that minute.
Took 16.92 seconds return code was zero, which means it was successful.
And now we can see that email show up in our Gmail account and this was
completely automated and it was done by Python anywhere.
So now if we have that code running in the background every day,
you can get it to run that code at this particular time or another time of your
choosing in fact. If you're not testing it,
you can actually get it to run much earlier. Let's say maybe seven o'clock UTC.
Then it'll send the email out in the morning.
And every day it's going to check whose birthday it is in your birthday CSV
and then send an email to them and do all of that fancy stuff
using what we did with Python. Python anywhere has really good forums for help
and advice. And on the free tier,
you can only schedule one task to run, so one particular code base.
Now I don't work for them and I have no relations to them,
but I find it really helpful to have a really simple way of getting my Python
scripts to run everyday at a particular time.
So have a look at that and you can use it if you find it helpful as well.
Hey guys,
Welcome to Day 33 of 100 Days of Code. It's Angela here
and today we're going to be learning about application programming interfaces,
also known as APIs. What are we going to use it for? Well,
we're going to learn this technology so that we're able to create an ISS
tracker.
So this is the international space station and it floats high above in the sky
and it circles earth many, many times a day.
Here's a video that's taken from the ISS and you can see how glorious earth
looks in the eyes of the ISS.
And what we're going to try to do is we're going to try and track where the ISS
is currently at in the sky. And at the time point
when the ISS is in the night sky, right above where we are,
then we're going to send ourselves an email
telling us to look up and spot the fast-moving ISS.
Once you are ready, head over to the next lesson and we'll get started learning
about APIs.
First, let's take a look at what application programming interfaces
are and then we'll see how we can use them to start pulling in some data from the
internet. So when you're browsing the web,
you might've realized that there's a lot of websites out there that carry a
whole bunch of data. For example,
you could go onto Yahoo weather and see next week's weather predictions for
any city in the world,
you could go onto Coinbase and see what is the current market value of various
cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin and Ethereum.
You can also go onto the MBA website and look at various stats about your
favorite basketball players. Now,
what if we wanted to use the data that they have?
How can we tap into it and use it in our own programs? Well,
that's where application programming interfaces come into play.
They all are a set of commands, functions, protocols, and objects
that programmers can use to create software or interact with an external system.
In the upcoming lessons
what we're going to be focusing on is this interacting with external systems.
Namely,
we're going to try and interact with various websites and pull live data from
those websites. Essentially,
the API is an interface or rather a sort of barrier between your program and an
external system.
And what you're trying to do is you're trying to use the rules that the API has
prescribed to make a request to the external system for some piece of data.
And if you have structured your request
according to all of the requirements that this external system has set out in
their API,
then they will respond to you appropriately and give you the data that you want.
But if you don't follow the rules,
then your request will be invalid and they will tell you to go away.
So if we think about the websites we saw before, Yahoo weather has a Yahoo
weather  API
which you can tap into using your programs or apps and get things like 10-day
forecast, wind, atmosphere, astronomy conditions,
and Coinbase has their own API,
which lets you tap into the current live prices of various cryptocurrencies.
And of course, the MBA also has an API for you to be able to get various
information that you're interested in on leagues, teams, players, games and a whole
bunch more.
So essentially, you can imagine these websites as the sort of restaurant,
right?
And the data that powers these websites as the kitchen behind the scenes.
We can't really go to a restaurant as a member of the public and just go in to
the kitchen and start raiding their cupboards. You can't, you know,
imagine going to your favorite Japanese restaurant and heading straight into the
kitchen for some of your favorite Kewpie mayonnaise.
That's not really appropriate. In a restaurant
we have a menu and this menu is kind of like the interface between you and the
restaurant.
It's the thing that tells you what you can order and what you can't.
So maybe you can get a cake, a sandwich or tea from the restaurant,
but you can't just go into the kitchen and demand whatever it is that you want.
Essentially an API is exactly that. It's the menu.
It's all of the things that you can do to interact with
an external system such as a website
that carries data like Yahoo
weather or the MBA website. In the coming lessons
we're going to be looking at how we can read the documentation for the API and
interact with them to be able to pull pieces of data that
we want in the moment that we want it. So for all of that and more,
I'll see on the next lesson.
Now,
one of the most important aspects of an API is the API endpoint.
And you can imagine that as a location, right?
So we said that if we want to get data from a particular external service,
then we need to know what location that data is stored. So for example,
if you wanted to get money out of a bank,
then you need to know where that bank is and what is its address.
And that, when it comes to API
lingo, is called the API endpoint. And that's usually just a URL.
So for example, if you wanted to get crypto data,
you might use api.coinbase.com.
This is the location where the Coinbase data can be found.
Now, in addition to knowing the API endpoint,
you also have to make a request over the internet.
This API request is kind of similar to going to the bank and trying to get some
money out, so trying to withdraw some data from their vault.
As you can imagine, the world would be completely chaotic
if everybody was allowed to just go into a bank and take out the amount of money
they need without any sort of checks and balances.
So that's why, in the bank, you have a bank teller
so somebody who is there to ask you, "Can I help you? What you want?" and to prevent you
from going to the vault by yourself. And to also call the police
if you try to do that. Now this bank teller is kind of acting like the API.
It's the interface between you and the external system or between you and the
bank vault. And you can make a number of requests to this lady.
You could, of course, ask her to give you some money,
but that obviously is going to involve checking your ID,
making sure that you have your account number and she'll have to do a whole
bunch of checks.
But you can also go into the bank and ask the bank teller for things that
doesn't require any form of authentication. For example, you can say,
well, what are your opening hours?
And this is the equivalent of making a very,
very simple get request where you just try to get a piece of data from a website
using their API. Now,
one of the simplest APIs that I like to introduce students to is the
international space station current location API.
This is the endpoint,
and you can see that it returns the output in the form of a JSON,
which we've already played around with quite a bit.
If you want to make a request to this API,
you can of course use your browser to do it. Just paste the end point,
which is a URL into the address bar.
And once you hit enter, you can see the result
come back in the format of a JSON.
And this describes the current ISS position in terms of its longitude and
latitude. If I refresh this,
then I will make a new request to this end point
and I will get a slightly different piece of data back because the ISS is moving
actually quite fast through the air. So every time you can see that
it's moved by a little bit. Now, if
reading the data like this is a bit difficult,
I recommend installing a free Chrome browser plugin quote, JSON Viewer
Awesome
and what it will do is whenever it sees JSON data being rendered in the
browser,
it will display it in a nice tree structure and it will look something like
this.
So you can collapse each of these parts and you can see that this is a
dictionary effectively with three items, timestamp, message, ISS position.
And then when you tap into the ISS position,
you can get the longitude and latitude.
Now we've already seen the JSON data format,
and we know that it was originally created for JavaScript,
but later became almost the standard way of transferring data across the
internet. And the reason for it is really simple.
If you take something like a Python dictionary, let's say you have a wardrobe,
right? It's kind of like you're going to Ikea. You spotted a wardrobe
you would like, but you don't want to carry this home in its entirety.
It might not even fit in your car. Well, what do you do? Well in Ikea,
at least the way they've solved it, is they sell you a flat pack.
So all the pieces flat against each other and you go home and you build it
yourself. This is the equivalent of a JSON. It's very minimalist,
it doesn't have a lot of spaces and a lot of indents.
It just has a couple of symbols to denote which are the keys,
which are the values, which are the separate key-value pairs.
And this can be transported across the internet very,
very quickly because of how small and flat it is. Now,
once you receive this JSON,
then you can reconstitute it back to your original Python dictionary or a
JavaScript object depending on what programming language you were working with.
And this is the equivalent of taking a screwdriver and putting it together that
Ikea furniture.
But luckily for you, this process is a lot less painful than putting together
Ikea furniture. It's actually super easy.
Let me demonstrate. Here
I've created a brand new project from scratch day-33 and inside my main.py
I'm going to try and make a request to the ISS location API.
So the first thing I need to do is I need to import a library to help me to do
that.
And the one that I'm going to import is called requests and note that there's an
's' at the end.
And this has to be installed because it does not come prebuilt with Python.
So you can click on it, and then once you see the red light bulb,
click on it and get it to install the package called requests.
Once that's done, then you'll be able to use it. Now,
what we're going to do using this requests package is we're going to call one of
its methods called get.
So this is going to help us get the data that we want from the endpoint.
The endpoint goes in in an argument called the URL,
and we have the check the documentation to know what the endpoint is.
So in this case, if we want to get hold of the current location,
then this is the endpoint URL.
So we can simply copy it and paste it in here as a string.
Now, once we've gotten the data from this,
then it's going to be returned and we can capture it inside a new variable
which we'll call response.
So this is going to be equal to the response that we get back from this
particular website's API.
Now let's go ahead and print this response.
So let's run our project and making sure that you are connected to the internet
because this line of code is going to go across the internet and fetch this data
for us. We get back a response.
Now we have successfully made our very first API request from within our Python
code. However, when we print the response,
we don't see the JSON data like we did when we made the request directly inside
our browser. Instead, we see this number 200 printed here.
That is our response code. And in the next lesson,
we'll dive deeper into how to work with these responses and what exactly these
response codes mean.
So what are the response codes that we can get from an API?
Response codes actually have a very specific meaning,
but the most important thing they tell us is if our request succeeded or
if it failed. Now, if you've been using the internet for a while,
you've probably come across the 404 response code. And the 404
response code basically means that the thing that you're looking for doesn't
exist. And you can see various websites having fun with this
404 page.
Basically when you're trying to retrieve something from a website and it doesn't
actually have the thing you're looking for, then this is the code you get.
But there's actually a lot more response codes other than just 404.
And in fact,
you could summarize these status codes just by looking at the first number.
If it is 100 and something, then it's telling you, hold on,
something's happening. This is not final.
If it's 200 something then it is saying, here you go. Everything was successful.
You should be getting the data you expected.
If it's 300 something then it usually means you don't actually have permission
to get this thing, so go away. 400 something, it means that
you screwed up. Either it could be a 404
which means that you screwed up
and the thing you're looking for doesn't even exist,
or it could be 500 something, which means I,
as in the server that you are making the request to, screwed up. And maybe the
server is down, maybe the website is down or maybe there's some other issue.
So that's just a quick,
at a glance, sort of way of remembering what's actually happening
when you are getting these response codes.
Now you can actually dig deeper into this response object and you can get a
whole bunch of things from it. For example,
if you wanted to know the actual status code instead of just a response object,
then you can say response.status_code,
and you actually only get the status code. But notice how
if I change this URL and I make a typo in here,
instead of iss I have is,
then now I get a 404 as my response status code.
OK. So if we get the status code 200 then it means that we were successful.
But what do we do when we get a different status code?
What should our program do when the request fails?
We might be tempted to write code like this. By checking to see if the response
.status_code is not equal to 200,
we can actually figure out well, this means that there probably was an error.
Now it doesn't really make sense to just print out an error because the user who's
using our program might be expecting something to happen.
So in most, cases you might want to raise an exception instead.
You could say bad response from ISS API.
But we learned from our module on errors and exceptions,
this is not very good. Firstly, this is not a very specific exception.
It's going to raise a very general type of exception. And secondly,
all that we're catching is when the status code is not 200.
What if we wanted you to know specifically which status code we got back? Well,
we could, of course check well
if the response status code was equal to say
404, then we'll raise a particular type of exception that says that resource
does not exist. And then we can have,
um, an elif that says, well,
if the response status code was 401,
then that means that you should raise an exception because this particular code
only happens when you are not authorized to access this data.
Now there's a lot of status codes that you could be getting back.
And in the course
resources I'll link to this particular web page where it tells you all of the
possible codes that you could be getting and what it means. As you can imagine,
it's impossible for us to write this many
if statements checking for every single possibility. What do we do instead?
You can actually do away with all of this by getting the request module
to generate the exception instead.
The requests module is the most popular way for Python developers to work with
APIs. And you can see in their statistics just the number of stars,
number of forks,
and from these stats, you can see just how much active development there is and
how popular this particular module is. Now,
if you want to take a look at the documentation,
then you get taken to their website and it tells you all of the things that it
can do, which is quite a lot actually.
Now I won't read through all of this with you,
but if we take a look at one of the sections, Errors and Exceptions,
you can actually call raise for status on the response you get back in order
to raise a HTTP error
if the request returned an unsuccessful status code.
Basically instead of us trying to raise an exception for every single possible
status code and telling the developer what might be the reason, we can simply use
the request module by saying response.raise_for_status.
So now what you'll see is that if we don't get a 200
which is the pass-- Let's say I mess up this end point again,
then you'll see an exception being raised and it's telling us, look,
it's a 404 client error. This URL is not found.
So this request module is actually really powerful and we're going to see how to use
various aspects of it in the upcoming lessons.
But for now, the first thing we need to get hold of is the actual data from this
particular API. To do that,
we tap into our response and we get the JSON data.
So this is the actual data. And when I print it,
you can see that it looks exactly the same as what we got in our browser.
Coming back to our code where we have this JSON,
we can tap into it just like we would for any Python dictionary.
We could use some square brackets and then type in the name of a key that we're
interested in. For example,
if this was a Python dictionary and we wanted to know the iss_position,
then we would add the square brackets and then pass in iss_ position.
And now when we print data,
you can see it's now narrowed down and drilled into the position to give us this
longitude and latitude.
So we can go even further and tag on another set of square brackets and try to
get hold of, say the longitude.
And now we get that actual piece of data. There you have it.
We get access to the longitude by tapping into our data in the format of a JSON
and then getting the iss_position. And inside that dictionary,
we can get hold of the longitude. And we can do the same thing in order to get
hold of the latitude,
right?
But we would change the key of course, to latitude.
So now I'm going to create a tuple with the longitude and the latitude.
And now if I print it out,
you can see how I've managed to nicely format my code and get the pieces of
data that I want in order to be able to work with it in my project. Now,
if you wanna see where that particular latitude and longitude is on the world
map, then we can use a tool called latlong.net.
So if you go to geographic tools and go to latitude and longitude to address,
then you can paste in the longitude and latitude values that we got from
our API. And when we click convert, then you'll see on the map,
it shows where in the world the ISS is right now.
So at the moment, it's somewhere to the East of Japan over the Pacific ocean.
And of course, it's telling you no address found because I don't think anybody
lives right there.
So have a play around with that and make sure that you've fully understood
what's happening in these few lines of code and how we use the API endpoint to
get the data that we're showing up right here. In the next lesson
I've got a challenge for you.
Now that you've seen how you can make the most basic type of request to an API
endpoint, I want you to build a Kanye quote machine.
This is what it's going to look like and these are real Kanye quotes.
So every time you click on this button
which has a Kanye emoji, you can see
he'll say different things.
And some of the things he says are incredibly deep and other things are a little
bit weird. But we've created the starting file for this
so you don't have to spend a lot of time building up the UI.
All I want you to do is to figure out how to use the API
which is at kanye.rest
and this is the API endpoint. So you can test it out of course
in your browser just by putting it into the URL bar.
And you can see you get back a very simple JSON with just one key and one
value. And every time you run it, it'll give you a random quote.
Head over to the course resources and download the Kanye quote
starting file. And once you've unzipped it and opened it up,
you can see that there's the background.png, the kanye.png,
and there's all of the existing code that's required to generate this user
interface in tkinter. The point here is,
I know you can make tkinter apps,
but I want you to use the request module that you learned about just now in
order to get this function to work so that every time the Kanye button,
this one, is pressed, then we trigger this get_quote function.
And this is going to fetch the quote from the Kanye API here and fill it into
this quote_text on the canvas. Using what you've learned before
I think you can do this pretty quickly. So pause the video now and give it a go.
Yeah.
All right. So to begin,
we, of course, need to import our very important requests module,
and you need to install it if you see some red squiggly lines.
But if you see it grayed out like this then it means that we've already installed
it into the starting files. Now,
once we've got hold of that module,
then we can write some code here so that we get our function to work.
Now, what should happen when the user presses on the Kanye button? Well,
we have to fetch a new quote from the API.
This is the API endpoint
and we're going to use the requests module to make a request and get some data
from this API.
So this is the code that we used before to figure out where the ISS was.
And we're going to save this as the response. Now,
once we've got our response,
we're going to call response.raise_for_status.
So if we don't get a 200, which is everything is okay,
then we want to actually raise an exception. Now,
the next thing we're gonna do is I'm going to get my response to show me the
JSON data. And I'm gonna save that as the data.
And then if we take a look at what the response looks like,
then you can see it's just a single key-value pair
and the key is quote and the value is the random quote.
So we can get hold of the actual quote by simply tapping to our data and then
using square brackets to fetch the value under the key quote.
And once we've got that piece of text,
then we want to put it into our quote_text which is on our canvas.
And as you saw before,
the way we do this is we say canvas.itemconfig.
And the item we want to configure is, of course, our quote_text.
And the thing that we want to configure about it is its text.
And we're going to set it to equal this quote that we fetched just now.
So now if I run my code,
you can see my Kanye says app showing up,
and this is where the Kanye quote is going to go.
So if I click on Kanye, you can see how it shows all of his quotes.
So did you manage to get that? If not, be sure to head back to the last lesson and
take a closer look at how we formatted our request and our response.
We've seen how APIs can have endpoints and we said
that's equivalent to the address of the place that you want to get some data
from, or you want to communicate with.
But APIs also have something called parameters.
And this is a way that allows you to give an input when you are making your API
request so that you can get different pieces of data back,
depending on your input in the same way that we've given different inputs into
the same function in order to get a different outcome.
Coming back to our bank analogy, that's kinda similar to going to the bank
and instead of just asking them for what are your opening hours,
a sort of broad stroke question, you can also pass in a parameter.
For example, you could say, well, what time do you close on Monday?
Or what time do you close on Tuesday?
And this allows you to get these specific piece of information that you're
interested in depending on the input that you provided as a parameter.
Now, not all APIs have parameters. Some are incredibly simple,
like the ISS location API.
But other ones allow you to provide parameters.
And this is a sunrise and sunset API that gives you the time when the sun is
gonna rise and set wherever you may be.
So you have to obviously provide a location so that they can tell you when the
sun is going to rise and set at your position.
We can do that through two parameters, the latitude and the longitude.
And you'll notice that in the API documentation,
they will usually tell you how you should structure your parameter.
So for example, here
the latitude can be specified using a lat key,
and the longitude is lng as the longitude.
And they want those pieces of input as floating-point numbers. Now,
you also see that some parameters are required and others are optional. Just as
we can have optional and required parameters when we create functions,
you have the same thing in APIs.
The optional ones all have a default value.
For example, the date you could provide,
say you wanted to know the sunrise and sunset on a particular day in the future
or in the past, but you can also leave it empty
and it will default to the current date.
Now the endpoint in this case is this particular URL,
api.sunrise-sunset.org/json. But don't worry.
I'll also link to this documentation in the course resources as well.
Let's see how we can get this to work.
I'm gonna comment out all of the things that were related to our ISS location,
and I'm going to use this requests module in order to get the sunrise and sunset
times
because this is going to be really important when we're creating our final
project
because it's almost impossible to spot the ISS in the sky unless it's actually
dark.
So we need to know when the sun is going to go down and when the sun's going to
come back up in order for us to know
if the sky is actually dark enough for us to be able to spot the ISS
traveling in the sky. Let's go ahead and set up another response
which is going to be set up to a request.
And this request is going to get some information from this particular endpoint.
So let's copy that over and make sure that you leave out this final
full stop.
That's just a part of the sentence and not a part of the API endpoint.
So it should look something like this.
And then we're going to get our response to raise an exception if there was an
error status code. So anything other than 200, basically. Now, if I run this
as it is, you can see I already get an exception.
And the exception is a 400
which, if you remember, means bad request.
This server cannot or will not process the request because of something that they
think is your fault. In our case,
the thing that we've done badly is we haven't provided the required parameters.
So how is it supposed to tell us the sunrise and sunset times
if we don't tell it our location? Let's fix this.
Let's create a set of parameters and you can do this by simply creating a Python
dictionary.
Now the keys for the parameters must match the ones specified in the API
documentation.
So it's lat for latitude and lng for longitude.
So let's create those keys as strings,
and then we can provide our latitude and longitude.
So how do we know what is our latitude and longitude? Well,
we've got our good old friend latlong.net.
So here I can type a particular place name. So right now I'm in London.
And if I click find, it will find me on the map and it will tell me what is my
latitude and what is my longitude.
So let's copy these over and let's create them as constants.
So I'm going to have a MY_LAT
which is equal to this as a floating point number.
And then my longitude--
Remember to include any negative signs if you see it.
That's actually a part of the latitude longitude encoding.
So now I can set my lat key to the constant
MY_LAT and the longitude key to the constant MY_LONG.
So these are the values that I got from my latlong.net search and
then I formatted all of this into a dictionary using the keys that were
specified in the API documentation here.
Those are the only two required parameters.
So if we now add this in to our get requests under the argument called params,
then we're now able to run this request again
and you'll see that this time we don't get any exceptions.
So we can assume that everything went swimmingly.
The data that we get back is under the response.json.
So let's go ahead and print out that data and see what we managed to get.
We got a JSON as usual and the JSON contains the sunrise time and the sunset
time, in addition to other things like when is the solar noon,
how long is the day, what is the day length and so on and so forth.
So you can see this one is a lot longer than what we had before. Now,
the two pieces of information that we're interested in is just the sunrise and
sunset times.
If we want to view this JSON data in a nicely formatted way,
then we can do that by putting the full request into the browser URL bar. And the
way that you format parameters in a URL string
looks something like this. In the sample requests,
they've shown you that this part is the end point URL.
And then afterwards you can add a question mark to denote that you're going to
add some parameters.
And then you add each parameter with the key equal sign and then the value
and then you can tag on more parameters with the ampersand or the and symbol.
So let's try putting this into our browser bar.
So here's the latitude which we'll paste in here
and here's the longitude which we'll paste in here.
So now let's hit enter and you can see there our JSON Awesome
Viewer which we installed at the beginning of today's lessons is now active
and it's showing us all of this data in a much nicer format.
So we can see that this sunrise time that we're interested in is the value for the
key sunrise which is then inside of another key called results.
So we can use these two keys to pull out these specific pieces of data that
we're interested in. So we can get the sunrise
which is equal to data, and then square brackets
we put in the first key
which is results
with an s and then we can add the next key
which is sunrise.
And we can do the same thing for the sunset time.
And now if we print out our sunrise or our sunset time,
you can see its actually the exact piece of information that we're interested
in. Notice how this data is formatted
and it's giving us the time in a 12-hour format.
So it's going to have AM or PM tagged on at the end.
Now what we want to do is we want to be able to get the current time so we can
use the datetime module. From the datetime module, we'll import the date
time in class.
And then we can get the time now by tapping into that class and then calling the
now method.
But you'll notice that the format of time now is very different from our sunrise
and sunset time. Our sunrise and sunset time
are in the 12 hour format
whereas the time that we're getting back from datetime is in a 24-hour clock
format.
So how can we change this data that we're getting back from the sunrise and
sunset API? Well, back to the API
we go. Notice in one of the parameters, there is a parameter called
formatted which is an optional parameter,
but it can be turned off or on.
On is by default,
which means it's going to format it in a particular way with the 12-hour clock.
But if you switch off the formatting,
then it will give you the Unix time in this particular format and this will be a
24-hour clock. So here's your challenge.
Go ahead and change the parameters that you have and make sure that the data
that we get back is not formatted, so it's set to zero.
Pause the video and complete this challenge. Alright,
all we have to do is to add one more parameter to this dictionary and the
parameter must have a key that matches the one specified in the documentation,
so I'm just going to copy that over, and then we're going to set this to 0
for off. So now if we rerun our code,
you can see the data we're getting back is now in Unix time
which is a 12-hour format time.
So currently where I am in London
the sunrise time is actually quite early, it's at four o'clock in the morning.
So notice how the first part is the date
and then we have a T and then after that we've got the time.
What we want to be able to do is to compare this part from our sunrise
sunset API against this part from our datetime API.
So how can we just isolate the hour number from each of these?
Well, we can use a Python method called split,
and you've seen this before.
Basically you have to provide a separator and it will split a string by that
separator creating a list. So if you click on this, try this yourself,
you can see that this string becomes this list by splitting that string with the
pound sign separator. Now, in our case,
the separator that we want to separate by is firstly,
to split it by this T,
which is going to give us this part as the first item in the list and this part
as the second item in the list.
And then we can take the second part and then split it by the colon and then we can
get this first part of the list. So here's how we would do it.
So we can say sunrise.split
and then the separator we want to use was that capital T.
Now if I hit print,
you can see we've got a list that is now separated with two things on either
side of the T. So let me just comment out the time now
and we've got the sunrise and the sunrise split next to each other.
So that T is removed
and the two things on either side have become two items in our list.
Now we want to split this part further.
We can get this item by tapping into the item at index one,
so 0, 1,
and then we can split this even further by tagging on another split function.
Here, we can split it by the colon. So let's go ahead
and provide that as the input.
And now you can see the result we get back is this. We've split the part that
comes after the T by the colon and we've got 04,
03, 32+00, and then 00.
This is clearly the item we want
so all we have to do is just to add a zero at the end.
And now we've got the actual
hour in the 24-hour clock formatted from our sunrise time.
You could in fact,
just simply take all of this part after the sunrise and tag it onto the end of
this line and also this line so that we actually get the sunrise and sunset
times in terms of the 24-hour clock, like this.
Now we're perfectly poised to start comparing it against the time that we're
getting right now.
So we can take our time now and tap into the actual hour,
and you can see now that we've got our sunrise, which is this first number,
sunset, which is the second number,
and the third number is the current clock time in terms of the 24-hour clock.
So in order to figure out whether if it is day or night,
all we have to do is compare this number against these other two.
Now in the next lesson,
we're going to finish off this project and put everything together in order to
get an email when the ISS is passing overhead and it's currently nighttime.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
All right. Congratulations on reaching the final project for the day.
Head on over to the course resources and download the starting files for the ISS
overhead notifier project.
If you followed along with all the lessons today,
then you've seen how we can get data from a particular API by simply just
providing an endpoint. So this is the simplest type of API calls.
And then you saw how we could pass, along with the API call, a set of parameters
in the form of a Python dictionary in order to get a specific piece of data that
we want based on the parameters that we pass over. So in this case,
it was the sunrise and sunset time of our local area.
Now later on,
I showed you how we can split the string that we get back from the sunrise and
sunset times in order to get the particular numbers that we're interested in,
which is the time of the sunrise and sunset in the 24-hour clock format.
Now it's time to put all of this together.
If the ISS is close to my current position and it's currently dark,
so basically it's nighttime, then send me an email to tell me to look up.
That's the objective of the challenge. However, as a bonus challenge,
see if you can further modify the code so that it runs every 60 seconds
if the ISS is overhead.
These are the three things that we need to achieve. And just as a quick tip
before you get started,
remember that the sunrise and sunset times are both in the format of strings.
So if you want to be able to work with them to compare to time
now, you also have to change this to an integer.
Now, the second tip I've got is that the ISS position,
the longitude and latitude that you get back, will be decimal numbers,
but it is currently in the format of a string.
So you'll need to convert that into a floating-point number
if you want to compare it against your current position. Now,
when we're checking whether if the ISS is overhead,
we want to have a margin of error. It doesn't have to be right above me,
precise to this number of decimal points. It can be plus or minus five.
So if the ISS's latitude with anywhere between say 56 and,
um, 51 minus five, which is 46,
then that's perfectly fine. That means I'll still be able to see it.
Take a look and find your own latitude and your own longitude
and see if you can figure out how to compare that against the ISS's a latitude
and longitude and adding in that degree of error. In fact,
consider creating a function that returns true if your position is within plus five
or minus five degrees of the ISS position and false otherwise.
So you should now have all the capabilities to complete this challenge.
Pause the video,
give that a little bit of a think and see if you can complete the challenge.
Thank you.
All right. What
we want to do up here is we wanna compare the ISS's position against our
position. Now,
what we want to check is to see if our position is within plus or minus five
degrees of the ISS position. So let's take one part of that position,
the ISS's latitude
and we want to check to see if it is close to my latitude.
If my latitude is currently 51,
then 51 minus five would be 46.
So we can check to see if 46 is less than or equal to the ISIS latitude.
And then if the ISS latitude is less than or equal to 51 plus five,
which is 56. Then if this is true,
it means that this value is in between these two values.
So let's replace these numbers with my actual latitude.
So MY_LAT - 5
and then MY_LAT + 5.
And then we have to make sure that it's also true for the longitude.
So we're going to do basically the same thing,
but this time using my longitude.
So in my longitude minus five is less than or equal to the ISS's longitude
and the ISS longitude
should be less than or equal to my longitude plus five.
If both of these things are true,
then my position is pretty much within plus or minus five degrees of the ISS.
At this point, I should probably create some sort of a function for this.
So I could say is_iss_overhead.
And I can indent all of this into that function.
And if this happens to be true, I'm going to return true.
This part deals with checking
whether if the ISS is at a similar position to my position,
the next part deals with figuring out whether if it's nighttime or not.
So again,
let's create a function and I'll call it is_night.
And this function is going to return true when it is actually nighttime. In
order to figure out whether if it is nighttime,
then we're going to get a response - so there's a typo there -
from our request to the sunrise-sunset API
passing in all of these parameters which contain my current location.
And then from the data we get back,
we figure out the sunrise and sunset time by formatting that string
and then turning it into an integer
which is going to represent the current hour in the 24-hour time format.
So then we figure out, well,
what is the current time using the datetime module?
And we can check to see, well,
if the time now is greater than or equal to the sunset time,
or if the time now is less than or equal to the sunrise time,
then it means it's dark.
So now we're getting a warning telling us that this time now is a datetime
object, but the sunset and sunrise are whole numbers or integers.
So what's happened well? Datetime now is, in fact,
the current date and time,
but what we actually want is the current hour and that converts it into an
integer making this comparison valid.
So if it is currently nighttime,
then we're going to return true. And if the ISS is overhead,
then we're also going to return true. So now we've done these two parts,
all that's left to do is once both of these things are true
we can send ourselves an email to tell us to look up.
So if the ISS is overhead and it is currently nighttime,
then we're going to initiate our email sending
which is going to require our smtplib.
And I'm also going to add my email and password as constants up here.
And now we can create our connection
and I'm using again a Gmail server.
So it's going to be smtp.gmail.com.
So we went through all of this when we talked about email in detail.
So I won't waste time talking about it again,
right?
I'm going to send this email from my own address and also to my own address
because after all I'm just making a notification for myself. And the message in this
case is going to have the subject line of look up and I can even add an emoji
here.
And then the content is going to say
The ISS is above you in the sky.
That's it. That's all there is to this. Now,
it'd be quite hard to test this code because we have to wait for the perfect
condition before all of these things will actually be true. While this is the end
of the challenge for you,
there's one thing I want to change with this code to make it a little bit
better.
We can actually put this if statement inside a while loop.
So we could say while true,
which means this loop is going to go again and again, and again,
checking if the ISS is overhead and it's at night.
Now this is going to happen quite frequently because its in a while loop,
but we can slow it down by using the time module.
So we could import the time module and then say time.sleep
and we can get
it to sleep for 60 seconds or however much long you want to wait between
running the script. So now if you hit run,
you won't see that final code where it tells you that your program is done
running.
It's actually continuously running in the background and it's going to execute
this code every 60 seconds.
So as long as you have your computer on and this is running,
then you can run this for a whole 24 hours. And I'll bet you
at some point in the night,
you'll get two or three emails telling you that the ISS is overhead.
So all you have to monitor is just to switch your notifications on on your phone
and when that email comes in to look up into the sky.
So I hope you enjoyed building this project with me
and I hope that you're going to be able to spot the ISS tonight.
If you do, take a video and let us know what it looks like.
Hey guys,
it's Angela here and welcome to Day 34 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be doing a little bit of review,
and we're going to be working with a trivia API to create a quiz app called
Quizzler.
Now we're going to be using a API that we've seen before a long time ago called
the open trivia database,
which contains over 3000 verified questions
which we can pick from randomly to fill into our quiz application.
Now,
the purpose of building this app is to review what we learned about using API
endpoints and sending requests to a particular end point to ask for some piece
of data.
And we're also going to be looking at what we learned about API parameters,
switching in and switching out different inputs in order to get different pieces
of data from the API. And with those things combined,
we're going to be able to build our Quizzler app
which is going to be built using tkinter.
So this is what it's going to look like,
and we're able to keep track of our score and see the true/false question
show up in the middle and then we can select true or false.
So I have no idea what the answer to this is. So I'm just going to guess.
Oops! Maybe not. Um, the
vapor produced by e-cigarettes is actually water. I think so. Nope.
I am really bad at this quiz so I'm just going to guess from now on.
So there you go. I got one right and my score went up.
This is a computer related question, so I know that one.
But essentially this is what we're going to be building.
And the questions that we're answering here come from the open trivia database
which contains loads of questions.
So we don't have to make up the questions and we can even select which category
of questions we want and also how many questions we want
and we're going to use this API to populate the questions in our quiz
application. That's what we're going to be building.
So if you head over to the next lesson,
we'll get started by tapping into that API.
To begin, head over to the course resources as always and download the starting
zip file for today's starting project. And once you've done that,
go ahead and unzip the file and open it up inside PyCharm. Now,
if we take a look inside the project folder,
you can see we've got a bunch of images
which is going to be used for the buttons,
and we've also got a lot of the code that we had created in our previous quiz
project. It may seem like it was a long time ago,
but back in day 17
we learned about creating classes and the project that we built to do that was a
text based quiz. And in fact,
once you've downloaded and opened up the starting file for today's project,
you can actually run this program.
So open up main.py and run it.
Then you can see the original format of the quiz application in action
inside the console. We can type true or false,
and it will give us some feedback, whether if we got it right
or whether if we got it wrong and also our current score.
Now this was great on day 17,
but now that we know all about creating graphical user interfaces using tkinter
as well as a whole bunch of things that we've learned about APIs just now, we're
going to upgrade this quiz app to the next level.
The first thing we want to upgrade is at the moment,
these questions are hard-coded.
So inside our data.py,
you can see all of these questions as a list of dictionary objects.
And at the time,
the place where we got all of these questions from was in fact,
the open trivia database.
But what we did here is we selected the number of questions we wanted,
we selected the category that we wanted,
and then we changed the type to true and false and we said, generate API URL.
And then once that URL is generated,
all we did was we put it into our  browser and we got this data and we put it
into our question data. Now,
this, being hard-coded, is obviously never going to change.
So what we want to do instead is we want to get 10 questions from the open
trivia database,
but this time we want to make a request to the API so that we always get
different questions and different answers.
The idea of this challenge is to modify the code in the data.py file to get 10
new questions using the open trivia database every time the program is run.
Here's what your code should do after you've successfully completed the
challenge. You'll still get a console based quiz, but this time,
the text and the correct answer came from the open trivia database via an API
call.
You'll see that any symbol like single double quotes will not be displayed
correctly just yet,
but getting the API call working is the first step and the goal of this
challenge.
So what I want you to do is to set the number of questions to 10 and leave the
category as blank, leave the difficulty is blank,
but make sure that the type is set to true-false and then generate this API URL.
Now remember what I said before that the API end point is everything before the
question mark. So this is the base URL that we're going to be working with.
And then after the question mark, we've got our different parameters.
So we've got a parameter called amount
which is set to 10, and we've got another parameter called type
which is set to the word boolean.
So you are going to have to think back to what you learned in yesterday's
lessons
and use the requests module to make a request to this API and passing in the
required parameters.
And then once you've generated the data from that API,
then I want you to make sure that you reach into the data that you get back and
grab the data that is in this format.
And we're going to replace this question_data with the actual questions that we
get from the open trivia database API.
When we make the request to the API in our browser,
we get back something that looks like this.
So we have a two item dictionary; one is the response code,
and one is the results.
Now the value for this key results is the list of dictionary objects that we
actually want and it looks very similar in structure to this.
So that is what we want. So everything inside here, basically.
Now we're going to still call it question_data because elsewhere in our main.py
we're tapping into this data here.
So make sure you name it the same.
And once you've done this successfully,
then you should be able to comment out all of this code here,
right?
And then simply run the program from main.py without any changes
and it should still work
but this time it should be using the questions and answers that you fetched from
the API. This is a challenge for you. So I want you to pause the video,
have a think about how you might do that and complete the challenge.
All right.
So the first thing we need to do that we learnt in order to work with APIs is to
import the requests module.
And once we've imported that,
we need to get a response from the URL that we saw over here.
As I mentioned, the end point is everything that's before the question mark.
So let's put that in as the URL for our get request.
And then in addition, we need to add some parameters.
So let's make our parameters a Python dictionary,
and the key must match the key that's shown here
and the value has to match the value that's given here as well.
So we've got two keys; amount and type.
So these are both going to be strings,
but the values can be numbers if it is appropriate.
So amount sets the number of questions we want back from the API,
and then the type sets the type of questions that we want. So in our case,
we want the boolean data type that matches this exact entry.
So that way we get back true-false questions.
Now that we've done that we can use this parameters dictionary as the
params,
and then we want our response to raise an exception if there were any errors.
And then we're going to get our response to give us the data using the JSON
method. If this is our data,
let's go ahead and print it and see what it looks like.
We can run this particular file, data.py, by right-clicking and just saying
run data. And once it's done, you can see we printed out the data
and the part that we're interested in is the value of this key results,
because it contains the list of questions.
That's the only part we're interested in. So in order to tap into that,
we have to add a set of square brackets and then pass in the key
which is called results. So let's put that as the key.
And now we're fetching all of the items that are the results from this data
object that we get back. So now, if I run this again, you can see
we now have a list of question objects
which each contains a dictionary
and it looks now pretty much identical to this structure that we had before.
Now, instead of printing this, we can save it as the question_data.
So now this question_data and has replaced this question_data,
and as I mentioned,
we can run our main.py and it should now work just as it did before.
But this time it's going to use questions that came from our API.
The cold war ended with Joseph Stalin's death, true or false.
I think that's actually false. But notice how
when we get the data back from the API,
it's formatted in such a way that we've got certain symbols that have been
encoded using this particular format
because all of this is meant to represent a single apostrophe. In the next
lesson,
I'm going to show you how we can format the text that we get back to turn this
encoding into the actual characters
that it should be. For all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In the last lesson,
we managed to get our API to work and we got back some live data.
But when we ran it,
we saw that some of the texts that we were getting back was formatted really
strangely with these pound signs and ampersands,
and it's not the actual text that we see.
So what's happening here? Well,
what we're actually seeing here are called HTML entities,
and there are a way of replacing certain characters in HTML so that it doesn't
get confused with HTML code. So for example,
the less than symbol could be a part of HTML code.
And instead of using that, we have to use the
< and then semicolon.
So if we look down this table,
we can actually see this " actually stands for a double quotation mark.
And that would make sense cause it's saying "Mario Kart
64"
and this #039,
if we look up in this list, is actually a single quotation mark.
And that would make sense as well, cause it would be Stalin's death.
So how do we get hold of the actual human readable text? Well,
we can use this tool called the free formatter to
unescape the HTML results that we're getting back from our API.
I've copied and pasted this part we've got here.
And if I go ahead and click on unescape,
you can see that it formats it into the original human readable format
and now it says in "Mario Kart 64" Waluigi is a playable character.
And if I paste the cold war ended with Joseph Stalin, blah, blah, blah,
death and I click unescape, then you can see
it says the Cold War ended with Joseph Stalin's death and it replaces that with
an apostrophe. Now,
essentially we know what to Google and that's kind of the first step towards
solving any problem.
So if you Google for escaping HTML entities in Python,
then the first result we get in Stack Overflow gives us the answer.
We have to import the HTML module and use one of the methods in that module
called unescape in order to unescape the text that we're getting back.
The part where we're interested in this is in our quiz brain,
because that's the part what we format it into our user answer.
Let's change the question
text to be equal to the self.current_question.text,
so this part that we have here
which is being put into our input and we can use this q_text instead.
But instead of using just the text that we get back from the API,
we're going to import the HTML module.
Yeah.
And we're going to use the method inside this HTML module called unescape
to unescape this string that we get from the API.
And now if I run this code again, you can see that this time,
no matter what is inside the string, say an apostrophe in this case or a double
quote in this case, they're all being formatted correctly.
There you have it.
We started off with some strange characters and after a bit of Googling around,
we found the solution to turn them into human readable text. Aas a programmer,
this is a skill that you have to really hone.
This is something that is going to take you to the next level
to this intermediate++ level.
You have to find out solutions to your own problems,
and Google is your best friend.
So now that our program works for text-based questions,
it's time to upgrade this program so that it actually has a graphical user
interface. You'll notice that in the project folder,
there is a file called ui.py,
and this is pretty much empty at the moment, other than a single constant
which sets the theme color. Now,
what we're trying to create is something that looks like this.
So we have some sort of a score board label,
we have a canvas with a white background,
and then on the canvas,
we've got some text in the middle and then we've got a true button and a false
button each using the true and false images from this folder.
Now we've seen how we can create graphical user interfaces using tkinter.
But in this case, we're going to do something a little bit different.
We're going to create our user interface in tkinter
but we're going to do it inside a class.
If you remember from day 17 where this project comes from,
that was when we learned about Object Oriented Programming,
and we learned about how to separate out our concerns like
the part that fetches the data or the part that model each of the questions
or the part that handles the actual quiz functionality,
and they are all separated in that own class. In order to create our user
interface
we're also going to create our very own class inside this ui.py.
So it's been a while since we've created classes.
So I want to do a quick reminder session on how to do that.
So we use the class keyword and then we provide the name of the class. Now,
in my case, I'm going to call this the QuizInterface.
And remember that the way that you name classes is what this is called. Pascal
case. So a capital letter,
and then each word is not separated by any underscores or any dashes.
So this is our class
and then we're going to create our init inside this class.
Now, if any of this is unfamiliar to you,
then make sure that you haven't skipped the lessons on Object Oriented
Programming and creating and using classes in Python.
We covered that in day 17. So if you skipped that,
be sure to head back before you proceed, because otherwise, the rest of this
is not going to make any sense at all. In our class init,
we're going to create our user interface.
So we're going to create all the buttons and all of the layouts.
And we start off by simply creating our window. Now this time though,
instead of creating our window as just a simple variable,
we're going to make it a property of this class.
So we're going to add self in front of it.
And then we're going to create it from the tkinter module.
So let's go ahead and import everything from the tkinter module,
and let's set our window as a new object from the tk class.
Next, I'm going to change some aspects of the window. So for example,
I'm going to change the title. So I'm going to set it to, um,
Quizzler which is going to be the name of this app.
We can continued like this inside the init function,
which remember, is going to be called whenever we create a new object from this
class.
This is where we're also going to have our self.window.mainloop
and that will set our program to run. In order to test this,
we're going to go back to our main.py
and we're going to import that class.
So from ui import the QuizInterface,
and then we're going to create that QuizInterface down here.
I'm going to call it the quiz_ui
and it's going to be initialized from our quiz interface. Now,
if you remember, when we first learned about
tkinter I told you that tkinter works by having this endless loop
essentially that's called the main loop.
And this is a bit like a never ending while loop.
It's constantly checking to see if it needs to update something in the graphical
user interface, or if the user has interacted with it in some sort of way.
So it will get confused if you have another while loop somewhere near it.
So we actually have to comment out this while loop
if we want this user interface to work properly. Now,
whenever we want to test out our UI,
all we have to do is to run our main.py.
And once it hits this line,
it's going to create a new object from our QuizInterface over here.
And once it does that, it's going to hit the init method
and it's going to create our new GUI.
You can continue coding up your user interface inside this init
and it will work just as it did before
when you created just a very simple tkinter graphical user interface
application. Here comes the challenging part.
I want you to create this particular user interface,
and I've created a slide that shows you all of the padding, the sizing,
the fonts, the background color,
and all of the components that go onto this screen.
I want you to pause the video here and see if you can create this user interface
inside the init method of the quiz interface class.
Pause the video now and give that a go.
Okay.
All right.
So we're going to continue where we left off here inside the init method.
And we already started off our window property
so we're going to continue making that a little bit better.
So we're going to call the config method on this self.window,
and we're going to change the padx and the pady so that we add 20 pixels
of padding on all four sites. Now,
the next thing I want to configure is the background color.
And as I mentioned in this slide,
we're going to use this theme color that I've already provided here,
which is a nice sort of midnight blue.
So I'm going to tap into the background attribute
and I'm going to set it to this theme color. Now,
if we go ahead and run our main file,
then we can see our user interface show up.
And it's now got the background color
and it's a little bit bigger because of the padding.
The next step is to create this label up here,
which is just a very simple text label.
So let's go ahead and create it as a property of this class.
So I'm going to call it the score label,
and I'm going to create it from the label class of tkinter. I'm going to set
the text as just Score: 0.
And I'm going to change the color of this text,
which is the foreground, to white.
That way it will actually be able to show up on this dark background.
Now, in order for this label to show up, we,
of course, have to give it some sort of layout.
So we're going to use the grid and I'm going to set the row to zero
cause it's the very top, and then the column to one.
So this way it sticks to the right. At this point when we run it,
because there is no column zero,
it's still going to be just showing up on the screen on the left.
And it's also got a white background making it impossible to see the white text.
Let's go ahead and change the background of this label to the same theme color.
And that way, when we run it, we actually see our label with its white text.
That's the label done. And the next step is to create our canvas.
Remember that our canvas is really useful because it allows us to layer lots of
things on top of it.
And we can also set its background and size very easily.
So we're going to create this canvas from the canvas class and straight away,
I'm going to set the width and height.
So the width is going to be 300 and the height is going to be 250
as we specified in the slide here. In addition,
I'm going to change the background color to white so that it stands out almost
like a card on the background. After I've created my canvas,
I'm going to add some question_text onto the canvas.
So I'm going to create this as the self.canvas.create_text
and this is going to have a single attribute called text,
and I'm going to set the text to say Some Question Text.
So we don't actually have that at the moment. We'll just put in a placeholder.
And if you want to, you can actually change the fill color of this text
which is the color of the text to the theme color as well
just to make it all matchy matchy. Now, finally,
we're going to put our canvas onto the screen by giving it a grid.
And this time we're going to set the row to one, so below the score label,
and then the column I'm going to set it to zero.
But then I'm going to set the column span to two so that it starts at column
zero and spans two columns to column one.
So now when I run this code,
I actually get an error and the error is super obscure.
Tells me tuple index out of range. Now, if you remember
when we worked with tkinter,
whenever we add an image or we add something to the canvas,
we always have to provide a position as the first two arguments.
And that is the tuple that represents the X and Y position of the text.
We have to make sure that we don't forget that.
So the first value is going to be the X,
so that's going to be half of the width so that it's centered on the canvas.
So that's 150, half of 300.
And then the Y is going to be half of 250, which is going to be 125.
Now, if we run this again,
hopefully we won't encounter the same error and you can now see this card show
up and our label show up on the right,
because its in the second column and this is the first column and this canvas
spans both columns. Now this text is a little bit small,
so let's take a look at the slide and see what we need to change it to.
So we want it to be arial font, 20 point size and italic.
Let's go ahead and add that to our text. And because its getting a little bit
crammed in here,
I'm actually going to put this on two separate lines just so I can read it a
little bit easier like this.
Now we can add that font argument and we're going to set it to a tuple with the
first item being the name of the font
and then the second is the size of the font
and finally we'll also make the text italic as well.
So now lets run that again and you'll see the text is now much bigger and its been
formatted in the way that we wanted it to. The next thing we want to do is to
add a bit of padding between this canvas and the score.
So we want to add 50 points of padding here and probably 50 here as well
just to push everything a little bit further away from each other. To do that
all we have to do is the tap into the canvas grid and then add a single pady.
We don't want to add any more padding on the X axis.
The original 20 is enough from the window. But we want to add 50
so that this way the canvas has some padding on the top and the bottom like this. And it
now looks a little bit more spaced out and easier to read.
That's pretty much the canvas done.
The last thing we need to add are the two buttons.
So we'll add a true button and a false button,
both created from the button class and neither of them are going to have to any
text.
Instead we're going to create a true_image from the PhotoImage class,
tapping into the file that comes from this folder.
So it's images/true.png.
And that is the image that we're going to slot in to this button.
Right.
Now. In addition,
I'm going to set the highlightthickness to zero. This way
it doesn't have that weird, awkward border around the button.
And I'm also going to put this button onto the screen using the grid method.
So now we're onto a row two,
so below the canvas, and the column
we're going to set it to column zero. Now, depending on what you prefer,
you can have the true button on the left or the true button on the right.
It doesn't really matter cause it's so big and it's quite easy for the user to
see. I'm going to set it on the left, so column zero.
And when I run this code, you can see that show up. So using the same method,
I'm going to create the false button.
Right.
Now we have a true and a false button and we pretty much have our final user
interface completed. Now,
one of the things you see here is almost everything that I've created inside my
init,
I've given it the 'self.' And remember from our lessons on OOP, this turns
this into a property which can be accessed anywhere in the class.
Now, some other things like the true image and the false image,
I've not done that for because we're not going to use it anywhere else
other than to set up our button right here.
This, hopefully, will be a good review of what we learned about Object Oriented
Programming and classes and objects as well as tkinter and all of the new stuff
around APIs. But this completes the user interface
and we're now ready to head over to the next lesson
where we're going to fill some text into this question area.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Now that we've sorted out the user interface,
the next step is to populate this with some questions that we got from our API
call.
So everything in our program is linked and the place where we get hold of the
next question is inside our quiz_brain. At the moment,
the quiz_brain, when this method next_question is called,
will find the current question from the list of questions that it gets from
data.py, and then it will serve it up in a input.
This is what used to happen,
at least, when we were still making our text-based quiz app.
But in this case,
we actually want to be able to output that question text and then get hold of it
inside our ui.py.
So let's update our quiz_brain so that this question is returned as an output.
I'm gonna comment out this part of the code where we check the user answer
because we no longer get a user answer from the input. Instead,
we're going to take this question_text and the question_number
and we're going to serve it up as the output.
So let's go ahead and return this entire string.
And we can comment out this line of code.
Now inside our ui.py,
we can call that method and put it onto this piece of text in the canvas.
Let's create a method in here, which we'll call get_
_next_question.
And this method is going to tap into the quiz_brain and call this next_question.
So how do we get hold of the same quiz brain that we create in our main.py?
Well,
we could pass it in when we create our quiz UI as an input.
So this quiz,
which is creative from the quiz brain, can be passed into the quiz interface. And
to catch it, all we have to do is just to
add another parameter in our init
which we'll call the quiz brain.
And then we can create a property called the quiz
and we can set that equal to the quiz brain that we receive when we initialize
this new quiz interface.
So now when we have our get next question being called,
we're going to tap into the self.quiz,
and then we're going to call the method quiz_
_next_question. Now notice how as I'm typing,
you don't actually get anything showing up.
And the reason for this is because even though we're passing in that quiz brain
into here through the init, this file
doesn't actually know what is the datatype of this particular object that's
being passed in.
So one of the things that you can do is actually to add the datatype when you
create it as a parameter.
So we could say that this quiz brain thing that's going to be passed in must be
of data type quiz brain. And in order for that to work,
we need to import it. So from quiz
brain import the quiz brain class.
And now we can declare that when we initialize a new quiz interface,
we must pass in a quiz brain object
which is of the data type quiz brain. And once we've done that
and we've ensured this,
then when we try to initialize this and we try to pass on something else,
let's say I try to pass in the question bank
then this is going to give me a error and you can see it says expected type quiz
brain, but instead got a list.
So this also ensures that we don't make any mistakes
when we initialize the quiz interface.
Coming back to here and scrolling down, now, at this point
once we know the data type of quiz,
then we can start typing next question. And you can see,
it shows up all of the methods that are available to the quiz brain
object. We know that this is going to give us the output,
so this is the question text. And once we get that,
then we want to update our canvas.
So what's tap into our self.canvas and then call the item config method to
change the item, which is our self.question_text.
And the thing we want to change about it is the text
and we wanna set it to this q_text that we got from here.
Now,
all that's left to do is to actually call this method and we have to do it
in our init so that when we first initialize our user interface,
we don't end up seeing this Some Question Text. Instead,
we actually fetch the first question from our list of questions.
But remember that everything has to go before the main loop
because all the code you write after this line is not going to be executed until
that window gets destroyed.
So let's put it here and we can call self.get_next_question.
And now if we run our code,
you can see that instead of some dummy text,
we're actually getting a real question here.
The only problem is that it's not fully visible.
One of the tricks that we can use is to get the text in the canvas
to wrap by setting the text width property. Back up here
where we created our question_text, we can add
another argument which is called width.
And if we set that width to some value that is maybe a little bit less than the
width of the canvas,
then this question_text is automatically going to go on two separate lines.
I'm going to set it to 280 so that it's a little bit less than 300.
So that way there's a little bit of padding, either side. And now if I hit run,
you can see the question now fits into the actual piece of card. There you have
it. We've now created our get next question method
which is able to fetch the question text from the quiz brain
by returning the question text that it got. Now,
we still have our principles of Object Oriented Programming maintained where
each module is responsible for its own thing.
So the quiz brain is responsible for managing the quiz, getting questions,
keeping track of score, and our user interface
or our quiz interface class is responsible for putting those things onto the
screen to be displayed. In the next lesson,
we're going to take a closer look at Python type hints.
And then afterwards, we'll figure out how to get our buttons working.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
A long time ago, we've talked about Python data types.
So the data types that we've been working with include things like integers,
strings, floating point numbers and booleans.
And we've seen how you can interchange between different data types by casting.
And we've also seen that in Python, the data types are flexible.
So you could create a variable and then change its data type later on.
This is known as dynamic typing.
Now I want to show you another thing that you can do with data types to make
your code less error prone.
Let's say that we were to create a variable, for example, a variable called age.
Now, normally we would set it with an equal sign.
But you can also simply declare its data type and then leave it as is.
So this means that later on, at some point,
once you've actually gotten the age of from the user or you've worked it out,
then at that point, you can set it. And this age now has to match
the data type over here. So for example,
if I was to change this to 12 using a string, then you can see that my
PyCharm,
my IDE, is now being very helpful in telling me that this age thing ages ago
when you created it, you said it should be an integer. Instead, I got a string.
So this is quite helpful. You can do this with all of the basic data types.
So for example, age is an int, name is a string,
height is a float and is_human is a boolean.
Now we can also specify the data type inside a function.
So for example,
if I was to create a function here called a police_check and it took the age as
an input, and then inside the police_check function, I would check well,
if the age is over 18,
then maybe we would have some sort of variable called can_drive and we could set
that to true.
But otherwise, we can set that to false
right?
Now, we're going to return this as the output.
So now at some point we can call our police_check function,
pass in the age and if we print this out,
you can see that it's going to give me false for age 12.
And if I decide to say I'm 19, well, then we get true.
We can actually use the output from this function to create a print statement,
for example.
So if the police check passes, then the policeman tells you, you may pass.
Otherwise you might have to pay a fine or spend a night in jail.
So this is our function
and if we were to use this function
police_check at some point
way down the line where we've forgotten what we created for this function
and we can't look it up very easily without scrolling up hundreds of lines of
code, now, if at this point we've mistaken the input type
and we put in, for example, 12 as a string,
then this is actually going to give us a type error and it throws an exception
crashing our
app. One of the ways that we can make our lives a little bit easier is by
declaring a type for this input. So we do it in the same way as you see above.
We can add a colon and then we can specify the data type of this particular
input. So now when we actually write this line of code,
you can see immediately we get this part highlighted.
And if I hover over it, it tells me that this input expected a datatype
that's an integer and instead I gave it a string.
So this is a quick hint for us to fix our code before we even run it and get
into trouble and create
bugs. In addition,
you can also specify the data type of the output of a function,
and you do that by creating a little arrow with a hyphen and an angle bracket.
So now we can say that this particular function is expected to return a boolean
data type.
And my return statement does in fact comply with this because can_drive can only
be true or false. Now, if I forget that this is what I need
and at some point I return let's say a string,
then also I'm getting this warning highlight here.
And when I hover over it again, it's expecting a boolean
but instead I'm giving it a string.
This is known as a type hint in Python.
And it is a feature that we got relatively recently from Python
and it has a lot of benefits especially when you want your IDE, for example
PyCharm,
to help you spot potential bugs and keep your code safer and spend less time
debugging and more time writing code.
So we've seen how we can declare a data type for a variable like this
and we've also seen how we can declare data type for the return type like this.
That's all there is to it.
In the last lesson,
we got our quiz app to start displaying the questions that we were getting from
our API. This question I landed on is pretty interesting.
Nintendo started out as a playing card manufacturer?
And I would love to know if that's actually true or false.
So I'd really like these buttons to work basically.
If I click on one of these buttons,
I want to be able to check my answer against the real answer that we got back
from our API. So in this lesson, that's what we're going to get to work.
So I want this to be a bit of a challenge for you.
We know that we can add a command argument to our buttons so that it calls a
particular method when it gets pressed. Now, when that method gets pressed,
we want to go into our quiz brain and call this check answer.
Now this check answer method expects a answer to check against.
Have a think about how you might solve this and get this to work so that we can
start printing out whether if we got the question right or the question
wrong. Pause the video now, and try to complete this challenge.
Go.
Okay. Here's the solution.
The first thing I'm going to do is create a new method called true_pressed
and also a method called a false_pressed.
This true_pressed is obviously going to be the one that will be the command for
this true button and it's going to be self.
true_pressed because we're inside a class and we have to make sure that there's
no parentheses at the end of it because we only want to trigger this method
when the button actually detects a click. In a similar way,
we're going to add a command to the false button and it's going to be
self.false_pressed. And again, deleting the parenthesis.
And now we can figure out what to do in here.
We already have access to our quiz brain object in here
which is saved under self.quiz.
When either of these gets pressed,
then we can simply tap into self.quiz and we can call the check_
answer method that exists over there.
And we can pass over true when true_pressed is called,
and then when false_pressed is called
...
we'll pass in false. Now it's going to go into this check_answer,
pass that answer in and it's going to print out whether if you got it right
or whether if you got it wrong. So let's test that out.
Let's run the code again and make sure that we don't make any silly typos like
comand.
Yeah.
So let's run our app and see if can answer some questions.
Gumbo is a stew that originated in Louisiana.
I think that might be true.
And when I click on the button,
you can see in the console it's printed whether
if I got it right or wrong. Now,
while our code works and we can see whether we got it right or wrong in the
console, that's not something the user will see.
This is only something that's available to us as developers.
So how can we give the user some feedback?
That's what we'll figure out in the next lesson.
We saw in the last lesson how we could see the feedback in the console.
But what if we wanna see the feedback on screen?
What I want to be able to happen is when the user taps on true or false
as an answer to the question, I want this card,
which is our canvas, to give us the feedback.
So if I click this and it turns green for a second,
then that means I got it right.
And then afterwards it goes straight to the next question.
And when I get the wrong answer, it should flash red.
Instead of getting check_answer in the quiz brain to print out
you got it right or you got it wrong, we want it to return true
if we actually got it right
and to return false when we get it wrong.
And we can delete these last two lines of code with the print statements.
So now we can catch that when we call each of these methods, check_answer,
and check_answer something like this.
What we want to happen is we want to check whether if the user got it right or
wrong, and depending on that, we'll give them different feedback.
So we'll create a new method called it give_feedback
and this is going to take input in the form of whether if they got it right or not.
Now, all we have to do is to call self.give_feedback
and then pass in the output to this method call, like this.
And we can delete this line. Alternatively,
you can use two lines of code for this
and you can pass in the value to this variable.
These two lines do exactly the same thing.
Once we get into this method, give_feedback, though,
we need to change the canvas background to red or green
depending on whether the user got it right or wrong.
And then after a delay of one second,
we need to change it back to white so that we can then go to the next question.
You might think that we can simply use something like time.sleep and then
sleep for one second. But if you remember from previous lessons on tkinter,
we mentioned that we can't mess with the time because we have this main loop
going on continuously. So we have to use a tkinter method
which is window.after.
And here we can set how many milliseconds we want to delay by, so 1000,
and then what function we want to call.
Have a think about how you might create this give_feedback so that it has
this particular functionality where the user gives their answer and if they got
it right then it's green and if they get it wrong, then it's red.
Pause the video and try to complete this challenge.
Go.
All right.
What we have to first check is whether if this variable that's being passed in, is_
right, is actually true or false. If the user got it right,
well then in that case,
we're going to change the canvas and call config on it
to change the background to green. However,
if this is false, if they got it wrong,
then we're going to change the canvas.config so that the background is red
instead. Now, once that's done,
then our canvas will be a different color.
And then this is where we set up our timer. So after 1000 milliseconds,
so one second, we want to go to the next question.
So let's go ahead and call self.get_next_question.
But in the same way that we can't have the parentheses
when we set the command method, when we use this as an input,
we also need to get rid of the parentheses. So now
if we run this code and I pick an answer,
then it goes red when it shows that I've got it wrong.
And then after once one second, it goes to the next question. Now,
once it goes to the next question, that's where we need to reset our canvas.
So if we can say self.canvas and then do the same thing to configure the
background back to white. And let's run this again.
I can see I got it wrong. And then after one second,
it goes back to white and it goes to the next question.
And that completes the challenge.
So the very last thing that we need to add is our score keeping capabilities.
And all we need to do that is to pick out the value of the score from the quiz
brain and populate it every time we get the next question.
In addition to configuring the canvas,
we're going to set the score label's config so that we change the text to
the new score. This is going to be a f-string
and we're going to say Score:
and then we're going to insert the self.quiz,
which is the quiz brain object, and we're going to get its current score.
Now you can see that every time we score a single point,
then that value gets updated,
right?
Whereas if we get it wrong, then that score doesn't change at all. Now,
the thing that we haven't seen yet is what happens when we get to the end of
the quiz, because we know that we only have 10 questions.
And once we get to the 10th question,
you'll see that we actually get an exception thrown: index out of range.
And that's because we've reached the end of our quiz,
but we're still trying to get hold of the next question.
So what we need to do is to check that we can actually get the next question. And
to do that, all we need is an if statement tapping into our self.quiz,
which is the quiz brain. And here,
remember we have a method called still_has_questions
which is either true or false. Now,
if we still have questions remaining,
then we're going to go to the next question. But otherwise,
what we're going to do is we're going to update the canvas text so that we
change the question text to actually tell the user that they've reached the end
of the quiz. Now there's just a few more bugs to iron out.
The first one is when we get to the end of our quiz,
you can see that it shows up this text
but we can still press on these buttons and it changes the background for no
reason. So we want to be able to disable these buttons
once we reached the end of the quiz
and we also want to make sure that the canvas background is actually white
again.
So let's move this line of code out of the if statement so that no matter what
happens when we go to the next question,
we always change the canvas background back to white. Now, in addition,
we want to disable our true and false buttons. To do that,
all we have to do is to tap into a keyword argument called state.
And if we change the state of the button to disabled,
then this will prevent the buttons from being pressed or activated.
[inaudible]
There, you have it. Here's
a upgraded quiz application that now has a graphical user interface
which we can interact with data
that's completely generated from random and fetched from the open trivia
database.
And we can even modify these parameters to change up this quiz to our liking.
So for example, if you want to change the category to say computers,
then once we generate our API URL,
you can see that it adds one other parameter called category,
and we can change that to 18. So let's try that.
Set the category to the number of 18
and now when we run our code,
all our questions will be computer science related.
So have fun playing with your quiz app
and if you've modified your quiz app to make it more interesting or added some
other features,
then be sure to share it with the rest of us in the Q/A section.
Hey guys, welcome to day 35
of 100 Days of Code. It's Angela here again
and today we're going to be learning all about API keys,
authentication, environment variables,
and also how to send SMS using Python.
It's going to be a pretty packed day and we're going to be learning a whole
bunch of things.
And the goal is the look at even more advanced ways of using APIs and
looking at how we can authenticate ourselves with an API provider so that we can
get access to more precious data. Now we're also going
to be looking at how we can use an API like Twilio to send SMS messages to
ourselves so that we can get an alert wherever we are.
And finally,
we're going to be taking a look at what environment variables are in association
with how they're used for safely storing API keys.
What all of this knowledge is going to amount to is to build a rain alert
application.
So we're going to be writing Python code that is going to send us a text message
in the morning, just before we head out, telling us to bring an umbrella
if it's going to rain in the day.
So this way we don't have to check the weather.
We know that our trusty application is always going to alert us via an SMS
message if we need to bring an umbrella before we leave home.
So that's the goal. And if you head over to the next lesson,
we'll get started building our application and learning about API
authentication.
The first thing we're going to explore is how to authenticate ourselves with an
API provider so that we can access more secure and more valuable data from the
API providers. Up to this point, we've learned about API endpoints,
so figuring out what is the URL that we need to hit up in order to get a
particular piece of data. We also looked at API parameters,
so passing in different inputs so that we can get different pieces of data
back from the API provider.
Now we're going to take one step further and look at how we can use APIs
that require authentication. Previously
all of the APIs that we've used were free APIs.
They were provided completely free and we can access all parts of it without any
sort of payment here. Now,
this is because the data that's contained in those APIs are very simple and
nobody is going to be using that data to build a very fancy or big commercial
application. Now, on the other hand, there's
other types of data that are very valuable, for example, weather data,
because it
makes a lot of energy and time for somebody or some company to collect all of
this data and provide it for you. In these cases,
some of these APIs can have a paid tier.
So you actually have to pay if you're running an application
or if you have a company that needs to get this data very frequently and you
need to get large amounts of the data.
Why do people charge for API anyways? Well, if you think about something simple
like the weather, it's not actually that simple. How do you even get
the weather
if I asked you to figure out the weather without using some sort of website or tool?
Well, in this particular case, open weather map,
they have access to over 4,000 weather stations across the globe,
and then their data scientists will take that weather data and look at the
satellite images and process that data in order to figure out the weather and
predict the weather for each city in the world. As you can imagine,
that's going to be really resource-intensive and it's going to require a lot of
employees and also server maintenance and electricity costs, right?
So for all of that hassle, if they're going to provide this data for you,
then it's reasonable that you should be paying for it, right?
Essentially you can see a lot of
APIs as a way of selling data.
If you own some sort of privileged piece of data that you are constantly
updating, or you are actively generating, for example,
weather data from satellite images or financial data,
then it's reasonable that you should be charging for this data
especially if somebody is going to rely on it heavily in order to build a
commercial app or a company. But luckily,
most of these APIs provide a free tier that allows you to test out the
application.
And if you are somebody who's just learning the ropes then it doesn't make sense
to charge you.
It only makes sense when your application or your service has a lot of users.
And then you start going into the paid tiers. Now,
how do you prevent people from abusing this free tier?
Because anybody can say, well, I'm just learning, you know.
You can be somebody who's running a 1000 employee company
and you could claim that you're just learning.
So the way that they prevent people from abusing their service is through
something known as an API key.
And this is almost like your personal account number and password.
This is the way how the API provider can track how much you're using their API
and to authorize your access and deny you access
once you've gone over the limit. Now,
different API providers tend to have different ways that you can authenticate
yourself with them,
but most of them involve some sort of an API key.
In the next lesson, I want to show you how we can implement the open weather
map API,
authenticate ourselves with an API key that we generate, and get the live wather
data. So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson,
Now whenever we start using a new API, the most important thing is to read the
documentation.
I know it's really tempting to skip over the instructions and just get right
into it.
I'm also the sort of person who buys a lawnmower and throws away the instruction
manual. And then two days later, something breaks
and I just want to hurt myself because it would be so much easier if I had
actually read the instruction manual. But in this case, it is really important.
So let's head over to openweathermap.org together
and let's go to the API section to see their API documentation.
As you can see, this API provider actually has several products.
So you could look at the current weather data, the hourly forecast,
the one call API,
the daily forecast and a whole bunch of other things.
So each of these have their own endpoints. And if we take a look at the API doc,
you can see this first one
the API is api.openweathermap.org/data/2.5/weather. That's the end
point.
Whereas the hourly forecast is pro.openweathermap.org/data/2.5/forecasts
/hourly. So depending on what it is that we need,
we can tap into each of these different APIs.
Let's start off with an easy one.
Let's try and get the current weather data for the city that we're in.
You can see that this part is the end point,
so the URL that we're going to tap into.
And then we have some parameters.
The parameter where we can specify the city name is q.
So that's the name of the parameter and then we have to provide a value.
Now, in addition,
there's another parameter which we have to include with all of the API calls to
this particular service. And that is an app ID.
We have to get hold of an API key in order to use this service. And they show you
an example here. If we click on this URL,
it takes us to samples.openweathermap.org
and this is just some sample data where they provided a sample App ID.
Now we can get our own app ID for free by simply signing up to this weather
service. And once you register and sign in,
this is the page that you see.
So we can now go into this section called API keys and grab our API key here.
So you can create as many keys as you want
and you can provide a name that's associated with the final usage for that key.
So I've named it Python.
And now I'm going to copy this API key and I'm gonna place it into my project.
So I've started a new project called rain alert and inside the main.py,
I'm going to create a api_key
and I'm going to save that key that I copied into a set of double quotes as a
string. Now, once I've got my API key,
I can actually test out this API call.
So I can replace this part with my city name
which is London,
and then I can add my country afterwards just to make sure that it goes to
London UK, and not London Ontario, or somewhere else.
And then finally,
I'm going to paste in the API key that I copied over just now. And now when I hit
enter and as long as my API key is valid,
I should get a result in the format of my weather data.
Now I want you to make sure that your API key works as well by using the same
method.
But remember that you have to get hold of your own API key by signing up to open
weather map if you want this to work.
Make sure that you replace this part with your own API key.
Otherwise, it's not going to work. Now that we've seen that this particular API
call actually works,
let's see what happens if we provide the wrong API key.
So if I just make up an API key and hit enter,
you can see we get a code back
which has an HTTP code called 401.
And we can also get a message telling us that that's an invalid API key
and we can go to this URL for more info. Now,
remember in previous lessons,
I mentioned that HTTP status codes are the codes that we get back when we try to
talk to another server. So in this case,
we got the 401 code back which means unauthorized.
And when you get this code back and you're working with an API, it
usually means that your API key or your way of authorizing with the API key is
somehow not working. So that is the thing that you should examine.
We can see that for this particular API provider,
we have to authenticate ourselves with their server by providing the API key as
a parameter. So now I want to give you a challenge.
I want you to go to the API doc for their one call API.
This one call API gives you a bunch of things. It gives you the current
weather, the minute forecasts for the next hour, the hourly forecasts for the
next 48 hours, and the daily forecast for seven days.
My challenge to you is to make an API request from PyCharm to the one call API
and to locate the hourly forecasts for the next 48 hours in the JSON response
that you get back. Now, I could tell you exactly what to do,
but it's really good to get some practice reading API documentation
because, after all, in the future
you're going to be using loads of different APIs
and they all have different ways of working with their services.
Have a look at this page, I'll link to it in the course resources.
And I want you to implement this API call by providing a latitude and longitude
of where you currently are.
Now you can leave this exclude parameter out and make sure that you add your
personal app ID by getting hold of your API key. Now,
remember you can get your current latitude and longitude just by going to
latlong.net and then typing a place name,
and then clicking find. Don't worry if it tells you a bot is detected.
Just go back to the website after a little while and try it again.
At some point, it should show you your latitude and longitude
which you can then plug in as a parameter to this particular API call.
So if you manage to work through all the lessons yesterday,
then this should be a piece of cake for you. Pause the video and give that a go.
Okay.
All right. So if that was hard at all,
make sure that you've not skipped yesterday's lessons because I go through in
detail, how to hit up a API endpoint,
how to provide parameters and how to essentially complete this challenge.
But hopefully you managed alright
and you're just here to check the solution. As always we're going to start off by
importing our requests package.
Remember that if you're creating this file from scratch and you haven't
downloaded it from a zip file,
then you'll have to install this module manually.
So if you click on it in PyCharm, you get a little red light bulb.
And then when you click on the down arrow, you can install that package.
Simple. Now, once you've got requests installed,
we can use the get method to pass in our endpoint.
Now the open weather map endpoint
is the one that we see in the API docs. So it's everything up to,
but not including, the question mark. So all of this.
And we can paste that in and save it as a string.
That is what we want to make our get requests to. So OWM endpoint.
And in addition, we're going to provide some params.
So this is going to determine what kind of data we get back. And in this case,
it's going to be the weather for a particular location that we're interested in.
Let's create our weather params,
and this is going to be a dictionary.
And we have to follow the keys that are provided in the API docs.
So the parameters that we can provide for this API are lat
which is the latitude, lon which is longitude.
And a lot of people make typos here because they add a 'g.' It's actually just lon.
That's the name of the parameter key. And then there's exclude
which tells you which parts of the weather data you want to exclude.
And finally, the app ID which is your API key that you got earlier on.
In our case, we want to provide a lat, the latitude.
We want to provide a lon, L-O-N, which is the longitude,
and we also want to provide our app ID. Now our app ID is
simple. It's simply the API key that we got earlier on. And again,
just as a reminder, this key is not going to work.
You'll have to register and get your own for it to work. Now,
the latitude we're going to figure out by using latlong.net.
So I'm trying to get the weather for where I currently reside, which is London.
So my latitude is this value and my longitude is this value.
Make sure that you copy everything including any negative signs like this.
So these are going to go in as floating point numbers.
And now that we've completed our
weather params, we're going to pass it in to this method.
And now we can save the output that comes from this as the response,
and we can print the response.status_code to see if it was successful.
So now let's go ahead and run our main.py and you can see the response code
we get back is 200, which means everything is OK. Now,
if you get a response code that's 401,
that means your API key is probably not valid,
or you misspelled the name of that key.
It should be appid all in lowercase,
as they've shown us in their documentation.
If you did get 200 though,
that means everything was successful and we can now tap into the actual data.
So let's tap into the response.json, and let's print that out.
So they're you have it.
We've got all of the data here that came back from that API call.
And if you scroll, there's actually quite a lot of data that's in there.
Now, in order to view this, it's not very easy to look at it in the console.
So I'm going to triple-click on this and copy all of that string
and I'm going to view it in a online JSON viewer.
So I'll link to this as well, but you want to pace that JSON
you got back into this and you can see, wow, what a mess. So much data.
But if you click on viewer then you can see
it's nicely formatted all of that data for us to get the current data,
or you can get the hourly data or the daily data.
So this is the data that's effective for this latitude and longitude
and this is the current time zone we're in. So in my case,
I want to know the hourly data for the next 12 hours.
So I can expand this list and you can see they're 48 data points here.
If we take a look at each of those,
they give us a timestamp for when this predicted weather is valid,
the temperature in Kelvins, the pressure, humidity,
but also the actual weather data.
The weather data is a list which contains a bunch of dictionaries. In this case
there's only one and it's telling us that right now, where I am in London,
there's scattered clouds, which is pretty normal
if you've ever been to London. At least it's not raining.
We've now managed to use this open weather app API,
authenticate ourselves with an API key, and get the required data back from the
service. So in the next lesson,
we're going to dig into the data that we got back
and we're going to use it to figure out whether if it's going to rain today.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In order to create my rain alert Python script.
I want the script to be run every morning at 7:00 AM.
Let's say that I'm going to head out of the door at 8:00 AM in order to go to
work, I want my script to run at 7:00 AM,
check the weather for the next 12 hours,
so the time when I'm going to be away from home, and then send me a text message
if it's going to rain today
so that I can remember to bring an umbrella. That way I'll get notified before I
leave home and I'll know how to prepare for the day.
The data that we got back from open weather map contains the hourly
weather forecast for the next 48 hours.
So it starts from zero and goes up to 47.
Now we're only interested in the next 12 hours
because, if you imagine, this script is run at 7:00 AM
then plus 12 hours, that's going to be 7:00 PM. By which time,
hopefully I'm already on the way home
and I don't need to worry about whether if it rains or not. That's the goal.
And if we head back into our code,
what we want to do is firstly modify certain parts.
Now we know that at the moment,
the response code that we're getting back from calling this API is 200.
So it's successful. So we're going to call raise for status
so that if there is right a problem and we don't get a 200 code that we
actually raise an exception. Now,
next we want to save our response.json as the weather data.
And then we're going to work with this data in order to get the particular
pieces that we're interested in. So if we look at this JSON that
we get back, firstly, we don't really care about the current weather or
the daily weather.
So when we look at the API documentation
which is probably the hardest part,
making sure that you're diligent enough to read the entire documentation,
there's often some good nuggets in there. For example, in this case,
we can add another parameter called exclude
which allows us to exclude some parts of the weather data that comes from the
API. This should speed up the API fetching process
and it also means that we're transferring less data across the internet. So we
can get rid of the current, minutely and daily.
We're only interested in the hourly and we have to provide this as a comma-
delimited list. So if we take a look at their example, you can see here,
they've said exclude and then they've said hourly, daily.
And notice how it says without spaces. So as I always say,
this is like going into somebody else's house.
Everything is different. The way that the washing machine works is different,
the way that their dryer works is different.
So you really have to look at the API documentation when you were working
with a new API just so that you're not caught out
and you understand exactly what you have to do in order to be a good API user.
Let's go back into our code and let's provide that extra parameter.
So that was called exclude.
And the thing that we want to exclude is going to be provided as a string.
So we want to get rid of current, minutely and daily.
So we're going to add that into the string and make sure that we separate each
with a comma and without spaces.
okay.
Now when we hit run
and when we get back our weather data and we print it out
and we copy this and put it into our online JSON viewer,
so let's replace all of the stuff that was there before
and you can see the JSON we're getting back is now a lot simpler.
We're only getting back the hourly weather
forecast.
So that's step one done.
The next step is to dig through this hourly forecast and get hold of the thing
that we're interested in, which is the actual weather condition.
The way that weather services tend to provide the weather condition is through
an ID.
And I know this because I read the API documentation.
It's not because I'm some sort of weather geek. Although, I mean,
that's not a bad thing to be
I guess. If we take a look inside the API key,
if we scroll down in this documentation past the examples,
you can see it provides all of the fields in the API response. So these are
all of the things that we could possibly get back and what they mean.
And you can see there's some really interesting things like the UV index or you
can get, um,
what does the temperature feel like based on the wind chill and actual ground
temperature.
But what we're mostly interested in is the hourly data.
And then inside that the hourly weather data.
So this hourly.weather.id is a weather condition id.
And when you click on that link,
it takes you to this table that shows you all of the weather condition codes
that we could possibly get back in this particular field.
Now you can see that all the codes that start off with a two means some sort of
thunderstorm, and then starting with three
that means some sort of drizzling starting, with five means rain, starting with
six means snow. And then afterward we have the seven hundreds
so these are atmospheric. Thing's like a bit of mist, a bit of smoke,
a bit of dust or fog. And this is also incidentally,
the reason why this weather key actually has a value that's in the form of
a list. You can see that's denoted by the square brackets here.
So there could actually be multiple weather conditions for a particular place
at a particular hour. And that's because you could maybe have, um,
snow, but you could also have fog at the same time. Now,
when I looked through a lot of the examples and the documentation,
it seems like the first item in that list is the main condition.
So if it's going to rain, then it's going to be in that first item
in the list of weather conditions. Inside that list,
we have a dictionary or many dictionaries.
Each of those contain a weather condition ID,
the main condition name and the description.
So if we look at this ID code 802,
we can decode it in this table and you can see it means scattered clouds,
25 to 50% of the sky is covered in clouds basically.
Based on this list,
we can say that well anything that has a code less than 700,
then we probably will need an umbrella.
I'm not sure how you stand on the umbrella in snow situation
but I personally do like to hold an umbrella when it's snowing,
especially because I live in a country where the snow is not crazy.
It's just sort of,
it's never sort of the beautiful snow where it's thick and it gets caught on
your eyelashes. It's is the sort of annoying slush
that's just sort of snow, but it sort of like somebody spitting at you.
So in my case, I would prefer to have an umbrella if it was going to snow.
I'm going to check for the codes that we get back from the open weather map
API, and if the code is less than 700,
then I'm going to advise my user to bring an umbrella.
Here's a challenge for you.
Can you figure out how to look through the data that we get back,
which remember looks something like this, get hold of
the first 12
items from that hourly list.
And then look at the weather and the first item in the weather list and also the
ID. So you are going to go all the way down to this, but remember,
you're going to do that for all of the items
and you're going to check for the condition code. Now,
if any of those ID codes are less than 700 then you want to be able to print
out, bring an umbrella.
So that's the goal, and the actual implementation
I'll leave up to you because there's quite a few ways that you can do this.
But I'm sure by now you're well prepared with all of your tools in Python to
figure this out. If you want to make sure that your code is actually working,
you can switch to a latitude and longitude that is definitely raining.
So if you go to ventusky.com,
they actually show you the live weather forecast.
So we can look at precipitation, which is basically rain.
And we can find some sort of unfortunate place
which seems to be really heavily raining. For example,
this place in Poland, Lodz,
and if I spell that name correctly,
right,
Lodz, and then I'll add the country code Poland.
And just to make sure in the map
it's actually found the correct place. Yep that looks pretty much it.
Then I can switch out my latitude and longitude with this rainy place.
And that way I know that at least one of the results I get back is definitely
going to contain some sort of rain
right.
Now if we look at their hourly data,
you can see that the weather is basically just rain, rain, rain.
So between looking at places which are sunny and places
which are rainy,
you should be able to get your code to work so that it tells you in the next 12
hours
if any of those condition codes are less than 700,
which means it's got some form of precipitation.
Pause the video and give this a go.
Now.
All right. So let's narrow down into this
weather. If we want to get the weather for the next hour,
then we have to tap into the first item in our hourly list
and then we get hold of the weather
and then we get hold of the first item in that list. Under the ID key,
we'll get the actual value.
We've talked about this in detail in previous lessons.
If you've skipped a lot of lessons and you've come here directly,
then it's going to be a little bit confusing
and I recommend to review the previous lessons before you continue.
Instead of printing the weather data, let's drill down.
Let's get to the first item here, which is hourly.
If we provide a set of square brackets and then we can access the value inside
the hourly key like this.
And now we've got a list with all of the hourly data and it looks pretty much
like this.
Now you can confirm this by also pasting this into the JSON viewer,
replacing the previous text that was there. You can see
we now have our 48 items in this list of hourly data. To drill further down,
let's get hold of the first item in that list by providing a square bracket
and then the index, which is zero.
Now we're into the first item and this is what the data looks like.
It's a lot shorter.
Now we want to tap into the weather condition.
So that means yet another set of square brackets and then the name of the key,
which is weather. Now, it's pretty simple.
It's simply giving us a list with only one item.
Let's tap into that one item by using, again,
square brackets, zero.
And now we've got just a simple dictionary
essentially. So if you want to get hold of the ID,
then its the final square brackets and the key
which is ID. The current weather data ID code is 500 and that, of course, refers to
light rain.
The next problem is how do we get hold of the first 12 items that we get back in
our weather data? In previous lessons, we covered the Python
slice function
which could work for this by simply providing a value and slicing a sequence
like a list or tuple to get hold of a particular section of that list or
tuple. Now you can also use the Python slice operator
which is the square bracket and a colon
and this is probably a more pythonic way of doing things.
And you'll see more people doing this in the wild than using the slice function.
So let's do it with this notation. We're going to use this version.
So we're going to tap into a list and then provide a colon and then where we
want to stop because we want to go from the beginning of the list through to
stop-1.
We know that it's this part of our code that gets us to our list of hourly
weather forecasts. So we want to create a slice from that data.
So let's copy that and comment this line out.
And then I'm going to create my weather slice
which is going to be generated from the weather data under the key called
hourly. If I print this,
you can see it starts off just simply being a list with all of the weather
forecasts. Now, if I go ahead and slice this,
I'll use that syntax that you saw earlier on where we have a square bracket,
a colon, and then where we want our slice to end.
And we want this slice to go from zero all the way up to hour 11,
so that's 12 hours in total. So if we want to go up to 11,
then we have to put 12 in here because it's going to be whatever number here,
minus one. And now if we print this data that we get back,
and
we replaced the existing text inside our JSON viewer,
then we take a look at it
you can see we've got the next 12 hours of weather data from 0 to 11.
Once we've got that slice, the next step is, well,
how do we get the rest of the stuff, right?
What if I created a new list that contains the condition codes?
We know that we've got a list of all of the weather conditions for the next 12
hours.
How can we loop through that list to find out the actual ID of the weather
condition for each of those hours? Well,
we can create a for loop that looks at each of the data from the hour,
so for hour_data in weather_slice,
so this is going to go through each of the 12 hours.
And then for each of those hours,
we're going to tap into the hour_data and try to get hold of the item that is in
the weather key. Like this.
Now I'm going to print each of these and you can see we've now got a list of all
of the weather conditions for each of those hours.
Now let's narrow down that a little bit further.
Let's get hold of the first item of each of these lists and you can see,
in fact, there's only one item in all of these lists.
It's very rare that you have multiple weather conditions for each hour.
Now, that gives us a Python dictionary for each of those hours
and we can tap into that final value we're interested in under the key id.
So now we've looped through the next 12 hours and got hold of the weather
condition id for each of those hours. Now,
all we need to do is to save this instead of printing it and we'll call it the
condition_code.
Yeah.
And remember previously we said that if the condition code is less than 700,
then we're going to print bring an umbrella.
So we can check if condition_code,
which remember at this point is still a string
so we have to turn that into an integer in order to be able to compare it
against another number.
If that condition_code as an integer is less than 700,
then we're going to print bring an umbrella,
right?
And you can see that for the next 12 hours
there's six hours which are going to rain at this particular place
in Lodz in Poland that I've put into that latitude and longitude.
Now, if I don't want to call this print statement many times,
then we can define a variable outside
the for loop called will_rain and we can set that to false
to begin with. Now, if during the next 12 hours
the condition_code is less than 700, then we'll switch that to equal
true instead. Now,
after the for loop has completed,
then we can check to see if it will rain in the next 12 hours. And if so,
we'll print bring an umbrella. This way
we'll only get one print statement being called instead of every single time we
land on a condition code for rain.
So this involved quite a bit of JSON passing and also understanding how to work
with parameters in APIs. Now,
I hope you managed to get this far by yourself.
But if not, be sure to review what I've written and fix your code as required.
If any of it was confusing,
be sure to review previous lessons before you continue
because we're now building heavily on your previous knowledge that you learnt
through the course. Now in the next lesson,
we're going to be looking at how we can, instead of printing
bring an umbrella, to send a SMS text message that notifies you to bring an
umbrella instead. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now that we've got the hard part out of the way, figuring out when it's
actually going to rain,
the next step is to figure out how we can send this as an alert to our phone
number, using an SMS service. So for that,
we're going to need to use a different API.
The Twilio API. Twilio is an API service that allows us to send text messages or
phone calls or have a virtual phone number in any country.
And if you take a look at their front page,
you can see there's actually a whole bunch of things you can do with the Twilio
API.
You could build an ordering system, you could create a video app,
you could have SMS to email, whole bunch of things basically. Now,
in order to create the service,
they obviously had to build a lot of infrastructure and they've invested a lot
into making this seamless and work well.
So that's why if you look at the pricing section,
they do charge for their service if you're using it a lot.
Now, in our case, we're going to get started using some trial credit.
So they're going to give us $10 of trial credit
and we can test out all of the API and use any of their features.
First, go ahead and click on, get started for free,
and you'll need to sign up to get a free Twilio account.
No credit card required. Now,
if you don't want to learn how to send a text message to yourself,
that's also perfectly fine. You don't have to sign up.
You can just do what we did previously using email.
Once you've signed up with Twilio,
you'll have to confirm your email and also confirm your actual phone number.
Once you've completed confirming your email and your phone number,
then it's going to take you to the console
and it's going to ask you a few questions. Do you write code? Yes,
of course we do. What's your preferred language? Python.
And what's your goal today? Well,
we're going to use Twilio in a project. And the first thing we want to do is to
send or receive SMS.
So now it's going to take us to our Twilio project dashboard and it starts off
by giving us some trial money.
So this is the money that we can use to test out and use the Twilio API.
Let's first start by clicking on get a trial number,
and it's going to generate for you a automatic number from the US.
Now, if you want to,
you can buy a number from a different country and you can start typing any of
these numbers. But in our case,
it doesn't actually matter where the number is from.
We can simply just get the default number and click on choose this number.
So now we have a new phone number based in the US. We're ready to click done and
start using that Twilio number to send ourselves some SMS messages.
Now we're going ahead over to docs and we're going to go over to QuickStarts.
Now, what we want to do is to follow this guide, the programmable SMS
quick start, in order to start sending SMS messages.
So we're going to click on the Python section of that Quickstart,
and you can see on the right,
it gives us the example code that we need to implement in order to make this
work.
The first thing we need to do is to download the Twilio library in order to use
it to import this client class.
Let's go ahead and copy this into our project.
So right below where we've got import requests,
let's go ahead and paste this line of code that we copied.
And you'll notice that it has some red underlines.
This is because we need to install this Twilio module.
So clicking on that underlined Twilio,
we can click on the red light bulb and install this package.
Once that's done,
all of the errors should go away and we can now start using this client class.
Going back to the example code.
We need to copy down our account
sid and our auth token.
We can get these details from the Twilio dashboard.
Notice here that this account sid is basically the identification for my
Twilio account. And the auth token we'll need to get from the dashboard.
If we go to the console here on the top right,
and we copy this auth token here,
or you can click on show to see it,
then we can paste it in here and replace this auth token.
And just for consistency sake,
I'm going to change this single quote to double quote.
So these are both strings. Now, as I mentioned before,
these IDs that you see on screen are not going to work for you.
So make sure that you've actually logged on and confirmed all your details
so you can get your own account sid and auth token.
Now let's head back to our quick start and we've done all of this.
What we need to do now is to set up a Twilio client using our account sid and
auth token.
Let's go ahead and create our client at the point where we want to send
ourselves a SMS message.
So I'm going to delete all of this. And instead of the print statement,
we're going to set up our Twilio client. Next,
we're going to create our message.
So this is the message that we're going to send ourselves.
The part that we need to change is the body.
So this is the text that we're going to send ourselves.
And then we're going to change the
from field to the telephone number that we got from Twilio and the to
number to the telephone number that we signed up with Twilio with.
So let's do one thing at a time. The message that I want to send myself is
um,
As always on a Mac,
you can go to edit emojis and symbols to pull up the emoji keyboard.
If you were in Windows or Linux,
you can simply just head over to Google and search for an umbrella emoji and
paste it in here. That's our message done.
The next step is to figure out what is the telephone number that is going to be
the sender's telephone number. Going back to our Twilio dashboard,
we're going to copy this trial number here
and we're going to paste it in the from field as a string.
The next thing is the to, so this is who the message is going to be sent to.
This has to be the phone number that you used to sign up to Twilio. On the
Twilio trial account, you can send messages and make calls to verified numbers.
And you can add verified numbers by clicking on this plus button
and you can enter somebody's phone numbers, so your friends or family,
but you have to be able to receive a message or receive a call in order to
verify that you actually own that number, or you have access to that number.
Any of the numbers that you see here under verified caller IDs can be used in
your code.
Go ahead and replace this part where it says to with your verified number.
Now, finally,
it asks us to print the message that we created here .sid.
And basically what it means is that once this message has an ID created,
it means it was sent successfully. Instead of printing the message sid,
we're going to print the message status instead
just to make sure that it was actually sent successfully.
All of this code is indented inside the will_rain block
and this is what's going to be triggered if indeed it will rain today.
Now let's go ahead and test this. But before we can test it,
we have to find somewhere that's actually raining.
It seems like people in Bern are getting quite a bit of rainfall.
So let's update our latitude and longitude to Bern in Switzerland.
Right.
Now that we've got somewhere that's raining,
let's go ahead and run our code and let's take a look at what happens on the
phone. There you have it.
We've got our message sent from our Twilio trial account.
It's going to rain today. Remember to bring an umbrella. Now, of course,
you'll be able to get rid of this part where it says sent from your Twilio trial
account if you sign up for an actual account. But for all intents and purposes,
this is working perfectly and we're now able to receive an SMS when the weather condition
in the next 12 hours contains some rain.
So the very last thing we have to do is set up our Python script to run every
morning at 7:00 AM.
Now that we've tested our code and we've managed to get it working locally,
the next step is to put our script online so that it can be run on schedule and
we don't have to manually open up PyCharm and run it every morning at 7:00 AM.
How do we do this? Well, we're going to use Python anywhere,
the same service that we use before when we created the automatic birthday
wisher. Now, the first thing we're going to do is of course,
log into the service and we're going to delete all of our previous files.
So that includes the letter template folder and also the main.
py and the birthdays.csv. Now,
instead of the previous main.py, we're going to upload our latest
main.py.
So let's go ahead and locate this in our computer,
and then we're going to upload it to Python anywhere.
There you go.
Now let's open up this file and click bash console here.
So that's going to create our console down at the bottom.
And once it's ready, like this, we can enter the command to run this code.
So it's pythone and then its the name of our file,
which is main.py.
And because it's directly within my users folder,
I don't have to specify a file path to it.
Now I don't recommend to have your main.py nested within other folders because
it's going to make this a little bit more complicated.
So as long as you've uploaded it to the same place that I have, just straight
after your username, then we should be able to run this line of code
and we can test out whether if this code now works,
when it's being run from Python anywhere. Now,
what you'll see instead of the message status however,
is a exception and it's a connection error. And the connection error tells us
something about this API Twilio
max retries exceeded with URL.
So if we go ahead and highlight that, which will copy it,
then we can paste it into Google and figure out what's wrong.
The first post you can see is a post from help at Python anywhere.
And they've created this post to tell you how to get Twilio
to work on free accounts with Python
anywhere. As they say, if you're trying to use Twilio on a Python anywhere
free account, you're going to run into an error that looks something like this,
which is exactly what we got.
And that's where Google search picked it up to show us this article.
The reason for this is because the Twilio API basically needs to be told how to
connect to the proxy servers that free accounts use.
When you have a paid account on Python
anywhere, you have an actual address to your dedicated server.
But when you only sign up with a free account like we have here,
we only get a proxy server.
So we need to change the code a little bit in order for it to work.
Even though we are actually using the latest version of Twilio, from testing
I found that this code doesn't seem to work for me. Instead,
we have to use this version of the fix that they've specified here.
So the only difference from their version of code and what we have here in our
main.py is three lines of code. First,
we have to import this class called TwilioHttpClient from the Twilio module.
So let's copy that and paste it below our previous lines.
Now, in addition,
we have to create a proxy client with the TwilioHttpClient class that we just
imported just now. So we're going to put that in our if statement
when we're about to create our SMS message.
The last step is where we have our client class being created,
we have to set this HTTP client parameter to the proxy client that we created
just now. That's going to go right here.
The rest of the code we can leave as is,
and we can simply hit save to update that code.
Now, once we've typed all of that code, you can see we get an error in here.
It says undefined name 'os'.
And that's because this os actually comes from an os module.
So we should import that in order for this error to go away.
So let's hit save again and you can see,
we are now free of warnings and errors.
We're now ready to go into our console and to run the same command again,
which is python3 and then it's the name of our file, main.py.
So now when we hit enter, you can see we get back the message queued,
which comes from this print statement
and that's because the status of our message has now been queued.
And you can see I've now received the message from Twilio.
And this is of course,
because my main.py was run on the Python anywhere servers instead of from my
local computer. So now that we've confirmed that this works,
we can now finally go back to Python anywhere and go to the Tasks section in
order to set up our task. Now here,
I've still got my previous task set up when we created the automatic birthday
wisher. Now because I'm demoing this with a free Python anywhere account,
I can only create one scheduled task. If I start paying them,
then I can schedule as many as I want and they never expire.
But because we're just learning here,
I don't want you to commit to a paid account just to be able to see how it
works. So we're going to use the same schedule task. Now,
if you don't have any task scheduled, just go ahead and create one.
And the command is going to be the same. It's python3
and then it's running
our main.py. So the same command that you entered previously.
And we're going to set the frequency to daily and it's going to run at 7:00 AM
every day. In order to test this,
I'm going to change the time from 7:00 AM to the current time.
So the current server time is registering as 10:01, but in fact,
I'm actually seeing 02.
So I'm going to change that to 10:03 and then hit the checkmark.
And now I'm going to wait patiently to see if that is going to be triggered
automatically from the schedule tasks
and I get the SMS sent to my phone. And there you have it.
This is now being sent to me from Twilio because we made the API call,
but it's being sent because I've got this scheduled task
which is calling this command in order to run our main.py
and it's being done at a time which I've specified,
which in fact, I want to happen at probably 7:00 AM in the morning.
Now notice that this is UTC time.
So if you want to convert the UTC time to your local time,
so at the moment, we're on British summer time where I'm at,
then you can type this into Google and change this to whatever time zone you're
in.
And that way you can figure out what time UTC is relative to your local time.
In my case, it's just one hour behind.
So if I want this to run at 7:00 AM my local time that I have to change this to
six o'clock. And now that's going to run every day at 6:00 AM without me needing
to do anything and I'm going to get my notification on time
if it's going to rain.
Now that we've got our app working,
you might think we've reached the end of today's lessons,
but there's just one final thing I want to talk to you about.
And that is the environment. Not the environment as a whole,
but more precisely environment variables.
Now what our environment variables anyways?
If you go into your PyCharm project
and you go into this tab where it says "Terminal", here
if you type in env (set on Windows) and hit "Enter",
you can see a whole bunch of variables.
So you've got a key and a value
and in between there is just a single equal (=) sign.
So these are the different variables that are set in the environment in which
your code is run.
These variables have values which are strings
which can be used in our applications or our code.
Now inside Python
anywhere you can also type env and you can see some slightly different
environment variables which are relative to the Python anywhere environment.
What exactly all these environment variables used for? Well,
there's two major use cases. One is for convenience.
Normally when you deploy a large application,
the process is quite complicated. And once you've done it,
you kind of don't want to mess around with the code base and update the code
files like your main.py for example. Instead,
you could have these environment variables, which you can change. For example,
if you had an application that was sending you emails out to your clients,
then your client base emails might change day to day.
So certain variables that are being used in your code base could be set as
environment variables
and you can modify those variables without having to touch the code.
A second reason might be for security.
So when you're developing software,
you might be uploading your code based somewhere, for example
to store it online or to a service like PythonAnywhere.
And it's usually not a good idea to have things like your authentication keys or
your API keys to be stored in the same place as the rest of your code.
That's where environment variables come in.
So environment variables essentially allow us to separate out where we store
our keys, our secret stuff,
and various other variables away from where our code base is located.
In our case,
it doesn't really matter because we haven't got a paid account anywhere in here.
It doesn't really matter if somebody steals our auth token or our API key,
because none of those are linked to our payment details. Now, however,
if we were to upgrade our accounts on open weather map's API
or on Twilio's API,
then we definitely want to keep these two things secret; auth token and the API
key.
Instead of having it located in the same place where we've got our code base
which means you might accidentally upload it somewhere on the internet where
other people can see it, instead,
we can store these two things as environment variables.
We can create an environment variable by simply typing export
and then the name of the variable which I'll call OWM
_API_KEY. And then it's really important that we have no spaces,
but just a single equal sign.
And then we're going to store everything that's in between the quotation marks.
So I'm going to copy that from over here,
and I'm going to paste that in here. Once I've exported that
and then if I hit "env" again, you'll see
now in this updated environment
you can see that environment variable go in right there.
And now we can tap into that environment variable in any of the code that we run
from this particular environment. To do that we have to use this os module that
we've already got.
So I'm going to delete everything that's currently stored in the API key.
And instead, I'm going to tap into os.environ,
and then I'm going to use a method called get to get the value of a particular
environment variable.
The name is everything that's before the equal sign.
So let's go ahead and paste it in here. And now when I run this code,
so using python3 and then the name of the file,
you can see that it successfully runs queuing our message into Twilio.
Now go ahead and do the same thing with the auth token.
You want to save this as an environment
variable code auth_token in all caps,
similar to what we've got here.
And you want to store this value in the environment variable.
Pause the video and give that a go. All right.
So we're going to follow the exact same thing that we did before. We use the
export keyword and then we type in the name of the environment variable
which is going to be AUTH_TOKEN. And then really importantly,
we just have an equal sign, no spaces,
and we're going to store this value without the double-quotes
and we're going to put it in here. Now in our environment variables,
you can see we've got our open weather map API key.
And if we scroll up a bit more, you can see our auth token as well.
So now we can replace this string with our os.environ.get
and then we pass in the name of the key which is AUTH_TOKEN.
And now let's run our code again with python3 main.py.
And you can see it's still works as before.
But now if somebody comes across this particular code base on the internet,
they won't be able to use our Twilio account or our open weather map account
because both of these keys are now hidden. Let's go ahead and hit save.
So now we're going to do the same thing,
but at the point where we run our code from our task scheduler.
So go ahead and right-click on this snake and then open the link in a new tab so
that we can go to our tasks section.
And here we're going to edit our command. Instead of just running Python main
.py, we're going to export those two environment variables.
This is why we've got two screens open up so we can actually copy the actual
values. The first value is going to be our open weather map
API key. So I'm going to copy that. And then here,
I'm going to write export and then paste in that first key. Now,
afterward, I'm going to use a semi-colon to denote a new line
and then I'm going to export the next key. Scrolling up,
we can see our auth token right here so we're going to copy that as well
and we're going to export that as the other environment variable.
And then finally, we're going to cap it off with a semicolon.
So now you should have your export OWM_API_KEY
and then your exporting your auth token as well. And then finally,
on the last line, we're running our python3 main.py.
Now let's change this to run at the current time.
So it's going to be UTC time which happens to be 10 o'clock
and then instead of 46, it's now 48
so I'm going to change that to 49. And then I'm gonna hit the tick.
And now we're going to wait to see if it actually works
even though we've taken out the API keys from our main.py
because we're exporting it in our command.
Let's see if we still get the notification message.
There you have it. It's still working as before.
But now this is invisible to people
if they happen to access our main.py.
Now don't worry. The service of Python anywhere are pretty secure.
Nobody's really going to hack into your account
just to look into your main.py.
The bigger problem is when you upload your own code to places like Git
Hub or a BitBucket,
basically places that are essentially a Dropbox for code.
And when you have it on there, because your code could be public,
that's where the problem happens.
If people look at your code file and they see that you've got API keys in there,
then they might steal them. So whenever you're uploading your code publicly,
always be careful that you strip it of all of the API keys and instead use
environment variables like we have here to pull it from the environment.
All that's left to do for you is to update your latitude and longitude to your
actual local latitude and longitude instead of the rainy place that we're
testing. And you've now completed the rain alert application.
Now I've showed you quite a few different APIs,
but there's a whole world of APIs for you to explore.
And if you have the patience to read their documentation and understand how to
work with their APIs, then you now know how to work with their endpoints,
how to pass parameters and also how to authenticate yourself with their servers.
So here's a list of fun APIs that you can use to build applications with.
I've shown you how you can make a rain alert and send yourself SMS messages,
or how to get the location of the ISS or the sunrise and sunset times,
but there's a whole bunch of other APIs for you to explore. For example,
things like the open movie database API,
which contains a whole bunch of movie related data,
or looking up songs and artists using the Spotify API and a whole lot more.
So I'll leave you to explore that.
And if you come up with something innovative and interesting,
be sure to share it with the rest of us in the Q&A below this lesson so that
we can all check it out and admire your hard work.
Hey guys,
it's Angela here and welcome to Day 36 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we've got a fun project for you.
We're going to be building a stock news monitoring project.
So I don't know how many of you guys trade stocks out there,
but I've recently started learning about it.
And one of the pictures that always come to my mind when I think of people
trading stocks is something like this,
where if you will sit in front of a million screens,
looking at all of the data and all of the news.
Now I did a bit of research into this
and it seems like a lot of the people who trade stocks professionally have
access to what's that a Bloomberg terminal, which looks something like this.
And it provides you with a number of things,
the current stock prices of whichever companies you're looking at,
and also the breaking news that's relevant to those companies. So
depending on whether if they had some good news
say they earned a lot of money in the last quarter, or
they built a really great product or they developed a new vaccine.
Then obviously you can imagine the price of their company's stock go up or down
depending on the type of news that comes out. And finally these platforms
also give you the ability to alert you when relevant pieces of news happen that are
related to stocks that you're following.
So I found out for my friend that to subscribe to one of these Bloomberg
terminals,
it costs something like $24,000 a year.
So that was the end of that research. Um,
but I thought about it and I thought about the kind of things that would be
really useful to somebody who trades stocks.
And I thought about how we could turn this into a Python project.
So here's what's going to happen.
We're going to DIY our own a Bloomberg terminal or at least the parts of the
functionality that are quite useful. First,
let's take a look at what stock market data looks like. So here,
I've got a website up called tradingview.com and I'm looking at the large cap
companies.
So these are well known companies that you've probably heard of like Apple or
Microsoft or Amazon.
And let's say that we had an interest in a particular stock.
Let's say that we bought shares in Tesla,
and we want to know how it's doing. Well,
we could take a closer look at it and we could take a look at
the full featured chart.
And this shows us the price of the Tesla stock over the past few days.
Now I'm going to change the time zone here to the actual time zone of the
exchange. And if I change the view to one day view,
then you can see the points at which the market is open and when it's closed.
So these blue sections highlight when the market is closed.
Currently it's the 22nd of July. So because this day's
data is not yet complete, we're going to look at the previous day's data.
So this is yesterday.
And you can see that NASDAQ opens at 9:30 AM New York time
and it closes down at 4:00 PM on the same day.
And often when you're getting data on stocks,
you can get the price of a particular stock at the point when the market opens
and when the market closes. For example,
we could compare the price of the Tesla stock at market close yesterday.
So that was about $1,567 and at market close the previous day
so that's four o'clock on the 20th of July,
and that was at around $1,641.
So there was a big difference between the end of the 20th of July and the end of
the 21st of July. As a stock trader would be quite
interested in these big fluctuations because it might mean that we would want to
buy more, or we might want to sell our stocks in Tesla.
When you look at a lot of these services
be it Bloomberg terminals or something much simpler like this,
they often give you a whole bunch of other data as well.
One of the most useful things is actually to look at the news that's related to
the company that you're investigating. So for example,
these are the current headlines for Tesla,
and it comes from various news sources like Reuters or my Wall Street or
Bloomberg. And it gives us some information to start analyzing.
For example, well why was there this big drop, what's the reason,
and there's various news sources that might tell us why. For example,
maybe they're experiencing problems with servicing staff,
or maybe as this news piece suggests, the stock is probably going to rise again.
So these are really interesting things
if we were to trade this particular stock.
If we were to create a Python program that's going to help us trade stocks,
then this is how it might work. First,
we're going to pull in the stock prices of the stocks that we're interested in.
So we would be using an API to get this data.
And let's say that we were monitoring the Tesla stock cause we bought some
shares and we want to know how it's doing. Well,
it might pull in the data for the price of Tesla stock that was at market close.
Let's say that today was March the 11th.
So we're pulling in yesterday's closing price and let's just say, for example,
it is $1,000.
Now the next thing our program is going to do is it's going to pull in the
closing price on the previous day.
And we're going to compare these two values. So over the course of one day,
what was the difference. And in this case,
there's a difference of a hundred dollars and the direction is up.
So it increased in value, right? Going from March 9th to March 10th.
So that's good news for us if we bought in. Now,
we can also calculate what is the percentage that this rise represents.
So if we look at this difference of a hundred dollars and calculate it as a
percentage of yesterday's closing price,
then we can see that the price on March 9th was 10% lower than on March 10th.
So let's say that in our Python program,
we set the program to run and fetch us some news
whenever we get a slightly extraordinary rise or an extraordinary fall.
So you can define that as anything you want, but let's say it's 10%.
If there was a difference of 10% or more between yesterday's closing price and
the previous day, then we want to know about it.
So we're going to get our API to fetch us some relevant news.
That way we can figure out what is the reason for this rise or what is the
reason for this fall.
And it might just turn out well because Tesla launched a new product,
or because they've acquired a new factory.
Some sort of indicator that says, well,
this company is going to do a lot better. Now,
once the stock prices have triggered this alert and we fetched the news data,
then we're going to send ourselves an SMS.
So we're going to send ourselves a message telling us what was the big
fluctuation that happened and what is the relevant news so that we can decide
there and then whether if you want to sell our stock,
or if we want to buy more.
We're aiming for messages from Twilio that look a bit like this.
That way
when you wake up in the morning and you're wondering what's happening with my
Tesla stock and it just so happens that over the last two days,
it experienced huge fluctuations,
then you would get sent the relevant pieces of news to help you decide and help
you figure out what you should do with your trades. That's the goal.
And the best part of this project is the fact that it's going to be mostly up to
you as to how you create it
In the course resources I've got links
to starting projects with the comment and hints,
and depending on which level of difficulty you want to choose, normal,
hard or extra hard, you can pick the starting project that's right for you.
Once you pick the starting project,
then you are going to work through each of the comments
and you're going to try and complete the functionality of this program.
Now I want you to spend at least a half an hour to 45 minutes working on this
project, just because it has quite a few APIs that you need to tap into.
And most importantly,
I want you to read through the API documentation yourself so that you can
understand how to work with it and how to figure out things on your own.
Because after all, there are millions of APIs out there
and if you're going to need it for a special project of your own,
you're going to need to go through this process that all developers go through
which is digging through documentation and understanding how to work with an
external piece of  software
or code.
That's the challenge I've set for you. Head over to the course resources now and
get the starting code so that you can get started working on the project.
Good luck.
Now I'm going to walk you through the solution.
And I want to make sure that you've actually given this a go before you look
through the solution, because you can watch me type in code all day long,
and it's still not going to get you where you want to be.
So make sure you've actually practiced and you've struggled.
Even if you get stuck,
it's still better than just watching the videos and seeing the code written.
You have to write code to get good at writing code. All right,
enough motivation.
Now I'm going to take the normal starting point to guide you through step by
step. Now, notice how in the starting project I've included a bunch of to-dos.
And one of the nice things about PyCharm is you can view all of the
to-dos a found in the file and you can delete them as you check them off,
and then you'll be able to see what is remaining. And when you click on it,
it takes you directly to that particular to-do's location, which is really neat.
Let's start from the top.
We want to be able to use the alphavantage.co's APIs in order to get
yesterday's closing stock price. So that's the first thing.
How do we do that? Well, Alpha vantage is a stock market API
and what we have to do is first set up an API key.
You can select yourself as a student and then your organization if you have one
and then enter your email. Now, once you filled in the form, you can click on
get a free API key
and you should see your API key show up below.
Make sure that you copy this API key and save it in your project.
So I'm going to head over here and right at the top,
I'm going to add my STOCK_API_KEY as a constant like this.
That way
I won't forget it because it's actually quite hard to navigate back to this page
and get your API key. Now, the next step is of course,
the digging through the documentation. Now,
for those of you guys who chose the hard and extra hard versions,
I didn't really point you towards which part of the API documentation is most
relevant, because I hope that if you had chosen to give yourself a challenge,
you would appreciate having the opportunity to dig through all of the different
things you can do with the API. Now, in our case,
we actually want is the daily data.
So this API will return the daily data
which will give us the open price, the highest price of the day,
the lowest price of the day, and also the closing price at the day
which is what we're mostly interested in. There's a couple of API parameters
which are required; the function
which in this case is a time series daily, and also the symbol
which is the name of the equity of your choice. In our case,
we've already defined that at the top. It's the stock name right here.
So let's see how we can fetch yesterday's closing stock price. To start
we of course need our trusty requests module.
And using requests
we're going to fetch from the stock endpoint.
So you can see that in their example,
the end point is everything up to and not including the question
mark. This should be all pretty familiar to you,
but you could also just type in simply the one that I've already included.
This stock endpoint. Now next we're going to need to add some parameters.
So let's create something called our stock_params and let's see what we need
to add. So we have to add the function
which is equal to time series daily. I'm going to copy that
so I don't make any typos.
So let's create a Python dictionary and this is going to be the key and value.
Next,
we have to add our symbol and that is going to be the name of our stock or
equity.
The symbol, in this case, is simply going to be our stock name TSLA
Right.
And stock symbols tend to have a maximum number of four letters.
So that's why you see it abbreviated like Snap for Snapchat or TSLA for Tesla.
Now the final required parameter is our API key.
The whole thing is not going to work unless we authenticate ourselves using the
API key that we got just now,
which is saved as our STOCK_API_KEY.
Now that we've got all three parameters in there, well, we can add it to our
request method, and it will just add it as the stock_params.
Now let's save this as the response and let's print out what the response
actually look like when it's in the format of a JSON.
So let's run this code and I'm getting a error that says indentation error
unexpected indent. And that's because my stock_params here
really should actually be within the same indentation as the starting point
like this. So be careful that when you have a to-do that's
indented every line that you start afterward is going to be indented as
well.
So it probably helps to just unindent everything so that they will start at the
margin here. So let's try that again.
And this time it looks like we're getting back actual data in the format of
a JSON. Let's view it using our JSON viewer.
You can see that we've got some metadata
which basically just describes what we told the API. For example,
we wanted the Tesla symbol and we wanted the daily price.
But what we're actually interested is in the time series daily data.
So you can see it's giving us the data for all of the dates prior to today.
So currently it's 22nd of July
so we can see the complete data for the 21st of July and the 20th of July. Right
now, what we're interested in is yesterday's closing stock price.
So this is yesterday and this is the closing stock price.
So it's 1,568. How do we get hold of it? Well,
we have to step through a number of keys in order to get to this particular
value. First,
we need to pass in our time series daily and notice how this has brackets and
everything. We have to include all of the spaces, all the brackets in our key.
Let's say that our data is equal to the response.
json, let's go ahead and add a square bracket,
and then we can provide the key
which I'm actually just going to copy from down here.
So I don't make any typos and
make sure that I preserve all of the spaces and all of the symbols.
So basically everything in between the quotation marks like this.
Now, if we print our data,
you can see it's stepped into that particular dictionary
and it's now giving us all of this data. But this is not a list.
As you can see, the data starts out with a curly bracket. In fact,
it's a really big dictionary with the key being the date.
Now, while I can tap into yesterday's data
by simply providing this as the key,
this is going to be pretty hard-coded because once I get to tomorrow
when it becomes the 23rd, then yesterday's date is going to change.
So we have to figure out another way of getting hold of that first value.
How about turning this large dictionary into a list where we get each of the
pieces of data that's associated with each of the keys? To do that,
we're going to need to do a bit of a list comprehension.
So I'm going to create a variable called data_list
and then I'm going to use my list comprehension keywords.
So we did list comprehensions a while back,
but this might be a good time to remind yourself of how to use it.
It's going to be new item for item in list.
Our list is actually not a list. It's in fact a dictionary.
So we're going to tap into our data, which is the dictionary,
and we're going to call the items method on it.
And this is going to give us not just the item,
but the key and the value.
So we're actually only interested in the values. So we can put that in here
so that each item in this new list is composed of only the values and not the
keys. Now, if I print this data list,
you can see I've now got a list denoted by the square brackets
and each item in the list is a dictionary with each day's data. Using that I can
get hold of yesterday_
data by simply tapping to our data list and getting the object at index zero.
Now, once I've got yesterday's data,
then it's pretty simple to get yesterday's closing price,
because that is simply stored under this particular key. Now again,
notice how the entire key is this. It's everything in between the quotation
marks, including the number and the dot and all of that.
So this is a bit of a strange way of formatting your keys, to be honest.
I haven't seen many APIs that do this because it's a little bit confusing to
have spaces and dots and numbers,
but that's just the way that they decided to do it.
So in order to get the closing price,
we can tap into yesterday's data, add a set of square brackets, pass in this
particular key. So now if we print out yesterday's closing price,
you can see we've narrowed down on the exact price of the Tesla stock at
yesterday market close.
Right?
That's to-do number one completed. We can delete the to-do.
Now
the next one is to get the day before yesterday's closing stock price.
So now that we've actually got this data list,
it's pretty simple to do that; day_before_yesterday_
data is going to be equal to the data list at index one
because remember everything in the list is ordered going backward from today's
date. So that is going to be the day before yesterday's data.
And then the day before yesterday's closing price,
we can fetch that in the same way
by passing in that key 4.space close.
And just to confirm everything works,
let's print out both of the closing prices
so you can see that yesterday it closed at $1,568
and then the day before it closed at $1,643.
So that's actually quite a big drop, almost a hundred dollars.
That's to-do number two done.
We've managed to get the day before yesterday's closing stock price. To-do number
three
involves finding the positive difference between step one and two,
so yesterday's closing price and the day before yesterday's closing price.
And it gives us a hint.
Now the hint takes us to the Python abs function,
which we've also seen before.
It's a function that returns the absolute value of a number.
So it basically just gets rid of any negative sign in front of a number.
And this is what we need in order to complete to-do number three.
Right?
The difference is going to be yesterday's closing price subtract by the day
before yesterday's closing price. Now,
because these two are strings, if we actually run the code right now,
you're going to get an error.
And the error tells you that you can't subtract between a string and a string.
We know that these numbers look like this,
so we can quite easily convert them into a floating point numbers just by
wrapping the float function around them. If we print that out,
you can see that it's actually going to be a negative number.
And the reason is because this is yesterday's price,
this is the day before yesterday's price.
The price actually went down by $74.
What if we want to get the positive difference between one and two?
Well,
this is where the abs or absolute value function comes in handy.
If we wrap all of that around the absolute function, now, if I run it,
you can see we're getting a positive value instead.
Now that's step three completed.
We found the positive difference between yesterday's closing price and the day
before yesterday's closing price.
Now let's tackle step number four.
We want to be able to work out the percentage difference in price between the
closing price yesterday and the closing price the day before yesterday.
The diff_percent is going to be the difference divided by the closing price
yesterday.
And in order to turn this into a percentage,
we're going to have to multiply it by 100. But again,
notice that this is a floating point number because it was calculated here,
but this is still the string.
So we're going to have to turn that into a float for this calculation to
actually go through. And once it does that, we're going to print it out.
We've got about a 4.75% difference.
Now we can tackle to-do number five,
which is if the percentage here is greater than five,
then we're going to print get news. This is pretty simple.
All we have to do is check if the diff_percent is greater than five,
in which case we're going to print get news. Now,
depending on the time when you're completing this project,
the stock price of Tesla may not show a difference
that's greater than five. Because in order to continue testing our code
we're going to need this to be true,
then we can change this number to a smaller number,
just so that we can actually get it to work. So my case,
the difference is 4.75. So I'm actually just going to change this down to 4.
And now if I run all of this,
then you can see it's going to print get news.
So that is what we're going to do on the next lesson
in the second part of the solution.
In the first part of the solution,
we managed to get our code to pull in the live stock data for the selected
stock name.
And then we looked at the difference in price between yesterday and the day
before yesterday and then we worked out the percentage difference.
Now we have this if statement which will print get news
if the percentage difference is greater than a specified amount.
Now, I've put right five here, just because ideally,
if you were monitoring a particular stock,
you'd probably only be interested if it changed by a large amount,
like 5 or 10 or 50% set by you. But at the moment,
because we're testing these things and the Tesla stock is only moved by one
point something percent, then this is actually never going to be true.
So I'm going to manually adjust this down so that we can continue working with
the rest of the challenge. So now onto step two of the challenge,
the first part is instead of printing get news,
we're going to use the news API to get articles related to
the company name. The news API is newsapi.org.
And we can start by getting hold of an API key.
Once you signed up, you should get a free API key
and we're going to paste that into our project.
Now we can start looking through the documentation and seeing how we can use
this news API.
There's a number of end points as we can see. There's top headlines and also
everything. These are the two main end points.
Now everything is better for article discovery
whereas the headlines tend to only have a limited number of headlines.
I've tested both of these
and I found that the everything one is more likely to give us a news piece for
stocks that we're looking for. Because very often a lot of these companies and
their stocks don't actually make it to the day's headlines.
So this is what the query looks like, this is the end point,
and these are the parameters. Now, if we scroll down,
we can see a number of request parameters; q
which is the keyword or phrase the same in the article title and body, qIn
Title is to search for in the title only,
and then you can limit the sources or the domains
which you want to search or exclude certain websites
and you can also specify the date, time, language,
and a number of other things. Now, the only required parameter is
actually this API key. Now, in addition,
we're probably gonna want to use one of these requests parameters.
There's a lot of stocks that get lumped in into these analysis articles.
So I think it will be more specific if we can actually check the title of the
article for our company name.
So let's get started putting this API to use. Up here
we've really got the news end point,
and we're going to delete this print statement,
and we're going to use the requests library to get hold of some data from that
endpoint.
And then we're going to add our params. Our new params is firstly going to
contain our API key and notice how it's spelled. When you are using parameters,
you have to make sure that any capitalization or spelling must match their
requirements exactly.
So the API key is just going to be our news API key that we added previously,
and then we're going to provide a queryInTitle as well.
And I'm actually just going to straight up copy it because I'm not sure if that
was an I or an L. That way we don't make any typos. Now,
the query we're going to search for is actually our company name,
because while we can search for the name of the stock,
it's actually better to search for the company name because most articles tend
to include the company name rather than the stock name.
This is going to be the params that's going to go in here.
Now we're going to get hold of our response
and I'm going to print out the response as a JSON.
All right.
If you take a look at the documentation,
they also tell you what an example output would look like.
Firstly, we have a dictionary with status,
total results, but most importantly articles,
which is a list. In that list there's a bunch of dictionaries
which contains things like the source, the author, the title, description,
and each of these articles are an item in this list of articles.
We can actually get hold of all the articles
just by tapping into the news_response.json and then passing in the key
articles. And now when I print that out,
you can see its a list first of all,
and then each article is a dictionary inside that list.
Now we've managed to complete to-do number six and we can move on to
to-do number seven,
which is to use the Python slice operator to create a list that contains the
first three articles. And as a hint,
I've linked to the Stack Overflow page
where they go through the slice operator in quite a bit of detail
actually.
If we want to only get the first three articles,
then our start is probably going to be from the beginning and then we're going
to loop to stop minus one.
So that's going to be :3 because let's start counting from zero. Like
that. And now if I print these three articles,
right,
to see them,
if you click on this soft wrap and you can see the three items,
one, two, and three.
That's
step two.
Now we've managed to use the news API to get hold of the first three articles
that talk about this particular company name. In the next lesson
I'm going to go through the final part of the solution which is step three,
and to figure out how to send the relevant parts of the articles to our mobile
number.
So previously we managed to check the stock price difference between the day
before yesterday and yesterday.
And then based on when that different is over a certain threshold,
then we trigger this bunch of code
which actually fetches some news from the news API regarding that company.
So now that we've got the top three articles from the news API,
now we're onto step three
which is to use Twilio to send a message with each article's
title and description to a phone number.
The first step is to create a list of the first three article's
headline, and description using list comprehension.
So what we're aiming for is a single string that says something like this.
Headline:
and then it's the actual article title.
And then we've got our brief
which is going to go on a new line,
and then this is going to be the article description.
You can see those parts in the articles that we printed out.
For example, this first article here,
you can see the title says Spartan Energy surges after something,
something, something, something. You can see this is the first title
and this is the first description.
So its basically the title of the article and also a brief description of what
the article is about. That is what we want to get messaged to us.
Now in order to use list comprehension,
we first use the keyword method.
So new item for item in list.
Now our list in this case is of course our three articles and each of those
items will be an article in themselves.
And for each of those articles, we want to have this format.
So I'm just going to cut that and then paste it in here
and then I'm going to use an f-string in order to insert these relevant parts.
So the article title is stored under the title key and the description is stored
under the description key.
So we can simply use that as the key to tap into this article.
Notice how we've got a set of double quotes outside to create our string.
If we have another set of double quotes to specify the key,
this is going to be a bit confusing for the code interpreter.
So let's change that to single quotes instead to make it actually work. Like this.
Now, next is the article description.
So this is going to go inside another set of quotes and also it's going to go
inside a set of square brackets. Like this.
Each of the new items that's going to go into this new list is going to be a
string that's comprised of the article title and also the article description.
Now we can save this new list into a formatted_articles list, like this.
So that's to-do eight completed,
and now we're going to try and send each article as a separate message via
Twilio. Here's our Twilio SMS Python Quickstart,
and we're basically going to replicate all of this.
So first we're gonna import the client class from the Twilio library,
right?
And make sure that we actually have this installed
if it's not already installed, and get rid of the red underlines. Next,
we're going to get our account SID and auth token from Twilio.
So I'm going to copy my account SID and put that over here.
Right?
And also get my auth token from here as well.
So now I can set up my client by creating it from the client class. Down here, at
the point where I want to send my message,
I'm going to create a new client from the Twilio client class
and this is going to be comprised of my Twilio account SID and also my Twilio
auth token. Finally,
we can create our message and send it to our own number,
right?
The body of the message is going to be each of the articles.
So in order to send three messages,
we can loop through our three formatted articles, like this, and then we can
create a message and send each of those one by one.
So the body is going to be each article in the formatted articles.
Now the
from number is going to be our Twilio virtual number and our to number is going
to be our actual phone number. Once we've done all of that,
we can now test this and run it to see if it actually works.
Now I'm going to go ahead and hit run.
And hopefully our messages will get sent
as you can see right now.
So we've got our headline and our brief and each of the three articles are being
sent as a separate message.
That's pretty much the end of this challenge.
Now you can of course improve this even further.
And one of the things I thought about is having a little emoji to show whether
if your stock is up or down and also showing a rounded percentage. To do that,
we need to figure out whether if the stock was up or down and we can work that
out by looking at the difference. If instead of using the abs here
which is going to get rid of our negative and positive,
if we had instead used an if statement to check if the difference is greater than
zero, so it's positive, then we can create a variable called up_down
which starts out as none. But if it's positive,
then we can turn that into a up emoji.
And remember emojis are simply just treated as strings in our code.
Otherwise, if it's below zero, then it will change that to a down emoji,
Right?
Like this. And as always,
you can always search for these emojis in Google and copy and paste them in
if you don't have the emoji and symbols keyboard.
But having taken away that absolute value function here,
we're going to have to put it back somewhere else.
So we're going to put it right here at the point where we do the if checking.
And in addition,
I want to change this diff_percentage so that we actually around it to the
nearest whole number.
With the rounded diff_percentage and also this up_down,
we can now format our message so that it says the name of the stock
...
and then whether if it's up or down,
and then the diff_percentage, and finally a percentage sign and also a new
line. So now if I run this again,
you can see that this time
these messages come complete with the stock name,
the movement percentage, the headlines and the brief.
So there you have it.
I'm sure you can think of even more improvements to this program.
And especially if you're somebody who actually trades stocks,
then I'm sure you'll think of even more ways of improving this project.
If you come up with anything interesting and fun,
be sure to share it with the rest of us in the Q/A so that we can all admire
your hard work.
Hey guys,
welcome to day 37 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be learning about advanced authentication methods using the
header
and we're also going to be learning how to make POST, PUT and DELETE requests
using the requests module. And once we've learned all of that,
we're going to be building a habit tracker. This lady is Simone Giertz
and she's somebody who I really admire.
She makes all sorts of useless robots, um, that's what she says,
but they're actually really fascinating.
And one of the products that she brought out through Kickstarter was this habit
tracker,
where you could go to it every day and just tap on today's date.
So if you wanted to meditate every day, if you wanted to read 500 pages
of a book every day, then you could track your habit. And because it's continuous,
it makes you really want to continue your streak and not break the line.
So we're going to be using technology to build a digital version of that today.
And we're going to be using an API called Pixela.
This comes from a Japanese developer and it's really awesome.
It allows you to track your habits,
but not just show which days you've done your habit, which days you haven't,
but it also shows the intensity. So for example,
maybe you want to track how many pages you're reading every day,
you want to build a reading habit. Well, you can see that on certain days you
will really reading a lot and you're heading a streak, but then on other days,
even though you are doing some breeding because the color is lighter,
it means that you read fewer pages. And over a year's time,
you can see your entire progress and you can see your habit being tracked day by
day, which I think is really awesome.
This is what we're going to end up building. You can take any example,
any habit you want to build, so in my case,
I want to try and cycle every day and I'm logging how much I'm cycling in terms
of kilometers.
And you can see that certain days I cycled a lot and other days I cycled a
little bit less.
But I can see which days I've missed out on cycling and try to keep up with the
momentum and the streak.
Maybe you want to keep track of how long you're spending every day learning to
code, or maybe you want to track how long you're meditating every day,
or maybe you want to track how many lengths in the pool you swam.
Whatever habit it is you're trying to build
I'm sure that by the end of today's project,
you are going to have a tool that's going to help you achieve your goals.
So once you are ready, let's get started by heading over to the next lesson.
We've been using the requests module for a while now,
and we've been using it to make HTTP requests across the internet.
We've already seen the get request,
and this is a way for us to get pieces of data from somebody else,
like an API provider.
Now there's also four other common types of requests that we should probably know
about; post put and delete.
We can use the request module to complete a get request by simply writing
requests.get
and then we put our parameters inside the parentheses. For the other three
requests,
the code looks pretty much the same. It's .post, .put, and .delete.
Whereas a get request is made where we ask an external system for a
particular piece of data and they give that to us in the response.
a post request is where we give the external system some piece of data
and we're not so interested in the response we're getting back other than
whether if it was successful or not. For example,
if you wanted to save a piece of data in Google sheets,
then you might use the Google sheets API
to you post your data into your Google sheet.
Or maybe you want to use the Twitter API to post a tweet
then your program is going to send your tweet through a post request to the
Twitter API. So that's how get
and post works. Put is where you simply update a piece of data in the
external service. So if you had a spreadsheet in Google sheets
and maybe you want to update some of the values in the spreadsheet,
then you would use a put request.
And finally delete is simply where you want to delete a piece of data in the
external service
like a tweet that you posted or a Facebook post. Today
we're going to be building our habit tracker using the Pixela API.
And in order to use this API,
we're going to post our habit tracking data, for example,
how many pages have a book we've read, how many kilometers we've cycled,
and we're going to be posting that data to Pixela
to be tracked in our graph.
If you head over to their website and you scroll down,
you can see that it tells you how to get started.
And it's a series of six steps.
So we're going to be completing these in order
and we're going to be pairing this short form
get started guide with their documentation.
So we're going to have that side by side in order to see all of the
documentation on each of the steps. Step one
involves creating a user account. And it says you have to hit up this particular
end point using the HTTP post request.
So this is the first time we're making a post request.
Now I've set up a new project in  PyCharm habit tracker
and in my main.py, as always, that I'm going to start off by importing the
requests module. Now,
because this is a brand new project we're going to have to install that package
to make this red underline go away.
And once it's been installed successfully, we can tap into that method requests
.post. What are we going to
put into this parentheses, what are the parameters, what are the inputs?
Well, the first thing is the URL endpoint, right?
So this is the Pixela endpoint,
and that is going to be all of this.
Let's copy that over and paste it in as a string.
Now, if we head over to the API document,
you can see that there's an index of the API on the right,
and also at the beginning of the docs.
So what we want to do is first create a user,
That's step one.
Now, this API is actually really well-documented,
especially given the fact that it's actually not a big development team behind
this. If we take a look, this is the end point,
and this is what we've got in our code. Next,
we're going to make our post request
and we're going to add some parameters into the request body.
So you can see that some of these are required and others are optional.
So we're going to add a value for each of the required parameters;
token, username, agreedTermsOfService, and that we're not a minor.
Cool.
So let's create our user_params. And the first key is our token.
Now let's see what this token needs to be.
It has to be a string that's used to authenticate your user
and we're going to use it later on as well when we access our graph
and when we add to it. So make sure you save this securely.
This is basically like an API key that you're going to generate yourself.
This token can contain any characters,
so you can make up a key like this,
but the length of the token has to be between 8 characters and 128
characters. So I think I've definitely got more than eight characters there,
so I can move on to the next key, which is my username.
I'm going to try and see if I can get away with just my first name. If it fails,
we can always try it again. Next,
we've got agreeTermsOfService and this is going to be either yes or no.
We're probably going to have to say yes
if we actually want to use this service.
And also we're going to have to say yes that we're not a minor.
Let's make sure that we don't make any typos by simply pasting this in.
So it's a yes for agreed to terms of service and a yes
to the fact that I'm not a minor, sadly. Not a minor anymore.
Once we've got our user parameters and our Pixela endpoint,
then we're ready to make our post request. Again,
we're going to start off with the URL which is going to be our Pixela endpoint,
and then we're going to add a new keyword argument.
And this is called json.
Notice how all the data that we're posting over to Pixela is pretty much in
the format of a JSON. String and string.
This is basically a piece of JSON data that we're going to send over.
And that's all there is to it. The endpoint
and also the JSON data that we want to send over.
So let's go ahead and save this inside a response variable just as we did
before. And then once this is completed,
let's go ahead and print what the response is.
Now you can either tap into the response as a JSON,
but given that in this case we're not really looking to do anything with the
response. We just wanna check if it's actually successful or not.
We can actually tap into a property called text.
So it'll give you back the response as a piece of text.
Let's go ahead and run this and see if I can get away with setting my username
as angela. Wow.
So there's actually no user called angela at the moment
and I was able to nab that username.
So the reason why we're interested in looking at the response is
if there were some issues, for example, if I tried to run this again
now that I've taken this username, I think it's probably going to fail
and it tells us this user already exists. Now, alternatively, if we said
no to one of these, agreed to terms of service or not minor,
it's probably also going to give us a message telling us why this post request
failed. But now that I've completed this step,
I can actually comment it out because I've now created my user.
We've now set up ourselves with a new account on Pixela with a username and also
a secret token that we're gonna use in the future to access this account.
It's effectively our user name and password. So in the next lesson
we're going to create our graph and we're going to learn how to use a more
secure method of authentication.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Previously we completed step one
which is setting up a user account on Pixela.
Now we can move on to step two
which is to create a new graph on Pixela for our username.
So notice how the endpoint is now different because in addition to /
v1/users
we also have to add our username now and then for /graphs.
So let's go back to the documentation and scroll down to the relevant part of
the API, which is this part to create a graph, that's step two.
This is also going to be a HTTP post request,
but the end point has now changed.
So let's go ahead and create our new endpoint
which is the graph endpoint.
And this is going to be comprised of the Pixela endpoint
and then in addition, it's going to be / our username.
So let's take out our
username and our token and put it as a constant at the top.
Right
Now we can add that in here using an f-string
and then finally it's /graphs.
Now, remember if you're doing this along with me,
this username is going to have to be your own unique username and the token is
going to be your own secret token.
Once we've created our graph end point,
the next step is to make our post request. Again,
we're going to use our request module and call the post method to make this
request. This time what is the data that we want to send over?
Well,
we want to be able to add the ID of our new graph,
so some way of identifying it in the URL, and then the name of the graph,
and then the unit of measure that we're keeping track of. For example,
if I'm keeping track of my cycling,
then that's going to be kilometers that I've cycled,
or if I want to keep track of how long I'm coding
then that might be minutes or hours.
And then the data type of the unit of measure.
If I was tracking the number of pages I've read then they'll be whole numbers,
if I'm tracking the number of kilometers I've ridden
then it's probably going to be a floating point number. And then finally,
we're going to specify the color of our graph. Here
you have to be a little bit careful because these are strings
which are actually in Japanese. So for example,
momiji is autumn leaves.
shibafu is grass, sara is sky,
and they've got a whole bunch of poetic names for each of these colors,
which wonderful, but it also prone to errors.
So you have to be careful when you're typing in the color that you want.
And if in doubt, just simply copy it from the documentation.
So let's go ahead and create our graph configuration.
To start off, I have to specify an ID. And in this case,
it has to start off with some letters from A to Z,
and then it could be letters or numbers.
And it has to be between 1 and 16 characters.
Let's say that the id of my graph is going to be graph1,
notice how we can't have the number just at the beginning because of these rules.
Next is the name of the graph.
So mine is going to be my cycling graph,
and then it's the unit of measure.
So because I'm tracking my cycling, it's going to be in kilometers.
And then it's going to be the type of data that I'm going to be posting in this
unit. Because it's kilometers,
I'm probably going to have some numbers after the decimal point.
So I'm going to keep it as a float rather than an int.
And finally, we're going to pick a color.
I'm going to pick purple, ajisai, which is hydrangea flower.
And just to make sure I don't make a mistake,
I'm going to copy that and paste it in.
That's all of my required graph config. But right now,
if I do the same thing as I did before
which is to put in my graph endpoint as the URL
and then the JSON is set to equal the graph config,
if I actually post this right now, it's not going to work.
And if I print the response.text, you'll see the reason.
The message tells me that the user angela does not exist.
I know it exists because I created in this step and I got a successful response,
or it's telling me that the token is wrong. So think about it.
Where have we actually provided our password?
Where if we provided our token in this request? No where.
It's not one of the request body keys.
So how do we provide our authentication? Well,
it's done using the request header.
We have to provide this key
and it's gonna look for the token that we used to register with Pixela.
You might have even noticed previously when we were working with the news API
that when we were looking at the authentication,
even though there's three methods for authentication, via a API key, query string
parameter
which is what we used or via the X-Api-Key HTTP header or via the authorization
HTEP header.
And you can see that they actually say we strongly recommend either of the
latter two, so using the HTTP header.
And the reason is so that your API key isn't visible to others in logs
or if they're doing requests sniffing.
So what exactly are these headers anyways?
Well if you think about a letter that you might get in the mail,
the header is the part that contains some relevant pieces of information,
like, um,
the phone numbers of the company or their website of the company or their logo.
And then the body is the actual message part sesentially.
It's the part that changes from letter to letter. Now,
back in the previous project where we created our stock news alert application,
you can see that we're simply sending our API key as a parameter
along with the get request. And what this effectively looks like
if we're doing it in the browser is we're taking the news endpoint,
we're putting it into the URL bar and then we're adding our parameters.
So the first one is the API key.
And then the next one is the actual query.
So we were querying for the company name in the title of the news piece
and we were looking for Tesla.
This is effectively exactly the same as our code here.
We make a request to that URL and pass over these parameters.
There's effectively no difference between this and that.
As you can imagine, all our secret stuff in the request itself.
So if anybody's monitoring this,
then they will be able to see all of this information and they might be able to
steal your API key. Now,
one of the things that's reassuring is that this API is accessed via HTTPS and
the S stands for secure.
So this request is actually encrypted,
but it doesn't stop somebody from installing something on your browser to look
at what requests you're making
and there are certain cases where this might leak your API key to somebody that
you don't want to. So for some API providers,
you'll see that they want you to provide the authentication in the header.
Let's go ahead and do that. So let's take the key that they're expecting
and let's create a dictionary called headers,
and let's make that the key,
and then the value is going to be our token.
This is our top secret password. Now,
in addition to our URL on the JSON that we're sending over to Pixela,
we're also going to add a optional keyword argument which is called headers.
This is not going to show up when you start typing, not like JSON or URL.
And this is because it's one of the kwargs or keyword arguments.
And that means you also have to spell it exactly right
and make sure you don't make any typos. It's headers with an S at the end.
And then we're going to pass our variable headers into this parameter.
Now what we're going to make our request once more,
and you can see this time when we print the response.text,
it gives us success and we've now managed to set up our brand new cycling graph.
So if we go back to step three,
we can actually go ahead and look at our cycling graph by going to this URL and
replacing this part which is the creator's username with our own,
so mine was angela. Yours will be something else.
And we're also going to replace this final part with our ID,
which in my case is just graph1.
Now we're going to finally tag on .html to the end,
and when I hit enter,
you'll see it go to my brand new cycling graph right here.
And it's going to be colored in purple and it's going to look beautiful and it's
going to start tracking my cycling data.
So this is how we can authenticate ourselves using a header
and the requests module makes passing over headers just as easy as passing over
other parameters or other parts of the message body. In the next lesson,
we're going to be moving on to step 4 so that we can finally add a
the pixel of data to our graph.
So head over to the next lesson and give that a go.
So we're now finally ready to move on to the last step,
which is posting a value to our graph.
And this is going to create a new pixel on our habit graph.
So I want you to pull up the relevant piece of documentation
which is going to be posting a pixel.
And I want you to take a look at the description and the header and the body,
and see if you can complete the step as a challenge.
Notice that, firstly, the endpoint is again different and everything that's
inside
these angle brackets need to be replaced with your actual values.
So your actual username and your actual graph ID. In addition,
this is again going to be a post request and it requires the authentication in
the request header. Finally,
you have to provide the date in the format of four characters for the year,
two characters for the month and two characters for the day.
So today would be 2020
0724 in this format.
And then you have to provide the quantity that you want to add to today's pixel.
So if you cycled 10.5 kilometers, then it would be 10.5.
If you originally set up your graph to track integers, for example,
the number of pages you read in a book, then that would be the number.
So I want you to pause the video and see if you can complete this step as a
challenge. Have a go now.
All right. So the first thing we're going to do is to update our end point.
I'm gonna comment out this previous step because we've already created our graph
and we're now going to move on to our pixel creation.
So that's what I'm going to call my endpoint.
Now, this pixel creation endpoint is obviously not what we need.
We need to format this URL so that we add in the first part
which is the pixela endpoint which goes up to /users.
So that's all of this part.
So we can use an f-string and add the pixel endpoint.
And then we're going to replace the /username with our own
username, and then it's /graphs
and we have to replace this graph ID as well. And in my case,
the graph ID is simply just graph1.
So it might make sense to create a constant for that as well,
right?
So that we can use it at the very end of this endpoint.
So now that we've created our end point,
the next step is to create the request body.
So passing over the date and the quantity.
So I'm going to create the pixel_data,
and this is going to first have the date,
but it has to be formatted in the way they specified.
So four characters for the year, which is 2020,
and then two characters for the month,
07, and then two characters for the day.
But notice here that they specify the data type for the date has to be a string.
So we can't simply leave it as a number.
So we have to add some quotation marks around it.
And then finally we can add the actual data
which is going to go under the key quantity
and this is also going to be a string
and this is the quantity that we're going to register in the pixel
and that's going to determine the intensity of the actual pixel.
So in my case, I did actually go for a quick ride today. Um,
and my stats were not fantastic, but, um,
I'm still gonna log it.
So that was 9.74 kilometers that I cycled.
So that's what my quantity is going to be, 9.74. And again,
this is a string because that's what the documentation tells us.
And remember that when you set up your graph,
if you set up the data type to receive floats,
then you can actually give it a floating-point number. If you set it up as int,
then you have to give it a whole number.
Now that we've got our data and our endpoint,
then we're finally ready to create our requests. So you request.posts.
And again,
our URL is going to be this new pixel creation endpoint.
Our JSON that we're going to pass over is our pixel_data,
and finally,
we're going to reuse the headers that we had from previously,
because it still contains the same token that we need to authenticate ourselves.
So let's see what is the response that we get back.
So I'm going to print out the response.text and hopefully if everything went
well, then we should get the success message.
But now is the most exciting part.
You can go back to our cycling graph and then hit refresh,
and we should see all brand new pixel show up in our graph right there.
And it tells us today we cycled 9.74 kilometers.
One thing you might be wondering is, well,
how can we get this date to be automated?
Because I don't want to have to check the date and type it in.
We can use the date time module, right? So in the next lesson,
I'm going to show you how you can use a method called strftime in order to
format the date time that you get from Python into any format that you require.
For all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In the previous lesson, we saw how we could create a pixel.
But one of the things that would be nice is instead of having to type this
manually,
I would really like to be able to create that using the date-time module.
I can import my datetime, so from datetime module,
I'm going to import the datetime class.
And now I can use it to get today's date by tapping into datetime.now.
But if I print this out,
you can see that this is clearly not going to be in the format that I need it to
be.
So I'm gonna comment out my request and I'm going to take a look at what my data
looks like. This contains the date and time,
and it's in a different format.
So whenever we're encounter a new API or a new service,
they often want the date and time in a different format. For example, in Asia,
the year tends to come first, in the US or in the UK,
the year tend to come at the end.
How can we format the Python date to any format we need? Well,
there is a really useful method called the strftime method.
And this allows us to pass in a string that will a format
the date that we get back from datetime into any format we need.
For example,
if we pass in %a then we'll get the short version of the week-
day. If we pass in a %b,
then we'll get the full name of the month and so on and so forth.
So we can use this table to actually create the exact date format we need.
Let's go ahead and take this today and let's go ahead and use the strftime
and we're going to pass in a string. Now,
the first string we need is the year in the full version.
So this is going to be %Y and it's a capital Y.
Now, if you need a dash, then you can add a dash. If you need a space,
you can add a space. But in my case, I actually wanted it all together.
So the next thing I want is the month as a number.
So that's %m
and then it's %d to get the day of the month.
Now, if I actually print this out,
you can see that this is formatted in the exact format I need.
And if I wanna add in a, I dunno,
asterix there then it'll format it like that.
If I want to change the date to a word like Wednesday or December,
then I can simply change that format string.
Now that we've managed to do this, then we can get our date
time programmatically using the datetime.now method.
We can also use it to create any datetime of our choosing.
So lets say I wanted a backtrack to create a pixel for yesterday.
Well then I can simply create my datetime by specifying the year,
the month and the day.
So today's 24th.
So yesterday was 23rd and then it's going to take that date and it's going to
format it into the correct format and then post a quantity.
So let's say that yesterday I cycled,
I did cycle a bit more actually, let's say it was 15 kilometers.
Now if I go ahead and uncomment this and run it again,
it's gonna post the latest piece of data to pixela and
if we now update our graph,
you can see I've now got two pixels and this one is a lot heavier in terms of
color to show that I cycled a lot further than today.
And we've now got a total kilometer, a max, a min,
an average and the total number of pixels.
The last thing I want to show you before we finish off with this project is how
we can update and delete pixels using the put and delete requests.
That's what we're going to do in the next lesson.
Now in the very beginning of today's lessons,
I mentioned that we can do other requests in addition to get and post like put
and delete.
And we can do that using a similar format as we have done for get and post.
Just by simply changing the method we end up with a different behavior.
So put will change an existing piece of data and delete will delete the piece
of data. Let's try it out for size.
If we go into the documentation and we scroll down to all the things that we can
do to pixels, you can see
we can also update a pixel, which is put, and delete a pixel.
So let's click on update first and let's say that, um,
I decided that yesterday I didn't actually cycle 15 kilometers. I lied.
I only cycled 4. Well, how would we do that? Well,
we would use the documentation here and also the put method to achieve this.
So I want you to give it a go and see if you can figure it out. Now,
I've already told you that you need to use the put method and you know how to
format the endpoints and provide the request body and the header.
So pause the video and give this challenge a go.
Right?
All right.
So the first thing we're going to do is to copy this new format of the end
point and I'm going to comment out the previous part
where we posted our pixel and I'm going to create this new endpoint.
So this is the update_endpoint,
and it's going to be a combination of everything up to here,
which is our pixela
...
endpoint. And then it's your own username
and then it's graphs and then the graph ID.
And finally, it's the year,
month and date for the piece of data that you actually want to update.
So let's say that I'm going to update yesterday's piece of data
which I've manually created up here.
And I formatted using strftime right here.
So I'm going to replace this with a set of curly brackets and paste that in
there. Now notice,
because I've got these two sets of double quotes,
it's getting a little bit confused.
So I'm going to change one of those sets to a single quote instead.
And now I get rid of all my errors and warnings.
So this is our update endpoint.
And the only thing that we're going to change is the quantity.
Let's say I create a new pixel data dictionary.
And now my quantity instead of being 15 kilometers was, actually,  let's say 4.5.
So this is my new pixel data,
and now I'm ready to make my put request.
So we're using requests.put,
and then the URL is going to be the update endpoint,
the JSON is going to be our new pixel data,
and finally, the headers is going to be our headers for authentication.
Right.
So now let's go ahead and run this code.
And once we get our message success, we can go back to our chart,
refresh it,
and you'll see that yesterday's pixel no longer is as dense.
And in fact,
it's now lost a bit of color and it's been updated with the new value.
So finally,
we have our delete method and we're going to use that to delete a pixel.
Again, I want you to do this by yourself.
See if you can delete one of the pixels in your graph using the endpoint and the
documentation.
Go!
All right. So the endpoint is identical to the update endpoint.
So I'm simply just going to copy it and create a new one called delete.
And I'm also gonna comment out this request so that I use this one
instead. Now the delete endpoint doesn't actually take any data,
but it does need the header.
So we can use our request module and call the delete method and pass in the end
point which is the delete endpoint, the headers
which is our authentication headers,
and we can already enact our request.
Right
Now when we hit run, if it gives us a success message,
then we know that we've updated our data here
and we now no longer have two pixels.
We only have one cause we deleted the one for yesterday.
That's all there is to it. If now you want to be able to track your habit,
all you have to do is to comment out all of the rest of the responses and
reactivate the one where we post our pixel data and changing the quantity into a
custom input. So in my case,
it'll be how many kilometers did you cycle today?
And then of course changing our datetime back to now.
And now when I run my code,
it will go ahead and ask me how many kilometers I run.
I could type in the number, and then when I hit enter there,
data is going to be posted to the servers. Now, of course,
because I already have a piece of data, this is not going to let me,
so I'm going to have to wait for tomorrow to post my updated cycling data.
I hope you enjoyed building this project together.
And I hope you'll have a go at trying to modify this to your own habit tracking
and see if you can do some creative stuff with it. And as always,
if you create something fun, be sure to share it with the rest of us.
Hey guys, welcome to day 38 of 100 Days of Code. Now,
today I've got a challenge project for you.
And this challenge project is going to be building an exercise tracking
application using Python and Google sheets.
One of the things I've been trying to do recently is to track my workouts and
I've been doing that on pretty much pen and paper.
But wouldn't it be nice if we could track the workout that we're doing,
what time, how long we've been doing the exercises for,
and also figure out how many ice creams we can eat because of the workout that
we did. So tracking the amount of calories we've used up as well.
Now,
a lot of the inspiration for this project comes from the recent news on the Open
AI's GPT-3 AI model.
And it's a really smart, natural language processing model where for example,
if you went onto Wikipedia, you found an article on bread,
you decide to use this model to ask it, well, why is bread so fluffy?
It can actually search through all of the text and find you the relevant part.
So it's doing some intelligent stuff behind the scenes to understand what you're
saying and also understand what the article is all about.
And this is called natural language processing,
but it's just a very powerful one. Now, in our case,
we're also going to use natural language processing,
and we're going to write down the exercises that we did,
but in a normal English sentence.
You can imagine the situation where you're in the gym and you pull up your final
Repl.it. So this is the link to the completed app's console.
Right
Now I've pulled up this same page,
but on the Chrome browser on my mobile phone.
So this is what I might do after a gym workout or after a quick cycle.
And what we're going to try and do is to get the data to go into our spreadsheet
here on Google sheets.
So here I'm gonna type the I ran 5K and cycled for let's say,
20 minutes.
So this is my full input and it's pretty much just a plain English sentence.
Now I'm going to go ahead and hit return to trigger the code to run.
And immediately you can see that my activities have been logged.
So the date and time have been added automatically,
it's understood that one of my activities was running and it figured out the
duration based on the distance. So on average,
it might take somebody 31 minutes in order to run 5 kilometers.
And then it worked out the number of calories I've expended doing that activity.
And it did the same thing for my cycling,
except this time the duration comes from my input and the calories is calculated
automatically.
So this is really exciting and the best part you're going to be building it all
by yourself.
You're going to be using a bunch of things that you've learned so far,
including the Python datetime, strftime method,
using APIs, making post requests, creating authorization headers,
and environment variables.
You're going to be doing a bunch of this, step by step, by yourself.
And if you head over to the next lesson,
there's the instructions for how to get started.
So I hope you're excited to get started and I'll see you on the next lesson.
Hey there. Welcome to day 39 of 100 Days of Code.
Now,
today we've got a two part series and this is the part
one of your capstone project.
So we've been learning about APIs for quite a while now,
and we're going to be using a combination of different APIs to create a cheap
flight finder. Part one,
our program is going to find amazing flight deals just for ourselves.
And in part two,
we turn this project into a fully-fledged product where we can start signing up
users to use our service. So I don't know about you,
but I am a travel aficionado.
I absolutely love to travel.
I'm the sort of person who can't stay stationary in one location.
And one of the reasons why I teach Programming online is to be able to travel
and work from different places.
Now I'm not that picky about where I go. I think everywhere I go,
there's beautiful people who can teach me a lot of things.
So instead of planning a trip where I have one destination and I plan out the
time and date, I actually just look for a good deal.
So when I can get a flight
that's really cheap and it's to a location that I want to visit,
then I pretty much just go for it. So for example,
whereas a flight to New Zealand normally costs something like 800 pounds,
I managed to get a flight for just a 350 pounds,
and it was such a good deal.
It even included a stopover in Beijing where I was able to get some tasty duck
before I went onto the next 12-hour flight. Another case, um,
was Japan where the flight normally costs around 500,
550. And I managed to find a flight that was just a 250 pounds return.
And the savings on the flight meant that I got to eat some extra tasty sushi.
The way that these deals come about is imagine if you go onto a flight search
website and you look for flights,
anytime in the next six months,
every day for lots of different locations.
Then you will see that at some point,
one of the flight prices will come up and it's much lower than what you expect
it to be. And that's how you get a good deal. But of course,
we're too busy to do that every single day manually.
So here's how my program works. First,
we have a Google sheet which keeps track of the locations that we want to visit
and a price cutoff. So a historical low price.
For example,
maybe I want to go to Carola and visit kitchen and eat some tasty South Indian
food. Well,
maybe I would set the price at 350 pounds return from London.
So we take this data from our Google sheet with lots of different locations
and their lowest prices and we feed that into a flight search API,
which is going to run every day, searching through all of the locations
looking for the cheapest flight in the next six months.
When it comes up with a hit and it finds a flight that's actually cheaper than
our predefined price,
then it's going to send that date and price via our Twilio SMS module to our
mobile phone so that we can book it right there
and then. That's the theory of it, but let's see it in action.
So here I've got the code for my personal flight club and I'm going to run it
and we're going to watch my phone and wait to see if there were any good deals
that they found today.
And we get a text message from our Twilio account and there we have it. Today's
message says low price alert,
only 41 pounds to fly from London Stansted to Berlin from the 25th of August to
the 10th of September.
That was triggered because it looked at my spreadsheet of flight prices and it
found that out of all of these locations,
the only flight that it found which was cheaper than my lowest price was
for Berlin. It was actually only one pound cheaper.
So now that I've got my message, I can go ahead and book my trip to Berlin.
But before I do that, we're going to complete this capstone project.
So head over to the next lesson and let's get started building this project.
Hey guys,
welcome to day 40 of 100 Days of Code. Today is really exciting because
we're going to be upgrading the project that we created in the last day
to a fully-fledged product. We're going to be building a company today,
and this is part two of your capstone project.
Now the first rule of flight club is you do not talk about flight club.
So in part one, we created our flight deal hunter for ourselves,
and we only had a user base of one. Now in this part 2,
we're going to be leveling up the code so that we can start signing up users and
send them an email with a notification of all of the best flight deals.
A little while ago, I discovered a company called Jack's flight club,
and it's pretty simple.
All you have to do is put in your email and then they'll send you cheap flight
deals. So any flight within the next six months
that is a lot cheaper than it normally is, you'll get it through an email.
And if you're like me, somebody who doesn't really care where they're going
just as long as they're getting a good deal, then these emails are pretty cool,
right?
They actually charge for this premium service in order to get an email with all
of the latest deals and all of the best flight prices. Now,
if you think about it,
their service is essentially the same as what we've created using Python code.
Maybe they'll have a larger Google spreadsheet with more destinations,
but essentially it's pretty much the same.
I want you to take a look at their website, Jack's flight club, and see how it
works and you can see that they've actually got a whole bunch of members,
but this is essentially what we're going to replicate.
By the end of today,
we'll have a text-based way of getting our customers or users to join.
So maybe you've got some friends and family who might want to use your flight
club to get the best flight deals. Well
then all you have to do is point them to a link in Repl.it
which contains your customer acquisition code and then they get to, um,
enter in their name and email.
And after a little bit of validation,
we hit enter and we get added to a spreadsheet. In our spreadsheet,
in another sheet called users
we'll see all the details of our customer being added,
and we're going to be using the SMTP module that we learned about a long time
ago to email all of our users with the latest deals every day.
So head over to the next lesson and get started by downloading the starting
files.
Hey, guys, it's Angela from the App Brewery.
And in this lesson, we're going to deep dive into how exactly does the Internet work?
So what exactly is the Internet?
A lot of people think it's a cloud, something that's hanging around in the sky.
It's super complex, super difficult to understand, but actually that's not it at all.
The Internet is pretty simple.
All it is, is just a long piece of wire and wire connects different computers to each other.
So you might have one computer that's in London and another one that's in Seattle, and they can talk
to each other and transfer data through this giant wire.
Now, some of these computers attach to the Internet, have a very special job.
They have to be online 24 over seven ready to serve you all the data and files that you are requesting
when you try to access a website.
And these are called servers.
And what they do is they serve you all the data and files you need to be able to access and interact
with certain websites.
So these computers are called servers.
And any computer that a user would use to access the Internet is called a client.
Now you can imagine a web server as a giant library that's open 24 over seven, and you can go in there
at any hour of the day and say, I want to see Google's homepage or I want to see the latest posts on
TechCrunch and would be able to serve you with all the files and data you would need to be able to view
whatever website you want.
Now, as you can imagine, if there's a library that's big enough to house all of these websites, then
it's going to be pretty difficult to quickly locate the thing that you want out of this giant library.
Right?
So how is this problem solved on the Internet?
Well, let's say that you're sitting at home on your computer and you type in Google.com because you
want to head over to the main Google home page.
Well, what happens behind the scenes is that your browser will send that message to your ISP or your
Internet service provider.
So these are the people who you pay to be able to access the internet.
If you live in the US, that will be AT&T or Comcast.
And if you're in the UK, there will be something like BT or TalkTalk.
Now the message that you're sending the ISP is I want to see Google.com and the ISP will then relay
that message to something called a DNS server, which stands for a domain name system server.
And a DNS server is essentially just a souped up phone book.
And what happens when you make that request through your browser is the DNS server will look up in its
database to find the exact IP address of that website that you're trying to access.
And every single computer that's connected to the internet has an IP address.
It's kind of like a postal code for your computer so that when people need to send and receive files
on the Internet, each computer can be located and contacted using their unique IP address.
And once the DNS server finds that IP address, it will send it back to your browser through the ISP
over the Internet.
Then you can make a direct request to that address.
And what lives at that IP address is of course the Google servers and they'll be able to send you back
all the files and data you need to be able to view the Google Home page.
Now you can try this for yourself to look up the IP address of the Google Home page, head over to this
website nslookup.io and type in google.com and they should show you the exact IP address of the Google
servers that you can access.
Now, if you try checking this on a different day, say in a week or in a month's time, you might see
that this address actually changes.
And that's because many websites, including Google, use something called dynamic IP addresses, as
well as a content distribution network or a CDN.
This basically ensures that it gets you to the closest server to where you are located.
And also this address will change depending on whether if it's being used or not.
So don't type in what you see on screen.
Instead, head over to nslookup.io and look up what is the closest IP address to you that is currently
being used.
So if you copy it and paste it into a new tab, then you'll be able to replicate that process and see
the Google Home page show up.
So to summarize, the Internet is just a bunch of wires that connects up different computers, but it's
just on a much bigger scale connecting up all the computers in the world.
But what about the oceans?
I hear you ask.
Well, that's one of the coolest things.
There are these massive undersea cables connecting all the continents on earth.
And if you head over to submarine cable map.com, you can see all of these cables and see the ones that
connect.
You up to the Internet.
And these undersea cables are massive, consisting of hundreds of fiber optic fibers, each of them
using lasers to transmit up to 400GB of data per second.
This is a cross-section of one of the cables that run to New Zealand.
It's an absolute marvel of modern technology.
And it looks really beautiful, don't you think?
And to think that every single time we load up a web page or click on a button on a website, behind
the scenes was sending signals that navigate all of this crazy underwater and above water wires.
And all I need is just an IP address.
And through tiny electric signals, traveling at the speed of light through the oceans and halfway around
the world in a matter of milliseconds, I get to view my favorite websites and that is how awesome the
internet is.
And we're going to be taming it to build our own websites and web apps.
And to be able to do that, we first have to understand how exactly do websites work.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now that we've spoken about how the internet works, in this episode
I want to talk about how exactly do websites work. What exactly does HTML,
CSS and JavaScript do exactly? Now, in order to access a webpage,
we all know that you need a browser, right? And that can be Chrome,
Safari, Firefox, whatever is your favorite one.
These are all pieces of software that allow you to look up the IP address of
your website and be able to receive data that it can render into this beautiful
websites that we see. Now,
the data that you receive from the server usually consists of three types of
files; HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
And it's very likely that you would have come across these types of files or
these words before,
because they're so common and there are so integral to how websites work.
But, what exactly do they do
and why are there so many different types of files?
Why can't we just have one file that's, you know, a website? Well,
they actually have very different jobs.
The HTML code file is responsible for the structure of your website.
So if a website was a house,
then the HTML would be the builder who would come in to build the walls or put
in a toilet. Basically they establish the structure of your house.
And when you write HTML code, you also build up the structure of your website.
So you could use HTML to add an image or button or text box,
whatever it is that you need in your website. Now,
the second type of file are CSS files,
and these files are responsible for styling your website.
If you were building a house, then this would be the painters and decorators.
They would be going around
painting the walls or adding stylistic flourishes to your place,
and generally making the place look the way that you want it to.
And that's exactly what CSS code does as well. When you incorporate CSS,
it allows you to specify how you want your website to look.
So you could say that, yes, I have a button that I got from my HTML,
but that button I want it to be red and I want the text to be white
and I want the font of the text to be an Arial. That is all done using CSS code.
Now the final component is the JavaScript code.
And this is the code that allows your website to actually do things or have
behavior. And if you were building a house,
you would have the electrician come in,
who would be able to connect the wires so that your light bulbs actually switch
on or somebody who comes in and does the plumbing so that your toilet can
actually flush. And the JavaScript code does exactly that.
It allows your website to actually do things and have behavior.
So if we take the Google website as an example again,
once we receive these files from Google server,
when our browser loads up the HTML files, we'll get to see the structure
of the website, namely, there's one image which has their logo,
there's two buttons, and there's a text box where we can enter our search. Now,
when we receive the CSS files,
then that will modify the appearance of all of those components.
We don't have any more buttons or any more images,
but the now look the way that Google wanted it to. And finally,
when we incorporate the JavaScript files,
then our website actually starts having behavior. It has functionality
and it's actually able to do something rather than just display some images and
texts to us. Now, with the knowledge that we've already acquired,
we can already start messing around with websites on the internet.
So open up Chrome and head over to techcrunch.com.
And if you're not familiar with it,
it's basically a technology news website where I get my latest tech news.
Once you're over here,
I want you to right-click on the title here and click on inspect.
Now this brings up the Chrome developer tools,
and we're going to be exploring this in a lot more detail,
but for now we're going to use it to do something really simple.
You can see that when I right-click on that heading and click inspect,
it automatically opens up the entire code file that was used to render this
website. So these are all of the elements that make up this website.
And when you click on inspect,
it will highlight to you the part of the code that corresponds to the thing that
you right clicked, right? In this case, it's this title.
And inside this title, you can see that there is a link,
which means that when you click on it, it'll go to another web page,
but it also got a bit of text. So right inside Chrome developer tools,
if you double click on the bit of text that corresponds to the title,
you can actually edit it.
So let's go ahead and change the front page of TechCrunch.
Let's say something like,
uhm..
So this is a great way of pranking your friends,
especially when they can see that you're on tech crunch.com and the title or any
of the texts on the website is what you want it to say.
And this is a great joke to play on friends who are maybe not quite as
technologically advanced as you,
because they haven't taken the course that you have. Now unfortunately,
when I hit refresh on this website, all of my good work is gone.
And the reason is because when I'm editing it here inside my browser,
I'm actually changing the local copy of this file that I got back from the
server. But when I click refresh,
then that makes a new request to the servers to load up a fresh copy of the
website. So of course, then it updates to the original content.
But in the coming lessons, we're going to be working with HTML, CSS,
and JavaScript so that you can create and host live on the internet,
your very own websites and through learning how to code and how to build
websites
you are going to be able to make websites that say anything that you want it to,
look the way that you want it to, and have the functionality that you need.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.
Now let's get started by learning a little bit more about what exactly is it and how do we use it to
create websites.
Now, no matter what browser you like to use, Chrome or Safari or Brave, even all of these applications
do the same thing.
They take different files such as HTML, CSS and JavaScript, and they render them into a website.
But even though most modern websites are created using these three different file types combined together,
you can't create a website with just a CSS file or just a JavaScript file.
However, you can have just an HTML file.
And in fact, that's exactly what the first websites were created with HTML.
Now HTML defines the content and structure of the website.
So for example, in this case, all that my HTML file does is it it renders a heading that says my website.
And when this file is opened by the browser, it will display that heading saying my website.
Now what exactly is HTML?
Let's break it down.
So HTML stands for hypertext markup language.
If we look at the first part, hypertext, what does that mean?
Well, it refers to the pieces of text which can link to other documents in the website.
So these pieces of text are hypertext or hyperlinks, and they are the foundation of how an HTML website
works.
Now, if we take a look at the World First website created by Sir Tim Berners-Lee, who also happens
to be the inventor of the Internet, then you can see it's filled with these hyperlinks marked in blue
and exactly as you would expect.
If you click on any of these hyperlinks, it takes you to another document, another HTML file.
So if we go back, you can see that we were on projecting HTML.
And if I click on one of the hyperlinks like how can I help, it will take me to another HTML file and
this is how hypertext works.
And there's even a link on this website explaining exactly what hypertext is.
So now that we know what hypertext is, what about the other part, the markup language?
What is a markup language?
Now, if you look at the English language, we often see little bits that function very similar to markup,
like these double quotes.
The presence of these quotation marks is what tells a reader that this part is a quotation.
And as you'll find, this is going to be really similar to what you see in the editor's review of manuscript.
So used to mark them up and show different things, such as, for example, which parts need to be bold
by adding a squiggly line underneath it and which parts need to be underlined by adding a straight line
through it.
So how do you do markup with HTML?
Well, it's done through what's called HTML tags.
Now, in the early days of the Internet, there were only very few HTML tags.
These days there are loads more, but realistically, you're only going to be using some of the most
important ones such as headings H1 through to H6 or the paragraph tag the P tag.
So here you can see all of the HTML tags, but when we narrow it down to the ones that you actually
need to know, then it makes it a lot more approachable.
And in the rest of the course we're going to be covering some of the most essential tags.
And so don't worry about learning them.
So don't worry about memorizing all of them or learning them.
We're going to cover them as we need them in our projects and in our exercises.
So in the next lesson, we're going to get started by learning about the heading tag, one of the most
OG HTML tags that ever existed.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now, in the previous lesson, we took a look at what is and in this lesson I want to get us started
using HTML as quickly as possible so we can learn how to write our own code and start creating websites
with it.
Now, in this lesson, we're going to be learning about one of the most important elements, the heading
element.
And this is what a heading element looks like.
It starts off with what's called an opening tag here, and it ends with what's called a closing tag.
Now, if you look closely, the opening and the closing tag actually have one thing that's different,
and it's this forward slash right here.
And that is what makes this a closing tag.
And what goes in between these two tags is the content of that particular HTML element.
So in this case, what we're saying we want to do is we want to create a H1 heading and what the heading
is going to contain is these words Hello world.
Now, very often when you hear me talking about HTML, you'll hear me refer to tags and elements and
you'll see this on the Internet and everywhere else as well.
So what exactly is the difference?
Well, the tag refers to these bits.
These are tags.
Anything that's inside an angle bracket we call these angle brackets is a tag.
And they have different names.
So as I mentioned, this one is the opening tag.
And this one at the end is, of course, called the closing tag.
Now, these are the tags.
So what's an element?
Well, the entire thing here, this is an element that includes the content as well as any opening or
closing tags.
This is the HTML element.
And these parts are the tags.
So hopefully that'll make things a little bit clearer the next time you hear about tags and elements.
What is the purpose of these heading elements?
Well, the idea comes from book binding.
If you create a book and you create a table of contents like this one, you'll see that there's a sort
of hierarchy, right?
You've got the top level headings here.
This would probably be a level one heading and these would be a level two heading because they refer
to something that's more or less related to this approval section.
And you can see inside section eight here, there's even another subsection 8.1, which goes into more
detail about some aspect of eight.
This in our case might be an H three heading.
These levels are what we get to define using our HTML headings.
This is what the code would look like for all six level of headings and remember that there is no heading
seven.
There is no such thing as an H seven that does not exist once you've gone to heading six.
That's pretty much the end as defined by the people and anything that's lower in importance, you would
start using a different type of tag, which will go into a little bit later on.
But for everything from one through to six, the structure is pretty much the same.
You've got an open tag, which is H one or H six, and you've got a closing tag that has the corresponding
number.
Now if you create a tag like this with an H one and then you end with a different one like an H six,
then that's not going to work either.
Just remember that when you're writing your own code.
Now, what does this look like?
If we were to run this code, this is what we would get.
We would get different heading levels and by default, they would be styled to have different sizes.
So heading one being the biggest and heading six being the smallest.
We can of course further style this later on, but as soon as we type these headings, it just gives
us an indication of our levels to make sure that we've written all our code as intended.
And this essentially follows that structure we saw earlier on with the table of contents.
The level one headings are the biggest and the level six headings are the smallest.
So now that we've seen a little bit about how all of this works, let's try an exercise where we create
our own heading elements.
To download the starting files, you have to go over to the course resources for this lesson and click
on the 2.1 heading element file in order to download it.
Now, if you don't know where that is, then you might have missed where at the very beginning of the
course there's a lesson called how to download the course resources and in there I show you exactly
how to download each of the course resources for every single lesson.
So if you miss that, be sure to head over there to take a look and see how you can do this.
Now, once you've downloaded this file, it's really important that you extract it or what we call unzipping.
Now, the first thing I want you to do is to create a folder for all of your web development projects,
and you can create that folder anywhere you like on your desktop in your C drive, in your username
section, wherever you want, but just call it web development projects like this.
Now, once you've created that folder, then I want you to go ahead and open up the zip file that you
just downloaded by double clicking on it.
And once you've opened up that zip file, I want you to drag it into your Web development projects folder
like this.
And then you'll be able to access them right here.
Now, the next step is we're going to open it up in VS code.
Inside vs code, go to file and we're going to create a new window.
Now open up the explorer here.
And then when we're here, we're going to open up our web development projects folder that we just created,
and you should be able to see that folder heading element.
Now, if for some reason this is not working for you, especially if you're on Windows, this might
be because you haven't actually extracted this folder properly.
So again, make sure that you double click on the zip file or on Windows.
You can also right click on it and click extract.
And then once you've done that, drag, that folder that's been extracted into your web development
projects folder and open up that folder inside your VS code.
When you're here, you can see that there are three files in this folder called 2.1 heading Element
one is the index.html.
This is where you're going to be writing your code and I've got some starting code for you which we're
going to need to modify in order to complete this challenge.
Now you've also got the solution, which I don't recommend looking at until you've completed the challenge,
just to check your code or see if there's any differences.
Now notice how I've added a little bit here so that you don't accidentally see it unless you wanted
to.
But if you want to see the solution, just scroll down and you'll see it down there.
The goal of this exercise is to make the code here, create a website that looks like this.
Remember previously when we did our setup and download for VS Code, I showed you how to install the
extension live preview.
If you don't see live preview when you click on extensions, that might mean that you've missed out
on some parts of that video.
So please go back to the setup and download videos for VS Code because there's some other things that
I need you to set up as well.
Make sure you don't skip any of these lessons unless you know exactly what you're doing and you're really
familiar with everything.
What that live preview allows us to do is to go into our code file index.html, right click on it and
click show preview.
So it should now open up another pane and you can see it shows us our book chapters, Section one,
Chapter one, chapter two, chapter three sections and Diagrams and Subsections.
Unfortunately, everything seems to be just on one long line, and if you drag it out, you can see
it's just one long line.
There's no formatting at all and there's no indication about hierarchy.
So that's where the challenge comes in.
You're going to use what you learned about heading elements in order to format this code here in the
index.html so that we end up with something that looks like this.
So we want the preview to show us heading one elements heading two elements heading three elements.
And this one this diagram one is actually a heading four element.
So you should have H one through to H four in your code here.
So now is the time to pause me in the video and try to complete this challenge.
And after you're done then you can resume the video and we'll walk through the solution together, pause
the video now and give it a go.
All right.
So we're going to have a single h one element up here, which is going to be for this word book.
So we're going to put an H one element right here, and we're going to drag our book, which is the
content.
Remember, in between these two tags, that's how our heading tags are formatted.
Now, the next one are these Chapter one, chapter two, chapter three sections, and they're all going
to be the next level of hierarchy, which is an H two.
So let's do that for all three of them.
And then we can move on to our H three, which is going to be the sections within the chapters.
And now I'm just going to fast forward through the rest of the code so that you don't get bored.
And then finally, this diagram, which belongs inside section one in chapter two, is going to be the
final and the lowest level of hierarchy, which is an H four.
And once we've completed all of this code, you can check yourself against the solution code and you
should see it's pretty much the same.
Now, one of the things that you'll find is when you hit save using command S or using file save, you'll
see that IT auto formats our code so that we lose any of the indentation.
Don't worry if this happens to you, it's perfectly normal.
And if we check ourselves against the solution, you can see they match.
Exactly.
And we end up with the same result as the goal image, which is what we were aiming for.
How did you manage that?
Don't worry.
If you got things wrong, this is where it's safe to go wrong and try things because we're just learning
there's no tests and there's nobody watching you.
All that matters is you're actually learning stuff.
That's what's important.
Have a play around with the code.
Don't worry, if you do anything wrong, there's always a solution.
And me here to help you.
There's a couple of things to note in terms of do's and don'ts when it comes to heading elements that
I want to talk to you about.
One important rule is notice how in our exercise there was only one H1.
It's not good practice to have more than one H1 because the H1 is the very top level heading.
Imagine the H1 as the book title and the table of contents as including the other parts.
So maybe the H2 would be the first chapter.
Don't have more than one H1.
Instead, if you need another subtitle or another level of heading, then go to the H2 or H3 or all
of the other ones up until H6.
Now the other thing to watch out for is don't skip a level.
When you're creating heading elements, don't go straight from H1 to H3.
If you have an H3, there should also be an H2 somewhere on that web page.
Instead, I recommend to just go in order when you have an H1 that you've created and then you realize
you need another heading, then go to an H2.
And then if you need another level of heading that's even lower in priority, go to an H3.
Don't jump between the different level headings.
These are not things that will break your code.
Your website will still look fine even if you break all of these rules.
But they're just rules for convention.
And because we're going to be professionals, we're going to start off on the right foot and learn all
the rules that we need to know.
Now, if you wanted to read up even more on the heading elements, then I recommend going to the professional
tool, which is our Mozilla developer network web docs, and they have documentation for all of the
HTML elements that exist.
And when you read up on each of these pages, they tell you more details about things that you need
to know, and they show you some interactive examples of how it all works.
Now, I don't recommend reading through all of these for all of the HTML elements, but I do recommend
that if you're going to use a new element that you haven't seen before and you don't know how it works,
you haven't had a lecture on it, then I recommend just taking a quick look at the docs and seeing some
examples about how they're used in a similar way that I've shown you in the lectures.
Now that we've learned about one of the most important HTML elements, the heading elements, in the
next lesson, we're going to move on to another super important element which is the paragraph element.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
So now that you've seen what you can do with the HTML heading element, the next one we're going to
learn about is the paragraph element.
And this is also related to formatting and putting text on our websites.
This is what a paragraph element looks like and similar to the heading element, you've got the opening
tag and the closing tag, and in between you've got the content that is going to be your paragraph.
Now the reason why we need a paragraph tag is because if you just had plain text in your HTML document,
when you run the code and you see it on a website, what you'll see is something like this.
The text, they run into each other onto the same line and you can't actually tell where one paragraph
begins and where the other ends.
On the other hand, if we had created two paragraph elements for these two lines, then when we run
the code you will see them being separated with a line in between to be able to distinguish the different
paragraphs.
And this is also really important for people who are using screen readers, so people who might be blind,
because what the screen reader will do is they'll see the beginning of each paragraph element and it
allows the blind user to be able to skip to the next paragraph easily and be able to see what's going
on each time.
Now let's put those skills into practice by trying an exercise using the paragraph element.
If you head over to the course resources for this lesson, you should be able to download the zip file
for the 2.2 paragraph element.
And once you've extracted and unzipped it, then go ahead and put it into your web development projects
folder and then open it up inside vs code.
I showed you how to do all of this in the previous lesson in HTML heading element as well as the initial
lesson when I showed you how to download course resources, so be sure to check those places if you
don't know how to get hold of this folder.
But once you have it opened up like this, then I want you to go ahead and open up the index.html file,
which as always, is where we're going to write our code.
Notice here we've got three paragraphs, the first paragraph, the second paragraph and the third paragraph.
And then there's some placeholder text in Latin, which doesn't mean anything.
It just is there so that you can see what a paragraph of text would look like.
And when you go ahead and right click and show preview, you should see that all of the paragraphs are
jumbled together into one long line and we can't tell where one paragraph begins and the other one ends.
So now it is your mission to solve this problem using what you've learned about the paragraph element.
So go ahead and format these three paragraphs using the paragraph tag and once you're done, you should
see the preview.
Show something like this where each paragraph is separated into new lines and clearly visually, we're
able to see the difference and we're able to distinguish these three different paragraphs.
Pause the video now, and once you're done, we'll go through the solution together.
All right.
We're going to use our paragraph tag.
So we're going to put the open tag here just in front of our first paragraph, and then we're going
to put the closing tag at the very end of our first paragraph, and then we're going to repeat that
basically for all of the other paragraphs.
Now you can see here I'm just clicking and dragging.
Alternatively, you can cut it and then paste it at the very end of the paragraph.
It really doesn't matter how you do it, as long as you get those tags in the right places.
And now hopefully your preview should have updated and you can see these paragraphs forming as we type.
So this looks pretty much the same as our goal.
And if you check the solution HTML, you should see the tags in the correct places as well.
So hopefully that wasn't too hard and you were able to do it all by yourself and you've seen now what
is the benefit of using a paragraph element to separate text into different paragraphs of content?
Now, what you saw in the exercise are bits of placeholder text, and it's what we would refer to as
Lorem ipsum.
It's something that you'll come across quite a lot, especially in web design.
It's so that we don't end up with something like this where we're trying to simulate content in a paragraph,
but then we're just writing content, content, content, or this is a paragraph, this is a paragraph,
this is a paragraph.
And the reason why we don't want to do this is because these are all the same words.
The sentence has the same length.
It doesn't look like what a natural block of text would look like, and we don't have the time or energy
to actually create the content just for testing and web design.
So that's why we use something called Lorem Ipsum.
And Lorem ipsum apparently comes from Latin classical literature by a famous author called Cicero.
If you've heard of him and it's over 2000 years old and this has been in use in the print industry for
many, many years, ever since the 1500s, even, where people started laying out newspapers and when
they didn't have the content for the layout, they would use this placeholder text.
If you want to get hold of them, you can go over to Simcom and there you'll find Lorem ipsum even in
different languages like Dutch or Polish, and you can use this tool to generate as many paragraphs
or words or bytes or lists as you need by simply using this generate button.
And here I've got five paragraphs ready to go to put into my new web design.
Now, instead of having something that looks like this where everything's all the same length, instead
we have very natural looking paragraphs that mimic pretty much what a regular English article would
look like.
And this is done in a matter of seconds using Lorem ipsum.
Now if Lorem ipsum is a little bit too boring for you, there's actually some novelty versions of this.
One of my favorite is bacon ipsum.com and it will generate similar to Lorem ipsum, but then you'll
get words like bacon and flank and pork loin and pork belly.
Now if you're not a meat eater, then maybe you should try something like bro ipsum.com where you can
have all of the bro terminology in a Lorem ipsum format.
And apparently the things that bros say are things like Taco pow and washboard and rail and heli paopao,
whatever it may be.
And if none of these take your fancy, then I recommend going on to Google and you can actually find
more of these kind of things by just searching for funny Lorem ipsum.
And there's a whole bunch of different ones like vegan ipsum or pirate ipsum and you'll come across
all sorts of different placeholder text generators.
But the important thing is you know how to get hold of them and you can use it in your code.
So as an add on challenge, if you want to, you can generate your own version of Lorem ipsum or Bacon
ipsum or bro ipsum and you can create an article using the paragraph tag and the Lorem ipsum that you've
generated.
Feel free to modify the index.html in the coding exercise that we just completed.
So have a play around with that and be sure to comment in the Q&A sections below.
If you find some Lorem ipsum that you think is ridiculous or really funny or really cool and I'll see
you on the next lesson.
All right.
So in this lesson, we're going to learn all about the void elements such as the horizontal rule and
the break element.
What exactly are void elements?
Well, we've seen what non void elements are, such as the paragraph element or the heading elements,
and they're not void because they have content right here in between.
A void element is an element where you are forbidden from putting any content inside the tag.
And in fact the tag itself even looks very different.
So this is a horizontal rule element and you can see that it starts out with an angle, bracket ends
with an angle bracket.
But then right here, there is this forward slash just before the end of the tag.
You might think this looks a bit like the closing tag of a normal HTML element, but it's actually subtly
different because here in the closing tag, that forward slash is just after the opening angle bracket.
It's right here in front of the letter.
Whereas in the void elements, the forward slash is actually just before the end of the tag.
And normally by convention, you'll see a little space here as well between the tag name and also that
forward slash.
This is just something to be really careful about.
When you're creating these void elements.
Make sure that you've got the forward slash slashing in the right direction so this way and not a backslash
like this.
So when it points to the right, then it's a forward slash and when it points backwards, then it's
a backslash.
So what does this look like when we add it to a HTML document?
Well, here we've got our previous two paragraphs and right in between the two paragraphs I've added
a horizontal rule which will hopefully help us divide the content to show that this part is not related
to this part.
And we've got some sort of separation in between when we run this code or when we view it in a web browser,
this is what you would see.
You would see the first paragraph, the second paragraph, and then you would see this horizontal rule
or basically a horizontal line where the air element would be in that document.
Now the horizontal rule is not the only void element.
Another common one you'll see is the break element.
And it looks like this.
Now, similarly, again, we've got the name of the tag and then we've got that forward slash and then
we basically end the tag.
So there is no opening tag.
There is no closing tag.
There is only a single tag that looks like this.
And the name of the tag goes right before the forward slash.
Now, how does the break element work?
Well, it's really useful when you have things where you need to separate things onto separate lines
in order to have the correct meaning.
For example, if you have poems, they are in fact meant to be in the same paragraph, but they should
really each be on different lines in order to make the rhyming work or in order to make the structure
of the poem correct.
So this is a poem from one of my favorite poets, William Blake.
And in order for it to work, we can't have it all run in one line, even if it's in the same paragraph.
If we had this code right here, even though yes, it is all in the same paragraph, it is all related
to each other and this does make sense.
But you don't look at poetry like this.
It doesn't really work.
We don't know where we're supposed to breathe and how we're supposed to read out the poem.
So instead we can add our break elements that we just learned about.
Our void element doesn't have any content in it, but it just shows where the breaks in this paragraph
has to go in order for this poem to look right.
And when this HTML document is rendered, this is what you'll see.
A perfect layout for a poem.
The World in a grain of sand and heaven in a war flower.
Hold infinity in the palm of your hand and eternity in an hour.
And it's all beautifully formatted thanks to each of our break elements at the end of each line.
So now it's your turn to try an exercise using these void elements.
So go ahead and download the starting files for this exercise from the course resources for this lesson.
And when you've extracted it and open it up, this is what you should see in the index.
We've got the name of our poet William Blake, and this is apparently his real address that he lived
at at some point in life.
And then we've got two paragraphs from Wikipedia which briefly describes the poet.
And I want you to use everything you've learned so far in order to format this document so that it will
look like the goal that I've got right here for you.
As you can see, this top level, the name of our poet is going to be rendered as an H one, because
that is the most important thing about this particular web page.
And then we've got the address of the poet, which is rendered as a paragraph.
But notice that addresses, even though they are a single paragraph, they again need to be broken up
into separate lines using our break element.
And then finally, we've got a horizontal rule that separates the address and the name of the author
from the little bit of description of this author, which should sit in two separate paragraphs.
Now I want you to pause the video and edit the index.html so you end up with this goal PNG.
When you preview this website instead of this jumbled block of text that we have at the moment.
Pause the video now and give this challenge a go.
All right.
So hopefully you've given it a go and everything worked out.
I'm going to run through the solution.
So first we said we were going to have an H one for his name, and then we're going to have a paragraph
tag that encloses the address.
Now, in order to have that address on different lines, we're going to add our break element to the
end of each line.
And remember, our break element is a self-closing tag.
So we're going to create it like like so.
Now I'm going to go ahead and simply copy and paste it to the end of each line and you can see how nicely
our address is now formatted.
And finally, we wanted these two paragraphs at the end to be separated.
So I'm going to go ahead and simply do that.
And now we are pretty much golden.
We've achieved our goal output.
We've got our H1, our address separated, and the only thing we need to do is to add that horizontal
rule between the address and the two paragraphs.
Let's go ahead and add the other void element that we learned about.
And now we've completed the challenge and you can check yourself against the solution to make sure that
everything that you did looks exactly the same.
Now, a neat trick I like to use is to simply copy the solution and go to diff checker.com paste in
the solution code.
And then paste your code and then go ahead and click find difference.
And it should highlight all the places that are different in case you've misspelled something or you've
done something wrong.
So for example, in this case, in our version, there is a space after the word Blake and the closing
tag, which in terms of HTML will not make any difference.
But had I instead maybe written the H1 incorrectly and I didn't write the H for the closing tag, then
you can see our output looks completely different and we're looking through all of this text.
We don't know why it's happened, so we go ahead and copy it and then diff it to the solution.
And it should highlight the fact that that is incorrect and we should now be alerted to check the difference.
That's one tip that I have for you today.
And let me just go back to our index.html fix this bug and we should now be ready to go.
Now in terms of do's and don'ts with void elements, sometimes you see people doing is they add a break
tag to add a new line instead of creating a separate paragraph element.
Now, this is not what you want to do because this is not very good for accessibility, which means
it'll make it harder for blind users with screen readers to understand the content on your website.
So I recommend you always create new paragraph elements when you have new paragraphs and use the break
element only when there is some sort of reason why you would want to separate the different lines in
a single paragraph.
But it still is a single paragraph such as in the case of a poem or in the case of an address that we
covered in this lesson.
Now, the final thing to mention is that sometimes when you look at the horizontal rule element or the
break element, you might see it represented.
Without this final closing tag, you might see people simply write this and this is perfectly valid
HTML.
So you could in fact have a horizontal rule that looks like this.
You could have a break element that looks like this instead of the one with the forward slash at the
end.
And these are both valid options.
You could go for this or you could go for this as of HTML5, the latest version of HTML.
What it's starting to do is it's starting to ignore this forward slash at the end so it doesn't even
look at it.
It sees the first part and already knows that a break is a void element and a horizontal rule is a void
element.
So it doesn't actually need to keep reading.
But I recommend to write your code with this end forward slash.
And the reason is because when you read your code, you as the human, it will be much easier for you
to see that this is a void element and it doesn't need a closing tag so that you don't end up being
confused and you can identify the void elements and the non void elements easily and distinguish them
from each other.
So that's just a quick tip and something to alert you to when you see it written like this on the internet.
Both versions are valid.
You can pick and choose, but I recommend going with this version.
So now that we've gotten a introduction to HTML, I want you to put everything you've learned together
in order to create a new project.
So the project that we're going to be building today is called The Favorite Movie Project.
It's going to be a website to keep track of all of your favorite movies that you've watched When you
go to Roger Ebert.com, he is one of the greatest film critics of all time.
In fact, he's passed away now, but he's got movie reviews and ratings for all the movies that he's
watched.
And you can see that when you go to his website.
I think this is a really great way of keeping track of what you've watched.
Because when friends ask me for recommendations, I can never remember what it is that I've watched
in this year that I really like and what to recommend.
So what we're going to be building today is a very simple website.
It's going to be a website that tracks your favorite movies maybe of all time, maybe of the last year,
whatever you want to do.
And the requirement is you should have at least three movies that you put in here.
So what you're going to need is to create a H1 as the title of the website, and then you're going to
have an H2 as the subtitle, and then you're going to have a horizontal rule as your void element in
there.
And then you're going to have three movies that you're going to list and they're all going to be created
using the H3 element.
And then finally you should have a section which is going to be a paragraph element that's going to
describe why you liked those movies.
And this is basically a very simple format for this website.
Now feel free once you've done all of this to continue to mod this website, to change it up, to add
things, to add break elements, whatever it is you want to do.
But at the minimum, I want to see all of these elements represented on a page.
And of course, feel free to add your own movies.
And I would love to see in the Q and A a picture of your website to see what it is that are your top
movies.
And maybe I'll get some inspiration.
So the next time when I have movie night and I can't figure out what to watch.
So I'm curious to see your recommendations as well.
So go ahead and download the movie ranking project ZIP file from this lesson's course resources.
If you don't know how to do that again, go back to one of the first videos in the course at the very
beginning of Section one where I showed you in a video how to download course resources.
And once you've unzipped it and extracted it, then open it up in vs code and go ahead and code to your
heart's content using everything you've learned.
Pause the video now and give that a go.
Now let's go through the solution.
In my case, I'm going to have an H one at the top, which is going to be the title.
So, um, top movies of all time, according to Angela.
And then afterwards, I'm going to create a subtitle which I will write my best three movies.
And then after that we were going to add a horizontal rule to separate this part from the actual content
of our website.
And I'm going to create an H three to represent each of the movies I'm going to recommend.
So I'm going to recommend A Spirited Away, which is one of my favorite animes.
And I'm going to use a paragraph tag to describe a little bit about why I like it.
So I'm just going to call it favorite anime.
And then the next movie we will be Ex Machina.
And I really liked it because it's a really cool sci fi movie.
And then finally, the third one is going to be the movie Drive with Ryan Gosling because it was really
beautifully shot.
Cool.
This is the basics of what you would need to have done for this project.
It has all of the elements that were required and you can see in the goal PNG that it's got all the
things that we've described, even if the text is a little bit different.
Of course it won't be, according to Angela for you, it will be according to your name.
And now that you've done that, feel free to add different things in here as you would want.
Maybe add a bit more to the paragraph tags, maybe add a poem about your favorite movie, go crazy,
try out things and share in the Q&A your project as a screenshot.
If you don't know how to do a screenshot, be sure to be sure to type that into Google.
How do I create a screenshot?
And then you can add it into the Q&A and we can all look at your favorite movies and be inspired.
So I hope you enjoyed building the project together.
And in the next section we're going to dive a little bit deeper into some more intermediate aspects
of HTML.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Now that we've seen how HTML elements and tags work, it's time to explore the bigger picture, what's
called the HTML boilerplate.
And this will allow us to understand the structure of our HTML files, just like how there is structure
to letters that you would write.
For example, there's the section where you have your address and then you probably would include a
dear so and so, and then you have the body of your letter and finally you would write something like
your sincerely and then your name and signature.
Similarly, there is a structure to our HTML files and it looks something like this.
And this is called a boilerplate.
It's what you usually start off with when you create any new HTML file.
And we're going to go through it line by line so that we understand it.
At the top of every HTML file, there should be a doctype declaration.
And that's what this tag does.
It tells the browser which version of the file was written in.
Now the latest version of HTML is HTML5 and the Doctype declaration looks like this with an angle bracket,
an exclamation mark, doctype in all caps and then HTML.
And this line tells any browser that's reading our HTML file that we have written our code in HTML version
five.
The next part that we've got is the actual HTML.
Now, this is going to be the root of the document.
It means that everything else, every other element, no matter if it's an H1 or an image or a link,
it's all going to go inside the opening and closing tags of the HTML element and this attribute where
it says Lang This is the language of the text content in that element.
So for example, if you're writing a website that is going to be targeted at English speakers, then
you're going to set your lang to English.
N.
Now this isn't very important for the users who can see your website.
It's more important for the users who can't because there are various screen readers and assistive technologies
that will look at this language attribute so that when they read out the website, they can pronounce
the words correctly.
Opens profile photo follow at you.
Angela Button.
Now, with the HTML element, we're starting to see the beginnings of a hamburger.
There's a bun at the top and there's a bun at the bottom.
For those of you guys who have been my long term friends, you know how much I love food analogies,
but this is a great one because when we have an HTML element, usually there is the opening and the
closing and everything that belongs in it is sandwiched inside.
Now the next part of the HTML boilerplate is the head element.
And this is an area where important information about our website is placed that is not going to be
displayed to the user.
It includes things that will help the website render in the browser correctly, but it doesn't include
any sort of content like text or images or anything that the user will see.
So one of the things that you should always have in the head section is a meta tag for the character
set encoding of the web page, and in this case it's set as UTF eight.
What this does is it ensures that the characters that you're using on your website gets displayed correctly.
So, for example, in certain character sets, it won't allow emojis to render in other character sets.
They won't have certain symbols like multiplication and division symbols.
And that's what this meta tag takes care of.
Usually by convention in our HTML boilerplate, we will simply just include this tag as is using the
UTF eight character set, which is one of the most common.
So you don't even have to think about it.
Now another thing that you should have in your head section is the title of your website, and that
title is usually what gets displayed up here in the Tab Bar.
And in fact, if you right click on any website in Chrome, you can click to view page source and you
can see we've got our Doctype, we've got our HTML element inside it, we've got our head, our character
set.
And then if we scroll a little bit more, you can see we've got our title here.
And in between the opening and closing tags of the title, it tells you what title should be displayed
up here.
So in our case here, the title was simply say my website.
Now there's a lot more things that can go into the head element, as you've seen when we looked at.
The Google Home page.
But for now, these two are the most important things that will always go into your files.
And it's important to know.
We'll cover other tags as we come across them.
Now, the next sandwich inside the sandwich, if you will, are two slices of tomatoes.
No, just kidding.
It's actually the body element.
Just like a person.
After the head element comes the body element.
Inside the body element is where we're going to be spending the majority of our time creating and writing
our website.
This is where all of the content of the website goes.
So the text, the titles, the images, the links, everything that you can do with HTML.
Creating content and structure goes in between the opening and the closing tags of the body element.
So somewhere inside here.
Now what can go in here?
Well, we've seen already how an H1 works so we can put in a heading, we can add images, we can add
lots of things.
And this is essentially where the meat of our website is going to live.
Once our burger collapses down, you can see that this is what a typical website's HTML code is made
up of.
So no matter what you add into your body, you can vary it up.
But by default, most websites will start off with a boilerplate that looks like this.
When you're starting out, I often recommend students to type this out when they're creating new websites
and in fact you can have a go doing this now by going into VS code, typing out these elements and creating
your website entirely from scratch.
Now we're beginning to see this idea of nesting in an HTML document, and this is going to be a concept
that's going to become super important as we learn more and more programming.
But it's simple to understand if we come back to this analogy of the hamburger.
So we have our HTML element which has the opening and closing tags here, and it is exactly like our
hamburger bun.
So this is our top bun and this is our bottom bun and sandwich.
In between is everything that goes inside the HTML element.
Now, if we take a look at our body element, then you can see here we've got the opening body tag,
which will represent with a slice of tomato and the closing body tag.
And in between those two slices of tomato is the content for our website.
Now you'll notice that some of the HTML tags, even though they have an opening and closing tag, they're
not on different lines.
And that's because if we can fit it on one line and we can see the beginning and the end very easily,
then we don't actually need to create several lines.
But nonetheless, it still got a beginning and an end.
Now the important thing for us when we're writing code and we've got all of this sandwiching going on
that we indent our code properly so that you can see that this clearly lines up with the opening tag
here.
So they are clearly sandwiching something in between.
And then we have two spaces and we've got the next indentation level here.
So this one lines up with the closing tag and through this kind of indentation you can quite easily
visualize that this head section is clearly embedded inside the HTML section.
So just like our lettuce is inside our hamburger, by indenting our code properly, we'll be able to
keep our code tidy and we'll be able to see at a glance exactly what our code looks like.
Now, finally, because we're using vs code, I want to tell you about a shortcut.
That means you don't have to type out this boilerplate every single time.
Once you've typed it out once or twice and you know exactly how this boilerplate looks, you can save
a lot of time by simply typing exclamation mark.
Hitting Enter on the first selection and then it will automatically insert all of that code for you,
saving you a lot of time, especially when you're creating many documents.
Now, the important thing here, though, is this only works if you have created a dot HTML website.
So notice that when you create a new file inside vs code, if you name it and save it as something something
dot html, then this trick will work.
If you save it with another extension, then it won't.
There's a couple of things here that we haven't seen before.
Couple more meta tags and there's a lot of other meta tags.
But here we've got one line here which says HTTP equivalent compatible content, i.e. edge.
This basically just keeps our code compatible with Internet Explorer.
And in fact, I normally don't write this line anymore because Internet Explorer has been deprecated
and is no longer in use.
So if you want to keep your code clean, you can actually delete this from your code or to generated
boilerplate.
Now the next one tells you the viewport and it defines how the website should be displayed relative
to the screen that it's being rendered on.
And this line of code just tells the browser how to display your website when it first opens.
So now that we've learned all about HTML boilerplates, it's time to build your own boilerplate, or
in this case, build your own burger.
As you notice, there are endless numbers of HTML elements and we're going to be creating our own HTML
elements.
But the important thing here I want you to understand is how nesting works in HTML and how you can keep
your code tidy by using good indentation and keeping good programming practices.
If we're building our own imaginary burger, let's imagine the world's best burger.
You can have it vegan, you can have it vegetarian, you can have bacon, you can have whatever it is
your heart desires, but you have to write it in code.
Let's begin by creating a bun.
So I've got a bun element that I've created which has an opening and a closing tag, and I've added
an attribute.
You can add as many of these attributes as you like.
And remember, we add attributes by giving it a name, and then after an equal sign, we give it a value.
Now the next part is for you to invent.
So head over to VS code and build your own burger, adding in whatever elements you want.
Add tomatoes, add ham, but make sure that you're keeping the indentation correct and that you're working
with this idea of opening and closing tags.
But you can be as creative as you like, and be sure to share your code for your burger in the Q&A section.
And if you want some inspiration.
This is one that I made earlier, but I want you to practice making your own and doing it your way.
Have a go at that and once you're done, head over to the next lesson.
Hey guys.
In the previous lesson, you've learned a lot about different types of HTML elements and you already
got started using them to create websites.
Now in this section we're going to take it a little bit further and explore some more intermediate and
advanced concepts in HTML.
We're going to get started in this lesson by learning about list elements, the ordered and unordered
lists.
Now, if you've spent any time around on the Internet recently, you'll notice that it's completely
full of lists.
If you go on to BuzzFeed or any of these sort of clickbaity articles, usually they'll create a list
of something such as great items that must have been invented by geniuses.
But also if you look at something like the FBI's ten Most Wanted Fugitives, this is also created in
this website using a list.
So how do we create these lists ourselves?
Well, let's start off with one of the most common types, the unordered list.
And it's super simple to create simply, you have a starting tag with UL and then have a closing tag.
Now, normally we've had one line elements such as this where we get to add some content in between
the open and closing tags.
Now in this case, however, it's a little bit different.
They actually go on separate lines because in between these two open and closing tags, we need an extra
type of tag in order to complete this unordered list.
And these are called list items.
So here you can see we've got three list items and each of them contain some piece of content.
But all three items are enclosed inside this unordered list.
So for any list to work and display content, then you're going to have to add list items into it.
So what does this look like if we actually run the code?
Well, this is what you would see.
Essentially unordered list items will create these bullet points because such as in the case of a shopping
list here, the order of the items doesn't matter.
So that's why an unordered list would be perfect for this situation.
However, on the other hand, if you needed your list items to be arranged in a particular order, then
you would create an ordered list.
And once you've added the list items inside there, what this will do is it will give you numbers.
So it would start from one and the number next to each list item will depend on the order that you put
into this ordered list element.
If this milk was down here, then it would get the number three and so on and so forth.
That's all pretty simple.
So if we compare the ordered list, the ol element that gives us numbers and versus the UL, the unordered
list item, which just gives us bullet points, simple as that.
And coming back to our FBI ten Most Wanted Fugitives website, you can see they actually created this
website using lists.
So when you right click on any of these images and select inspect, you can see that each of these photos
are actually a list item placed inside an unordered list.
Now there's a whole bunch more to this website which we're going to learn in future lessons.
But the really important thing is for you to see that this is a really important part that you see in
websites all over on the Internet.
So it's really important that we understand how to use them.
So now that we've learned a little bit about ordered and unordered lists, let's try an exercise to
make sure that you've understood everything.
Go ahead and download the list element zip file from this current lesson.
And as always, if you forget how to do that, or if you just started on this lesson, then I recommend
going to one of the earlier lessons where I show you how to download course resources.
Now, once you've downloaded and extracted the folder 3.0 list elements and dragged it into VS code
or your web development projects folder, then you should be able to see it here on the file Explorer
on the left.
If we explore some of the files for this current coding exercise, you can see we've got an index.html
that contains some plain text which you're going to be formatting into lists.
And if we take a look at the goal, feel free to choose whichever heading sizes you want.
But for me, I think it made the most sense to have one H1 and then the ingredients and the instructions
as h2's and then any other headings like this part and this part as h3's.
But the most important thing I care about in this exercise is you manage to create these lists.
So we've got an unordered list for.
Section one of the ingredients to create the dough.
And then we've got another unordered list for the filling ingredients.
And finally, we've got all the rest of the instructions as a ordered list.
Think about how you're going to create this and don't worry about typing all the text out because if
you look inside the index.html, you'll see all the text typed out for you already.
All you need to do is to add the HTML tags and to format the document into an HTML website.
And in the end we should end up with this recipe website for creating delicious cinnamon rolls.
Now, if you watched my recent Instagram takeover of the Udemy account, you'll see me making the same
cinnamon rolls.
And if you want to do the same, then this is the recipe for you.
This is what you're aiming for and using what you've learnt about list elements.
I want you to go ahead and pause the video and complete this challenge.
All right.
So did you manage to do that?
Let's go ahead and walk through the solution together.
So I'm going to show you the preview on the right side so you can see the website update as I type.
First, we're going to start off with our heading tags.
So I'm just going to add a bunch of headings in quite quickly.
All right, so that's all the headings out of the way.
So now we're on to the proper work, which is creating our lists.
As I said, the ingredients don't really need an order, so we're going to create an unordered list.
So in between our start and end UL tags, we're going to have each of these as a list item.
So I'm going to create the list item tag.
And once I've created that, then all I need to do is to drag my first list item in between the list
item.
Now, if clicking and dragging doesn't work for you, if this doesn't show up, then you can also just
right click, copy and paste that also works.
Now I need to do this many times, so for efficiency's sake, I'm just going to paste in another 4 or
5 of these and drag in all of the other ingredients into each of these list items.
Now, when you're actually coding this from scratch, you won't need to do all of this dragging because
you'll be typing your list item and then you'll be writing your item name in here like so.
But because we've written all the text for you, hopefully to save you some time so that you're actually
doing more coding and less sort of busy work, then this is how we do it.
Again for the filling.
We've got another unordered list and then inside there are three list items.
So let me go ahead and paste those three list items in and drag each of them in between the tags like
so.
So now we've got our ingredients and we've got our two unordered lists showing up perfectly.
Now all we have to do is to create the final list, which is going to be an ordered list, because if
you think about it, instructions have an order, right?
You can't first bake the thing if you haven't created it yet.
Inside this order list, we again need these list item elements and we need to create as many of them
as we have steps.
So I'm going to drag each of the lines into the list elements.
And there we have it.
We've got all of our list items and all of our instructions showing up perfectly inside an ordered list.
And if we check against the goal, then you can see we've pretty much completed everything perfectly.
Now, one thing to talk about at this point is notice how some HTML elements are one line and other
HTML elements are on multiple lines.
When you paste long lines of text in between the start and end tags of an element, sometimes vs code
will automatically put the closing tag onto the next line.
Now you can edit this so that it all goes onto the same line, or you can purposely make sure they're
on different lines and you see it being sandwiched between the open and closing tags.
Now this is a personal preference, so it really doesn't matter how you want to do this so you can do
this however you like.
But for me, I like to have list items all on the same line.
This just kind of helps me see visually how many list items I have, and it doesn't clutter up the list
with all of these list items.
So have a think about whether, if you like to see your elements like this all on one line with the
content enclosed or if you prefer to have it like this where things are more indented and you have the
content in between two lines of your list item.
In the next lesson, we're going to talk a little bit more about this type of indentation.
So don't worry if that doesn't make sense just yet.
We're going to talk about nesting and we're going to talk about indentation of HTML elements.
So once you're ready, head over to the next lesson and we'll continue from there.
Now, in the previous lesson, we learned a little bit about ordered and unordered lists.
Now in this lesson, we're going to take that concept a little bit further.
I want to show you how you can nest things inside others.
For example, we saw that we could already nest the list elements inside an unordered list and you would
see it indented like this.
But we can actually go a step further and we can actually nest a list inside another list.
So in this case, what you see is we've got the first unordered list that starts here, and this is
where it ends.
But we've also got another unordered list here.
And this is where the second one begins and where it ends.
When this is rendered in a website, this is what you'll see.
You'll see it's looking like this.
So you've got the first list that is this entire part.
And then inside the first list, we've got a separate list.
Under this particular bullet point.
Now, how does the code look?
Well, it looks quite simple.
All you have to do is inside a list item.
You see how the starting list item is right here.
And the end list item is down here inside this list item.
Instead of simply just having a single line of text such as what we've got up here, instead, we've
actually embedded an entire unordered list.
So first we'll write the text for the list item, and then after the text we embed our unordered list,
just as you would see in any other normal list.
And then we end up with what's called a nested list.
This is the part where indentation your code becomes super important because imagine the code looked
like this and not like this.
When you look at this code at a glance, it's a lot harder to see that you've got a list embedded inside.
Another list.
Right.
Because you have to actually read what each of these tags are instead of using the clues that's offered
by that indentation.
And as you can imagine, we can have even crazier nested lists like what I've got right here.
So there's actually three lists here.
One is up here.
This is the first list.
This is a unordered list.
And then we've got a second list right here, which is again, an unordered list.
And that's embedded under the list item for be.
And then to complicate things, I've added a third ordered list that's listed under this second item
right here.
This amount of craziness starts to really highlight the issues that you're going to have reading this
code.
Imagine somebody else gave you this code and you had to figure out without looking at the right hand
side, what is going on right here.
It's a lot easier if we have it indented, right, Because we can clearly see one unordered list, the
second unordered list and the third ordered list because they're all nicely indented and is a lot easier
visually for when we're reading code.
So when you're writing code, you also are thinking about how other people are going to find reading
your code.
Now let's try an exercise to really drill this home.
I want you to download the nesting and indentation zip file from this current lesson, and I want you
to open up inside vs code as you have done previously.
Now, in this case, if we take a look at our goal is to create a super complex nested list.
In the last lesson you already saw how you can create simple list elements, whether it's unordered
lists or it's ordered lists.
It's pretty simple to create just a list with some list items.
But in this challenge, I want you to create something a lot more complicated.
Let me walk you through it.
So firstly, we've got a unordered list that has just three list items A, B and C, but under item
B, notice here we've got a ordered list.
This ordered list also has three items and under item B to the second item, we've got yet another unordered
list.
And inside the first item we've nested another unordered list.
And inside the third item we've embedded another ordered list.
This is a little bit complicated and in order to really understand it, you need to take a look at this
part of the video because here I've got the code that will create this simpler structure.
And the important thing to notice is that whereas normally you would probably have a list item that
starts like this and then you would have it closed like this.
In the case when we're embedding a list, that closing tag does not go here, but instead it goes all
the way at the end of the nested list.
Once we're done nesting, this unordered list right here, then do we close that list item?
So this is a really important thing to take notice of.
And then I want you to just study this page a little bit to see how I created this list using this code
and then take this and apply it to the challenge in the coding exercise.
Have a good think about it.
Take some time to try and complete this challenge.
I for one, believe that you can do this if you just spend some time thinking and trying it.
And as always, remember you can use the preview feature to see how your code is turning out and shaping
up while you're writing it.
And I think that will help you quite a lot.
Pause the video now and give that coding exercise a go.
All right.
So how did that go?
Now, if you didn't give that a go, I want you to stop the video now.
Make sure that you've tried it.
You're not going to learn coding through just watching me code.
You're only going to learn programming by actually doing it.
Solving challenges, feeling stupid, sometimes feeling like you're not good enough.
But at the end, when you do get it, when you do succeed, it's going to feel amazing.
And I promise you it was the same for everybody who's gone through this journey.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to run through the solution and I'm going to drag my goal up over
here so I can compare it to the preview as I go along.
So the first step is creating the first unordered list with three items A, B and C That should be pretty
easy to do.
And let's go ahead and create that.
All right, so now we've got the top of our nest, which is our A, B and C.
If we take a look at our goal, compare it.
We've got A, B, C inside the bullet.
B, we're going to embed right here, a ordered list.
So it's again going to have three items B1, B2 and B3.
And we know it's an ordered list because it starts off with the numbers one, two and three.
Let's go ahead and embed that inside this second B list item.
Remember what I said when you embed a list in another one, you find the list item you want to embed
it in.
And after the content of the list item, which is of course, this B right here, then we go ahead and
hit enter and that is where we create our list.
We're going to create an ordered list in this case and it's going to have three items.
The first one is going to be B1 and then B2 and B3.
Now let's again compare and contrast.
We've got our B1, B2, B3, but take a look inside this B2 item.
Again, we're going to nest another list and here we've got a unordered list B2, a B2B and B2C.
Let's go ahead and do that.
Right here inside the B2 list item, we're going to create our unordered list, our UL, and we're going
to have B2, a B2B and B2C.
Let's compare.
We've got B2B, B2B, B2C, so we've already got most of the parts done.
The final nest in this big long chain is under B to A, we need to add a unordered list, B to A and
B to a B.
Now, the way that I've named each of these hopefully should help you with the nesting.
If it doesn't, then you just have to compare against the goal and try matching it visually.
In this case instead of under the second item, it's actually nested under the first item.
And again, it's an unordered list with just two list items B to A and B to a B.
Now we've got pretty much all of this part sorted.
All we need to do now is just to add the final ordered list in bed under the B three list item.
Let's find our B three list item.
After the text, let's hit enter to create a new line and then we're going to create an ordered list
like this and we're going to add our two list items B31 and B32.
So now if we compare our goal and what we've got in the preview, you should see it's completely identical.
And through this process, hopefully you've learned a little bit more about nesting.
And one of the nice things about Visual Studio Code is that it will automatically indent things as you
write your code.
It knows, for example, list items, go inside a list.
So whether if it's a UL or an O, L, when you go to file and save or use the shortcut command here,
in my case on a mac, it's command s.
If you're on a windows, it's probably Ctrl s.
When you do that, it automatically re indents everything.
So even if you kind of mess things up in a big way as you type like I've got here and you've made all
of the structure look very weird.
If you save Visual Studio code will re indent everything for you so you don't have to necessarily indent
things, but it's important you understand what the indentation means.
So here you see a line right here and it links the opening UL to the matching closing tag, and then
it has indented these two list items over so that you can see these two items probably belong to this
unordered list.
And very often in HTML you will have matching tags.
If there's an open tag, there's probably a closing tag.
And all of these things on screen such as these lines.
And the indentation is here to help you to understand how your code looks so that if you actually have
an error, such as, for example, if you had forgotten to close this UL and when you see your code
doing weird things like for example, in this case, why is my C in an ordered list when it should be
at the top level with the other unordered list?
What is going on here?
Well, I can then follow these indentations.
I can see that this UL obviously matches along this line down to this closing one.
And then this next one is a list item.
So these two are on one line, they're matched and then this next list item is matched up with this
one.
But then wait a minute, what's going on here?
Why is this ol matched to a list item?
Or maybe there's something missing right here?
Well, it is, of course, the missing closing tag.
So this way I can start to figure out where my errors come from.
So we're going to do a lot more of this kind of error checking and mistake correction, which we call
debugging in future lessons.
But this is just a taster in this lesson for how you can use some of the tools to help you make sure
that your code is working and that you're writing the correct things.
And when you do make a mistake, as we all do, you can use the nesting in indentation in order to diagnose
what's wrong with your code and help you fix it.
So that's all for nesting and indentation.
In the next lesson, we're going to learn about anchor elements and we're going to start creating hyperlinks
in our web pages.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Hey, guys.
In this lesson, we're going to understand a bit more about another aspect of HTML, which is their
attributes and understand that we're going to learn all about the anchor element, which allows us to
create hyperlinks.
This is what an anchor element looks like and similar to previous elements, we've got the opening tag
and the closing tag, but there's something a little bit special about this one because right now if
you wrote the code as it is here, this is not an active hyperlink.
What you need is to add an additional attribute, and the attribute for an HTML element goes in the
opening tag.
It goes into the part just after the name of the tag and just before the end of the opening tag where
we have the closing angle bracket.
And what an attribute does is it adds additional information to this HTML element, such as in this
case where this link should link to.
Now, the way that we structure an attribute looks something like this.
So we have the name of the element and then we have a space and then we have the name of the attribute.
And afterwards we have a equal sign.
And after the equal sign, we have the value of the attribute.
Now you can have as many attributes as you want and all you have to do is simply separate each one of
them with a space and make sure that they all go into the opening tag.
Now, in the case of our image element, if you take a look on the Mozilla developer network documentation
for the anchor element, then you can see it has the special attribute of href and href is the part
where we add the URL that the hyperlink should go to without the attribute.
This is what you would see.
It is an anchor element and you do see the content in between the tags, but you do not see an active
link when you click on it.
Nothing happens.
Now.
As soon as you add that href attribute and you provide it with in this case a target.
So where should this hyperlink go to then?
This link actually gets styled to show you that this is now an active link in the familiar blue with
the underline.
And at this point, if you click on it, it is going to go straight to this URL that we've specified
in addition to the specific attributes.
So for example, in the anchor element documentation, we saw that it has all of these specific attributes
which are relevant to this particular element.
Now we're not going to be using all of them and some of them are also deprecated and no longer in use
in HTML5.
But in addition to these specific attributes, there are also global attributes that every single HTML
element has access to.
And if you look through some of these, an example is something like draggable, right?
And it basically allows us to set true or false to say whether if the element may or may not be dragged,
you can apply a global attribute to any given element.
So in this case, we can apply it even to our anchor element.
Again, we have the name of the attribute, we have the equal sign and we have the value of the attribute.
So in this case, the name of the attribute is Draggable, and we've set it equal to true.
So once this attribute is set, what happens is you can click and drag that anchor tag around.
Now, if that attribute wasn't set, then when you try to drag it, it's just going to highlight the
line and it's not going to allow that behavior.
So we've learned that there are specific attributes which are reserved for only certain elements, such
as the href for the anchor tag, and there are global attributes which can be used on any HTML element.
So now let's try an exercise and see if you've understood how to use anchor elements and more specifically,
see if you've understood how the HTML attribute is written in HTML code.
In this exercise, we're going to create a website that shows our top five favorite websites.
I've got the H1 already written for you, but what we're aiming for is something like this.
So you have a list here and notice that this is actually an ordered list because it goes from one all
the way to five and the fact that the list is not highlighted.
Is in blue should show you that this is actually created using a list element and not a part of the
anchor tag.
It's not a part of the content.
And the anchor tag only starts here.
I want you to document your top five all time favorite websites and feel free to Google or check mine
if you want to see what they do.
These are some of the websites that I go to when I'm bored or when I'm trying to look for some new ideas
and new inspiration.
So I want you to use what you've learned previously about creating lists.
And within those lists, I want you to create five anchor tags, each of them pointing to a different
website that you like.
And if you've got everything working, then you would end up with a website that looks like the goal.
And when you click on any of these links, then they should take you to the correct website.
Pause the video.
Now, give this challenge a go, and once you're done, come back here and I'll go through the solution
with you.
All right.
So how did that go?
The first thing we wanted to do was to create a ordered list.
We already saw how to do this in a previous lesson.
We create our tags and inside we add our list elements.
Inside the list element is where our anchor tag is going to go.
It's an anchor tag, which is inside a list element, which is then inside a ordered list.
So several layers of nesting that's going on here.
Now, once you've created your anchor tag, then in between the open and closing tags, we add the text
for our link.
So in my case, it will be the name of my website that I'm linking to, which is called Product Hunt.
And this is a place where you can see all the latest product launches and great websites and start ups
that people are building every day.
The important part comes here when we create the attribute for that anchor tag.
So remember that the attribute for linking a anchor tag is called the href, and we're going to add
it after the equal sign.
As you start typing, you might see code, start suggesting what you're looking for.
So if you pick the ref and hit enter, then it will format everything for you ready for you to enter
the URL.
If you're wondering why there are these quotation marks here, well, that's because it's actually a
piece of text that we're going to add in here.
So this is treated slightly differently in code.
So whenever you have text, normally you will see them enclosed inside a set of double quotes.
This is to differentiate from the reserved words like, you know, I or a or h ref.
These are all special words.
And in order to show that you're not creating anything special, you're just pointing to our URL, which
is just a piece of text.
We have our double quotes around it.
Inside here, I'm going to paste in the URL of product hunt, and now I have myself a link and if I
go ahead and show preview, then you should see that we've got our list item one.
And when I click on it, it goes to the website that I have linked to.
You can repeat this process and link to all of your five favorite websites and you should end up with
something that looks like this.
And as an extra challenge, I want you to head over to the developer documentation for the ordered list,
which you're using in this current code exercise.
And look at the attributes.
I want you to see whether if you can change one of the attributes, the start attribute, so that your
list, instead of starting from one starts from five.
This is what you're aiming for.
Pause the video, give that a go, and then afterwards we'll go through the solution together.
Let's take a look at the documentation.
We can see that for the ordered list.
One of the attributes is called START.
And in the explanation, it says, All we have to do is to set this attribute to a number for it to
start from.
So that's pretty simple.
But we need to remember where our attributes go.
So they go in the starting tag, which is here, and the name of the attribute is Start, and we can
set it equal to five.
Now once we've done that, if we take a look at our website, you can see the order list now starts
from five and ends at nine because we've changed that attribute.
Hopefully that wasn't too difficult and you managed to get it to work.
Have a quick review of the concepts that are covered in this lesson.
And remember, we're always trying to repeat things that we've learnt before just to make sure that
we reinforce those pieces of knowledge from earlier on.
And one thing I like to do as I learn is to make some notes on the things that are new to me that I
didn't realize before.
So if there's something new in this lesson that you want to write down, take a quick note of it and
then head over to the next lesson where we talk about image elements.
For all of that and more.
I'll see you there.
Now, a website would be pretty boring if it had no images on it, right?
So in this lesson we're going to learn how we can add images to our website using the image element.
Now this is what it looks like.
It's pretty simple.
And you'll notice that similar to the anchor tag or the anchor element that we learned about in the
last lesson, the main component of an image tag that renders the image is this attribute, which is
called source or SRC.
And what this does is it tells the image element what is the source of the image.
And that's why after the equal sign, the value is going to be the location of the image.
One last thing to notice about the image tag is, unlike the anchor tag, it doesn't have a closing
tag.
Instead, it is a self closing tag, also known as a void element.
Remember, previously we learned about void elements where we learnt that you can have horizontal rule
elements, you can also have break elements.
And similarly the image element is also a void element that doesn't have a closing tag.
Because if you think about it, what is the text content of an image?
Doesn't really make sense, right?
The main content is actually the image that will be rendered from the source.
What does this look like?
Well, here's an example image element where we've set the source to a real life live photo on the Internet.
Now, when this code is rendered in a website, it will display a random image.
So in this case, the random image I got was a forest.
And the reason why it's random is because I'm getting these photos from a source called pixham.photos.
So if you type this into your browser, you should see a website and the idea is kind of like the Lorem
ipsum for placeholder photos.
So when you don't really care what the photo is, but you need a photo on your website as you're creating
it in order to see what it would look like, then you could use this website and you could put in the
URL, which is the standard one like here.
And then after a forward slash, you can add in the size of your image.
So in this case, I'm saying I want a square that is 200 pixels by 200 pixels.
It gives me a random image from its data bank, for example, in this case of a forest.
The other attribute for an image tag that's super important and one that you should always have is the
alt attribute.
And the alt attribute stands for Alternative Text Description.
This is really important because people who are blind or visually impaired, they don't look at the
Internet the same way we do.
They often use something called a screen reader.
And what the screen reader is going to do when it hits an image is it will look at the alternative text
provided.
So in this case, I've provided that this is a forest at sunset or sunrise.
I'm not quite sure, but that means that the person with visual impairment will get this read out to
them and it will help them understand what the website's all about.
So what is this process like?
As an example, I'm using the Silktide Toolbar, which is a Chrome browser extension, to simulate what
a person with visual impairment might hear as they're browsing.
In this case, the BBC website.
As I click through next, you can see it describes the different things that are on screen.
And if I go over to the image, it describes the image for me.
Item two Dolphin leaping from the sea image.
So where is it getting this description from?
Well, if we right click on the image and inspect it, and if we look for the image, which I think
should be down here, you can see as I highlight different parts, it shows me which part.
So in this element, I'm probably going to find an image at the end right here and you can see the alt
text saying dolphin leaping from the sea.
And that is what gets read out from the screen reader helping somebody with blindness.
Be able to understand what's on this website.
Now, if you want to check out this tool, it's a Chrome browser extension called Silktide and it should
be a free plugin, but it might only work on Mac or certain versions of Windows, but it's not so much
about the tool, but I wanted to show you how important it is the alt text that you provide for accessibility
and for disabled users browsing your website.
Now let's try.
An exercise and create some images of our own.
Download the zip file from this current lesson and go ahead and drag it into your web development project
folder and open it inside vs code.
If you take a look inside the index.html, you can see I've provided to you two image URL examples that
you can use.
And what we're aiming for is to find out if you're a cat person or if you're a dog person.
I want you to create a H1 that says I'm a cat person or I'm a dog person.
And also I want you to add a image element straight afterwards.
Now you can use the URL for the dog or for the cat.
It doesn't really matter at the end of the day, as long as you've understood how to create images.
That's the challenge.
Pause the video and give that a go.
All right.
So personally, I'm more of a dog kind of person.
And if you're also a dog person, then you might see my little Easter egg that I've buried in there.
So first, let's go ahead and create our H1, and then we're going to create our image.
Remember, we create a image tag and it's a self-closing tag.
Then we add in our source as the image source, and we're going to put our URL right inside there.
Now, already, if we go ahead and show preview, you can see our little dog digging in the sand.
Because if you've noticed, this is actually a gif image.
GIF images work exactly the same way as normal images, JPEGs or PNGs.
As long as you put it into the source, it will be rendered in a website and it will start animating
or by itself.
And you get a cute little dog digging through the sand.
Now if you're a cat person, then this is just a static jpeg because cats are more chill.
So I hope you manage to get that part right.
But we haven't finished creating our image element yet.
Remember what I said about the alt tag?
It's a good idea to always add an alt tag to describe our image when we can.
Now, there are some cases where you don't create an alt tag because it's not really relevant to somebody
reading through the content of a website and you can in fact leave it blank.
But in this case, it's very simple.
We've got a puppy who is digging through the sand.
And now when we take a look at our preview, then nothing visually for us changes.
But behind the scenes, we will help our visually impaired friends to be able to understand our website
just a little bit better.
So I hope you managed to achieve either of these goals.
And once you're ready, we can head over to the next lesson where we've got the final project to create
a birthday invite website using all the skills that we've learned so far.
So all of that and more.
I'll see you there.
All right.
It's time to put everything we've learned so far together and create a project.
In this project, we're going to create a website for your next party to help you invite all your guests.
Because paper invites and WhatsApp invites are only for people who can't create websites.
Am I right?
We can do it better.
This is what we're aiming for.
We're aiming for a retro 90s look website because we haven't learned about styling websites yet, which
is yet to come, but this is already pretty nice.
We're going to create a website to tell people that it's our birthday, which day it is, and we're
going to add some images.
We're going to tell people what to bring using lists.
And also we're going to add an anchor tag to show people where they need to go.
Hopefully, we're going to combine a lot of the things that you've learned in previous lessons.
And once you're ready, head over to the course resources for this lesson.
Download and extract the zip file in order to get started.
When you take a look at the index.html, you can see I've provided an example image URL and an example
Google Maps link.
So if you take a look inside the goal, you can see what the example image will take you to.
And if you're ready for an Easter egg slash mini surprise, you can head over to the Google map link
and see where it's located as well.
So this is a project and it's not a coding exercise.
It's not something that I'm testing you on.
Everything I'm saying.
It's just a guideline.
I want you to at minimum, have an image in there, have a list in there, and also have an anchor tag
in there.
Everything else is totally up to you.
You can mess around with it as much as you like or change as much as you like, or keep it as simple
as you like.
It doesn't really matter.
Pause the video and give this project a go and happy birthday if it is your birthday today.
All right.
So want to walk through one possible solution?
I just want to say this is just one possibility.
You can change it as much as you like.
There is no right or wrong in the project.
It's all about practice and also your own personal style.
So in my case, I created an H1 for the top level heading, which is the most important thing.
It's my birthday and then I've got some h2's and some H3.
So for what to bring and where you need to go in the image tag.
I've added a source to that image I provided in the starting code, and also I provided an alternative
text to show people what this image is all about.
If you manage to get the image source and the alternative text and your image shows up, then congratulations.
You did a great job.
Now the next part I've got is a unordered list to tell people what they should bring with each item
in its own list item element.
And finally, I created an anchor tag to tell people where they need to go.
So I've added an href attribute and I used the link that I supplied in the starting code and I told
people that the link text is a Google map link, which hopefully will take them to where they need to
go, which is somewhere in Tokyo where all the pigeon people meet, apparently.
So if you found that Easter egg, then congratulations.
But if you're really proud of what you managed to do for your project, then be sure to take a screenshot
of it and post it in the Q&A to share it with the rest of us.
I would love to see what you came up with, but that's all from me for this section.
I hope you enjoyed learning more about HTML elements and I'll see you soon.
Hey guys, welcome to the introduction to CSS section.
And in this very first lesson, we're going to be introducing you to CSS.
You'll be learning what it is, how it works and why we need it to be able to style our websites and
make them look beautiful.
What exactly is CSS?
Well, it stands for cascading style sheets.
It kind of conjures up the image of a cascade.
Right.
And a cascade is simply like a waterfall.
You have water at one level that then drops down through a waterfall into another level.
And we're going to see as we start to use these cascading style sheets, why that analogy is so apt.
Because the way that the style is applied cascades like a waterfall.
We start from the most general all the way down to the most specific styling requirements, and we're
going to see that in use as we use these cascading style sheets.
The other part of this name is the style sheet.
A style sheet is a type of language similar to how we had the HTML, which is a markup language.
That's what the part of stands for.
We have the style sheet, which is what the SS part stands for, and this is a language that allows
us to specify how things should look in our website.
And there are many different types of stylesheet languages.
The one that's most important and what we're going to be learning all about in this section is the cascading
style sheet.
But there's also others like Sass, which stands for syntactically awesome style sheet and Less, which
stands for Leaner CSS and many, many others.
But the most important one that every web developer needs to know is CSS.
And that's what we're going to be focusing on today.
So why did we need CSS?
Where did it come from and what exactly is the history of this whole thing?
Well, in the very beginning when the Internet was very, very new, there was no CSS, there was only
HTML.
And one of the things that developers started wanting to do is they wanted to style their website and
make it look the way they want it to, but they were really, really limited by HTML.
And this is a now famous email sent by Marc Andreessen, who is the founder of Mosaic, which is one
of the earliest Internet browsers who later founded Netscape and now the very famous Andreessen Horowitz
VC Fund.
And in this email he famously said that the answer he has for so many developers who want to simply
control what their documents look like, meaning what their websites look like in a way that would be
trivial, say in Microsoft Word.
His answer to these developers is just sorry, you're screwed.
There is no way to do it very easily at that point in HTML.
That's why all the website looks pretty much the same.
Pretty boring.
And there was no variation.
So what happened next?
Well, the W3C consortium responded by releasing a new version of HTML, HTML 3.2, and this came out
in 1997, so it was still in the very early days of the Internet.
And what this 3.2 HTML allowed was it introduced new HTML tags such as the font tag, which allows you
to define the font size, the color and the font face.
So the type of font you would want to use for your document.
Similarly, there was also the color attribute for font.
There was the face attribute, the size attribute, and these attributes allow you to change all sorts
of things about the way the text looks on your website.
And then there was also the center element which allows you to format your document and define how it
would be laid out on the screen.
Now, what you'll notice in all three of these Web pages is the deprecated symbol next to it.
All of these are deprecated, which in programming lingo, simply means you should no longer be using
these attributes and elements.
And the reason for this is because, as you can imagine, our HTML is supposed to be for content.
Now, if you add in a ton of styling into all of that content, you tell the website how it should be
centered, how it should be laid out, how the font should look, what color it should be, what kind
of border your tables should have, and a whole bunch of other styling effectively.
Then this is going to massively clutter up all of your HTML.
And you can imagine this is a really, really short website and it's already got so much junk in it
that we can't really tell what exactly is the structure and the content of the website and.
If you extend this to a larger website and you just want to do some simple things like give it some
colors or put things into the center, then your whole HTML file is going to be many, many, many thousands
of lines long and it's impossible to differentiate the content from the styling.
So what happened next?
Well, in 1996, a new recommendation was proposed by the W3 consortium, and this was led by Hakon
Wium.
How come?
How come by how come?
And he's basically the father of the cascading style sheet.
And what this recommendation allows us to do is to allow us to attach styles such as font colors and
spacing to our HTML documents.
And this is the breakthrough that allowed us to separate our styling from our content.
And as in many different situations, a separation of concerns so that somebody is responsible for putting
together the car headlights and somebody else is responsible for dealing with the wheels rather than
one person making an entire car.
This kind of modularity, as you'll see in coming lessons, is super important, not just in manufacturing
and in real life, but also in programming.
If you want to see what CSS is able to achieve.
I've built this website for you to be able to do that.
If you go over to App Brewery, Github.io and then forward Slash, just add CSS, you should be able
to see this website.
And when you first go over there, you'll see that it's just a very, very simple website, pretty bland.
All it's got is HTML.
And now if we go ahead and press this button to toggle and turn on CSS, then you'll see the entire
website transform and look way more beautiful.
It's now got different fonts, different colors and different layouts.
But you'll notice that if you go ahead and right click and view the page source in these two versions,
the HTML does not change at all.
So let's toggle our back and then let's go ahead and view page source again.
You'll see that in these two versions.
As you see me switch it on screen, nothing changes in our index.html.
The only thing that is different is the CSS that gets added.
Now don't worry too much about the script tags down here or how we've created our buttons.
We're going to learn all of that later on when we learn JavaScript.
But I created this website so that you can play around with toggling the CSS on and off to see how it
can transform a simple HTML website without touching any of the code inside the HTML.
And all that we're doing is adding style to our website in a completely separate language.
The cascading style sheet.
To learn more about how CSS works, head over to the next lesson where we're going to get started styling
up a website.
Now, I hope you had to play around with this example website where you could toggle the CSS on and
off.
How exactly did I add CSS to this plain HTML website?
Well, that is what we're going to be learning about in this lesson.
There's three ways of adding CSS into an HTML website.
Inline, internal and external.
We're going to be exploring all three of these different styles of adding CSS, and I'm going to show
you why they're important and in which situations you would use which one.
Now, the first one is the inline style of adding CSS.
As the name suggests, it goes into the same line as a particular HTML element.
So in this case, you can see we've got an HTML open tag and an HTML closing tag.
Now, we know from learning about HTML boilerplate, this is an element that goes into all of our HTML
documents.
There's nothing special about this particular element.
It just tells the browser that this file is made up of HTML.
Now, in this case, the inline CSS goes into the opening tag of the HTML.
This is where the CSS exists.
It's in the same line as the HTML tag.
What the inline CSS looks like is something like this.
You've got a style attribute, which is an attribute that is globally available to all tags, not just
HTML, but anything else.
Image or break or anything you can think of.
You can add the style attribute to it.
As we know, normally attributes look like this.
They have a name of the attribute.
Then we add the equal sign.
And then finally we add a value for the attribute.
In this value section is where we add our CSS code.
Our CSS code is broken down like this.
The first part of it is the property that you want to change.
And the second part is the value of that property that you want to set it to.
So in this case, what we're trying to do is to set our website's background to blue.
And if I go ahead and run this code and load it up in a browser, you would simply see a website that
has a blue background.
And this is achieved using our inline CSS.
Inline elements are really useful for adding CSS style to just a single element on your HTML page.
But normally that's quite cumbersome because as you can imagine, there's tons of different HTML elements.
If you have more and more of them and you wanted them to share similar styles, then you would have
to add these inline styles to each and every single one of them, which is pretty tedious.
It's not normally recommended to use inline styles in your entire document.
It's only for specific sections or when you're testing or when you only want it in one single element
or one line in your HTML document.
Now, the second way you can add CSS is through what's called internal CSS.
Now this is done through a special HTML tag called the Style Element.
We've got an open style tag and a closing style tag.
And in between those two lines is where we add all of our CSS.
All of this is our CSS.
The CSS looks a little bit different from what you saw previously, right?
Because previously all we had was this line.
Now, in this case, we've got something a little bit extra here.
Why is that?
Well, this is because last time when we had the CSS rule, we had it inline inside a particular element.
So we said for this HTML element, we want to apply a background color.
Now, in this case, it's a little bit different because our internal style can apply to anywhere within
the same HTML document.
So it could go into any of these elements, the HTML or the head or anything that you've got coming
up later on as well.
What we have to add in addition often is what we call a selector, and this selector comes before a
set of curly braces and then the CSS goes in between these two sets of curly braces.
Now, when I say in between a set of curly braces, you have to imagine it a little bit like this.
This is the opening curly brace and this is the closing curly brace.
And if you had it all on one line, then it would look something like this with your CSS going in between
on multiple lines.
That's why we open and close them on separate lines.
But if you imagine it as one line, then it would look something like this.
Our internal styling can apply to anywhere in our HTML document, and inside we can target or select
as many elements as we want.
We could say let's apply the background red to the HTML, and when this code is rendered in the browser,
you will see the background of the entire HTML turn red.
Internal styles are really useful for applying it only to one HTML document.
As you can see, this style and any code that goes in there is limited to the HTML that it sits in.
So it means if you have a multi-page website, then you probably shouldn't be using the internal style.
Instead you should be using something called an external CSS styling.
Now the biggest difference between the external and the internal and inline styles is that this actually
lives in a completely separate file, which you'll normally see as Styles.css or Main.css or anything
that has a dot CSS extension inside this CSS file is where we write our CSS rules.
So we've got our selector, we've got our property and we've got values and we can make many, many
of these inside this file.
Now how do we link up the style sheet file with our index.html?
Well, inside the head section of our HTML, we would add a link element which you'll notice is a self-closing
tag.
So it doesn't need a closing tag.
And we have two things that we normally write.
One which is a relationship which refers to what is the role of this thing that we're linking to?
And the second thing is the href, which is where is it located?
In this case, we're saying it's in the same directory and it's inside a file called Styles.
CSS, which points to this file right here.
And when we go ahead and run this and show it in the browser, you'll see it turns our HTML background
to a green color.
And this style of external CSS is what's used most commonly in web development.
And this is what we're going to be focusing on most of the time.
But it's important to be aware of the other two styles the inline, the internal, because you'll see
it out there in the wild in other people's CSS code.
So remember, inline is really useful when you only want to target a single element.
And internal is really useful when you only want to target a single web page.
But for most cases and when you have a multi-page website, then what you're going to need is the external
way of adding CSS through the use of a separate file, which will be called something, something dot
CSS, and it's inside this file where you're going to be writing the CSS code that can target an entire
website with all of its multiple web pages.
So these are the three ways that you can add CSS to your HTML documents.
And don't worry, we're going to be practicing this and all of its forms many, many times so that you
understand how it works.
Let's try an exercise and see how to add CSS in various different ways to our HTML file.
All right.
So once you've downloaded and extracted the project file and open it inside vs code, you should see
this folder.
And here notice that our five files that have already been created for you.
And in this exercise there is a little bit of revision about creating multiple web pages about file
paths.
But more importantly, we want you to practice using the three different ways of adding CSS inline,
internal and external.
So starting inside index.html, the first thing I want you to do is to create three links to the three
different web pages.
This one, this one and this one.
And once you've done that, then you can go inside each of those web pages.
So starting with the inline and then internal external, and you're going to follow the instruction
that the H one tells you to.
So in this case, we want to use inline styling in order to style this h one in blue and then you get
to go to the internal and do the same thing, but this time using internal styling and styling the H
one in red and then finally using external styling using this style.css file and styling the h one in
green.
If you want to take a look at what the final outcome will look like, you can go into the solution folder,
right click on the solution, dot HTML and show preview and then make sure that you collapse this solution
folder.
Because having all of it out, two versions of each file is very confusing.
So I recommend just collapsing that folder so you don't get confused and this is what you're aiming
for on the index.html, which is the home page.
We've got an H one and then we've got three links.
And if we click on each of these, you can see they've got an H1 that says style me in blue style,
me in red and green and we're going to achieve that using the three different ways of adding CSS.
Once you're ready, go ahead and download the starting files and give this challenge a go.
Pause the video now.
All right.
So how did that go?
I'm going to run through the solution code with you to explain some of the things that you would need
to do to complete this challenge.
The first thing we said was to style the home page.
So we added in three anchor tags, which is how we create links.
And once we did that, we were able to use the href of each of the anchor tags in order to link to the
relevant web page.
The first one links to the inline web page, inline HTML, internal external, and we use the dot slash
notation in order to reach within the current folder.
So solution dot html lives inside solution.
And in this case, in order to get to inline dot html, we use the dot slash to get to this folder and
then we forward slash to go to inline dot html right here.
Now once you've created your three links, the next stage is to go into the first web page inline and
here we want to style the H1 using CSS, but adding it inline.
As I said, it's in the literal line of the H1 element, so it only applies to this H1 element and we've
added it in right here saying that the style should be set so that the color of this text is blue.
And remember that the inline style goes in the opening tag of the element that you want to target.
The next one is internal, so we add internal styling, usually by putting it inside the head section.
So between the open and closing tags of the head element, and this is a convention that most developers
will stick to, although this will work no matter where you put the style element.
So here we've got an open and closing style tag and in between we've added in our CSS.
So we're saying that our selector is going to select all the H1 on this page, of which there is only
one, and we're going to change its text color to red.
And finally we've got the final version, which is the external HTML.
And we do this by creating a link element right again, inside the head section of your website.
We establish the relationship is we're setting up a style sheet and then we provide a href to the location
where our stylesheet is located, which is in the current directory, and then it's in a file called
Style.css.
So we can see that right here.
And inside here we've again targeted the H1 and we've set the color to green and all of that together
creates these different web pages in our multi-page website with the code that sets the style in three
different ways.
So did you get that right?
If you had any issues at all, be sure to go back into your code and fix anything that was wrong and
make sure that you've understood the three different ways of adding CSS.
In the next lesson, we're going to learn more about the different selectors that we can use to select
different parts of our HTML file.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Hi guys.
Welcome to another lesson on CSS.
In this lesson, we're going to be talking about CSS selectors, and this is going to help us choose
where to apply our CSS.
We've seen previously that we can create CSS rules by simply specifying two things.
One is the property we want to change and after a colon we get to specify the value to change that property
to.
In this case, what we're saying is we want to change the text color into a blue color.
Now we've come across some of these rules already and I'll be showing you in a later lesson in the next
section how to find out more about these rules.
But more importantly, in this lesson, what I want to talk about is the part outside of these rules.
It's the part that comes right here.
And this is known as a CSS selector.
What is a CSS selector?
Well, it's the part that selects the HTML in order to apply whichever rules go in between these curly
braces.
How do we know which part of our HTML file to make the text color blue?
Well, we look at this part and we can see we're targeting the H1.
Now, this style of selector is one of the simplest CSS selectors.
It's called an element selector.
And all it does is it selects a particular HTML tag.
So in this case it's targeting all h ones.
If your HTML is any good, you should only have a single H1, but it will be different for other tags.
If you had anchor tags or if you had paragraph tags or h twos or any of the other HTML tags.
Then when you select each of these in your CSS, it means apply to all elements that have that particular
tag.
Let's see this in action here.
I've got two files.
One is the index.html and another is our stylesheet.
And inside our index.html we've just got three H twos, red, green and blue.
And when displayed or run they will look like this.
Three headings.
Now if we go ahead and add a little bit of CSS and target our H two element, in this case we're using
an element selector which is simply the name of the tag.
And then after the curly braces, we can define whichever CSS rules we want.
In this case, turning the color of the text red.
If we go ahead and run this code, I want you to imagine what you expect to happen.
Which of these texts will turn red?
So let's go and run the code.
And once this change is incorporated, this is what we see Red, green and blue all turn red because
they are all h twos.
And this element selector here selects all of the h twos turning them red.
So pretty simple so far.
Now let's look at another type of selector, a class selector.
This requires a special symbol, which is the dot.
And then after that dot immediately with no spaces right here, then you have the name of the class.
So this is the actual name of the class that we're selecting.
In this case, I've called it Red dash heading.
And then after the curly braces again, we have the same CSS rule to apply.
Change the text color to red.
Now, what is a class?
Well, a class is something that we can add as an attribute to any HTML element.
And this attribute is kind of like saying, well, let's group these particular elements into a class.
So it's used for grouping elements in your HTML file to apply the same CSS rule to all of them.
So in this case, we've only got one H2 that has a class and the class is set to red text.
Now when I go ahead and write some CSS and I target the class, which remember requires the DOT and
then the name of the class, which is this, and it has to be spelled exactly the same.
These two cannot have any differences.
So you can't have, for example, a capital R or a capital T, This will not work.
Instead, what we have is our class selector and our CSS rule.
What do you expect will happen when the code is run in the browser when this CSS gets applied?
Well, it'll look like this.
It selects the only element that has that class and turns the text color red.
Now what if we had multiple elements with the same class?
So here you can see we've actually got two different types of HTML elements.
One is an H2 and another is a paragraph element.
Even though these two are completely different elements, we can tag them using the same class.
We're saying the H2 should have the class of red text, as should the paragraph.
Now if we write our CSS and we select again all the classes that have red text, then what do you think
will happen?
Well, in this case it doesn't matter if it's an H2 or if it's a paragraph.
As long as they've got that class, they've been converted into red text and the style has been applied
to these two HTML elements.
As you can see, the class selector is really versatile.
It allows you to group different parts of your HTML file into having the same styling.
And this can be really, really useful on multi-page websites with lots of different elements.
And you don't just want to select a particular type of HTML element.
The next one I want to show you is called the ID Selector and the ID Selector.
It has its own special symbol, which is a pound sign or a hash tag, and you put that pound sign and
again, no spaces in between the pound sign and the actual name of the ID, and this selects all elements
with a particular ID attribute.
This is what an ID attribute looks like, it's simply the words ID, and then after the equal sign,
we can give it a particular ID and it works similarly to the class selector, because if I go ahead
and select this ID of Main and I apply these changes, then you can see it will add the styling and
apply it to the only element that has that ID.
So then what is the difference between the ID and the class selector?
Well, the class selector can be applied to many elements, whereas the ID should be only applied to
one element in a single HTML file in a single HTML file like our index.html.
There should only be one ID of this particular name main.
It should be completely unique and this is the difference.
If you had say three h2's you can't select all of them using the element selector like this because
that would select all of the h2's.
Instead you apply the ID to the unique element that you want to apply your style to and it selects it
in the HTML file.
Again, remember, IDs are unique only one element per file and classes you can put on as many elements
as you like to group them together.
Another way that you can select parts of your HTML is using the attribute selector so we know that we
can create a HTML tag and add as many attributes as we like.
So we had attributes such as ID or class or draggable or source for the images or RF for the anchor
tags or alt for the images and a whole bunch more that will get to see in the future as well.
Now we can select these elements that have particular attributes or particular attributes values by
using this notation.
Notice the first part here is the HTML element that you want to select, and then using a set of square
brackets, these ones right here.
Then inside we can include the attribute that you want to select.
What this entire selector says is select all paragraph elements with the attribute draggable and then
apply this CSS style.
To it.
What does this look like in HTML code?
Well, here we've got three paragraph tags, but only one of them has the attribute draggable set to
true.
If we go ahead and apply the CSS style where we select the paragraph element with the draggable attribute
and give it this CSS style, then when this CSS is applied to our HTML, this is what will happen.
It will find the unique paragraph tag with that particular attribute.
Now you can go one step further with attribute selectors.
You can actually select the value of the attribute that you want to apply your CSS to.
So in this case, you can see we've got all three paragraphs with the same attribute.
All the draggable attributes are set, but the set to different values.
So the first one is set to true and the other two are set to false.
So now we can actually write our CSS like this.
We can select all the paragraph elements which has an attribute of draggable set an equal to false.
And what this selector is going to do all of this is it's going to look inside our file and it's going
to find these two paragraph elements in order to select and apply the CSS when this CSS is applied instead
of the first one, which previously was selected, we actually have the other two selected and turned
red.
This is again a really versatile way of applying CSS, but as you can see, it selects on different
things than what we've seen before.
The element, the ID or the class selectors, the final selector.
I want to talk about is the universal selector.
And it's really simple.
It's just an asterix.
And after the Asterix you have your CSS rules.
But what this means is it means select all.
And when you apply this, it doesn't matter what class you've got, what ID, what attribute set, which
different elements.
If you select all, it's going to apply the style to everything where the stylesheet is active.
And this is probably one of the simplest selectors to understand.
So now that we've seen all the different ways that we can apply our CSS to different parts of the HTML
using selectors, let's try an exercise where we experiment hands on and see if you've understood all
the concepts in this lesson.
Now, once you've downloaded and extracted the starting files and have it open in vs code, then I want
you to go into the index.html file and here you'll notice a couple of things.
Firstly, we've already set up the stylesheet for you, so we've got an external stylesheet set up using
a link and it's pointing to this file right here, the Style.css.
The part that we want you to do is to revise what you've learned about CSS selectors.
And I've set up five to do's for you and I want you to do them in order.
So start from one and then go to two and continue downwards.
What this is going to involve is for you to write actual CSS code.
I don't want you to actually touch anything inside the index.html because I don't want you to change
any of the HTML with the classes or values or IDs.
I want you to leave it exactly as it is.
And instead your job is to write the selectors in the style dot CSS.
Notice when you open up the style.css there's a little bit of CSS already here for you and I want you
to leave this alone.
Don't touch it, don't change it.
It's important so that the final styling looks right when we haven't covered all of the different CSS
styling rules.
In the next section, we're going to be talking about all of this in a lot more detail.
Where to find out about different rules and how to use them.
But for now, I want you to ignore this part and write your CSS below.
Similarly, I'm not expecting you to know which CSS rules to use because I'll provide all the rules
for you in to do one.
I want you to change the text color to red and to do two, I want you to change the font size or change
the text align and this is all going to be provided for you completely formatted.
So it's got the property, the colon and the value I want you to set it to.
Now, the part that you need to think about and where your challenge comes in is how to select.
The correct paths.
So how to select all the paragraphs, for example, or how to select parts with a class of this or an
ID of this?
So that is the challenge.
And this is what you need to do in this exercise.
And if you take a look at the preview right now, it's very plain, all black, no styling at all.
But if you take a look at the goal PNG, you'll see this is what the final outcome will look like.
It's going to be centered, it's going to have different colors and you can almost even use this website
as a revision tool because each of the bullet points are linked to a particular style of CSS selection.
This hopefully will be quite a fun challenge for you and if you get stuck, be sure to rewind a little
bit in the video to see how to do the different things as seen in the previous examples.
And I want you to really give it a good go before you continue and watch the solution.
Pause the video now.
Give this a go.
All right.
So the first thing we're going to do is we're going to pull up our preview to make sure we are doing
the right things.
And to begin the first to do is to set the CSS for all paragraph tags to this color.
Now, remember, I said we're not writing any code or changing anything in the HTML side.
We're doing it all in our CSS, but it's still really important that we look at what's in our HTML code
in order to complete each of the steps of the challenge.
The first one's easy.
We're going to target all paragraph tags and we're going to apply this CSS style.
So let me copy the CSS style, paste it in, and now I've got an error because I haven't selected what
this style should be applied to.
In this case, we're applying it to all the paragraph elements, so we're using the element selector
and all we have to do there is simply add the name of the tag and then apply it and you can see the
first line of our bullet is now read.
That's to do number one.
Done.
Let's move on to the next to do so.
In this one, we want to set the CSS for all the elements with a class of this to this CSS rule.
So let me again copy the CSS rule and then paste it below.
And now we're going to use a class selector and select all the elements.
So notice how we've got many elements with the same class, even though they're applied to different
elements, but we can select across them using the class selector.
The class selector, if you remember, requires the dot, and then immediately afterwards we add in
the name of the class, and then we enclose our CSS rule in between the curly braces again.
And what this has done is it's applied a larger font size to all of the HTML elements that have that
class applied to them, which is all the bullets here, but not the H one or H twos.
So that's to do number two done.
Next one is to set the CSS for the element with a particular unique ID and the ID is this one.
So which one has that ID?
It's this particular list element and we're going to set it to have access rule to turn the color green
with ID names or class names or attribute names, any of that.
It's very important that you don't make any spelling errors.
What I normally do is I normally just copy it and then paste it in so that I don't actually mistakenly
add a capitalized s or something else that I could write incorrectly.
So remember, the ID selector is a pound sign or a hashtag.
And once we enclose our rule inside that selector, you'll see bullet number three turn green, because
that is the only item and it should be only one item that has the same ID.
Now let's move on to To-Do number four, which is to set the CSS for the elements that have the value
attribute set to four.
And notice now that all of the items in the ordered list, I've set a value attribute.
And what this does, if you take a look at the web docs for the list item element is this attribute
can indicate the current ordinal value of the list item.
When you have a list item inside a ordered list by default, it starts numbering from one like so this
is this list item.
But because I've got that paragraph tag above and I want to format this so that we have an interesting
CSS exercise, I've set the value attribute so that the list starts from two, which is totally valid
and I've set it for all of the other items as well so that we continue the list.
In this case, we're going to use the attribute selector to select this value attribute and turn the
text blue.
Let's paste in the CSS rule and then remember, the way that we use the attribute inspector is we first
select the element in this case list item, and then we add some square brackets.
And inside the square brackets we add the attribute that we want to select, which in this case is called
value.
And if right now I already close these curly braces, so we select on that attribute is going to turn
all the list items that have a attribute of value set, which is basically all four of these.
Now, some of you might have noticed that bullet number three, which.
Remain green instead of turning blue like the rest of the list elements.
Now, if you're curious about why this is, this is to do with something called CSS specificity relating
to how specific the rule is.
Now, we're going to be covering this in Section seven for our advanced CSS module.
So that's something you get to look forward to in the future.
Now, if we want to set the attribute that we want to select to a particular value, which in this case
is the one that's four, then I have to go a little bit further and set this equal to four.
And now you can see it's only selecting this fourth bullet and turning it blue.
Now attribute selectors can be a little bit tricky.
So if you didn't understand this at all, be sure to rewind in the video and watch that section of the
video again, just to make sure that you fully understand what's going on before you move on.
The final to do is the easiest.
All we have to do is set all the elements to text, align to center.
When we want to select all the elements, we use our universal selector, which is the asterisks.
And then once we paste in this rule, you'll see now our preview looks exactly the same as what we wanted
for our goal Everything center aligned.
There's lots of different styling being applied and we've now managed to achieve all of the to do's
in our exercise.
So hope that made sense.
And it helped you review all the things we learned in this lesson.
Once you're ready, head over to the next lesson where we've got our final project for the section.
All right.
So now it's time for our final project of the section.
And in this project, we're going to be building a website to help you learn Spanish.
Now, you might already know Spanish, but I'm currently learning Spanish, and there's so much vocab
to get through.
I thought, Why don't we build a vocabulary flashcard website?
But a really, really simple one.
Using everything we know so far in this project, we're going to be creating a website where we list
the words in, well, in this case in Spanish.
It could be any other language you choose, and we're going to match it with an image of a particular
color so that we learn all the colors in our foreign language.
This is what the final website should look like.
We've got our word which is foreign in the color that matches the image.
And we've got our images all lined up as nice little squares so that we can scroll through this website
and learn the words for the colors in Spanish.
Once you're ready, go ahead and download the color vocab project starting files, extract it and open
it up inside vs code in the index.html.
You'll see that I've already set you up with some starting code.
If you go ahead and show it as a preview, you'll see some words for the colors in Spanish and the different
images for the different colors.
Now don't worry about the fact the images are all different sizes.
We're going to fix that with CSS very soon in the project.
First thing to note is we've already set you up with a link to an external stylesheet which is inside
Style.css.
But notice that we haven't created that file for you, so I want you to create a new file inside the
correct location by using this button in VS code and then name it once you've created it so that it
actually works.
And one of the things that I often check to make sure that my external CSS is linked up is to target
everything on the page and to set the background color to red.
That way you know that if actually does work, then it's linked up correctly and it's really obvious
when it doesn't like right now.
And the reason here is because my style.css is actually outside this folder.
It's just floating about somewhere and I have to get it so that it's at the location that I specified
in the external stylesheet link.
So I don't want you to change anything inside the index.html.
Instead, all of your work is going to happen inside the CSS file, which you will create and you will
incorporate into your project using this file path to make sure that you understand how file paths work
and how you can create this for yourself in the future.
Now, if we scroll down, you can see there's five different colors, five different images, and there
are some h2's and H ones.
In order to complete this project, I've created some steps for you in the to dos which you can follow.
Alternatively, you can simply look at the goal image and try to figure out yourself.
You can either use a stepwise approach in the to dos or you can use the goal and do everything yourself.
It totally is up to you.
But what you're aiming for in the final version of the website, which you can view by right clicking
on solution dot HTML, opening it up in the preview.
And the most important things I want to point out is that the images are squares.
They are 200 pixels by 200 pixels, so 200 pixels high, 200 pixels wide.
Secondly, the font weight of these h twos are different from normal h twos.
They're actually a lot lighter.
So we've set the font weight to be normal rather than the default, which is h to get bolded.
The next thing is that the color of the text should match the meaning.
So rojo means red azul means blue.
And because in our index.html I've matched each of them up together.
But also you can look at the IDs if you don't know Spanish words because we're learning them after all
right, so yellow is Amarillo, green is Verde and so on and so forth.
So I want you to make sure that these h twos have a text color that matches whatever it is supposed
to be.
So blue or orange or green or whichever.
So if you get confused, look at the goal dot PNG.
If you want to go step by step, then look at the to dos at the bottom.
But importantly, don't write anything or change anything in the index.html.
All your work goes into the CSS file.
Pause the video and give this a go now.
All right.
So let's run through the solution together.
So the first thing we're going to do is we're going to make sure that the solution folder is collapsed.
So it's not confusing.
And then we're going to select this folder and then add a new file, which I'll call style dot CSS.
Remember, the file name has to match what it's referred to here.
Exactly.
Sometimes you'll see people have styles.css, sometimes you'll see main dot CSS, but as long as the
file name matches, it doesn't really matter.
It's up to you how you want to name it.
Once I've created that, let's just make sure that my CSS file is properly linked up by doing that background
color change.
So let's change it to Red and then let's go ahead and preview this.
And if the background is red, then it means that it works.
So I can now delete this and get rid of that horrible background.
The next step is to go ahead and use CSS to style each of the color titles so that the color matches
the meaning.
The first one that we want to select is this H2, which displays Rojo and it has the ID of red.
So remember, IDs are unique, so we can simply select that.
So let's select the element with an ID of red and set its color to red.
And so we can do the same thing for the rest of the colors.
So now they're all matching with their meaning.
The next step is to use CSS to change all the color titles, to have a different font weight.
And this is what we want the font weight of normal.
If we want to select all the h2's, then we're going to have a problem because this one is also an H2
and we don't want that one to have a normal font weight.
We still want that to be bold.
We want these to have the lower font weight.
So what is unique to all of these?
Well, we've applied a class of color title to each of them, which this H2 does not have.
Then that means that we can simply select color dash title and then apply the font weight to all of
those with that same class.
And you can see that differentiates between this H2 and this H2.
And instead all of these which are grouped together have that style applied.
Now the final thing we need to do is to use CSS.
No, not HTML to make all the images 200 pixels high and 200 pixels wide.
How can we do that?
Well, we can simply select the image element.
So this is using an element selector and we can set the height to 200 pixels and the width to 200 pixels.
And there you have it.
All of our images are now squares matching the height and width that we've specified.
You can of course change this and personalize it as much as you like.
Change up the colors or change up the words, learn the colors in a different language, make things
even more beautiful using the styling that you've learned.
But in the next section, we're going to be covering more about different CSS rules and you'll have
more tools at your disposal in order to style your websites.
So I hope you have fun in this section where we introduce you to CSS once you're ready.
Maybe tomorrow, maybe the next day, head over to the next section and continue learning about intermediate
aspects of CSS.
For all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Now we've already used some CSS properties in order to apply to our different HTML elements, but in
this section we're going to do a deep dive into some of the most important CSS properties that you'll
see and use.
And we're going to start with CSS, color properties, some of the color properties you've already seen
previously.
I've shown you how you can set the background color of a particular HTML element by using the background
color property.
And previously we've been setting it to basic colors like red or blue or green.
And remember that the way that the CSS rules work is the first part is the property.
And the part that comes after the colon is the value that you want to set that property to.
So in this case, we're setting the background color of the HTML element, which remember contains everything
on our website.
So the entire web page to a color of red.
That's what that rule does.
Now, there are different types of color properties.
There's the background color, but you can also simply use the color property.
And what this does is it sets the text color.
So always check the docs.
If you're not sure which property does what.
Notice that in this case we've got two colors, which we've named Red and Blue.
Well, how do we know that we can use these colors?
And what exactly are they?
Well, they're called named colors.
And there's a whole bunch of them out there with poetic names like Cornflower Blue or Cadet Blue or
dim gray or olive drab, etcetera.
And you can find all of them by, of course, going to the developer documentation.
If you Google for docs named color, the first link should take you to this web page.
Alternatively, you can use this URL as well, and the syntax is pretty simple.
You simply use the name of the color and if you scroll through this table you'll see all the different
colors.
And don't worry too much about the CSS level one or level two or level three.
It just describes historically when each color was introduced.
So these were introduced first because it's basically the rainbow.
And then over time we got some more fun colors like cyan and dark khaki and all of these different colors.
So you can simply copy the name of the color and paste it into your code and you'll be able to see that
rendered in your website.
Of course, even though there's many colors available in the default CSS named colors.
But you still sometimes might want to have a more unique color palette.
So what do you do in that case?
Well, one of my favorite color palettes is color hunt.co.
It's a free tool that's created by designers for designers and of course, for us as well.
Here you've got professionally designed color palettes for colors stacked together that would look perfect
on any website.
You can imagine that if you select any of these random websites, maybe this could be the background
color of the website.
This could be an H1 color, this could be a subtitle or H2 color.
You have accent tones, you have main tones, and you can use all of these colors in your website.
But how do we use them if we don't have a name that's attached to it?
Instead, we've got all these numbers and letters.
What exactly are these?
Well, these are hex codes and they are a way of representing a larger number code for that particular
color.
So, for example, in this case, this is a color purple which is formed of three fractions, red,
green and blue.
And these are colors out of 255.
So if you imagine a fraction, 93 out of 255 red, 56 out of 255 green and one for five out of 255 blue.
And when you mix all three of these primary colors, you can get so many different types of shades.
So in this case, we've got 93, 56, one four, five.
So 93 out of two, five five, 56, green out of two, five, five and one, four five.
So a little bit more blue and we end up with exactly the same shade as this purple you see right here
converting that RGB into a hex code.
So a different way of representing that number.
We get this particular hex code.
What does this mean for you?
Well, when you're using something like color hunt and you want to apply these different colors to your
website, you can simply copy the hex code and use it instead of the name.
And even on the docs for the named colors, you can see their hex codes lined up next to the names,
and in code it looks pretty much exactly the same.
Instead of the name, you just put the hex code.
So now it's time to try an exercise.
Go ahead and download this zip file from this current lesson, extract it and open it inside vs code.
Once you're here, you should see it's a pretty simple website with just two elements inside the body
an H1 and H2.
And if we look at the preview, then you can see it's clearly a drab, black and white world.
We're going to change all of that by adding in CSS colors.
So you've got five steps that you need to complete here and you should follow them one by one and by
the end of all five steps, you should have a website that looks something like this with lots of different
colors and different background colors as well.
Pause the video now and give this challenge a go.
All right.
So let's walk through the solution together.
We've got the background color of the body, which is set to antique white, which is this color right
here.
And we've got the text color of the H one set to white smoke.
But you can also set the background color of the H one.
It's a property that's available on any of the elements and it simply takes the existing area of that
element and colors the background.
Now, that might have required a little bit of lateral thinking, but hopefully you got there in the
end.
And notice how in the H one we've got all named colors and in the H two, I've asked you to use hex
colors and this is just so that you have practice adding colors using the two different methods.
Hopefully you got there in the end.
Once you're ready, head over to the next lesson and let's learn more about formatting fonts using CSS.
Now, in this lesson, we're going to talk a bit more about the different CSS properties that we can
set for fonts so we can change the appearance of the text in our websites.
And we've already seen some of them, for example, the color property which sets the text color, but
there's other ones as well, such as the font weight, the font size and also the font family, which
is the typeface that we want to use.
Let's explore some of these newer ones.
The first one I'll talk about is the font size.
We can change the size of a font by simply using the font size property and then setting it to a particular
pixel size, as you might have seen me do already.
But if we think about it, what exactly does a 20 pixel font size mean?
How big is it really?
Well, this is how big it is.
One pixel is about 1/96 of an inch.
And the reason why we're using imperial units is because a lot of the sizing for websites and for design
work actually comes from the olden days of book printing, book binding.
And it was very traditional.
If you know how big an inch is, then you know how big one over 96 of an inch is.
It's absolutely tiny, but if you have no idea how big an inch is, then in metric units it's about
0.26mm.
That's about how big a pixel is.
It's 0.26mm wide and 0.26mm tall.
So it's a small cube that's very, very tiny.
There are other ways that we can represent the font size when we're writing CSS.
One common way that you'll see in addition to pixels is using something called a point.
A stands for a pixel and a P stands for a point.
Now how big is a point?
Well, it's a slightly bigger than a pixel.
It's about one over 72 second of an inch.
So that's just slightly bigger.
If 1.96 of an inch is 0.26mm, one over 72 of an inch is about 0.35mm, just a tiny bit bigger.
Now the point is actually often used in many different applications.
So when you select a 12 size font in, say, word, you're actually selecting 12 points.
So that means when you're using 12 points on your web page, you can expect that when a website is at
100%, it will look about the same as a 12 font on your word document.
In addition, there are some other ways of representing font size, the M and the M.
What are these units?
Well, the M is actually not pronounced M It's pronounced M, so it's pronounced in the same way that
this letter is in the alphabet.
Why is that?
Well, one M is defined as the full width of an M.
The letter M is probably one of the widest letters in the English alphabet, and this unit simply represents
that entire width.
But what does it actually mean when we use it?
Well, what it means is that when you set an H one to have the font size of one M, your CSS code would
look something like this.
Then it means that if it had a parent, for example, if we had a body tag that enclosed this h one
tag, then if this body had a font size of say, 20 pixels, then this h one if we set it to one M or
one M, then it means it's going to be a 100% of the parent size.
So it means it's going to be 20 pixels.
Now, however, if we set it to two M instead, then in this case it's going to be two times the parent
size.
So two times 20 pixels, which is going to be 40 pixels instead.
It's basically a relative size.
And I'm going to explain to you why this is important very shortly.
But closely related to the M or the M is the M, and it's got that extra word.
Ah, And basically it works the same thing.
It's a relative size, but it's now relative instead of to the parent.
It's relative to the root of your HTML file, which if you remember, the root is usually an HTML element
that encloses everything inside.
What is the difference then, between the M and the M?
If we take a look at this code where we've got a body tag that encloses an H1 and then we've got a footer
tag, which is one of the tags that you can use to define a section in your code for the footer area
of your website.
Then inside here we've got an H2 that's enclosed.
If I set my H2 to have a font size of two M and my footer had a font size of 20 pixels, then two M
is two times 20 pixels, which is equal to 40 pixels.
So this H2 is now 40 pixels.
However, if I go in here and I change this footer to have 80 pixels, then all of a sudden this is
going to change and it's no longer going to be 40 pixels, but instead it's going to be two times 80,
which is now equal to 160 pixels.
So it's moving relative to its parent size.
On the other hand, if I had set this H2 to have a size of two REM and I change the size of my footer
from 20 pixels to 80 pixels, then it does not affect this.
Whatsoever.
It still remains the same size.
It's only if I change the root element, which if you take a look, it's the thing that encloses all
of the rest of the code, which is normally the HTML element.
If I change this size to something larger, say 90 pixels, then that is the thing that will affect
this sizing.
So the main difference between the M and the M is the fact that this is a more consistent way of changing
the sizing.
So I normally recommend that everybody who develops websites when you're setting the font size to use
the REM, because the way that you have different things embedded in others.
So this H two is inside a footer which is inside the body, which is inside the HTML.
Then the relationship to the parent can very quickly get very confused and you don't know whose parent
you're referring to, especially when you're working in a separate CSS file.
So understand how the REM works.
Remember, it is a scaled size of the root one.
M is one x, the root size two M is two x, the root size.
And this is a much easier way to control the different sizes of various elements on your screen and
have more clarity around what's going on in the starting file that you downloaded previously.
I've got some sample code for you.
If we take a look at all the different ways of setting font size, you can see that we can use the pixel
size, we can use point size, we can use M REM, and we can also use named font sizes such as extra
large or large.
And when all of this is rendered, you'll see the different sizes in play.
The fact that a pixel is much smaller than a point, but these two are static font sizes and then the
M is relative to the parent and the M is relative to the root.
But these are relative sizes.
If you want to see this code and be able to edit it and change it and see it working, then download
the zip file from this current lesson called 6.1 font properties.
Once you've extracted it, open it up inside vs code.
Head over to font size dot HTML and you'll see exactly the same code as in the demo.
But in this case it's of course in VS code.
So you can change things such as the REM, the m, the different font sizes, the root font size, and
you'll see it reflected on the screen.
For example, if I change this root font size from extra extra large down to say, 20 pixels, then
you'll see that this paragraph change accordingly because its size is based on REM.
So have a play around with that so that you can understand what's going on.
There are some other font properties that I want to briefly cover.
One is the font weight, which is relatively simple.
You can have normal or you can have bold, and we all know what that means.
It just makes the font look a bit heavier.
But out in the wild you might see some other ways that people use to change the font weight.
In addition to the basic keywords, you can have a relative font weight which is relative to the parent
to have the font lighter or have it be bolder.
In addition, you can also use a number from 100 up to 900 to determine how light or how bold you want
the font to be.
And similarly, when we say lighter it basically minuses the number by 100.
And if we say bolder, it just makes it bolder by 100.
Somewhere along this range, in addition to font size and font weight, there's also the all important
font family.
And this determines what you want your text to look like.
For example, in this first example, we've got the font family that is set to Helvetica.
This is a particular typeface and the name is called Helvetica, but this is a mac specific typeface.
So there are many Windows computers that do not own this typeface.
That's why very often when we write a font family, we don't just write the font name, we have a comma
and then we have a backup generic font type.
So in this case it's a sans serif.
A sans serif is simply the type of font where all the edges are pretty much at right angles.
If you had these little feet or these little decorations at the edges.
Of your letters, then very often what you're looking at is a serif type font.
So that's the main two types of different typefaces.
And in later lessons, we.
Cover typefaces in more detail.
So you can either search for that lesson or wait until it comes up to learn more about that.
What is important, though, is having this generic typeface.
This means that when you have this set that Mac users will see this font, but Windows users will see
something that's relatively equivalent and it will be automatically displayed for them when it doesn't
work.
Now what if you have a font that has many words in it?
For example, times new Roman consists of three words.
Well, in this case, we can't simply just type it out like this and then have a comma.
We actually need the quotation marks around it so that we can tell the CSS file that there are spaces
in the name of the font family.
So just be careful about that when you're using it.
And because times new Roman is a serif type font, then the backup, the generic type is also a serif.
Now what if you want a completely custom font that maybe the user doesn't have?
Well, one of the best places to find free fonts is going over to Fonts.google.com.
And here you can find all sorts of different fonts and there are so, so many for you to choose from
and you can browse to your heart's content.
Now I want you to do this with me.
Go over to Fonts.google.com, find a font that you like.
So maybe I really like a particular font and if you click on it, sometimes you'll see that it has different
font faces for the different weights.
So there's Bold, which is 700 or regular 400.
But then other fonts you might see in here doesn't actually have any weight other than just the regular
one that you can use depending on which of these type you have.
Simply select the weight that you're interested in.
For example, with this font, maybe I want the medium size, and with this font, maybe I'm just going
to select a regular one.
And once you've selected that, if you go to the top right corner, you can see all of your selections.
So you can remove all or you can remove the ones that you're not interested in.
But either way, you should end up with a font that you want to include.
Now make sure that that link is selected and then copy that over to your starting file.
So select the font family dot html inside the head element just after the style tag.
Go ahead and paste all of that in and this is basically a link that is going to pull in the Google font
for any user on the internet.
So it doesn't matter if they have a mac or a PC or which fonts they have downloaded on their computer,
they'll all be able to access this font because we're including it in the link.
And then let's go ahead and copy the CSS rule, which Google has very helpfully included for us.
And if you scroll up, you'll see that I've again got an internal style set in here so that we can more
easily see the CSS alongside the HTML on the same file.
While we're doing the exercise.
Let's go ahead and create an H1 here and I'm simply going to write the words font family because that
is what this page is all about.
And then let's right click and show it in the preview.
Now I want you to set the H1 CSS style to the one that you just copied over.
Pause the video and do that right now.
All right.
So we need to target the H, one of which we've only got one so we can use the element selector and
then we paste in our CSS style as easy as that.
And you'll notice immediately that updates that font into our custom font from Google.
And it doesn't matter what you've chosen, this should always work as long as you've included all of
the links that are required and added in the relevant CSS.
Also on this page you'll see the different font families, for example, the Helvetica and the sans
serif.
Or on a windows.
The default sans serif will be an Ariel type font.
And then you've got serif type fonts, which are the ones with the little feet that I mentioned.
You've got these sans serif fonts and you've got all of these other generics such as cursive monospace
and fantasy cursive is a little bit curly.
That's how I remember it.
Monospace has all the letters occupying the same width, so similar to a typewriter or code, and fantasy
is usually something kind of wild.
And these generic fonts will be different depending on the computer that you use and the browser that
you use.
So you might not see the same type of fonts that I have here, but if you specify a specific font and
you make sure that it's linked to, then we should all be looking at the same font face right up here.
And notice how when we copy that over it specified the specific font, but also a backup font in case
these links didn't work or something messed up and it would default to a cursive font.
The generic cursive font would then look like this.
So the final thing I want to talk about in terms of text styling is alignment.
So text alignment.
And this, this property called text align where you can set it to say centered or you can set it to
the left or to the right.
And you've also got some values like start and end.
And basically start is when you have text that maybe starts writing from the right to left, such as
in Arabic.
And so in this case, the start is actually here and the end is here.
But then if you're working with Western text, then the start will be right here and the end will be
right here.
That's just a more flexible way of determining the text align.
But all in all, this is a pretty simple property and you can take a look at it in the docs to learn
more about what the other values in addition to start end are and try the demo to see how they work.
Now once you've done all of that, I've got a final exercise for you and that's located in the index.html
here.
There's a number of to do's I want you to complete and I want you to go through them one by one.
It involves changing some colors, changing some font sizes, font weight, font, family, the text
align and also changing a root element font size.
The important thing is that you don't change any of the CSS that's already included, but instead write
your CSS below in this internal style element so that you can quickly refer to the to do's and see what
you need to write in the CSS.
Don't worry too much about setting external CSS.
We're just completing this as a quick exercise.
And remember, while you're doing this, if you want to see what the end result should look like, go
ahead into the goal dot PNG.
To see all the colors and layout and relative sizes of everything.
Pause the video now and go through each of these two dos.
All right.
So let's go through the solution together.
Now, step one was to change the color of this particular element to a named color called coral.
And the solution should look something like this.
The second one is to change the font size of this element to two times the size of the root element.
Remember, to do that, we have to use the REM and two times the size is two REM.
I've selected it based on the size ID and I've changed the font size to that.
The next step.
I've changed the font weight of this element to 900 by using the font weight property and then we change
the font family of this element to use the caveat font with a regular font weight.
So I selected that font from there and then I added in all the required links just before the end of
the head section.
But outside of the style section, this is very important in terms of placement.
And then I added in the font family and a backup font in case it goes wrong.
Next I changed this particular paragraph element so that it's right aligned.
And finally I change the route, which is the HTML element to have a 30 pixel font.
And when that was changed, then the two REM one, which is the font size element here, actually changes
with it.
So it gets bigger or it gets smaller depending on the route size.
So hopefully that was easy enough for you to complete and it tested you on all the things that we learned
in this lesson so far.
Once you're ready, head over to the next lesson where we're going to learn more about CSS inspection
and how you can find out what is happening with your CSS using the Chrome developer tools.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Hey guys, welcome to another lesson where we learn more about CSS.
Now in this lesson, we're going to deep dive into CSS inspection and learn about the Chrome developer
tools that allow us to figure out what our CSS is doing and potentially diagnose any bugs or resolve
any issues.
As I mentioned before, the Chrome developer tools are a really powerful suite of tools that is completely
free and comes bundled with the Chrome browser.
If you are not using a Chrome browser, you won't get access to it.
And it's really important, at least for this course, that you've got the same browser as I'm using
so that we can go through these tools together.
If you head over to this URL, which we visited before in the last section where I showed you how CSS
works and how we can simply add CSS to make our website look beautiful, then we can use this as an
example to learn more about CSS inspection.
In order to bring up the Chrome developer tools, we go over to these three dots and then we go to more
tools and we go to developer tools.
Now you'll notice that on the right hand side of this selection, you have the shortcut for your computer
on how you can bring it up quickly.
On a mac.
It's usually set by default to command option and I on Windows it's normally control plus shift plus
I.
So holding down those three keys together.
But if you have the function keys up here, pressing F12 usually also brings up the chrome developer
console.
But the shortcut could be totally different for you.
So make sure you take a look over here to figure out what your precise shortcut is.
Another way of bringing up this developer console is simply to right click on any element you're interested
in.
For example, this button and then click on inspect and it will do the same thing.
But in addition, it will highlight in the HTML that element that you selected.
Now what if you wanted to select a different element while you're here?
Well, you can use this button up here to select an element visually so you can click that and then
say, okay, I want to look at the footer here, this paragraph, Well, then it will select it for
you in the HTML.
Or I want to look at this H1 so you can select it visually or you can select it using the HTML.
This is the Elements tab and we're going to be exploring a subsection of this, which is the styles
section.
Notice that when I select any of these elements, it shows me the styles that have been applied to those
elements.
For example, if we take a look at this button, at least in the CSS on version, you'll see that it's
got a background color that I've set.
I've set a color for the text and lots of other things that we don't need to worry about too much right
now because in the next lesson we're going to learn more about different CSS properties.
But the important thing is that notice if I go ahead and press that button and switch off all the CSS
and I select that button again, then you can see that most of the element style is actually all automatic.
Whenever you insert a HTML element, it comes with automatic preloaded CSS and that's what you're getting.
By default, it looks something like this, but when you actually apply your own CSS, then it gets
shown here and you can even see which file it's coming from.
In this case, it's the Styles.css right here and you can click on it to view the source code of that
CSS.
The next thing I want to show you is how you can actually change the CSS live in the Chrome developer
tools.
Right now you can see I've got my H1 selected and by simply clicking add I can add a style to this H1.
So I could say let's change its color instead of white to um, maybe black instead.
And you can see that reflected live over here.
Now I can switch that off by hovering over here and clicking on the button to put a slash through it
and it deletes that CSS.
Now, the important thing to remember is any of the changes that you make in the Chrome developer tool
does not affect your original file.
Previously, remember we looked at TechCrunch using the Chrome developer tools and we were able to change
the text by simply typing in the Chrome developer tool.
This does not change Techcrunch's website and some of you have asked Is this illegal?
Am I doing something bad?
No, it doesn't.
It's just you affecting your local copy that's loaded up inside the Chrome browser.
It doesn't affect any of the other users and certainly doesn't change anything on Techcrunch's servers.
Similarly, back over here, when we're editing the CSS, when we are selecting or unselecting or adding
new rules, it doesn't affect the actual website.
Even if you load up one of your local websites that you're developing and you change a whole bunch of
things, this is just temporary.
It's for you to look and try things out and.
See how you like it before you add these rules into your actual CSS source code.
And you can further confirm this by seeing that I've got an H1 that says color black.
But if I go into the sources, my style.css for this file and I look in this file, you can see that
nothing has changed here.
There is no H1 that has a color of black.
Again, I recommend don't worry too much about the different properties.
There's lots of them that's coming up that we're going to talk about.
But the main thing to focus on here is how to use the inspector to understand other peoples as well
as your own websites and how the CSS is laid out.
If you go ahead and inspect on one of these anchor tags.
So when you click this and hover over it, you should see an A tag show up.
So click on it and it'll select it in the HTML.
Now, if you look over here, you can see that it's got some default properties that have been striked
out and the reason for this is because when we apply a CSS rule that conflicts with some of the automatically
applied rules, such as the color of that anchor tag, remember, by default, the color of any anchor
tag is blue to start with.
But here we've got one that's white.
Well, we've overridden it simply with this line.
So if I switch this off, you can see the other one switched back on.
But if I do have my own rules, then it can override other existing rules.
So how do you know what's actually being applied to your CSS element?
Well, that's where the computer tab comes in, because when you click on it, you'll see the actual
color in terms of RGB.
So how much red, green and blue is being applied to the text color and other properties as well.
And it removes all of the craziness of all this crossing out stuff.
And you can actually see in one place what is being applied.
Now another feature of Chrome Developer tool that I find really useful is to go over to the three dots,
go to more tools, and remember, this is the three dots for the settings of the Chrome developer tools,
not the one for Chrome.
This is easily confused, but when you go here and you go to more tools, you should find CSS overview.
And this is a neat feature where you can select capture overview and it will show you a bunch of useful
things like, for example, that there are two background colors here.
There's a sort of whitish gray and there's a sort of purple going on.
There's two different text colors, white and black.
And we've also got information on the different fonts that are being used on the web page.
I find this really neat when I come across a website that I really like and I'm trying to figure out,
Oh, what font is that?
Well, it seems like they're using Helvetica Neue or What color is this green Exactly.
Well, I can actually find out simply by looking at this inspector and maybe I can copy it for my own
use later on.
So you can see the colors, you can see the fonts.
And for now, we won't worry too much about the last two.
We'll come to that in later modules.
Have a play around with the CSS inspector and I want you to take a look at selecting different elements,
looking at their styles, trying to add some styles in the Chrome developer tool and looking around
at some of the other things we've mentioned.
Once you're happy that you know how to do that, I want you to head over to this URL at Brewery dot
Github.io slash CSS dash inspection and I've created a website for you to inspect in this website.
We've got some things that are on the screen and this is an H1 and H2 and a paragraph tag.
Now I want you to use the CSS inspector to answer these four quiz questions and once you've put in the
answer, click submit and you'll see if you got it right or if you got it wrong.
Pause the video and try to complete this challenge.
All right.
So the first question is, what is the named color of the body?
Well, what is the color?
So let's go ahead and pull up our inspector and let's select the body element if we haven't already
got it selected in the HTML.
And let's take a look at what styles are applied.
You can see it's got a background color that's being applied.
And if we switch it off, you can see it changes it to the default, which is white.
So this is the background color of the body and it's called Alice Blue.
If I type that in here and click submit, then I get my answer correct.
Now let's move on to the second question.
What's the font size of the H1?
Let's select the H1 right here and let's take a look at the font size that's mentioned here.
Well, it says it's three REM, which makes it a lot bigger than the default.
So let's type three REM in here, hit submit.
And we got that question right to number three is what is the font weight of the H2?
Select the H2, look at the font weight, its font weight 500.
Okay.
And hit submit.
And finally, what's the font family of the paragraph tag?
So let's select the paragraph tag and then look at the font family.
And this is a little bit tricky because it's actually not applied directly to the paragraph, but it's
actually one of the automatically inherited parts.
So you can see down here it says the font family.
And also if you go to computed where everything's all stacked up together, as I mentioned, where you
don't have to go through the entire list of what's being striked out, what's being applied, etcetera.
You can see the font family is Ariel comma sans serif.
So Ariel comma, sans serif and hit submit and we get all our answers correct.
So did you manage to do that?
Did you manage to use the inspector to figure out the answers to these questions?
If not, be sure to review the previous parts of this video so that you understand exactly what's going
on before you move on to the next lesson.
Hey, guys.
In this lesson, we're going to talk about some other really important properties and the ones that
you might have already seen if you've been doing a little bit of inspection around the Internet.
And these are margin padding and the border properties and these three properties, along with width
and height, form a really important CSS concept known as the box model.
So what exactly is it?
Well, if you think about a typical website here, I've created one called I Love Bacon.
Then you've got different components that are on screen, different HTML elements.
And even though we can't really see it effectively, each element is a box in itself and we can change
the dimensions of those boxes by changing things such as width and height.
So in this case, I've made my bacon much, much bigger.
And that invisible box around the element describes how it would be laid out on screen.
If we have an element that has a height of 300 pixels, we can change that height to allow our element
to take up more vertical spacing on the web page.
And when this happens, it pushes the box of any other elements lower on the web page.
Now, similarly, we can also change the width of an element to allow it to take up more space horizontally.
And we can either do this using pixels as defined here or we can use percentages.
So in this case, we've gotten our blue element to take up the entire width of the website and that
can be done using percentages in addition to width and height.
We can also set a border on each of the HTML elements.
If you imagine, again each HTML element being a box, then this would be the border of the box.
And the way that the border property works is a little bit different from what you might have seen before.
It can take three values separated by a space.
The first value that you should provide is the thickness of the border.
And this, as you can see here, is the thickness of this line.
If I made it thicker, then it would look like this.
And so we can provide a pixel value for the thickness as the first item.
Now, the second item is the style of the border.
You can have, for example, solid, but you can also have a dashed line, in which case the border
would look something like this instead of a solid line as we've gotten here.
And finally, we've got the color of the border in which you can set to any named color or hex color
as we've covered in the color properties lesson, These are three items together determine what the
border should look like.
So if I was to change the border from ten pixels to 30 pixels, then we would get a lot thicker of a
border.
But remember, the important thing is that the height and the width of your HTML element, your box
does not change.
It's exactly the same as what it was before.
So this border actually goes outwards rather than inwards.
And that's the important thing to remember here.
Now, once you've defined a border, you can further modify it with more specific rules.
So, for example, in this case, I've got a around 30 pixels solid black border around my element.
But then afterwards on the next line and this is very important where this line goes, it has to go
after the point where we've created the border.
In this case, I'm saying I want the top of that border to be zero pixels instead.
And, well, the way that these rules are evaluated is first they will look at this line creating this
border, which is 30 pixels all around.
But then once it lands on the next line, it evaluates this rule and sees that actually I should amend
the top of the border to have zero pixels.
So effectively getting rid of the border at the top here.
This border width works similarly to the way that the border property works, namely that it can take
a maximum of four values.
The first value is the top, the second is the right, third is the bottom, and the fourth is the left.
It goes in a clockwise direction.
In addition, you can also just provide two values for the border width.
And what that does is it sets one and three.
And then it sets two and four.
For example, if my border width, I had set to zero pixels and 20 pixels, then what that would do
is it would set two and four, which is the left and right to 20 pixels, and then it would set one
and 3 to 0 pixels.
This then becomes top and bottom.
And then we've got our left and right.
Now, another property I want to talk about in regards to the box model is something called padding.
And this is most easily seen when we have content such as text.
So in this case, imagine that this blue box is a paragraph element.
And in the paragraph element we've got Hello world repeated many, many times.
This paragraph element has got a border property and it's a solid black border, measuring 30 pixels
wide all around.
If at this point I add a padding property to this element, then what would happen is it would push
my border out by 20 pixels.
And in this case, I'm pushing it by 20 on all sides.
And notice how, again, in this situation, the height and the width of this box does not change.
It's still the same.
The padding simply adds this padding or space between the element and the border.
In addition to the padding, there's also something known as a margin.
And the margin is actually the part that's outside of the border.
So here again is the border in between the border and the width and height of the element.
Is the padding and the part between the border and any other content that's on screen is the margin.
So in this case, we've added a margin of ten pixels on all four sides.
If you imagine, we had two elements, each with the same padding, margin and border, then this margin
or this distance between the two elements in this case will actually be 20 pixels because it's ten pixels
from this side and ten pixels from this side.
And it adds this spacing between elements that you would not get with the padding.
So that is the main difference.
In your inspection, you might have seen the box model already shown in the inspector, and it shows
you the margin, the border, the padding and the width and height.
So that's what all of these different colors represent.
And when you take a look at the box model on inspection, then you can actually change each of these
values to see how it would look differently if you head over to this address.
App dot Github.io forward slash box dash model, and then we go ahead and open up the developer tools
and we select on the first image here, which shows a daytime world and we go into the box model that's
under the Styles tab.
If I go ahead and add a margin right here, let's say, I don't know, 100 pixels, then it's going
to add that gap.
Did you see it just now, that gap between that image and anything that's below it?
And similarly, if I add a little bit of a margin above, say, 100 pixels, then you can see it adds
a gap between that image and the next element above, which is that paragraph tag.
However, if I added the padding as 100 pixels, then you'll see it add the space as well.
But it's actually inside the border of the image.
If this element actually had a border which will set as a ten pixels solid black, then you can see
how that padding goes to a different place versus where the border goes.
And this box model is going to come really, really handy when you start to try and lay out different
items on your website determining how they look and where they're placed Relative to each other.
The final thing I wanted to mention is that padding and margin, similar to what we saw for the border
and also the border width function in that same way where we've got one, two, three and four values
that we can provide and if we provide a different value for each of them, so zero, ten, 20 and 30
pixels, then this will determine how it looks on all four sides.
And you have to remember that this is where the first value is second, and it goes around in a clockwise
direction.
Again, with the border width, you can change to only provide two values.
So say ten pixels and 40 pixels, then this is going to be applied to the top and the bottom and also
the left and the right.
So this is just a particular way of how these three properties can accept multiple values.
If you only set one value, say ten pixels, then that's going to affect all sides in addition to the
boxes that are created by elements, we can actually create our own boxes independent of that, and
that's really useful when we want to group different bits of content together so that we can style it
together.
Or maybe we want to lay it out together.
For example, here we have an image and maybe I would want the image to have a caption and I would probably
want to style these two bits together so I can wrap a box around these two elements.
And the way that I would create these artificial boxes is through the use of a HTML element, which
is called the content division element.
There was no point learning about the div element before we could learn about CSS because these are
completely invisible unless you apply CSS style to it and the whole purpose is to act as an invisible
box that can contain content in between the opening and the closing tags.
In the middle, we can put as many elements as we want and we can group them into separate boxes known
as Divs.
So here I've got the HTML code from that website I showed you earlier with the two versions of our world
the Morning and the Evening View.
And it's really simple and I've only just taken the body section of the HTML.
But here notice that we've got a paragraph tag and an image tag and they're grouped together through
the use.
Of this div element and notice that the div element doesn't really do anything else other than act as
a container to group this section together so that it's separated from other content.
For example, this section right here.
And now we've not only added meaning to our HTML by saying this is one section of content and this is
another section of content, but in addition we can style them differently in CSS.
When we run our code, this is what the website would look like.
You would not see any of these div elements, but if we were able to see them then they would look like
this.
Grouping our elements together because these divs are invisible.
Sometimes it can be really hard to debug them and understand what's going on or more likely what's going
wrong with your CSS.
So there's a free Chrome extension that I recommend you download to make this process of debugging a
little bit easier and hence that's why it's called pesticide.
We're going to use it to get rid of bugs in our CSS.
I'll add a link to this Chrome extension and all you have to do is click add to Chrome and then add
extension.
And once you've got it, then you should be able to look inside your extensions and then open it up
to activate it.
Now what does it do?
Well, let's demo it.
In addition to the suite of developer tools you've got now, you've also got the pesticide working for
you.
And once you activate it, you can see these div boxes now show up on screen and you can also see the
different elements highlighted in boxes and it really helps you diagnose what's wrong with your box
model when it does go wrong.
In addition, if you close down the Chrome developer tools and hold down the control key, when you
hover on each of these boxes down at the bottom of the screen, you can see how it tells you which node
you're actually hovering on.
So in this case, I'm inside a div and it shows you if there are any classes or IDs on that div as well.
And then here I'm hovering on an image element and here I'm hovering on a paragraph element and this
can be really helpful for you to see exactly what's on screen and almost like put on night vision goggles
so that we can see our divs and our elements and their alignment and their sizing.
Finally, we're going to use everything that we've learned and put it all together in this exercise.
We're going to write some code and apply our knowledge.
Go ahead and download this zip file from this current lesson, extract it and open it inside vs code.
Now, once you've done that, open up the index.html and you should see a bunch of to do's.
I want you to follow each of the steps one by one, just as if you were a web developer following client
instructions.
And we're going to use everything you've learned so far in order to create something that looks like
this.
Now, I've marked up this page a little bit so I can show you the important parts of the requirements.
For example, notice that here I've said 20 pixel padding, and that applies to the distance between
that paragraph tag and the border.
And then here I've said it should have a 20 pixel border at the top and at the bottom, but then only
a ten pixel border on the left and the right.
And notice that the layout is very specific here.
Each of these boxes should be touching corner to corner.
So you're going to have to figure out how to use the margin property in order to push these boxes around
so that they're literally aligned right up to each other on the same pixel.
I'm going to leave you to pause the video and go through each of these requirements and hopefully you
will be able to create a website that looks like the goal image.
Pause the video now and complete this challenge.
All right.
So let's go through the solution together.
Now, the first thing you'll notice is we've created three Divs and I've added a paragraph tag into
the first div so that we can see our padding a bit more easily.
The next thing is we've set each of the divs height and width to a pixel size, namely 200 pixels.
Next I've added a paragraph element inside the first div so that we can see any padding that gets added
very easily.
And I've set the first div to have 20 pixels of padding all around with a black ten pixel border and
that you can see under here.
Now notice how I've used different IDs for the different boxes or divs, and this way I can uniquely
identify each div and set different styling to them.
Next step.
I've targeted the paragraph element so that I remove any of the margins that go on it, because if we
preview our solution and open this up inside Chrome, you can see that by default, each paragraph element
actually gets one m of margin at the start and the end.
So if I cancel this, you can see how it pushes that away from the containing div.
So we wanted to add the zero margin so that we would have it centered and it would not be affected by
its default styling.
Next we had you set the second div to have a 20 pixel border, top and bottom and ten pixel border left
and right.
And if you remember from the lesson this is achieved through that multi-value method of setting border
width.
So the first value is top and bottom.
And then after space we have the second value for the left and right.
And even if you hover over this, usually the code is quite helpful for pulling up the reference on
this and it tells you how the rules work.
So that's a quick tip.
Finally, we set the third div to have a ten pixel border and I wanted you to set the margins so that
they would each touch corner to corner.
Now that could be done either by trial and error.
Alternatively, you can also work it out because if you think about this first div right here, it's
got a width of 200 pixels, so this part is 200.
But in addition it's also got a border of ten pixels all around.
So then we have to add ten and ten here.
Now that takes us up to 220.
But in addition, remember that we added 20 pixels of padding all around.
So then there's 20 here and 20 here.
So then if we add it all up, 200 plus 20 plus 20 plus ten, ten, that ends up with 260 pixels.
So then we know that we have to push the second div over by 260 pixels and we can do that using the
margin left setting, which is how we manage to push this box over.
And in a similar way we can work out how much to push this third box as well.
I hope this challenge was sufficiently challenging enough for you, but don't worry if it's not because
there's way more challenging layouts are coming up in the rest of the course and you're going to be
able to flex your box model muscles in the coming sections as well.
But once you're ready and you've reviewed your code and fixed any errors, head over to the next lesson
where we've got the final project for the section.
All right.
So for the final project, we're going to be building a motivational poster website and we're going
to make our own memes.
You might have seen some of these around the Internet.
There are the serious ones which are based off these 90 seconds motivational posters where you have
some sort of title and you have some sort of motivational text like potential.
We all have the tools for greatness within us, and I believe that is true.
And you've got a cute little Arctic fox.
But also there are some pretty hilarious ones like Coolness.
You may be cool, but you'll never be for popped collars.
Cool like this guy.
So the goal is to make our own website where we can create our own motivational poster.
The important part of a motivational poster is there is a image that is going to be big.
There is a border around the image.
So we now know all about borders and we can do that.
We have a black background and that is easy because we know all about CSS color properties.
We have a big main title, which we're going to use a custom font for to mimic this font a little bit
better.
And finally, we have a paragraph at the bottom and we're going to figure out how we're going to center
things on the screen, how to add borders and how to apply basically everything that we've learned so
far in this section.
Go ahead and download the starting project files for the Motivation Meme Project and extract it and
then open it up inside vs code.
I've created the task in a sort of to do list breakdown for you.
Now the main thing is that it's your website, it's your project, and as with all the projects in the
course, it's totally up to you how you want to create it.
But there are some caveats and it's important that you touch all of the learning points.
So these six points are important, and after completing these six points, you can change your website,
you can mess with it however you like, but want to make sure that everything you've learned so far
has consolidated and it all makes sense.
We're going to use a custom font from Google called The Libre Baskerville, which looks somewhat similar
to the motivational main title font.
You should add your own image into the images folder under the assets folder.
I've got an example image in here for you just in case you want to use it, but I recommend putting
in your own images just for practice.
And that image should have a five pixel white border and the text should be center aligned and you should
adjust the margin so that the image and text are centered on the page.
Now, this is going to be the trickiest part because centering elements using CSS is a whole science
in itself, but we're going to do it simply.
We're going to horizontally center the div by giving that div a width of 50% to take up 50% of the screen.
And then if you think about it, there's only 25% left on each side.
So if we have a margin left of 20% on that div, then it should push it into the center.
In addition, you might find it useful to set the image to have a width of 100% so that it fills the
entire container div so that you're not having to center the image along with the div.
Some of these hints are only going to make sense once you get started writing the code for it, so don't
worry too much about it.
Now I'm just highlighting certain points in the to do so that when you get to it, to pay more attention
to these parts and these helpful tips, which you'll probably need because especially at this point,
number five, it's quite a difficult task and it will take some time for you to figure out how to get
it to look like this.
And if you want to push the div down vertically, then I recommend just adding a top margin to push
it down by a pixel amount.
It doesn't have to be spot bang in the middle of the center because as I said, that is a whole science
in itself and we're going to be covering it in coming sections, but it's just a little bit more complicated.
So we're going to judge it by eye for this project for now, in order to get something that looks like
the goal image, I recommend putting the H1, the paragraph and the image inside a div.
That way you can center the div on the screen and you won't have to mess with all three elements and
their centering, which is already a hard enough task.
Finally, you're going to use your developer doc reading skills and learn by yourself about a property
called text Transform and figure out how to make the H1 look uppercase like what I've got in the solution
goal website.
All of these elements are on screen.
We've got the white board around the image, we've got the black background, the white text, the custom
font, and our H1 is totally in uppercase without us having to type it in uppercase.
So that's where that text transform property comes in.
And notice how this entire content div is roughly somewhere in the center, horizontally and vertically,
just judging it by eye.
It's not perfect, but as long as you find the perfect avocado, everything else is easy in life.
Pause the video now and complete this project and once you're done, come back and I'm going to walk
through the solution code with you.
All right.
So hopefully that wasn't too hard.
If we take a look at the solution HTML, you can see that I've completed all of those tasks with a small
HTML and a small CSS file, so it shouldn't be too hard.
Now, some of the steps are pretty self-explanatory, but there's a couple of things I want to just
briefly touch on.
One is you will need the Google font links in the head section if you want to be able to have that custom
font on screen.
And this is the custom font.
In addition, we want to have all our elements inside a div so that we can style it all together.
And that's quite important in terms of positioning.
So I've created a class for the div.
In this case you could have also used an ID, but if you were going to extend this website then it's
safer to use a class.
So you might be able to reuse the CSS in the future.
The poster is the part that is more or less center aligned and we use that trick with setting its width
and setting its margin, using percentages to get it more or less in the horizontal center.
And then I simply set a 100 pixel margin top, just judging it by eye to get it somewhere in the middle.
And I added the custom font and the border to the image and made the image 100% wide so that it would
fit fully into that poster div if you had any problems.
This is a time where you can look at the solution code and look at your own code and see if there's
any fixes you want to make.
And once you have, then you can also modify the website any way you like to personalize it and make
it your own.
Hey guys,
welcome to Day 45 of 100 Days of Code. Now,
today, we're going to be getting back to coding with Python,
and we're going to be learning how to scrape the web for data
using a module called BeautifulSoup.
Now we've been working with APIs for quite a while now,
and we know that
we can use a website's API to access their data or to interact with the
website using code.
But some websites don't have an API or their API
doesn't let us do all the things that we want to do.
So this is where we start thinking about using web scraping
where we look through the underlying HTML code
of a website to get hold of the information that we want.
So the aim of today is to learn how to make soup,
but not this kind of soup. We're going to be making BeautifulSoup.
What exactly is BeautifulSoup? Well,
it's a module that helps developers like us make sense of websites.
We could think of a lot of websites as a bit of a spaghetti soup,
even something seemingly as simple as the Google front page,
when you right click on it and view page source,
you can see that it's horrendously complicated.
And if you wanted to make sense of this webpage and pull out the relevant parts
of the data,
then you'll need an HTML parser like BeautifulSoup so that you can
find and pull out the HTML elements that you're interested in from this
soup of jumbled HTML code.
And once we've mastered this skill,
then we'll be able to take any website, for example,
Empire's 100 Greatest Movies Of All Time,
this is a huge list of a hundred movies that apparently everyone should have
watched at some point in their life,
and we can pull out the relevant parts to us
namely the title and the ranking of each movie
and we're going to use it to compile a list of movies that we have to watch so
that we can look at the list, cross out the ones that we've already seen,
and then pick at random one from the list so that we can watch all of the
hundred movies of all time. That's the goal.
And once you're ready head over to the next lesson and we're going to get started
using BeautifulSoup.
In this lesson,
we're going to get started using a library called Beautiful Soup to pass an HTML
file. Parsing
the HTML file is the first step to extracting the data contained in a website. To
get started, the first thing I want you to do is to head over to
the course resources and download the starting project for today.
It's called bs4-start and once you've extracted it and opened it in
PyCharm, then I want you to take a look inside. First, we've got an empty
main.py file
which we're going to write  in order to use Beautiful Soup and extract the data
that we want. And the data is going to come from this website.html.
Now, a really nice thing about PyCharm is when you have an HTML file,
you can always just click on your favorite browser icon here
and it will open up the website as it is.
And you can see that this is a simplified version of our HTML CV page that we
built on day 41. Now,
if you've skipped day 41 to 44
because you already know HTML and CSS,
then have a quick read through the HTML.
It's a very simple document with a bunch of different HTML tags,
attributes like class and ID,
and also a list. I've kept this as simple as possible
just so that it's easy for us to work through it
when we're trying to get hold of things
using Beautiful Soup. In the course resources,
I've also got a link to the Beautiful Soup documentation.
So this is where you can find out everything that you can do with Beautiful
Soup. But I wanna walk you through some of the most commonly used components.
Beautiful Soup,
as they say, is a Python library for pulling data out of HTML and XML files.
So HTML and XML are both structural languages and they're responsible for
structuring data like the data in a website using these tags.
And the great thing about Beautiful Soup
is it's super easy to use, and it can save you hours or,
days of work to get hold of the data that you want from a particular website.
And you can see the documentation's also been translated by kind users into some
other languages as well. So if you find it easier,
then these languages might help you as well. Now,
the first thing I have to do here in my main.py is to actually get hold of
this particular file.
Now you might remember from previous lessons,
how we open a file in Python.
So have a quick think and see if you can figure out how to get a hold of the
content in this HTML file as a string or as a piece of text.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge. Just as a hint,
you might need the keyword with and the
keyword open.
All right. So the way we do this, as we say with open,
and then we provide the name of the file, which is website.html.
And we can open this as a alias name which we'll call file,
and now we have access to this file and we can say file.read.
Now, once we've read this file,
we can save this to a variable
which we'll call contents. And once we've gotten hold of these contents,
then we can start using Beautiful Soup.
So as always, we always start with the import,
so the name of the library that we're going to install is called bs4
and this is Beautiful Soup version four
which is currently the latest version of Beautiful Soup.
And from this particular package, we want to import the class
which is called Beautiful Soup. Now,
if you downloaded this project from the course resources,
you should see that there's no errors underlining this line because bs4 has
already been installed. If you see some squiggly underlines,
just click on the red light bulb and install the required module
which is called bs4. Now,
once we've got hold of our BeautifulSoup class
then we're ready to make soup. In order to make soup,
we use our BeautifulSoup class and we create a new object from that class
and we pass in a string. So this is the markup,
and that's the same M that you find in HTML and XML.
It's the hypertext markup language and the extensible markup language.
So the markup refers to basically all of this.
We've already gotten hold of it through this contents
so let's go ahead and pass that in.
So now that we've specified what it is we want to use to create our soup,
the next thing we have to provide is the parser.
This is going to help the BeautifulSoup module
understand what language this particular content is structured in.
As they mentioned, it can parse HTML and XML
so we have to tell it what particular type of document we've got.
And the easiest way is just to use the Python
html.parser.
So after we've parsed in the text that we want to turn into soup,
we're going to add the parser as html.parser.
And this is going to help Beautiful Soup understand these contents.
Now, depending on the website that you're working with, occasionally,
you might need to use the lxml's parser. And do that,
all you have to do is say import lxml
and then install this particular package, and here in a string
instead of using html.parser, you can use lxml.
And this is basically just a different way of parsing or understanding the
content that you're passing to Beautiful Soup.
And I found that with certain websites the html.parser might not work
and you might get an error that tells you something about your parser not
working. So then you might consider using lxml instead.
So this one line of code basically completes our parsing.
And this soup is now an object that allows us to tap in to various parts of the
website, but using Python code. For example,
if I wanted this title tag out of this whole website,
all I have to do is say soup.title.
And now if I print this soup.title,
you can see that we'll get the title tag being printed out in its entirety.
Once Beautiful Soup has made sense of this website by parsing the HTML,
we can now tap into that object
which is the HTML code as if it were a Python object.
So we can tap into the title,
but we can dig even deeper. Instead of just tapping into the title,
we can also get hold of other things like the title.name,
and this is going to give us the name of that particular title tag.
So remember this gave us the title tag,
so all of this, and this next stage drilling even deeper into the name of this
tag, you'll see that it gives us title.
So the name of this title tag is called title,
and we can also get hold of the string
which is contained in the title tag by simply using .title.string.
And you can see this is the actual string that's inside that title tag.
If we think about it, this entire soup
object now represents our HTML code.
So I can also actually just print out the entire soup object.
And you can see that this is basically just all HTML.
And if you want to, there's even a method called prettify
which will indent your soup HTML code.
So now, compared this where everything's all on one line, with this prettified
version where everything's all indented properly and easier to read.
In addition to getting the title tag, we can also get hold of,
for example, the a tag.
So this is going to give us the first anchor tag that it finds in our website,
which happens to be this one right here.
And we can swap that with maybe the first li or the first paragraph.
Essentially what we're doing with beautiful soup is we're just drilling down
into this HTML file, finding the HTML tags that we're interested in,
and then getting hold of the
either name of the tag or the actual text of the tag.
But what if we wanted all of the paragraphs or all of the anchor tags in our
website, how would we do that? In the next lesson,
we're going to dive deeper into searching through websites for all of the
components that we're looking for. For example,
all of the P tags or all of the anchor tags.
And we're going to see how we can refine our search and specify exactly what it
is that we want. So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now there's two things you'll notice here.
One is we're only getting hold of the first, for example,
p tag or a tag, but we're not getting hold of any of the other ones.
So what if we wanted to get all of the anchor tags,
all of the paragraphs in our website? Well,
then we can use a function that comes with Beautiful Soup called find_all.
This is probably one of the most commonly used methods when it comes to
Beautiful Soup
And here we can search by a bunch of things. We could search by name,
so we can say
find all of the tags where the tag name is equal to a.
So this is going to give us all of the anchor tags,
right?
And if I print that,
you can see that it gives us a list and it gives us all three of the links that
exists in our website.
And if I change this to p for example,
then it'll find all of the paragraphs and we can change this to basically any of
the tag names in our website. Now,
what if we wanted to drill a little bit deeper?
We've got a list of all the anchor tags,
but what if I only wanted the text in that anchor tag?
So I just wanted this part. Well, how would I get hold of all of them? Well,
firstly, we would probably need a for loop.
So we could say for tag in all anchor tags and we can loop through all of those
anchor tags and use a method called tag.getText.
And now if I go ahead and print this,
you can see that it's basically going to print out all three of the text that is
in all three of the anchor tags that it found. Now,
what if I didn't want to get the text,
but instead I wanted to get hold of the actual href,
so the link, right? So let's print our all_anchor_tags again.
All right.
And you can see that there is a attribute called href
which stores the actual link that the tag goes to.
So very often, you'll want to isolate that link. So how would you do that?
Well,
you can tap into each of the tags and you can use another method called get.
And here you can get the value of any of the attributes.
So if I pass in href here and I print this,
then it's going to give me all of the links and it's not going to give me
anything else. It's basically just stripped out the link
which is what I'm interested in. Similarly, when we use find_all
we can also find things by their attribute, so the moment we're searching by
the tag name, but we can also get hold of things
by the attribute name. For example,
if I wanted to get hold of this item, I can of course search for an h1.
But what if I had lots of h1s? Well,
then I could isolate it by this ID. So I could say,
soup
.find_all which will give me a list of all of the items that match the search
query,
or I can use the find method to only find the first item that matches the query.
In my case, there's only one thing I'm looking for.
And this particular tag has a name of h1
but it's also got a ID of name.
As you can see,
this ID is equal to name and it's also an h1 tag.
So this will give us that particular element.
So if I print out this heading and let's comment out everything else,
then now you can see I've just isolated that one h1.
And this also means if I just add another h1 here,
...
and I run this code again,
that is not going to show up because I've said it has to have a name of h1
and an ID that matches this particular value.
Now, as you can imagine,
you can also do the same thing with the class attribute.
So we can say,
...
soup.find because again, I'm only looking for one.
And the thing that I'm looking for has a name
which is a h3
...
but it's also got a class that's equal to heading.
So I'm just going to copy that and paste that in here. Now,
one of the things you'll get here is an error because this class keyword is a
reserved keyword in Python.
And what that means is that it's a special word
which can only be used for creating classes. Now, in this case,
we're definitely not creating a class or an object here. Instead,
we're trying to tap into an attribute.
So in order to not clash with the class keyword,
this attribute is actually called class_re.
Now it's going to look for all of the h3s where the class attribute is
equal to heading.
Let's go ahead and print this section_heading and you should see now we'll get that
h3 with the class of heading show up. And again,
if we wanted to get hold of the text
that's contained in that h3, then we simply use the getText method,
or if we want to know the name of that particular tag,
then we can say .name.
Okay.
And if we want to get hold of the value of an attribute, for example,
get the class value,
then we can do something like this. Now,
while that's a pretty good way of selecting elements from the entire website,
there's certain cases where it might not work. For example,
at the moment here, we've got our three anchor tags.
If we wanted to get hold of a specific anchor tag,
let's say we wanted this anchor tag, then what do we do?
Well,
then we could just simply find all of the anchor tags and then find the first
one. But as you can imagine,
this is a incredibly simple website.
Most websites will have thousands
if not tens of thousands of links. In that situation,
it's really hard to know which particular link you want from the list of all of
the anchor tags.
So we want to have a way where we can drill down into a particular element.
What's unique about this particular anchor tag? Well,
it sits inside a strong tag and it sits inside an emphasis tag and it sits
inside a paragraph tag, which itself is in the body.
We can narrow it down using these steps. In our current website,
nowhere else is there an anchor tag that sits inside a paragraph tag.
And you'll remember from our previous lessons on CSS that you can use CSS
selectors in order to narrow down on a particular element in order to specify
its style. And if we were to write CSS code,
then it would look something like this.
So we would select first the paragraph and then we would select the anchor tag
and then we can specify what the style should be
.
Now. When, we're using  Beautiful Soup,
we can also use the CSS selectors.
I can get hold of that company URL by simply saying soup,
and instead of using find or find_all, I'm going to use select_one.
There's select and select_one. Select_one will give us the first matching
item and select will give us all of the matching items in a list.
Now we get to specify the selector as a string. And again,
I'm going to use the same selector that I showed you before.
So we're looking for a a tag  which sits inside p tag.
And this string is the CSS selector. So you can write anything in here
really. This means that we'll be able to get that anchor tag.
And then once I've gotten hold of the company URL and print it out,
you can see its that exact anchor tag that we wanted.
We don't have to just stick to the HTML selectors.
You can also use the class or the ID in your CSS selector.
So remember, to select on an ID,
we use the pound sign. So let's say
we want to get hold of this h1, which has an ID of name,
we can say #name,
and now this is going to be equal to my name.
And if I now run it, you can see that last one,
the element that was picked out is the h1 with the ID of name.
And finally you can use a CSS selector to select an element by class.
So for example, here, we've got heading and here we've got heading as well.
So if we want to select all of the elements that have a class of heading,
then we could say soup.select so this will give us a list
and then the selector is the first item that goes into the method.
So similar to this, we can have this keyword argument there or we can delete it.
And this selector will be using the .heading in order to select the element
that has a class of heading.
And this is now going to be a list if we print it out.
Right here.
So,
you can use everything that you've learned about CSS selectors to select a
particular item out of an HTML file.
And this is usually really useful because a lot of these elements will be nested
inside divs and the div will have an ID
and then all you have to do is to narrow down on the div and then narrow down on the
element you want.
So you can basically drill through using CSS selectors to get to any item you
want on the page.
Now that we've looked at how to find various items from HTML using Beautiful
Soup, in the next lesson, I've got a quiz for you
for you to have a go and have some practice at selecting and finding elements
from an HTML file using Beautiful Soup.
So for all of that and more, head over to the next lesson.
In the last lesson, we got started using Beautiful Soup and we saw how we could
use it to parse through the HTML of a website and pull out the pieces that we're
interested in.
Now it's no fun scraping a website that you've already got access to locally.
It's much better if we can get hold of something that's currently live on the
internet. So I'm going to go ahead and comment out all of this code,
and I'm going to be using Beautiful Soup to get hold of a live website and grab
data from it.
And the website that we're going to be using is the YCombinator's Hacker
News website.
This is where anybody can post a link to a news piece that they've discovered
that's tech related, or you could show off things that you've built.
For example,
I've just been looking at this guy's website that he built called My Desk Tour
where you can post a picture of your desk setup,
and you can see all of the tools and gear that they've got.
So we're going to be scraping the main Hacker News website
which is under this particular URL.
And this is usually where I go to find the latest tech news.
We're going to copy this URL, and we're going to go back to our main.py.
And in order to download the data from that website,
we're going to be using our handy friend, which is requests.
Now requests allows us to get hold off of the data from a particular URL,
which in this case is news.ycombinator.com.
And once we've made that request,
then we can save the data that we get back in a response variable.
And once we've got the response,
we can actually print out the text of the response
and this is basically equivalent to what we did when we opened up our HTML file
and we read the file contents, the text of the file.
So now if I go ahead and run this,
then you can see that it's going to print out loads of stuff,
but this is basically the code that represents this particular page.
So in fact, if you right click and click view page source,
you'll see that this is exactly the same HTML code that we're getting back over
here. So we don't actually want all of this jumbled mess.
What we're more interested in is the specific titles and the links
for each of these pieces.
It shows by default 30 of the top articles,
and this is ranked by an algorithm.
So it's most recent and also getting a lot of traction,
so a lot of upvotes,
but it doesn't represent the most upvoted items. So you can see here, in fact,
the most upvoted at least today anyways,
is Mozilla laying off of 250 employees.
So what if I wanted to get hold of the article title and the link of the post
from this page that has the highest point.
I don't want to have to manually check all of this. I want to do it with code.
So let's go ahead and scrape it. Now,
if I right click on each of these titles and I click on inspect,
then it takes me to the precise line of code in the HTML
that's responsible for rendering this component.
This is actually a anchor tag, so that's the
a tag. And the text in the anchor tag is the title of the article,
and then the href is the link that will take me to the actual story. So
if I click on this, you can see
it takes me to the actual news piece about Joan Feynman.
So what about this point? Well,
let's go ahead and right click on it and click inspect.
You can see this is in a span and it has a class of score while this title is in
a a ref and it has a class of story link.
So with those two pieces of information,
we can use Beautiful Soup to scrape all of the titles,
all of the links and all of their points.
And we can compare all those points and figure out which one has the highest
point on this page. So let's go ahead and do that.
So I'm gonna save the yc_webpage as the response.text,
and then I'm going to use Beautiful Soup to parse that webpage.
So BeautifulSoup
and then I'm going to pass in the actual HTML document that we want to parse.
So this is the YC webpage,
and then we provide the method to which we're going to parse it.
So html.parser, with an ER at the end.
And this is our soup. Once we've created our soup,
the next step is actually to dig in the soup and find the parts that we want.
So if, for example, if I want to get hold of the title of all of that,
then I can just say print soup.title. And now you'll see
it gives me the title which is Hacker News.
And that's the same as what you see here in the tab bar.
Now, what if I didn't want the title?
What if I actually wanted to get hold of this text here,
the title of each of these articles?
See if you can figure out how to get hold of this text and print it out in your
code. Remember it has the class that's a story link,
and it's an anchor tag.
Pause the video and see if you can get this title,
so yours might be different from what I've got on screen of course.
It depends on what's showing up on Hacker News on the day you are doing this.
But get the title of the first article printed out using BeautifulSoup.
Okay.
All right. What we want to do is we want to use find.
So we're going to find the first instance from this webpage where the actual
name of the tag is equal to a, so that's an anchor tag,
and then the class is equal to the story link.
So I'm just gonna copy that and paste it in.
Remember that in order to not clash with the reserved class keyword,
we have to add a underscore afterwards.
Now this should be our article tag.
And if we go ahead and print it,
then you can see that we get this exact anchor tag.
But if we want to get hold of the text that's actually in the anchor tag,
then we have to go one step further and call the getText method
that's also from Beautiful Soup. So now when I run that, you can see
I only get the actual text of the article.
Let's work on some of the other pieces. So this is the article text.
And then if we want to get hold of the article_link and the article_upvotes.
See if you can figure out how to complete these two parts as well.
So we want the HTML link that is, of course, all of this HTTP,
et cetera. And then we also want to get hold of the upvote
which is this little number right here.
It's inside a span with a class of score.
Right?
All right. So let's do the first thing, which is article link. Well,
we can actually already tap into the same article tag we already got up here.
And instead of saying getText,
we can use the get method to get the specific value of a attribute.
So what we want is of course, the href.
And then the article_upvote,
we'll have to tap into our soup and find the tag with a name that is span
because this is what we're looking for, and has a class of score.
Right?
Like this. Finding this particular tag is not enough.
This actually just gets us the tag. If we want to go further
and we actually want to get the text that's inside that span
which is of course the 19 points,
then we have to dig one step deeper and call the
getText method like this. Now,
if I go ahead and print out the article_text and the article_link,
and also finally the article_upvote,
then you can see
I get all three pieces of data that I'm interested in. Now,
instead of getting the first occurrence, I want to get all of the ones that are
on this page, so all 30 results. Now, in order to do that,
I have to change the find to find_all both here and here.
This way
we get a list of all of the articles and I'll get a list of all of the article
_upvotes.
So now it's going to be a little bit different. In order to get all of the text
and all of the link, then I have to use a for loop.
So I'll say for article tag in articles,
so articles is of course,
this list where we find all of the anchor tags with a class of storylink,
and then I'm going to loop through each one of those and for each of the tags,
I'm going to get the text and also get the Href.
I'm going to create two new lists, articles_text, and article_links.
And then I'm going to save each of the new articles into those lists.
...
Like this. And in fact,
we could probably simplify this a little bit by refactoring and renaming the
article text,
so the singular version into just text and the article_link
to just the link.
So now let's print out the lists. So the article_texts,
the article_links and the article_upvotes.
And this find_all
gives me a list and I can't call getText on the list.
So I'll also need to create a new list.
So I'm going to choose to use list comprehension here.
So I'm going to say for score in all of the scores,
we're going to create a list using each of those scores
and we're going to call getText in order to get each of them.
This is the same as writing out a for loop like this
but it's obviously much shorter. Now, when I hit run,
you can see that each of my lists are ordered.
So this is the first article's text, this is the first article's link,
and this is the first article's points.
What we want to do is we want to get the article_upvotes into a number format,
so an integer. And to do that,
we of course have to get rid of the points that comes afterwards.
But notice how each of these items are strings. So that means we can split the string
by the space and only get hold of the first item in that space.
Let me show you what I mean. So we've got all of the article upvotes,
let's go ahead and just print out the first item.
Right.
So now we just get the first item, which is 40 points. Now,
if I take that item and I call the split method,
then it's going to split every word in the sentence. By default,
it splits by the space. Now, if I run this code,
you can see
I get a list where I've got the first item being 40 and the second being points.
So it's basically split that string by the space.
Now the next stage is I could get hold of just the first item that comes from
that list, which is now 40.
If I now finally wrap it around an int,
then I can turn that into an actual number. Don't worry if your number changes
because you're pulling data live from a website. That upvote number can change in
any second. So this is the method
how we can get hold of the actual number from the upvotes.
Now we're going to apply all of this .split
and also getting hold of the first item into our list comprehension.
So for each of the scores that soup finds,
we're going to get hold of the text and then split the text and then get the first
item from the text. And then finally,
we wrap all of this around an int and turn it into an integer. Then if I go ahead
and uncomment all these lines of code,
then you can see I've got all of these numbers being printed out,
which means I can now sort them.
I want to get the index of the list item that has the highest value.
And then I want to use that index to pick out the title, text,
and also the link from these two lists,
because they're all ordered in exactly the same way.
So this first item corresponds to this first link corresponds to this first
upvote. And I want to pose this to you as a challenge.
Can you print out the title and link for the Hacker
News story with the highest number of upvotes?
Since we're working with three different lists at this point,
you'll have to find the index of the largest number inside the article_upvotes
list to accomplish this.
I'll give you a few seconds to pause the video before I show you the solution.
All right,
here's the solution. We can use the max function that Python comes with to get
the largest number from our article_upvotes.
And then we can print this largest number and see if it works.
So we've got 1,312. Now,
once we've gotten hold of the largest number,
then we can find its index from this list.
So we can say article_upvotes.index
and then we find the index of this largest number.
Right.
Now, if we hit run, you can see that we're getting index number 27.
So instead of just printing out that index,
we can print, instead, the article_texts with that index, so passing in the largest
index, and also the article_links and passing in the same index.
So now if I hit run,
you can see that the most popular article at the moment on this page has this
title text and this particular link. Of course for you
it will be different because it depends on what's currently showing up on Hacker
News. But if I refresh this page,
you can see that this article with 1,313 points is of course the most popular
article and it is the one that's about Mozilla.
You can imagine a use case for this where every day we scrape all the data on Y
Combinator and then we send ourselves through a text message through an email,
the most upvoted title and article
so that we can just look at that one thing.
And you've seen now how we can use the requests module to get hold of the text
the HTML code from a particular website,
and then use Beautiful Soup to parse through that website
and then to get hold of these specific parts that we want by using find_all or
find,
and then getting hold of the text or getting hold of the link or getting hold of
any other thing that we want.
So now that we've seen how we can do web scraping using Beautiful Soup, in the
next lesson
I want to talk a little bit about the ethics of scraping websites and when to do
it and what you can use the data you get from this
for. So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now that we've learned how to do web scraping with requests and Beautiful Soup,
it's time to step back for a moment and have a think about what we're allowed to
do and what might not be a good idea when we're scraping data from other
websites. Because after all, we don't own that data, right?
When you think about services like Google or Bing or any other search engine,
essentially what they're doing is they're constantly scraping data from all of the
websites that are listed on the internet.
And that's how they manage to get the information about what's on each page
and for it to show up for users who use their search service.
Now we have to step back for a moment and think about what is the law on web
scraping? What is legal and what is illegal?
Even as we were looking at Hacker News
just now I noticed that one of the articles in fact talks about the Genius law
suit with Google. And in terms of recent history,
there's two really famous cases, which is Genius suing Google
because they're saying that Google is scraping the song lyrics from their
website and they're actually displaying it without taking people to Genius.
So for example, if we're looking at the lyrics for Code m
Monkey,
you can see that Google automatically shows the lyrics straight inside of
Google.
That means that a user can potentially just get all the information they need,
say all of the song
lyrics to this song, without ever needing to visit the website where this lyric
might come from.
And that lyric might've been compiled by somebody on Genius.
Genius has a lyric annotation website. And of course,
as with all websites,
they rely on users actually visiting their website to make money or to show ads.
And if Google simply just shows it in their search results,
then this can be a problem for websites like Genius.
So they sued them over this and actually ended up losing the lawsuit.
Another really famous example of a lawsuit over scraping is hiQ versus
LinkedIn. So hiQ was scraping data from LinkedIn to use commercially.
So LinkedIn sued them and ended up losing in the lawsuit.
Based on these lawsuits,
we have a little bit of a better idea of what is legal when it comes to web
scraping and what is not legal.
The law actually seems to favor web scraping in the sense that you're allowed to
scrape a website data
as long as you think about a couple of things.
A lot of people have been writing about web scraping being legal based on the
LinkedIn versus hiQ case.
But the important thing to remember is that this is not a blanket sort of,
you can do whatever you want, scraping any website's data.
It only means that data that is publicly available and not copyrighted is
probably legal for companies to scrape. Now,
if you are using this data privately
like we are creating some sort of service for ourselves, then it doesn't really
matter. You're  just a user.
The difficulty comes when you're trying to commercialize that data,
when you set up a business and your business kind of involves somebody else's
data. That is a bit of a gray area. Now,
the things that we definitely know are
that you can't commercialize copyrighted content.
So if you scrape data from YouTube and you scraped the video data,
you can't just use that video on your own website. That is still not allowed
because that video is copyrighted and it's created by a YouTube user and the
copyright belongs to that user, not to you. So this is still illegal.
This might also apply to other things like a Medium blog post that somebody else
wrote or a piece of music that's being hosted on Spotify.
So copyrighted content you can't commercialize.
The second thing is that you can't scrape data that's behind authentication.
So if you have to log into Facebook in order to scrape the data,
then that's pretty much illegal.
And the reason for this is when you sign up as a user to any of these services
like Facebook or Twitter or Instagram,
there's a policy in there that you are agreeing to when you sign up that says
I agree to not use this data that I obtained on this website commercially.
But the data that is not behind authentication,
so any website that you can access as it is,
they can't bind you to a policy because you haven't agreed to anything.
So if the website has data that just out there in the open that you can access
without logging in and the content is not something that can be copyrighted,
then it is fair game legally. Now,
just because it's legal doesn't mean that you can actually do it.
A lot of websites will use captcha or recaptcha in order to prevent bots like
our Python code to get data from their websites. Every single time,
you're agreeing to one of these captchas, it's testing
whether to see if your actually a real human
or if you just a bit of code that is trying to access their data. Captcha was the
old version where you had the type in some squiggle letters and recaptcha is the
new version where you just have to tick a checkbox.
And it's actually really interesting how it works.
It looks at things like how your mouse approaches the checkbox,
how you maybe quiver a little bit before you actually check it
and other things like your cookies and the store data that they have on you.
Essentially, this service is used by websites to prevent people
to scrape their data using a bot. The other thing to remember is that,
you know, if you get sued by somebody like LinkedIn
because you're using their data and you're building a business on it
like hiQ is, then you can
at any moment be hit with a really expensive lawsuit
and you are going to have to pay a lot of money to lawyer up in order to contest
this and actually to fight them in court.
Unless you have the money to lawyer up and fight a company like LinkedIn,
it's really important to know what are the implications of web scraping,
especially when you're selling that data as a part of your business.
But in addition to the sort of legal side of things,
the other part that you should really think about is the ethics of web scraping.
This is basically putting aside what is legal and what is illegal,
but more thinking about what is right
and what's wrong because let's say that you've built a website and you've got
some sort of bot that's constantly scraping it for data, data that you know,
has been generated by your own users
that's really precious and that you might even charge for it, then,
is it really right for somebody to do that?
So I often follow the rule where if I don't want something to happen to me,
I try to not do that to others. In terms of the ethics, a couple of things
I would recommend abiding by is
if you come across a website and they have a public API
which we've already learned about and we know how to use, then always
always go for the API. If it requires an application, then apply for it.
Don't just go ahead and try to take their data when there's already a route for
you to use and access their data.
The second thing is to respect the web owner, because you know,
you don't want somebody to access your website a million times a second,
potentially making your website go down
or it could count as a DDoS
attack where it affects other users using the website.
When you are on a website,
they actually provide a way for you to tell what it is that you can scrape and
what it is
you can't. At the very end of the URLs after the.com or.co.uk,
if you put a forward slash and put robots.txt, you can see
this is the advice that they give to any bots that are potentially scraping
their website.
User agent is the person who is scraping, the person or the bot that's scraping,
and it tells you what are the things that it disallows.
So it doesn't want you to access the /vote?, /reply?,
/submitted?, /threads?.
So basically any of these end points are ones that they don't really want you to
use. For example,
here I've access the /reply?
which is a way to log in and reply to a particular comment.
Now that really shouldn't be a bot kind of action
because then it means the data that's generated
or the replies on here will be automated, right?
You actually want humans to comment and reply on the articles rather than some
sort of robot.
So these are the paths that they don't want you to access as a bot.
And finally, it even tells you a crawl-delay.
So this is the number of seconds that you should leave between each time you hit
up the website.
If we're writing Python code and we're using Beautiful Soup and response to
scrape data from YCombinator,
we could potentially get that code to run every fraction of a second right?
I could just write a for loop and just get this to keep scraping again and again
and again.
But that means that you're adding a lot of extra traffic and a lot of extra
demand on their servers which could potentially mean that real users,
real humans who want to access their website might not be able to do it at a fast
speed. So this is the reason why
when a lot of people accessing the same website,
say when a new ticket has been released for Glastonbury or some sort of big
concert, that the website can go down.
Its because a lot of servers can't cope with so much demand.
And when that demand is coming from a for loop,
then you can imagine that you're just adding a lot of extra work onto the web
server. So always respect their crawl-delay
if you see one in the robots.txt, and even if you don't see one,
just try to limit your rate so that you don't max out their server.
I recommend not scraping more than once a minute.
The YCombinator's of robots.txt is actually quite permissive.
It allows you to do pretty much anything you want,
but that's not true for all websites.
If you look at the robots.txt for LinkedIn,
you can see that they really don't want anyone to scrape it.
There is a bit of legal jargon,
there's a lot more disallows that you can see, right?
This is probably not a website where I would scrape their data and try to build a
company around.
So remember that this is a piece of text that the website owners have written
for you to look at to see what you can do and you can't do with their website.
So before you scrape a website,
always go to the root of their URL and check out their robots.txt and follow
the ethical codes of conduct when you're trying to commercialize a project.
So this is just the quick tip on the law and ethics of web scraping
just so that you don't get into trouble in the future.
Now here's a question.
Have you ever gotten into a situation where it's evening time and you wanna
watch a movie, but you don't know what to watch?
Like there's just no ideas coming to your mind and everybody's sitting around
the TV, like, what do we do?
So what if we scraped a list of the top 100 movies of all time and you pick one
from there?
So I recently came across this article on empire where they list the 100
greatest movies of all time.
And you can see that it goes from 100 all the way down to one.
These are supposed to be the top rated movies that have ever been produced
and I always wanted to watch through all 100 of them and check off each one as I
go along. So this is what we're going to be doing for our final project today.
You're going to be scraping from this website the 100 movies
and you are going to be using Python code to create a text file called movies
.text that lists them in order, starting from one.
Notice how each of these are just the titles of each of these movies.
Essentially, it's this part that you want.
And because the listing starts from 100,
you have to figure out how to flip it the other way so that you get it
starting from one. But essentially this is the goal.
And this is the project for today.
You're going to have to use what you learned about web scraping,
but also other things that you've learned along the way about Python.
Pause the video now and try to complete this challenge.
Okay.
So here I've created a brand new blank project,
which I've called top100-movies, but of course, that doesn't matter.
But in the main.py is where we're going to be doing all the serious stuff.
So the first thing we'll need is to copy the URL.
And at the time when you're doing this project, this URL might change.
So don't get it from here. Instead,
go to the course resources and copy the URL from there.
Once you've got the URL,
we're going to paste it into our main.py and save it as a constant.
In addition, we're going to have to import all the things that we need,
including requests,
and also the bs4 module
where we can get hold of our Beautiful Soup.
I'm going to need to install both of these because I don't have them yet.
So I'm going to click on the red squiggly line, install requests,
and also install beautiful soup. Once that's all done,
then my red squiggly lines should be gone and I can now start using my request
module to
make a get request to this particular URL. And I'll save the response
I get back as the response.
The actual HTML files,
so the website HTML, is actually under response.text.
So this is going to be the raw HTML text,
and this is what I'm going to be using to use Beautiful Soup to parse.
So now we make soup and we're going to use Beautiful Soup and we're going to
parse in our website HTML
and also the html.parser
which is the method which we're going to use to parse through this website.
Now that we've made soup,
let's go ahead and print out our soup in a predefined format so that we can just
see what it looks like.
So let's run our main.py and we can see that we've got basically that
entire website's HTML being printed out
here. Now comes the part where we need to use our Google Chrome inspector.
The part that we want from this website is just these lines. Now,
of course, if we didn't know how to code,
we would be here copying and pasting for hours on end,
and we would die of boredom or we'd get repetitive strain injury from doing so
much copy and pasting. But because we know code, we know better than that.
So let's get hold of the part that we want. Let's right-
click and click inspect. Now,
we can see that this lives inside and h3  with the class of title.
Now let's just check against one of the other pieces that we want and just make
sure that they've got the same structure.
So this is also inside an h3 with the class of title.
So basically as long as we can scrape this entire page and get all of the
h3 with the class of title and get the text that's contained inside the
h3 element, then we're golden. Let's go ahead and do that.
So instead of printing our soup.prettify,
I'm going to tap into soup and I'm going to say
find all. The thing that I want to find has the tag name of an h3 and it
has the class of title.
So that all came from our inspections right here.
This should get us a list of all of the
h3 elements with this class
and we should be able to save that into a variable called all_movies.
Let's print all_movies and see what we get.
Now, we've got a list of all of our h3s,
and we're now going to go one step further and fetch the text from within these
h3 elements. We do that using the
getText method. But we can't do that on the list
so we're going to use list comprehension.
So we're going to say the movie_titles is equal to a new list
and in this list,
each item is going to be formed from a movie in the all_movies list.
And this new item is going to be created by taking each of the movies in the
list and then calling getText on it. Now,
if I go ahead and print my movie_titles
instead of all_movies, then this is what we get.
We get all of the titles of all 100 movies.
Now we want to reverse this list so that we can put it into a text file starting
from 1, going down to 100.
So there's a couple of ways that we could do this.
One is we can use the Python splice operator.
So we add a set of square brackets
and then we add a ::-1,
and this will reverse the order. And as always,
you can find out this information either by Googling or through what you've
learned before in previous lessons. So this is the syntax that we're using,
which comes from the slice operator where we have a start,
a stop, and a step. So in this case,
the start is at the very beginning of the list,
the stop is at the very end of the list so
we don't have to specify those cause they're the defaults,
and then the step is basically -1 and this syntax will reverse that list.
Now, alternatively, you can,
of course also use a for loop where you create some sort of n in a range and the
range again, can take a start, stop and step.
So you could start at the end,
so the length of our movie_titles-1
because remember lists in Python start numbering from zero.
So the very last item is actually at the total number minus one.
And next is going to be the end, which is going to be zero, and finally
it's going to be the step, which is minus one each time.
So this time we start off from the very end of the list,
go back to the beginning, stepping by minus one each time. And this way,
if we print n,
you can see that this is going to give us basically all the way from 99 down to
1.
And we can use that to tap into our movie titles and get hold of each of the items
at index n.
And because range actually doesn't go beyond the end
we actually have to put -1 there if we want to get the very final one
which is number 100. And you'll notice also that there's a
bit of a typo here for number 93,
and this is actually not our fault at all.
It's in fact, in the original empire post.
They actually screwed up and this should be number 93. Because we're scraping
data we can't really be picky.
We're just going to end up with what we end up with.
So I'm going to choose the method where we actually take the movie title
and then we use the splice to get hold of it in reverse.
And I'll call that the movies.
And now we can create our new text file. So with open
we're going to create a new file called movies.txt,
and we of course have to change the mode two write mode so that we can actually
create this file. And then
because this file movies.txt doesn't exist, once this line runs
it's going to create that file and then we're going to write to it.
So we're going to say file.write
and we're going to write each of the lines in our list of movies.
We can again use a for loop
so for movie in movies,
let's go ahead and write the name of the movie
and then lets add a new line operator,
so \n, so that we get each of the movies onto its own line.
Now, finally, if I run this code,
then it's going to create our movies.txt. And if I take a look at it,
you can see it's now got all of the 100 movies listed on here from 1 down to
100.
And now you can go through this list and delete the ones that you've already
watched and then continue watching through the rest of the list.
I hope you had fun trying out web scraping by yourself in this project.
So that's all for today. Take a look at what you've done.
If there's anything confusing about the class or ID or HTML,
then be sure to review some of the lessons in the previous four days.
That's all for today.
Hey guys,
welcome to Day 46 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we've got a pretty special project for you.
It's a musical time machine project. So what does that mean?
Well,
recently I received a mixed tape from a friend and the mix tape contained all of
the top songs from the period of time when we went to school together.
And it was a really, really beautiful gift
and it was a really nice way of jogging your memories for that particular time
point in your life. This got me thinking,
and I thought about how music can take you back into a particular time in your
life as if it just transported you. By listening to the same songs that were hits
during that period of time
it was like as if I was being transported back and could relive a moment in my
childhood. And you might have the same experience.
Maybe there's certain songs that were really popular in your childhood that
brings back memories, or maybe for a particular relationship,
or maybe a holiday that you went on. Trying to jog these memories by using music
is a really,
really fantastic way of reminiscing and savoring some of your favorite moments
in time.
So what we're going to be building today is a Python time machine,
not the sort of time machine that might take a human back in time,
but it will go back in time to find the music that was in the top 100 shots that
was being played all over the radio so that you can relive that period of time
once more through music. Billboard
compiles a list of the top 100 songs.
So these are the most played songs during a particular week.
And if you go to chart/hot-100, you'll see it for the current week,
but there's also a feature where you can change the date to any data in the past
20 years.
So if we select a random date in year 2000,
you can see that the songs that come up here, and it depends on your age
but some of these artists
you might have never heard of like N Sync or Destiny's child or Vertical
Horizon. But if you listen to these tracks in order,
then it will be almost like you've been transported back to year 2000,
August 12 and you're just listening to the things on the radio.
This is how we are going to approach this task. First,
we're going to use Beautiful Soup to scrape the top 100 songs from a particular
date of your choice.
And then we're going to extract all of the song titles from the list,
and then we're going to use the Spotify API to create a playlist for that
particular date.
And we're going to see right through Spotify for each of the songs and add
those songs to our new playlist. So that by the end of this whole process,
we end up with a playlist that has the top 100 songs for a particular date in
the past.
So if you've got an anniversary coming up or a birthday coming up,
this might just be the perfect present where you create a playlist of the
top of that 100 songs that was playing on the day that you met your wife or your
husband, or maybe when you started a friendship or started a new job,
and you can send them this playlist as your gift to jog their memories and
remind them of that day in the past.
So are you ready to build the time machine?
If you are, head over to the next lesson while you will find step by step
instructions and a lot of challenges
that's going to get you to use all the skills you learned about how do you use
Beautiful Soup
as well as the Spotify API in order to complete this project.
So head over there now.
Hey guys,
welcome to Day 47 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be building a project that I personally find really useful.
It's a Amazon price tracker project.
So I don't know about you,
but I find it much more time-efficient to go online and search for the thing
that I need rather than have to go and browse through the shops,
find the thing I want and I just find the whole shopping experience,
really tiring. Whereas with buying stuff online,
you can simply go on Amazon, type in the thing you want,
and then a few days later you'll get it delivered straight to your door.
But one of the things I've noticed with online shopping is that the prices of
things vary dramatically from day to day. For example,
one of the things I've been really tempted to buy is a instant pot.
Um, it's basically it like a souped up pressure cooker.
It can do all the normal things like cook your rice
or work as a slow cooker, or pressure-cook your meat until it's really tender,
but it can even do crazy stuff like bake a cake in the pressure cooker or make
yogurt. This is something that I've had my eye on for a while,
but I haven't really even able to pull the trigger just because I can't really
justify paying $120 for something that I can sort of do with the other things
I have, right? You can bake a cake with an oven, you can, um,
you can make everything on the stove,
but it's something that I've really been fascinated by
and I wonder if I could cut down the amount of time I spend cooking so I can do
some other things like making Programming tutorials.
But one of the things I've noticed about this item or a lot of items on Amazon
is that the price really fluctuates.
So I've been keeping my eye on this product for a while now
and I've seen it go up and down even on a day to day basis sometimes.
And there is a really cool website that I discovered called camelcamelcamel.com,
where you can simply take a product's URL,
so you select the size you want, the style, the item, whatever it may be,
and then you take the URL and you paste it into camelcamelcamel.com
and it will give you the price history of that
product. isn't that cool?
So now you can look and get actual data on how much that product costs over the
past few months or year and you can now see what was the lowest price,
what was the highest price and see how it just fluctuates almost randomly.
Now, normally I would think that on big sale days
like black Friday or prime day, that you would get the cheapest price,
but actually, that's not always the case. For example, in this case,
the cheapest price for this item happened on May 25th,
which is, I think, just a normal day.
I don't really why it got price-dropped to that amount.
So let's say that we have set a price in our mind at which point I'm ready to
make a purchase. So for me,
maybe if this item drops down from $119
um, to let's say $99, then I'll actually buy it.
Now we can actually do this using what we've learned,
and then on that day, I get an email and it tells me Instant Pot price alert,
the product price is now $99.99 below your target price, go ahead and buy now.
So this is basically the functionality that we want to build using our knowledge
of Python and web scraping.
And our Python bot is going to be the one that's going to be constantly checking
for the price. And when the time is right,
it's going to be the one that's going to alert us, using an email,
telling us to buy so that we don't have to spend every day looking at the
website,
checking the price and doing something that our Python bot could do by itself.
The idea here is our little Python body is going to have a set time, let's say
9:00 AM every day where it checks that URL that we got.
So it's going to look at a specific thing on that webpage,
which is the price. So at the moment, it's right, registering as
$119.99
and the moment when it checks that price and it sees 99.9 something,
so anything that's below our set target of a hundred dollars,
then it's going to send us an email and give us an alert.
So then we can go to the URL and purchase is that product.
Instead of having to check it out ourselves,
we now get notified when our condition is met.
As you can imagine, this is going to involve a little bit of web scraping,
where we try to get hold of the value of this price and we turn it into a number
and we check it against our target price. And then when the conditions are met,
then we use the SMTP module to send ourselves an email.
So that's the goal of today's project
and I think if you're somebody like me who buys a lot of stuff online,
then this is going to be pretty interesting for you.
And I hope that will actually come in handy at some point as well.
So head over to the next lesson and let's get started building our Amazon price
tracking bot.
Hey guys,
welcome to Day 48 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be introducing a new technology for advanced web scraping,
and that is Selenium WebDriver.
Now you might have heard of Selenium WebDriver before
because it's probably one of the most well-known automation and testing tools
for web developers out there. But you might be wondering, well,
we already have Beautiful Soup. So why do we need to learn a new technology?
Well,
one of the things that we've really been limited by is we can't actually use all
the capabilities that browsers can do.
So when we load up a website with beautiful soup, we can't, for example,
type something into the website and then click on something. And to create these
chains of continuous actions
where we basically automate the entire flow of a particular job or a particular
task. To do that,
we're going to need to use Selenium WebDriver.
Now, this is a free tool and it basically allows us to automate the browser,
get the browser to do things automatically
depending on a script or a piece of code that we write. Now,
this is going to enable us to type as well as click as well as scroll.
Basically anything that a human pretty much can do on a website, you can do using
a Selenium driven browser.
It's kind of like we're building a robot and telling it what to do on a browser.
And selenium is the tool that allows the robot to interact and communicate with
the browser. And once we've leveled up,
we'll be able to do all sorts of things like, for example,
play web-based games like cookie clicker automatically to click on this cookie
all by itself using the code instead of us having to manually do it and then to
select upgrades and to purchase them, again, completely automatically.
If you ever wanted to be the best at cookie-clicker or any other web-based
game and you don't want to invest the time in scaling up and getting good at it
yourself, well then this is where automation might help you.
But on a more serious note,
you might use something like selenium to automate
filling in forms or transferring information from an Excel spreadsheet to a
online Google form,
or basically doing anything that is repetitive and tedious,
and you don't want to do it yourself.
So once you are ready, head over to the next lesson
and let's start learning about this new superpower.
In order to start using Selenium WebDriver,
we're going to have to go through a number of steps in order to set up our
browser and also to install and set up Selenium. Now,
the first step, if you haven't already, is to install the Chrome browser.
Now, while you can work with selenium using other browsers
like Firefox or Safari,
we're going to be using a number of Chrome developer tools. And also
in order for you to work alongside, to do exactly what I'm doing,
it'll be much easier if you're working on the same browser and the same
technology. If you haven't already got Chrome,
then head over to the course resources where you'll find a link to download the
latest version for your computer. And then once you've done that,
the next step is to download the Chrome driver.
And this is different from the actual browser. Again, in the course resources,
you'll find a link to all the Chromedrivers and we have to download the
version of Chromedriver that matches
the version of Chrome that we have. In order to find out the version of Chrome,
all you have to do head over to the top-right corner,
click on these three dots, go to help,
and then go to about Google Chrome. Here
it's going to tell you which version you are currently running.
And because you're going to be watching the video in the future,
this version might not be the same for you as you see right here. Currently,
I am completely up to date, so the latest
version that I'm running is version 84. Now,
all I have to do is go back here and find the version of 84 and download it.
So I just have to click here and it will take me to a
page where I've got three options. Now
if I'm running a Linux computer, then I click on this one. If I'm running a Mac,
I click on this one and Windows users will click on this one.
So I'm running a Mac so I'm going to take that particular file.
Now I'm going to have to unzip the file
and I end up with the actual Chrome driver.
Now the final step is to move this Chrome driver to a location of our choice.
I don't recommend keeping the driver inside the downloads folder
just because I'm sure you, as well as I, will and delete everything in the
downloads folder without a lot of inspection.
So we should move this Chrome driver to somewhere else,
somewhere where it's not likely to get deleted accidentally. In my case,
I'm going to go up a level with command up and here
I've got a folder that I've created called Development.
Now you can create a folder anywhere you like, um,
and then call it anything you like and move this Chrome driver over to the new
location. Now, the most important thing though is
to actually get the file path for this particular file. To do that on a Mac
all we have to do is right-click and go to get info.
And then where it says where we're going to copy all of that hit command+C to
copy. And then we're going to go into a new project that we've created
which I've named day-48. In the main.py
I'm going to paste this entire file path and I'm gonna save it as the Chrome
driver path like this.
Now the final step we have to add to this path is to add a forward slash to the
actual Chrome driver.
PyCharm should auto suggest the name of Chrome driver,
but this is now the full path that will take us to that particular driver.
Now, if you are on Windows, the process is pretty much the same.
Once you've downloaded the driver for your system, so Windows 32,
then you're going to go ahead and open it up and unzip it.
So click on this extract button so that you can actually extract everything
that's inside. Now,
it's going to ask you for a destination for where you want to put the extracted
file.
So we're going to click on browse and you're gonna select a location on your
computer. Now, if you don't have a preference,
I recommend just going to your C drive and then here creating a new folder
called Development.
And then inside this folder is where you're going to extract the Chrome driver.
So go ahead and click extract. And then once that's done,
we'll go and navigate to that location.
So it was in the C drive and it was inside the development folder.
And you can check and just make sure that your Chrome driver is sitting inside
here
and it's an application that you've extracted from the zip file. Now to find out
its file path, we're going to right-click and go to properties.
And then in the properties you see the location right here.
So here is the location
and all we have to do is just to select everything that's here and then go ahead
and use control+c to copy it
and then we can paste it into our file in PyCharm.
So we're going to paste it inside a string like this. And again,
we're going to save it into the name that is chrome_
driver_path like this.
And again, we're doing the same thing that we did with the Mac.
We're going to add another backslash and then add the name of our Chrome driver
like this.
So now that we've installed Chrome and we've downloaded the Chrome driver,
the next and last step is to install and set up Selenium. In my main.py
I'm going to import Selenium. And make sure that you spelled it correctly
so it looks like this.
And then we're going to click on this red light bulb as always to install our
package. Now,
once Selenium has been installed successfully,
I'm going to change the import statement.
I'm going to say that from this newly installed selenium package,
I'm going to import a module called WebDriver and it's this webdriver
which is going to be driving the Chrome browser and doing all of our automated
tasks.
Let's create a new driver from that new module.
So driver = webdriver. and then we can now instantiate any browser of our
choice. So in our case, we're going to be creating a Chrome browser to drive,
but you can see that you can also have Firefox or Safari and a large number of
other browsers.
We're going to choose Chrome and notice that this is Chrome with a capital C.
So we're initializing a new object here.
And the only required argument we have to give is the executable path.
So this is the path of the executable
that is the Chrome driver that we downloaded previously.
This is going to be the path and notice that it's the location where that Chrome
driver lives. And then at the very end,
we've got the actual name of the executable
which on a Mac is called chromedriver, on Windows it's chromedriver.exe.
Let's go ahead and pass this in here. And now that we've created our driver,
we're pretty much done with installing and setting up selenium WebDriver.
But if you're wondering what this Chrome driver is, well,
here's the way to think about it. We've got our Selenium package
which contains code for us to be able to interact with browsers.
Now it can interact with the Chrome browser which is what we're choosing to do,
but it can also interact with a bunch of other ones like Safari or Firefox.
Now,
how do we make sure that this package which can handle all three knows
specifically how to work with the Chrome browser? Well,
we're going to need some sort of a bridge that bridges the selenium code to work
with the Chrome browser.
And this bridge is provided by the Chrome driver.
So there'll be a different driver for a Safari,
and there'll be a different driver for Firefox.
And just by switching up those drivers,
it will tell selenium how to work with the latest version of these browsers.
All we have to do is now use it.
So the first thing I'm going to use my driver to do is I'm just going to get it
to open up a webpage. We'll use driver.get
and then we can pass in the URL here.
So it's going to be HTTPS
and then I'm going to go to amazon.com. Now,
if you're on Windows and you go ahead and run the code,
then it should run without any issues. But if you're on a Mac,
this is what happens.
You'll get a popup that says chromedriver cannot be opened because the developer
cannot be verified even though we know that this is actually created by Google,
specifically for the Chrome browser. So if this happens,
you're going to click cancel
and you'll get all of these errors because it's unable to access that file. Now,
in order to enable it, we're going to go to the Apple symbol, system preferences.
And then we're going to go to security and privacy and here,
because we try to run it before,
we've got something that says chromedriver was blocked from use.
So we're going to click on the allow anyways.
And now if we run this again, then it'll give us this popup
and all we have to do is click open.
And once we've done all of that,
now it's going to finally open up the site that we wanted to go to, amazon.com,
using this automated version of Chrome.
And you can see this because right at the top here,
it says Chrome is being controlled by automated test software.
That is our selenium.
The driver.get method effectively opens up a new browser window with the URL
that you've specified.
Now you'll also want to close down the window or the entire browser once you're
done with whatever it is you may want to automate or do. To do that
all we have to do is tap into driver and then we can call the method close.
Now, when I hit the run button,
you can see now it's going to open up amazon.com
and as soon as that page loaded, it pretty much just closed it down.
Now there's also another method called driver.quit.
Now what's the difference between close and quit,
you might wonder? Well, close actually just closes a single tab,
the active tab where you've opened up a particular page.
Now quit is actually going to quit the entire browser.
There are certain cases where you have more than one tab running at the same
time.
Close will close that particular tab while quit will actually quit the entire
program. Once I'm done using my driver,
I prefer actually just using quit to shut down the entire browser.
That way we can always start again from scratch and we'll have a fresh browser
to work with. And in the next and coming lessons,
we're going to show you how to use selenium to do basically anything that we
could do with a mouse and keyboard as humans,
but instead, we're going to automate the entire process and workflow.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.
Now that we've seen how we can get started using selenium webdriver to automate
our browser, the next step is to figure out how to use selenium
to find and locate specific HTML elements on the webpage.
Just between where we quit our driver and where we get hold of a particular
page,
I'm going to show you how easy it is to complete the previous task in day 47
where we try to get hold of the price of a particular item on amazon.com.
This was the item that we were interested in. This was the instant pot
and this is the price.
So if I go ahead and take this URL and replace this previous
just amazon.com URL with the URL that takes us to this page,
then, we can start inspecting on this particular element.
So here we've got the price,
which is that inside a span with the id of priceblock_ourprice.
Now, if I use that,
then I can simply say driver.find_element_by_id
and then I can paste in the id that I found just now,
and this is going to be equal to the price element. Now,
if I want to get hold of the price,
all I have to do is to print that element.text.
And now if I hit run,
you'll see our browser open up briefly to the page with the Instant pot
and then it'll close down and you can see the price printed right here.
Now,
the reason why this is so much shorter than what you did in the last project is
because we're driving a browser.
So the browser is already sending all of those headers,
all of the information that Amazon would expect from a actual user instead of
using a get request using the request package.
So in only three lines,
we can do so much more than we could do with Beautiful Soup. Essentially,
if you think about it,
Beautiful Soup is really good for just grabbing and scraping pieces of data
from an HTML website.
But it gets stuck when that website is being rendered
using JavaScript or Angular or React
and the content that was HTML was taking time to load,
or it requires certain conditions to load.
Whereas in this case,
we're effectively doing exactly the same thing as we would as a human,
going to this particular URL,
and then looking at this element and its value.
I wanted to show you a couple of other ways that you could find elements because
as soon as I write driver.
find, you can see there's a whole bunch of ways of finding elements
and there's a lot more methods than you have with Beautiful Soup.
One that I want to show you that's quite useful is find_
_element_by_name. If we go to python.org,
you'll remember from your lessons on HTML and CSS that most forms,
these input forms, will have a name attribute.
So if I go ahead and inspect on this search bar, you can see its got an ID,
it's got a name, it's got a type, it's got a role, it's got a class.
It has got a whole bunch of attributes.
Now I'm going to search for it by this name, which is q.
And I can do that by saying
find_element_by_name and then specify the name as q.
Now of course I'll have to change this URL to actually python.org.
And now once we've found our element by name,
we'll call it the search_bar,
...
and then we'll go ahead and print out this search bar.
Right.
When selenium locates a particular element,
it won't actually print out the actual HTML.
It'll give it to you as a selenium element like this. Now,
if you want to tap into its various attributes or text or tag name,
then you'll actually have to do that using a dot.
So we can say search_bar.tag_name,
and it will give us that that is an input tag.
Or we could say search_bar.get_attribute
and we can specify the attribute that we want the value for. So for example,
if I wanted to know what the placeholder value was,
then all I have to do is put, get attribute placeholder,
and then we can print that out.
And it will tell us that placeholder says search.
So that is something that you'll find people commonly use with Selenium, find
element by name.
And it's really useful when it comes to filling in web forms because most forms
will have elements that are organized by name because when the form is
submitted,
that name is carried along with the value of the inputs.
In addition to find element by name, you'll also see the usual ones.
So find element by class name, for example.
So if we wanted to get hold of this logo here,
then it has a class of python-logo.
So all I have to add here is the name of the class
which is python-logo
and this will give me that logo element. Now from the logo element,
I can actually get hold of things even like it's size.
So let's go ahead and print out the size of the logo.
Right.
It has a height of 82 and a width of 290.
So you can see that we can do a lot more with selenium than we could with
beautiful soup.
So that's fine element by ID, by name, by class name,
but there's also of course find element by CSS selector.
And this is probably one of the easiest ways of narrowing down on a particular
element.
Let's say that I wanted to get hold of this link to the docs.
Let's go ahead and inspect it, and it lives inside an anchor tag.
But you can see that this anchor tag has no class,
it has no ID, has no easy way of identification.
So how do we get hold of it? Well,
we can see that it lives in a paragraph element and then going further up,
it's inside a div with this particular class.
So this has a class of documentation-widget.
So that's pretty specific. So if we wanted to get hold of that anchor tag,
we could just say, well, inside this div of documentation-widget,
let's go ahead and find any anchor tags.
And to express that as a CSS selector,
we would specify the class documentation-widget,
and then inside the element with that class, we're looking for an anchor tag.
So this would get us our documentation link.
And now if I go ahead and print the documentation_link.text,
you can see that it's actually getting hold of this particular link.
And this is done
even though the actual link doesn't have any easily identifiable name or class
or ID. Now on a similar vein
sometimes it's extremely hard to even find an element even by CSS selector.
So if all else fails, one that will always work as the XPath.
The XPath is a way of locating a specific HTML element by a path structure.
So you've seen what paths look like right?
Users/angela/Development, et cetera. Well,
we can also express the navigation to a particular element drilling down from
the top of the tree to a particular node using the XPath.
Let's say I wanted to get hold of this link at the bottom, submit website bug.
Let's go ahead and inspect on it.
And you can see it's not particularly unique in terms of having an ID or a class
or a name. And even in terms of its structure,
it's sort of in this ul and then an li and it might not be that easy to get
to it. But here's where our XPath comes in handy.
Let's go ahead and right click on it and then go to copy, copy XPath.
And now we can go back to our code and use it to tap into that element.
So we'll say driver, and then we'll say, find_element_by_xpath.
And then inside here, we're going to paste our XPath.
Now notice that the XPath itself actually has some double quotes.
So we have the change
our double quotes into a single quotes so that it doesn't clash with the
inner double quotes. So like this.
Now once we found our bug link,
then we're going to print out the link and I'm going to get hold of the href
here.
So now I'm going to print my bug_link.txt just to prove that this worked.
And if I hit run,
you can see it opens up our browser and you can see it's managed to get hold of
that particular link using this very specific XPath
which looks very much like a file path that we've been using.
But it's essentially the way that we would navigate down through the divs,
the uls, the lis,
all the way down to that particular anchor tag. And the best part of all is of
course,
you can use this button here in Chrome to locate any element.
And then that would select its location in the code
and then you can right-click and then copy it XPath to get hold of that
particular thing.
Now I'm going to link to the documentation on XPath from w3schools.
It goes into a little bit more detail about how XPaths are constructed,
but you don't need to know this in order to work with them. As I've shown,
you can simply use the Chrome developer tools and it will help you get to the
particular item you're interested in.
Now we've been looking at finding elements using selenium,
but notice how we've always stuck to the singular version of that method,
find element. Now for every single method that I've shown you,
there's also a counterpart, which is the find elements.
So, for example, find_elements_by_css_selector. And of course,
this is just going to find you everything on the screen that matches your
criteria and give it to you in a list.
And there is a version of this for every single find method that we've shown
so far. In the next lesson
I've got a quick challenge for you to put into practice what you've learned and
to be able to locate any given elements on a webpage. So
for all of that and more I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now in the last lesson,
we looked at various ways of finding and locating elements on a particular HTML
page. Now, in this lesson, we're going to put all of that to practice
and you're going to get hold of all of these upcoming events. Now,
because these events are time-dependent,
the events that you'll see will of course be different from what I've got here.
But the idea is to get hold of all of these dates,
so all five of these, and then get hold of all five of these names,
and we're going to create a dictionary from these events.
And by the end of the challenge, you should be able to print out a dictionary
that's structured like this.
It's going to contain five items. Starting from zero to this is the first key
and then the first value is a dictionary with a key of time and a key of name.
And then the values corresponds to of course,
the first date and the first name.
So the first one we've got here is PyCon JP 2020
and you can see down here in this section, upcoming events,
the first one is this item.
So we're basically converting whatever is here in the upcoming events into this
dictionary format. That is the goal
and you're going to be needing everything that you've learned previously.
In addition,
it might be worth taking a look at the documentation for locating elements with
selenium. So I'll link to this page in the course resources as well,
and once you're ready, get inspecting and see if you can complete this challenge
and print out this dictionary. Pause the video now.
All right.
So our goal is to get hold
of this piece of data and this piece of data,
but just the text.
So we're going to have to first figure out how to locate these items.
So if I go ahead and inspect on this date,
you can see that it's inside a HTML element called time.
Now, in order to get hold of this element time,
we can of course use an XPath.
But the problem is that this XPath will be specific for this first item.
While we actually probably want to use a find method that can find all of the
dates and all of the event names.
So we're going to be using one of these multiple element finds.
So where it says find elements.
Now I think the easiest way here, at least for me,
is to think about it in terms of CSS selectors.
This is a time element that lives inside a li
which is inside a ul, but we still haven't found anything
that's unique to this particular structure here,
because if you take a look over here, when we look at the latest news,
it's also a time inside an li inside a ul.
And none of this is unique until we get to this div where we have a blog widget
while here we've got a event widget.
So there finally is a unique class name.
So we're going to use this class name and then find the time element. Back in our
code,
let's go ahead and tap into our driver and then use the find_elements_by_css
selector which is going to give us a list of elements that match the selector.
And the selector is going to be first find a div with this particular class.
So it has to have the class event-widget,
so we write .event-widget. And then after a space,
we specify the next thing we want to drill down to,
which is a time element.
So let's go ahead and just put the name of the HTML element like this,
and we'll get the event times as a list, hopefully.
So let's go ahead and print this out, event_times,
and because this is actually going to be a selenium object
rather than the actual text,
we'll need to use a for loop in order to actually see what it is.
So for time in event_times,
let's go ahead and print each of the time.text.
So once selenium has done its thing,
you can see it's now got hold of all five dates.
Now,
the next thing we need to do is to get hold of the event names,
and we're going to use a similar method.
So let's go ahead and inspect on the name and you can see that this is now a
anchor tag.
Now you might think that the solution will be just as simple as copying what we
had before and replacing the time element with an anchor tag element.
But you'll see as I write my for loop, for name in event_names,
print name.text.
This does not actually get us what we want because it also gives us the first
anchor tag in that div with class name event-widget
which is this 'more' link here. So if we don't want that more link,
we're going to have to be a little bit more creative.
This anchor tag is also inside an li while that more link is definitely not
inside an li. So we can narrow down on our selector by saying,
okay, so it's inside a element with class event-widget,
but then it's inside an li and then it's inside an anchor tag.
Now that I've updated that CSS selector, you can see when I hit print,
it gets us the actual names of all of the conferences.
So the final thing to do is to actually create our events dictionary.
You could do this using dictionary comprehension,
but I'm going to do it in a slightly more long form way
just so that anybody who's a little bit confused
it'll make it a little bit easier to understand.
So we're going to create a for loop and I'm going to use n. So I'm going to say
for n in range
and the range is going to be from zero to the length of event_times.
So it's basically going to be a range from zero to four.
Once I've got that range, now I'm going to add to my events.
The key of the event is the actual n, so the number,
and then the value of the event is a dictionary with the key of time
and also a key of name, like this.
Now the time is going to be from the event times and then getting hold of the
item at index n,
and the name is going to be event_names and the item at index
n.
Now the final thing we need to do is this gets hold of a selenium object and we
have to get hold of the actual text. So let's write .text.
And now we can print our events dictionary.
And once that's done, you can see this is in the exact format that we wanted.
We've got dictionary with five items,
each item has a dictionary in itself, time
and name of the upcoming Python conferences.
So did you manage to complete that challenge? If not,
it might be worth either reviewing CSS selectors
which we went through in previous lessons or reviewing some of the lessons
previously where we discussed
how to locate and how to get hold of the text from elements using selenium.
In this lesson, I have another super quick challenge for you
so you can practice setting up the selenium
webdriver in a blind project and scraping a different piece of data from a
website. This time we're going to work with the Wikipedia main page.
So you can head over to the course resources and find the link to this page
or you can just type it in. Back in our project
I'm going to create a new file and I'm going to call this
...
interaction.py. Now in this new Python file,
we're going to interact with this Wikipedia webpage and as a challenge to you,
the first thing I want you to do is to figure out how you can get hold of this
particular number and print it out inside our interaction.py.
Remember that you'll need to import selenium and also use the web driver to get
hold of this page and then find this particular number and finally print it out.
And then when you're ready to run it, all
you have to do is right-click and then run this interaction
.py and it'll work
and you should see the outcome being printed in your console.
So pause the video now and give that a go.
Right.
All right. So here's the solution. First,
we're going to go into the selenium package
which we've already installed into this project,
so we don't have to install it again.
And then we're going to import the web driver. Now using the web driver,
we're going to create a new driver from the Chrome browser.
So we're going to have to navigate to that path again.
Now this is my path and your path might be a little bit different,
but this is what we put to initialize a new Chrome driver. Now,
once we've created our driver,
now we can use the driver to navigate to our webpage
which is done using get.
And this is the URL which we'll copy and paste into here.
And once we've gotten hold of this page,
then we're going to try to narrow down on this particular element.
So let's go ahead and inspect it.
And you can see that it's inside an anchor tag with no particular identifiers.
There's no id, there's no name, there's no class.
But this anchor tag lives in a div that has an id.
So this articlecount is going to be a unique identifier for the div that holds
this particular anchor tag.
So we can narrow in on this anchor tag using our CSS selectors.
So we can say driver.find_element_by_css_selector,
make sure that it's element not elements. And then inside here,
we're going to put our selector
which is first the ID of article count
and that is going to be proceeded with a pound sign.
And then inside that div with that id,
we're looking for the first anchor tag.
Now notice that inside of that div there's actually two anchor tags.
But by using this find_element_by_css_selector,
it's only going to give us the first one that matches this criteria.
So this is going to be our
article count.
And now what we want to do is we want to print the article_count.text.
So now let's go ahead and right-click and run our interaction.py.
It should open up our browser to this page,
and now it should have found and printed out that number.
So this is what we've been doing so far,
creating our driver, opening web pages
and then finding specific elements and printing some sort of property.
But the next step is to actually form some sort of interaction with the webpage,
for example,
clicking on a link or typing something into the search bar because after all,
when we're working with websites,
it's often that we'll need to interact with it in order to navigate to new pages
and get hold of specific pieces of information that we're interested in.
And that's what I'm going to show you in the next lesson. So I'll
see you there.
In the last lesson,
we looked at how we can find elements using selenium on a webpage.
In this lesson,
I want to focus more on how to interact with those elements that you found.
For example,
typing into a input field or clicking on a button.
The first thing I want to show you is how to click on something.
In this case, we've already gotten hold of an anchor tag
which is inside a div called article_count.
It's basically this anchor tag. And if I want to click on it,
not using my mouse, but using selenium,
all I have to do is to get hold of the element
which is this article_count, and then call the .click method on it.
It's as simple as that. And once I hit run,
you'll see that my cursor is nowhere near the link,
but it actually clicked through and it got to the statistics page from that
link. So its basically the equivalent of me doing this,
but it was done automatically.
This was one way that we could have gotten hold of a link and then clicked on it.
Now because this is such a common requirement to click on a link on a webpage,
selenium actually has a specific find method that makes this really easy.
For example,
if we wanted to click on this link that says All Portals where it lists all the
different Wikipedia portals, basically subsections of Wikipedia,
well, one of the things that we could do is simply get hold of this link text
which says All Portals
and then we can create an object using our driver by tapping into find_element_
by_link_text. And all we have to put in there is the link text,
which said All Portals.
So now I can say all_portals.click
and if we go ahead and comment out this part,
then you can see it's going to open up our webpage
and it's going to click on that all portals taking us to this page.
So this is a find method
that's pretty specific to links where we just find it by the text that is in
between the anchor tag. So for example,
when I inspect on that all portals,
you can see that this is the anchor tag and the link text is the part between
the opening and closing tags. So it's now searching by that text,
which is a common need that you might have when you're going onto a website.
Now that we've seen how we can click on links once we've identified them,
what about typing?
Let's say we wanted to search for Python in this search bar.
How might we do that?
Well first let's go ahead and get hold of the search bar.
So I'm going to inspect on that and it takes me to this input element and the
thing that we can identify it by its name, which is equal to search.
Yeah.
So I can use our method which is find
_element_by_name and then pass in search as the name of the element I want to get
hold of. Now, once I've gotten a hold of that element,
then I can use a method called send_keys
and this is going to be the keys from the keyboard that you want to send to this
particular element. So let's say I wanted you to type Python in there. Well,
all I have to do is type send keys Python.
And now when I hit run,
you can see that it's going to automatically go over there and type in the word
Python.
My hands are completely off the keyboard and my cursor is nowhere near the
search bar. So that was all done automatically.
Now once we've typed in Python,
the next thing we want to do is hit the return key, right? Or the enter key.
Now, when we wanna send a key
that's not a letter or one of the numbers or symbols,
then we actually have to do a separate import.
From the selenium package inside the webdriver folder,
there's a folder called common. And inside there, there's something called keys.
This keys contains a class called Keys and that contains a bunch of constants.
What we can do is we can say search.send_keys
and the key that we're going to send comes from this keys class.
And it's one of the constants in there which is called ENTER.
This is basically the return key,
but you can see there's also other ones like shift or tab,
basically any key that you have on the keyboard can be replicated by the keys
class. Effectively
what we're doing here is we're finding that search bar, typing in Python and then
hitting the enter key. So let's run this and see it in action.
And that takes us to the search results.
So now we've seen how we can click on buttons
once we've located something that is clickable like a button or an anchor tag,
we've seen how we can type something into a field using send_keys,
and finally we've seen how we can import this class of Keys
which contains a whole bunch of constants that represents the key codes for a
lot of the common keys, like enter, shift, control, et cetera.
Now I have a challenge for you.
I want you to try and see if you can figure out yourself how to use selenium to
automatically insert your name, your last name and email address,
and then hit the sign up button in order to fill out this form. Now,
if you are successful, it should take you
to this success page.
Now don't worry if you actually type in your real email address or not.
This is a webpage that we created as a part of the complete web development
course. It's another course that I do,
which goes into detail on web technologies like JavaScript, Node, React,
and this is a site that we built in that course. Now,
the reason why I'm taking you to this page is because I don't want you to go
onto a random webpage like a real website where they're actually collecting
valid data.
If we're doing our practices and our exercises on a real website,
we'll end up giving them a lot of bot traffic and it's not great for the
website. This is why I'm getting you guys to use my own website
which is set up for testing anyways.
So the link to the page is in the course resources, or you could type it in
as you can see here. Now, as I mentioned,
this is not a sign up to our actual newsletter which lives on this page,
where every month I personally write a letter to you updating you on what we've
been up to,
what I've been up to and some articles that I've come across on the internet
that I found to be really interesting in terms of Programming, design, or
startup culture. If you actually want to sign up to the newsletter,
then head over to this link and put your email address here.
But in order to test your skills on selenium, we want you to head over
to this link and see if you can fill out this form automatically using what
you've learned and then get your selenium to click sign up.
Pause the video now and see if you can complete this challenge.
Right.
The first thing we need to do is to copy the URL and then back over here,
I'm going to comment out everything that I've got so far and I'm going to change
my driver to go to this new URL. Now,
once I've gotten to the new URL,
I want to go ahead and try to find and identify each of these fields.
So let's click on inspect and you can see that this first field has a name of f
Name,
the second one has a name of lName and the final one has a name of email.
So let's identify those using our driver.find.
And we're going to use the find_element_by_name passing in fName
and then it was lNname for the last name and then it was email.
So this is going to be our first name, last name and email.
The next step is to actually you fill it in.
So we're going to say first_name.send_keys, and then I'll pass
in my first name. And then it's going to be last_name.send_keys
and then I'll pass in my last name. And finally,
we've got our email and I'll just pass in a dummy email.
So now I'm going to try and find this button by inspecting on it and seeing how
I can identify it using my code.
So it's a button with all of these classes and a type,
but no ID or name. Given that this is the only button element inside this form,
then I'm going to go ahead and identify it by using CSS selector.
Right.
So it's inside the form and it's a button element.
And finally, once I found it, I'm simply gonna click on it.
So our script is going to go in order.
So it's first going to load up the page, type in all of these things and then
finally click on it. So let's hit run and see if that worked.
That was lightening fast because obviously it's not me typing and it clicked on
the button and it took us to the success page. How did you get on with that?
So now we've seen how to use selenium to find elements, to
interact with them by clicking and typing,
and also we saw how we can import the keys constant to interact with the
website with any key on our keyboard.
So there's quite a few methods we've gone through.
It might be worth taking some notes and having a quick review of how we've
managed to do all of these things using selenium because in the next lesson
we've got the final project coming up and it's going to be all up to you to try
and solve it. So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
It's now time for the final project where we put everything into practice.
Now, before I reveal the next message, just a word of warning.
It has explicit content. If you are hungry,
if you haven't eaten, if you are intermittent fasting like me,
it might be worth skipping over the next image.
Let us describe what we're going to do
in this project, we're going to be baking some cookies.
We're going to be playing the cookie clicker game,
but we're not going to do it normally like a normal person.
We're not going to go and click on our cookies and tirelessly end up with
repetitive strain injury and play the game as if we're a human. No,
we're going to play it using a Python bot created with selenium.
So recently I've been looking on Reddit and there's a lot of posts talking about
how addictive this cookie clicker game is. Why is this game
so addicting, cookie clicker ruined my life. And when you think about it,
it's such a simple game.
All it is is a big giant cookie, you click on it as fast as you can.
And once you've gotten a number of cookies,
then you can buy certain upgrades like a cursor,
which will click on the cookie automatically for you.
And if you get even more cookies, you can end up buying other things.
For example, once you have a hundred cookies,
you can by a grandma which will bake more cookies for you.
But we're not going to do it manually because I can physically not click at this
rate. We're going to get our bot to decide which add-ons to
buy that makes sense, and to buy as many of these add ons as we have money,
and we're going to get all bots to continuously click the cookie to bake even
more cookies.
So the goal is we're trying to max out on this cookies per second rating,
because the more of these add ons that you buy,
the more often that you click on the cookie,
the more cookies per seconds you can bake.
So basically what we want to do is to not even touch our mouse and use selenium
to play this game for us.
And we're going to try and get some high scores by cheating basically.
So the goal is to max out the cookies per second,
and we're going to be playing this game by clicking on this cookie automatically
using selenium.
And once we've clicked for five seconds,
we're going to see what is the highest value add on we can by,
and then we'll buy it to help us with the game.
So the goal at the end of the day is we're going to run the program for five
minutes. And at the end of the five minutes,
we're going to check our cookies per second.
And we're going to compete with each other on that number because of course you
can get selenium to play the game in different ways. So what I recommend first
before you get started with the project is just to head over to this link
which is in the course resources,
and actually play the game first as a human so that you can understand how it
works and see how these add ons really help us improve our rate of baking
cookies. Pause the video now, head over to this link,
play the game for maybe five minutes and then head over to the next lesson where
there's the full instructions for how to complete this challenge.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 49 of 100 Days of Code.
We're almost halfway and today we've got a really special project for you.
Now,
I know a lot of you guys are learning Programming to get a new job or change the
area in which you work,
and basically just find better opportunities for yourself.
So today's project is going to test what you've learned about how to work with
selenium,
and we're going to be building an automated job application bot.
This is going to put all the skills that we've learned yesterday into use
where we get selenium web driver to drive a browser
to open up a website and apply for jobs.
So applying jobs can be quite tedious working through each of the
applications,
filling in the required details and hoping that your application stands out.
So let's see if we can make this easier for ourselves by automating the process.
Now, one of the ways that a lot of people apply for jobs is on LinkedIn.
So they have this section called jobs. And when you go there,
you can search for the kind of jobs you're looking for,
where you're looking to work, you can even add in filters
like show remote jobs only where you can work from anywhere in the world.
And they've also got this really neat feature called easy apply.
And all you have to do is just to click on this button, easy apply,
fill in any of the fields that you haven't filled in before
and then just click submit application.
Some applications are a little bit more complicated than this.
This is the simplest format. Now,
in order to actually show you the whole process without messing with anybody
else's job applications,
I decided to create a job posting on LinkedIn from our own company.
So we're currently looking for a marketing intern to help us launch courses.
And when I click on this job, you can see this easy apply button show up.
So if I click on easy apply and I fill in my dummy phone number,
then I click on next.
Then I can include a resume.
Now the resume comes from your settings.
So if you go to your settings and privacy and you go to job seeking preferences
then here, you can actually already pre-upload your resume.
Once you've done that, then when you click easy apply,
you'll see the resume already uploaded. So we don't even have to do that
using our bot. Finally,
we click review and we're ready to go ahead and send and submit our application.
So that's how easy it is to submit our application
and you can see that there's only four or five steps that we need to automate in
order to apply for a job. That's the project for today
and I hope you're as excited as I am to tackle this project.
And you might even see a practical use for it in the future.
Once you're ready, head over to the next lesson where you'll find step by step
instructions on how to complete this project.
Hey guys, welcome to Day 50 of 100 Days of Code. You've made it.
It's half way. You've gone so far from the beginning.
And today I've got a special project just to celebrate that. We're going to be
building a auto tinder bot.
So for those of you guys who don't know what Tinder is
and I'm not sure if I believe you,
but Tinder is basically an app which helps people date online.
The idea is that you see somebody's profile, you hit like,
and if they like your profile as well,
then you've made a match and you can chat to each other and potentially set up a
date. Super simple and it's probably one of the top
most downloaded apps currently.
So there's a bit of a backstory about how this project came about. A few weeks
ago,
I was at a barbecue and some friends started talking about how they were so
frustrated with online dating. One of my friends, let's call him
Jason says that he spends about two hours a day swiping and chatting on Tinder.
But even after all of that time and effort,
he just doesn't end up getting any dates.
And at a time I remember looking around and pretty much all the boys in the
group actually agreed with him and said they were also spending a lot of time
swiping on Tinder, but they all have the same problem, very few matches.
So this got me really curious, and I did a bit of Googling.
It turns out that Jason and my friends are actually not alone.
It's not just them who's not getting enough swipes.
I found a guy on Reddit who requested their data from Tinder and he posted his
stats online.
So apparently he only got a total of 110 matches out of 26,800 swipes over for
four years, that's 0.41%.
This poor lad has almost a better chance of winning the lottery at that rate.
And this is not just a one off.
I found another guy who posted his tender stats and this guy did a little bit
better, um,
where he got 133 matches out of 12,631 swipes.
So basically just one match for every a hundred swipes.
All of the swiping means that they must've spent a lot of time inside the app as
well.
And I looked around for Tinder stats that they give their investors to show how
great their user engagement is and why they're worth how much they were.
So back in 2014, the New York times interview the company
and they said that users login about 11 times per day
and men spend around 7.2 minutes per session
and women spend about 8.5 minutes per session
cause we're a bit more picky with a total average daily engagement time of
around 90 minutes.
That's one and a half hours of swiping per day. That's crazy.
I didn't know that much about Tinder, but after all this research,
it gave me an idea. What if Jason didn't have to do all this wiping manually.
What if he could just write a program that would automate this whole process and
swipe for him? Long story short,
I introduced Jason to selenium and Python,
and now he's happily married with three children. Just kidding.
Uhm, actually, Jason is still trialing our little program,
but he's doing pretty well and much better than before and saving himself a lot
of time. But most importantly,
I think it makes for a fun project for us to practice our Python and selenium
skills.
Now the first time I realized that people actually want to automate this instead
of choosing the people they want to swipe on is when I came across this product
called the Tinder finger,
which is something that you plug into your phone and it powers the finger to
just keep swiping right
which basically means I'm liking everybody until somebody likes you back
and then you've got a match and you can chat with them instead of endlessly
swiping right. In fact,
I found a whole bunch of YouTube videos out there of people building
contraptions to swipe for them.
So we're going to try and create this only using software more specifically
using Python and selenium. Now just the word of warning.
If you are going to be swiping right on Tinder,
it might be worth telling your other half about it just in case they
accidentally find you on Tinder through the corner of their eye
and you end up in some sort of bad situation where they really get angry at you.
Also, I know that you might not be looking for a date right now
or you might have your doubts about signing up to a dating app
using your real name and photo just to practice some Python programming.
In that case, you can try a website called
thispersondoesnotexist.com to auto-generate some profile pictures for you.
These images,
every time you refresh is an image that's generated by a neural network using
machine learning. And these are not real people's faces,
but they look pretty real to me anyways. And you could in fact,
use this profile for this auto Tinder swiping project.
Pick somebody, sign up to Tinder,
and then we're going to use selenium to automate the entire process by swiping
on the Tinder website. This is what it looks like.
Your bot is going to log in using Facebook.
And then it's going to click on all the things that needs to be clicked so that
you can actually reveal the buttons for swiping.
And then it just swipes through everybody. And once it hits a match,
that's going to be a popup.
So it's going to click on back to Tinder and continue swiping. Now,
remember that Tinder has a maximum of a hundred swipes per day.
So unless upgrade to one of that paid tiers your bot is only going to work on a
hundred swipes per day, no matter how much you're automated.
But I'm sure you're a busy person saving your hundred swipes is probably
already worth creating the bot.
And if you're somebody who's on Tinder premium or whatever it is they call it,
then you could actually continue swiping all day. Now,
if you are somebody who doesn't want to hurt anybody's feelings by auto matching
with them using a Tinder bot like the one that we're about to write,
then feel free to complete the challenge just by hitting dislike on everyone so
that you don't match with anybody.
So that's the project that we're going to be building today.
And if you head over to the next lesson, we can get
started with the step by step challenges.
Hey guys welcome to day 51
of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be building a Complaining Twitter bot.
I dunno about you, but I'm the sort of person who really,
really hates dealing with customer service. Very often,
if I buy a product and it doesn't work
or it gets shipped to me broken,
I will actually just put it down to bad luck to avoid having to deal with
customer service. I find it really hard calling up customer service,
waiting on the line,
and it's just generally a really difficult experience for me.
But what if it's something that really bothers you that you need to complain
about in order to get it fixed? Well,
this particular internet user was promised a internet speed from Comcast,
so Xfinity in the US where he was meant to get 150 kilobits down and 10
kilobits up.
But what he found was that actually for a lot of the time,
he wasn't getting the promised internet speeds.
So he would do a speed test and then send his internet speeds by Twitter
to Comcast to complain. Now,
depending on who your internet provider is and how much you're paying,
they tend to guarantee a minimum internet speed. Now,
very often though, most people aren't testing their internet speeds every day.
Just occasionally you feel like, oh, it feels a bit slow today.
Or why is my download taking so long? If you look in your contract,
you'll often find that guaranteed minimum speed in terms of megabits per second.
For most people, it's probably going to be around 30 megabits or 60 megabits
depending on how much you pay. Now for a lot of providers,
they actually have a guarantee where if you can prove that the internet speed
that you're getting is not what they promised,
they'll actually give you your money back or even better
they might try and fix it.
So what this Comcast user did is he would test his internet speed and then tweet
automatically to Comcast and complain that his internet speed is only 23 down
5 up when he's paying 150 down 10 up. Now,
the reason why people interact with Twitter in terms of customer service is
because it's public.
Everybody else can see your complaint to a particular company
and if they're a large brand or a large company,
then they tend to have a social media monitor.
And often the customer service you get by complaining on Twitter can actually be
even better than if you call them up or if you email them.
One of the best customer service teams on Twitter is JetBlue.
And on the internet,
you've got lots of examples of people having a really great experience with the
customer service team on Twitter from JetBlue, for example,
this guy who was on a flight and his TV didn't work,
and they actually ended up offering him, um,
flight credits just on the spot for having a broken TV,
all achieved using a couple of tweets. Now,
recently I was even reading this article in time magazine
where it's talking about 'Does tweeting at companies really work?' And very often,
yes, it really does. And even when you look at this basically Python
Twitter bot,
you can see that he often got replies from Comcast and other users chipping in
trying to get ahold of Comcast to fix their internet as well. Now,
Comcast is probably quite well known to having pretty bad customer service.
In fact, there's this post which I'll link to, um,
where a journalist was trying to cancel their Comcast service
and it took something like 5 or 10 minutes where the customer service guy was
just trying really,
really hard to not let them cancel even sometimes being quite condescending and
a bit mean. But in this conversation,
you actually hear the Comcast person saying we're the only people who can
promise you a hundred megabit download speed. And in fact,
when you look at the Comcast users tweets,
you can see often that is actually not the case.
So this can also bolster your argument when you want to leave an internet
service or when you want to get money back
or when you just want somebody to fix your internet speeds.
The website we're going to be using is speedtest.net
which is probably one of the best speed test websites out there.
And what we're going to do is we're going to use our bots using selenium to
press go.
You can see it's going to start working out my download speeds and my upload
speeds. Now this often takes anywhere between sort of half a minute to
two minutes depending on your internet speed.
But once it's done,
then we'll end up with a result ID as well as our download speed and our upload
speed.
And you can then compare these against what you were promised by your internet
service provider. And then we're going to tweet at our provider.
So if it's Comcast or AT&T or in the UK, it could be BT or Sky,
whatever it may be.
And then we're going to tell them about our terrible internet speeds compared to
what we pay for. So that's the goal.
And when I run my internet speed Twitter bot, you can see
this is what happens.
[inaudible],
That's the goal. Once you're ready head over
to the next lesson and let's get started.
Hey guys, welcome to day 52
of 100 Days of Code. Today
I've got yet another pretty fun project for you.
It is a Instagram follower bot.
So here's the thing is. Have you ever felt a little bit lonely?
Have you ever wanted more friends? Well, I can't really get you more friends,
but I could figure out a way of getting you more followers on Instagram.
So recently I was talking to a Instagram consultant.
This is somebody who actually advises businesses and startups on
how they can build their Instagram presence.
And they've worked with a lot of successful companies.
And one of the secrets that they shared with me,
which I thought was really cool actually, is let's say that you are somebody
who's trying to build a brand around cooking.
So you could do is you could look at all the accounts on Instagram that are
already, um, cooking related.
One of my favorite probably to this day is a company called ChefSteps.
They just have the coolest content and they have amazing YouTube videos with
tutorials. And a lot of the stuff that they make are just gorgeous,
like real molecular gastronomy and everything looks amazing.
Let's say that you are trying to build a company where it was also doing
something that was food related and you want to get more followers for your
company. One of the ways that you could do it is if you think about it,
if you find a company that has a similar demographic or a similar audience to
yours,
basically people who like food or people who like cooking, well,
what you could do is you could go to their Instagram account and then look at
their followers.
And then you can go through this list of people who follow ChefSteps and follow
each of these accounts. Now, for a lot of these people,
they are small individuals who are just interested in cooking or food.
So if you have something that's food related and you're following somebody,
then they might notice you as well. And in turn,
you'll probably get more followers. So I thought this was a really cool idea
and it's something that's really ripe for automation,
because who wants to go through a list of 247,000 people and click on each of
these buttons. Nobody, right?
So we're going to do this using code. More specifically,
Selenium and Python. Here's what it looks like when I run my code.
It's gonna log into Instagram automatically
and then it's going to go to the account that I want to replicate followers for.
And then it's going to click on that link followers
and it's going to start following each of these individual accounts one by one
automatically. And you can see my mouse is nowhere near there.
Yeah.
That's the goal for today. If you're building a business,
if you're building a startup or if you're building your own custom brand,
or if you just want more followers on Instagram,
this might be something that you would be interested in.
And it definitely helps you tap into some new skills with Selenium and Python.
So once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and put your skills to the test.
Hey guys, welcome to day 53
of 100 Days of Code. Today
it's time for your capstone project.
And it's time when you review everything that we've learned over the last 10
days or so... everything to do with web scraping.
The project that we're going to be tackling is a data entry job.
Now there's a lot of data entry jobs out there where you're kind of just meant
to transfer data from one format to another.
So maybe you have it in a physical print copy,
or maybe it's on a website, maybe it's on
a PDF and you just have to transfer it somewhere else,
usually typing it into a spreadsheet.
The inspiration for this project came from, um,
when I was browsing Reddit actually on the /r/Python subreddit
which is a really good community for you to actually look at and see what other
people are doing with Python and seeing the latest and greatest things built or
news about Python. Now,
one of the posts I saw was asking whether if anyone has automated their job
completely, basically using Python.
Now we've seen how powerful Python can be
especially when we apply it to web scraping using Beautiful Soup and Selenium.
And looking through or the comments
there's actually a lot of people who have done this,
including this one guy who basically pretty much automated his entire job. And
the jobs that tend to be easily automated using Python
are data entry jobs, moving data from one format to another.
And if you think about it, if that job is in fact remote,
so if you search on indeed.com for a remote data entry job
and you get up and running with the company and you start doing it manually,
and then once you've understood what it is you have to do. For example, um,
gathering statistical data,
preparing reports and maintaining these spreadsheets.
If you realize that this is a large part of your job
and you can automate it pretty much with Python,
then you could probably get Python to do 70% of your job
and you spend the rest 30% of the day doing the rest of the job,
but still being paid as a full on worker with full benefits.
So this is something that a lot of people in the Python community has talked
about and explored,
and this is something that we're going to be trying out using both Beautiful
Soup and Selenium in this project. In our case,
we're going to be tackling a research data entry job where we're researching
house prices that fit a particular criteria for a client on the Zillow website.
And then we're going to be transferring that data into a form
which will create a spreadsheet in Google sheets
and that is usually how as a data entry person,
this is how we would make our money. Now,
because this is a capstone project, we're going to be using everything that we've learned in
this section. So that means Beautiful Soup as well as Selenium.
So you might have to revise up on some of the things you learned
especially the stuff on Beautiful Soup which we covered a few days ago.
And we're going to combine all the skills that you've done so far.
And this project really is going to test all of your web scraping skills that
you've acquired so far and see how far you can run with it. Because it's capstone
project there's not going to be a lot of guidance.
So you're going to have to persevere and try to see if you can solve your own
problems and see if you can get to the end outcome.
This is what we're aiming for. We're going to go to Zillow,
which is one of the largest real estate listing sites in the US, and we're going
to search to see if we can find a place to rent in San Francisco. Now,
San Francisco is notorious for really expensive housing,
and it was also really difficult often to actually find somewhere that you want
to live.
Let's say that you have a client who wants you to compile a list of all the
places that they can rent in San Francisco up to $3,000 per month
and it has to have at least one bedroom. On Zillow
you can already filter on these things. So for example, you could say
this is the area San Francisco California, that I want to rent.
And then of course changing it to for rent
rather than for sale switching the maximum price up to $3,000,
and then adding in the extra requirement that it must have at least one bedroom.
So once you've added all of those filters in, then all of those filters will go
into the URL
and this is the URL that you will be able to use to try and find properties that
match our client's criteria. Now,
in addition to using that URL,
you are also going to be using Beautiful Soup to scrape through all of this
data. And what we want is the price, the address,
and also the URL that this will link to. So, for example,
when I click on this, it will link it to the actual listing of the place.
And then once you've scraped all of that data using Beautiful Soup,
then you are going to be using Selenium to autofill in a Google form.
So we're going to be adding in the address of the property,
the price per month and the link to property. And of course,
we're going to fill out one of these forms per listing that we have on Zillow.
And once all of that form's been compiled,
then you will have the option to turn it into a spreadsheet.
Whenever you create a form in Google forms,
you can see that when you go to the responses tab,
you can click on this button in order to create a Google sheet from the
responses that have been submitted
and this is what you end up with: a spreadsheet with the address of the property,
the price per month, and a link to the property. So this way,
once you've done this research,
then you can send it to your client so that they are going to filter down on
each of the listings that match their criteria and decide which one they want to
go and make a viewing. So this of course makes their job a little bit easier,
and this is our research task that we're going to complete today.
So the first part of scraping the data for the relevant listings is going to be
done using Beautiful Soup,
and then the second part where we're going to be filling in this form is going
to be done using Selenium. So that is the project.
And once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and take a look at the requirements of the
project and we can get started with the capstone project.
Hey guys, welcome to day 54 of 100 days of Code.
And today we're going to be moving on to a new topic and that is going to be web
development.
And we're going to be working on this for the next few days as well.
Now there's quite a lot to cover today.
We're going to be talking about the command line, Python decorators,
as well as web development using Flask,
one of the most popular frameworks for creating websites using Python.
Now, before we get started though, you might be thinking, well,
I already know how to make websites.
I learned about HTML and CSS on days 41 through to 44.
So I really know how to make websites.
So what exactly is it that you're teaching me now? Well,
if you think of a website,
a simple website just contains HTML and CSS.
Now that is also what we call the front-end.
This is the beautiful mermaid that the user gets to see. Now for the website to
actually have some functionality, for example, if you're building a web app
instead of just a simple display website,
then it's also got to have a backend.
And the backend is the part that we're going to be learning how to build right
now.
So if the front end is just the part that displays information to the user,
the backend is the part that does a lot of the business logic,
a lot of the calculations,
and a lot of the things that we've been doing with Python. Now,
when people talk about full stack web development
which is a term that you would've heard of
if you were searching for web development jobs. Now full stack basically just
means frontend and backend.
So somebody who can deal with both frontend and backend technologies. Now,
usually there's quite a few languages that are used for the front and the back
end. So the front it's usually HTML,
CSS and JavaScript. HTML gives the website structure,
CSS gives it style and JavaScript allows it to have some sort of interactivity.
Now the backend can also be created by a bunch of different languages,
and here is more of a choice. Um, you could choose between JavaScript, Java,
Python, Ruby,
there's whole bunch of different languages. To make it even more
complicated, in addition to languages,
there's also different frameworks that you could use for the front and back end.
So some popular frameworks you might have heard of
are things like Angular and Rreact from the front end and Node and Flask or Django
for the backend.
So these frameworks are basically tools that really come with a lot of code
prebuilt for a lot of the common functionalities that you find when building
the front and back end.
So that way, we don't always have to reinvent the wheel and we can simply just
use the wheel and build a bicycle or build a car or built a scooter and whatever
it is that we want. Now,
when we're considering Python backend,
there's a whole myriad of different frameworks that you could choose from.
For example, Flask, Django, Bottle, Cherry pie, pyramid,
and a whole bunch more. But the most popular ones, if you look at job search
anyways,
is Flask and Django where Flask is better suited to beginners and also small
projects and Django suited much more to larger commercial projects. In order to
build out a website which has a front end and a backend,
we have to kind of understand what exactly is the backend.
There's three components that you really need to understand when it comes to the
backend. And that is the client,
the server and the database.
These three components together will determine how your backend will work.
Now, firstly, the client,
you can sort of imagine just as a user going onto a browser,
this is the client's side. This is the part that faces the user.
And then there's the server.
So you can think of the server as basically just a powerful computer
that's hooked up to the internet and it's on 24/7
always ready to receive requests over the internet. Finally,
you've got the database
which is kind of like a souped up spreadsheet where you are storing all the
information related to your website.
So let's say the client wanted to go to google.com. Well,
when they type that into the URL bar and they hit enter,
that gets sent to the server as a request,
and this goes across the internet to this other computer.
And this server has to respond. And it responds by sending over the HTML, CSS and
JavaScript files that it has for that particular website.
And once that gets sent back to the browser,
then that can be rendered by the browser as the actual webpage. Now,
if you're a website that has a lot of use of data or different types of data
that could be requested by a user, then usually you'll have a database.
So when the client requests, for example,
to see all the tickets they have on Eventbrite, well,
the page that they're viewing, that is the front end. That is the client side.
But in order to render all the tickets they have,
the client makes the request to the server and the server fetches the data from
the database. Once it gets the data back from the database,
it puts the data into the HTML, CSS and JavaScript files,
and it sends the whole bundle back to the browser to be viewed by the user.
If this whole process seems a little bit convoluted and complex, don't worry.
We're going to be diving deep into creating our server, creating our database,
and we're going to be creating all of these parts from scratch step-by-step
ourselves. So at the end of the web-dev section,
you'll find that if you come back to this video,
everything's going to make a lot more sense.
Now in order for you to have a good overview of what the whole system looks
like, I'd like to use the analogy of a restaurant.
So imagine if you have a restaurant and you've got the front of house
which is where the tables are,
when the customer sit. And then
you've got the kitchen
which is where the chefs work and where you're creating all the dishes.
And finally, you've also got the larder
which is where you store all the ingredients in the fridge or on the shelves.
Now this front of house part
which is where the user seats in is the client site. Now in the middle,
we've got the kitchen, which is the server. And finally we've got the larder
which is basically the database of ingredients.
Now the client side is completely separate from the rest. So as a user,
when I go onto a website,
I'm not interacting with the server or the database directly. Instead,
I'm interacting with my browser, which is on the client side. Now,
when you go to a website and you request to see some piece of information,
for example, you log in to Spotify and you want to view your playlists,
what actually happens is, you know,
you don't have the chef sort of cooking up the dish in front of you on the
client side. No,
instead what happens is that the server fetches the relevant ingredients from
the database, so the data that's related to your Spotify playlist,
and then it takes that data and it renders it into a HTML,
CSS and JavaScript files.
And then once that endproduct is created,
it ships it out to the browser on the client side, which you
as the user, can now view.
So this is basically an overview of how our frontend and our backend interact in
order to create a website experience for people. And in the coming lessons,
we're going to be building out each of these parts and you gonna see in greater
detail how they work together. So head over to the next lesson
and we'll get started building our very first website.
All right. Let's get started developing websites using Flask.
Now Flask is one of the most popular web development frameworks,
but what does it mean to be a framework? Well,
we've seen libraries before like Beautiful Soup. Tools that we can use and tap
into whenever we need a particular piece of functionality. Now,
a framework is a little bit like a library in the sense that it's a package of
code that you didn't write, but it also got some differences.
So here I've got a graphic from the differencebetween.net and one of the
biggest differences is the fact that a library is something which you call upon
to do something specific.
Whereas a framework is something which you have to abide by their rules,
you have to use their architecture.
And when it comes to triggering some sort of functionality,
it's the framework that calls upon your code.
So what does that mean? Well,
remember when we used the requests library and we would say something like requests
.get and then we would tell it which webpage to go and fetch.
Well,
this is us tapping into that library and then giving it a command to do
something. Now, when we're working with a framework,
it doesn't really work like that. We don't really say, hey framework,
do this thing for us. Instead,
we make sure that our code is defined in a way that the framework wants it to
be. And then when the time is right,
the framework is actually going to call our methods
instead of us calling the framework.
All we have to do is to plan ahead for certain situations.
If it was this situation, what do we want to happen? If it was that situation,
what code it should be run?
So it might be that all you have to do is just write some functions like hello
world and when the user goes to the website,
then it's going to display this text Hello world.
Let's try this in practice. Now by
now you would of known that as developers,
especially now that we're in the advanced stages of becoming a Python developer,
the most important thing when we approach a new tool or a new technology is to
read the documentation.
So Flask actually has a really good piece of documentation in order to tell us
how to get started quickly using Flask. As you can see,
they've described what a minimal Flask application looks like.
And this is a very simple server set up with flask.
So let's go ahead and copy this code. And I'm going to create a new project
which I've decided to call hello_flask. And then in this project folder,
I'm going to create a new file which I'll call hello.py.
Now it's important that the name of your file does not conflict with the name of
the framework or library in fact. So for example,
if I was to create a file called requests.py
and I had, um,
imported the requests library.
And then I tried to do something like requests.get.
Now when I run this,
because the name of my file conflicts with the name of the module, what will happen is
I will get this error. And it might be a little bit confusing
cause it says, well, request has no attribute get. Well
we know it does because it's in the documentation.
And the reason why we're getting this error is because we've named this file
the same name as the module.
So this is something that happens to a lot of people
so make sure that you don't commit this mistake and you could name it anything
like main or server or hello in our case. Notice that now
if I change the name, it actually automatically changed the import
which is not what we want. We want the import to be requests
and we want to make sure that we install our package  requests.
And once that's done,
you can see our module and our file have completely different names.
So now, if I run this file,
it works perfectly and it ends with exit code zero,
which means everything was successful.
So now I'm going to go ahead and delete this file
and go back to our hello.py. Now inside our hello.py
I'm going to paste in the minimal Flask application from the Flask
documentation. So paste that right here.
And as you might remember,
there's several ways that we can install new modules. So in this case,
the module is Flask and we can either click on the red light bulb to install
this package. Alternatively, we can go to PyCharm, preferences,
and then go to our project and into the interpreter to add the Flask package like
this.
Right.
Now, if you have the PyCharm professional edition,
there's additional tools to make it easier to install Flask into a project and
to work with Flask projects. But because we're using the free community edition,
I'm just going to go ahead and dismiss that popup.
So I've shown you two ways of installing a package.
Now I want to show you the third way,
which you might come across if you're looking at the installation.
So notice here, in order to install Flask,
they're using pip install Flask.
So pip is something that allows us to install Python packages from pypi.
So any package that you on pypi.org, you can install using pip.
And what we have to do is to type in the name that you see right here.
For example, if we want to install Flask,
then it's pip install and it's the capital F for Flask.
So we can copy that into our clipboard.
And if we go to the terminal tab at the bottom,
we can paste that instruction in here and hit enter.
Now it should have successfully installed Flask . And once I dismiss that,
you can see my errors go away. So all three methods work.
I personally prefer the red light bulb, just because it's much quicker.
It's just two clicks rather than typing a lot of code. Now,
once we've installed Flask,
we can go ahead and add some space to get rid of all the warnings from Py
Charm. Um, we can go ahead and run our project.
Now, as soon as I run the project, you can see
it tells me the process was finished with exit code zero,
which means everything was successful,
but where's my server and where's my website.
So let's go back to the Quickstart to see what we actually have to do in order
to set up our server. So to run our Flask application,
we're going to firstly, need to export a environment variable.
So in previous lessons, we've talked about environment variables,
but basically this is going to tell the Flask framework
what is the name of the file that contains our server.
So in our case, as well as in the Quickstart,
the name of that file is hello.py.
So we basically have to point to that file to get Flask
to be able to recognize it and to use it as the server. So on Mac
we're going to type export space
and then we're going to put in the name of the environment variable
which is FLASK_APP and its all caps.
And then with no spaces, we've got a equal sign
and then the name of our file, which is hello.py.
So now when I hit enter,
that's going to add that environment variable under the name that Flask is
expecting, which is flask.app. Now,
as it mentions in the Quickstart, if you're on Windows
the keyword is not export, but instead it's set.
So again, inside your terminal down here, you're going to type set.
And then you're going to put in the name of that environment variable
which was FLASK_APP and then with no space equals and it's our hello
.py. And once you hit enter,
it should give you the prompt again indicating that everything went smoothly.
Now, once we've done that,
the next step is to simply use the Flask command called run.
And when I hit enter, you'll see that it's created my server.
So it's serving up the Flask app that I've created in hello.py
and we're get a warning telling us that this is a development server and telling
us that if you want to actually launch it as a product,
don't use this development server. There's a few steps
you have to carry out if you actually wanted to make this production ready and
ready for the internet and customers. But in our case,
we are developing. So this is perfect.
And it tells us where to go and find our website.
So if you imagine that Google is at https://
www.google.com. Well,
this is the address of our website and it's being served by our computer.
So when you're trying to get hold of a website on the internet,
then you have to point towards the IP address
of that particular webpage.
But because we've created our server locally and it's being served on our own
computer, then this is basically the local address
of that website.
Now a neat thing about PyCharm is if I simply just click on this link,
then it's going to launch my website in my browser and you can see right up
here, we've got hello world showing up
which is the same as what we've got here in this method.
So that proves that we've successfully managed to create our very first web
server using Flask.
And it's able to serve up our very first Flask website. Now,
if you go ahead and open up the Chrome developer tools and you go to elements,
you can see that what we wrote here which is just a string
was actually converted by Flask into full HTML.
It's got the HTML tag, it's got the head tag,
it's got the body tag and we didn't have to do any of this.
We just told Flask what we wanted to be returned onto the page
when the user goes to the homepage,
which has just the web address plus a forward slash.
Now the very last thing to remember is once we're done with our server,
because it's still ongoing
it's still waiting for a client to hit up this website,
we have to get it to stop waiting. So we can quit by holding down control and
then pressing C. And you can see this takes us back to our prompt
where we've got our name and our project. Now,
if you don't stop it and you try to run two Flask applications to the same
address then the second one is simply not going to run.
So just be aware that once you're done with your server, hit control+c to quit.
Now in the next lesson,
I want to talk a little bit more about the commands that you can use in the
terminal because this is called the command line.
And just as here we use the command line to run our Flask application, to export
our environment variables, we can also do other things like create folders,
create files, move files around. It's actually a very,
very powerful way of interacting with our computer.
That's what we're going to do in the next lesson. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you there.
Now,
in the last lesson, we saw how to get up and running with our brand new Flask
server. In this lesson
I want to take it back a little bit and talk briefly about some of these
commands that we put into the terminal here,
because the terminal is actually a really powerful tool.
And it's something that's also referred to as the command line and its a way of
typing in commands one line at a time in order to control our computer.
The command line is also known as the shell.
So what exactly is a shell?
If you think about your operating system as a pistachio nut,
then the kernels of the actual pistachio, the thing that you're going to eat,
I'm really sorry about all the food analogies.
You can clearly tell I'm pretty much hungry most of the time when I'm recording
these videos, but let's get back to the topic.
So if your operating system is a pistachio,
then the actual nut is the kernel. And in computing
the kernel refers to the actual program that interfaces with the hardware.
So it's the core of your operating system. Now,
the shell of your pistachio or the shell  in computing refers to
the user interface for you as a human
to be able to interact with the kernel and in turn with the hardware of your
computer. And there's two variants to the shell.
There are graphical user interface shells, so for example,
when you open up finder
you're using a graphical user interface to access and find your files.
But there's also a command line interface
which is what we're going to be talking about and what we're going to be
learning about in this module.
So this is an alternative way of interfacing with the kernel.
Now it can seem intimidating at first,
but I want to show you that it's actually super simple.
And once you understand it, you're going to see that it's actually really,
really useful tool at your disposal.
A lot of the things that you can do with command line can be done using the
graphical user interface. So why use
the command line at all? At the end of the day,
what it all boils down to is about greater control.
And in your journey of becoming a better developer,
you will need to understand and exert more power over your tools,
that is the computer hardware. But on a more day to day basis,
you will find that if you're a regular command-line user
that it's actually easier and faster to do a lot of really common things.
If you're a Mac user, you've actually got a dedicated terminal application.
So if you go to spotlight and hit the search button and look for the terminal
and hit enter, you can see that this is the actual terminal application.
Now I've styled it up to look a bit more like a hacker because I like scaring
people in Starbucks, but that's not the only you can change.
You can change the color of your terminal,
you can also change the type of shell you're using. Currently,
if you are running macOS Catalina or above, so Big Sur
or any of the future operating systems, you're going to be using zsh
which has now the default Mac shell.
All right,
Now, if you're on Windows however, the default shell is the command prompt.
So if you type in to search for the command prompt, you can see
this is the app you need to launch and this is your command prompt.
For the most part, you can type in the same commands on Windows and on Mac
and it will work on both.
I want to show you some common things we can do in the terminal. Here
I've got my terminal and the address of the terminal is determined by the part
that's just before the prompt. So at the moment, it's a ~ on my Mac.
There's a couple of things I want to show you that you can do with the terminal.
The first thing that's really useful to know is where am I in my file path?
And to do this, we have to write pwd, print working directory.
And this tells me where I am. Once you open up your finder
as you can see up here, go to view and then go to show path bar.
And this is showing us the path from our hard drive/ users/angela,
which is exactly the same location as what I've got now in my terminal.
So the print working directory is really useful for you to locate where you are.
Similarly, on Windows, you can see when I do print working directory,
it tells me that I'm in the C:\users\username.
So C drive, users, username... right here.
The next command that is really useful is ls,
which stands for list.
And what this does is it will list all of the files and folders at your current
working directory.
So it's going to list everything that's in this current location where I am at
basically this. So if I go ahead and hit enter,
you can see all of the same folders showing up as it does
in finder. Pwd and ls are really useful for finding things out, for displaying
things.
But we can also use the terminal to move around in our computer.
And we do that using the CD command, which is changed directory.
So if at the moment, my working directory is users/Angela
and I want to get into my desktop folder
which is clearly one of the folders that I can access, then I can simply say
change directory to desktop. Now,
one of the things you can do to prevent yourself from getting repetitive strain injury and
typing a lot is you can type the start of the folder, so for example desktop-
De and then hit tab,
and it will narrow down on the possibility that you can go to so there's
development or there's desktop.
So if I add one extra S and I hit tab,
it's now going to automatically insert the folder that I'm looking for,
which is desktop. So now if I hit enter,
you can see that this part before my flashing prompt has changed and it's
changed to the desktop. So now, if I do pwd,
you can see I'm now in users/angela/Desktop,
which is the equivalent of double-clicking on this basically.
Okay.
On my desktop what if I wanted to create a new folder? Well,
we can do that using the make dir or make directory command.
So we're saying make directory and then we give it a name. So let's say
I want to call this Test then I'll just say mk
dir Test. And notice the location while you are at.
So I'm going to be making this test directory on my desktop.
And as soon as they hit enter, there you see it.
It's created that folder from scratch.
So now here's a question. If you wanted to navigate into Test so that when you
print the working directory,
it's going to output users/yourusername/desktop/test.
What would you do? What would be your command? Pause the video and
have a think about that. Alright,
of course, we have to change directory coz at the moment we're in the desktop
which is this, and if we want to go inside this test folder,
then we have to cd into it. So cd into test,
and now we're inside the test folder. And if I hit pwed, you can see
this is where I'm at. Now,
once I've cded into this new directory,
I'm going to create a new file in this directory. To create a new file
the command is a little bit different from creating a new directory.
The key word is touch. And after the key word, there's a space
and then we can provide the name of our file.
So let's say that we want to create a new Python file
which we'll call main.py. Now,
what it's going to do is create this file code in main
which is a Python file and it's going to do that inside the Test folder.
So let's hit enter and there you see it.
There's our Python file created without any clicking or dragging completely done
with our command line. So we've seen how we can create folders,
how we can create files. And by the way,
if you want to create a different type of file that you just change the
extension. So it could be .text,
or it could be .docx or whatever file format you want to create. Now,
what if we wanted delete our file? Well,
all we have to do is make sure we're in the correct directory to be able to
access that file. So when we hit ls,
we should be able to see the file we want to delete.
And then all we have to do is type rm which stands for remove
and then we could put our main.py. So there it is, it's gone.
Okay.
Now, what if I want to delete the Test folder? Firstly,
I have to navigate one step up. Instead of being inside the Test folder,
I can't delete the Test folder while I'm inside the Test folder.
I have to go one step up, which is the desktop folder.
Now of course I could say cd into the full path
which is /Users/angela/Desktop.
Now this would work, but this is really wordy.
A really simple shortcut for navigating
just one step up is writing cd and then two dots.
This is going to take us to the parent folder, which is now Desktop.
Right.
From here I'm going to delete this folder. Now to delete a folder
we can't just put rm. We also have to put a flag.
So a - and then rf. So this is going to recursively, forcibly, remove this
folder that we're going to add here, which is the Test folder.
Now the thing you have to be really careful about rm -rf is it does things
recursively. So if there were lots of folders inside this Test folder,
then it's going to delete everything in there.
And if, God forbid, you actually have this and you put it onto your whole computer,
well then that's going to be a real disaster.
Because the thing you have to know about the terminal is that it's a very
powerful. And what did Spider-Man's uncle say? With great power comes great
responsibility.
There's some pretty funny stories about people who accidentally deleted
everything on their computer just by messing with rm -rf.
So be really careful that you are in the correct location to delete the folder
and to double check that it's the right folder.
Because when I hit enter,
you can see it's not going to ask me for a confirmation
and it's also not going to put that folder or the containing files into the bin.
So be really careful when you're using the terminal.
There you have it.
There's an introduction to the command line using zsh on a Mac and using the
command prompt on Windows. Now,
when you open up PyCharm and you go to this emulator terminal,
so it's a sort of application within an application,
you can see that it looks pretty much the same.
Basically, all that PyCharm's done is just bundled the command
prompt into the PyCharm on windows and the zsh terminal into the PyCharm
on Mac. So you can do everything that you can do in the terminal
inside PyCharm as well
which makes it really easy to pip install modules or to run our Flask server.
Now,
if you want to know about other things that you could do in the Windows command
prompt or the Mac terminal, you can simply just search for command prompt
cheatsheet or terminal cheatsheet.
And what it will take you to are lots of addresses
which contain basically a lot more things that you could do with your command
line. But the ones that we've talked about today
are some of the most common ones and 99% of the time,
those are going to be the commands that you're going to be sticking to.
So write them down if you need to review them regularly.
And if you just use them on a regular basis,
you won't have any trouble remembering them.
Now that we've understood a little bit more about the terminal commands,
let's come back to our Flask code and understand what the code is doing in a
little bit more detail. For example, what is this name?
Because we're creating this app from this Flask class
and in order to initialize a new Flask application,
there is only one required input,
and that is the import_name.
Let's go ahead and print it out.
So if we print this __name__ and comment out the rest of our
code and hit run,
then you can see that it prints out __main_
_.
This name is one of the special attributes that's built into Python.
At any given point,
you could tap into the name to find out what is the current class, function,
method, or descriptor's name.
And when we get main, what it's telling us is
basically we're executing the code in a particular module.
So that means it's run as a script or from an interactive prompt,
but it's not run from an imported module.
It gives us this code here, if the name is equal to main,
then execute something only if it's run as a script.
This also takes us to
one of the common ways that you'll see people run Flask apps.
You'll see if __name__ is double equal to _
_main__ as a string,
so exactly what was printed just now when we printed out this name,
well, if this is the case,
then that means we're running the code from within this current file.
We're running hello.py. So in that case,
we're going to tap into our app and we're going to call the run method.
Now this app.run
basically does exactly the same thing as when we went into the terminal and
we said flask run. But notice when we say flask run,
firstly, we have to provide the FLASK_APP environment variable
and secondly, we have to stop the code using control + c
instead of using our normal run and stop.
But if we use app.run, we can now use our standard controls.
So I can simply hit run to run this hello.py,
and it will start serving up our Flask app at this address just as it did
before, when we did flask run. And instead of using control + c to quit,
we can simply use the stop to stop our Flask application,
making it a lot easier.
Basically by providing the name to Flask, Flask
will check that this is the current file where the app code is located.
And we're not in fact using an imported module. For example,
if I was to import the random module and I was to print the random.name,
then you can see the first thing that gets printed is the name of that module.
But the name that's printed from hello.py
which is the file that's being run is simply __main__.
So this basically denotes the file that is currently being run
and you say, Run 'hello' Well then inside hello
name is going to be equal to main.
Right.
The next part of the syntax that might be unfamiliar is this @ sign and
something that comes after the @ sign. Now we sort of know what it does.
It's basically saying when the user hits up this path
which is what's called the home route, basically when you go to a website,
for example, www.google.com
and you go to the first forward slash well, that is going to be the home.
And it knows that when you go there you want to see the home page.
So that's effectively what we're saying here.
When the user navigates to our URL with just a forward slash they want to see
the homepage and so we're going to show them hello world.
But what is this syntax exactly? Well,
this is code a Python decorator
and this is something that you'll see in more advanced Python projects.
So what exactly is a decorator? Well,
let's imagine that you have a bunch of functions in your class or in your
module
and you want to add some functionality to each of these functions. Well then you
might use a decorator function to do that.
Essentially you can think of a decorator function as a function
that's going to give additional functionality to an existing function. In order
to really understand this,
we have to understand a couple of other concepts as well.
So I'm going to do a couple of demos in this Repl.it
and if you head to this URL or find it in the course resources,
you'll be able to see all the code that I've written in this file.
So a long time ago,
we learned about Python functions and we know that a function allows us to
have specific packages of functionality,
allows us to add inputs, to increase the reusability of the function,
and also allows us to get outputs from the function which we can pass into
another function or do something with it. As an example,
we've got four very simple functions, add, subtract, multiply,
and divide that uses all three components of a function.
Now, what if we wanted to get a little bit fancier? Well,
one of the things about Python functions is that they are known as first-class
objects,
which basically means that you can pass a function around as an argument,
just like what you could do with an integer, a string or a float, it's treated
identically.
That means we can take these functions and we can build another function that
uses these functions. Let's say I create a calculate function
which takes a calc_function
and then the n1 and n2.
Inside this calculate function,
I'm going to call the function that was passed in and give it the values
n1 and n2 that was also passed in.
So now when I call the calculate function,
I'm going to pass in the name of one of these functions and then some numbers.
Those numbers are gonna become the input for this specified function
and then we're going to return the result of that calculation.
So now lower down,
I can call my calculate function, pass in the name of a function
so for example our multiply function, and then pass in some numbers,
for example, two and three. Now let the output that's returned
be our results
and let's go ahead and print this result. And you can see we get six.
So basically it has now multiplied two by three. Now,
if I change this to one of the other functions, add,
and I run this again, you can see instead of six, I'm now getting five.
The ability for us to treat functions as first-class objects basically means
that we can pass them around as if they were just any other argument
like a number or a string or a floating point number.
And then later we can activate them by adding the brackets around them and then
any necessary inputs. Now, the next concept
which you might've come across
but we haven't really used it a lot is the concept of nested functions.
Functions can also be nested inside other functions.
For example, if I create a function called outer_function
and this function is just going to print and say,
I'm outer. Now inside this outer_function,
I could create another function. So notice the indentation here
means that this function is now created inside this function and I'll call it
the nested_function.
So this function is simply going to print I'm
inner.
And now we have the problem of trying to call this function. Now,
because this function was declared inside this function,
its scope means that it's only accessible inside the confines of this function.
So if we were to go outside of the function, so by
indenting back to the beginning and we try to call this nested function,
then it's actually not going to work.
We're going to get a name error. It's not defined. However,
if we call this function inside this outer_function,
then it will now no longer generate an error.
So let's go ahead and trigger the outer_function by calling it in our main.
py. And when I run this, you can see it says I'm outer
and then it says I'm inner.
So this first gets executed and then this. And this I'm inner is being
printed when this line is being evaluated. Now,
one of the other things you could do is you can actually return a function from
another function.
Right.
Functions can actually be returned from other functions.
So if I make a copy of this previous function right here and comment out this
other function and all the steps before,
...
and we only have this bit of active code,
then you can see that instead of calling this nested_function here,
I could also return it as the output.
But the important part here is I'm going to get rid of the parentheses
which means I'm no longer activating that function right here.
So now when I call this outer_function,
the output that this line is going to evaluate to is going to become the nested_
function. So you could almost store it inside a variable.
So let's say I create a variable called inner_function
which is equal to the output of the outer_function
which is basically this nested_function that's being returned. Well
then, not only can I trigger the outer_function
which is just going to give me I'm outer,
now I can also trigger the inner_function separately by calling it
and then adding the activator which is the parentheses.
So now it says I'm outer after it evaluates this line,
I'm inner after it evaluates this line. Now,
if this is confusing to you,
I recommend heading over to the course resources where I've got a link to this
Python Tutor where I've entered all the code that we've seen just now
and we can execute this code line by line.
So you can see that the first thing that happens is it looks at this outer_
function and it creates a reference to that function. Now
next, it's on this line where our outer_function is actually being executed
because it has the parentheses at the end.
So now it's actually going to go inside this outer function and go through it
line by line where it prints I'm outer and then sets up a reference to this second
function, which is the nested_function.
The nested_function can now be called by its name
which is nested_function. But the very end of the outer_function,
that function is going to be the return value. So it's going to be outputted.
Finally,
we get to the end of this line nine and we set up a reference from this variable
called inner_function to this nested_function. And finally,
when we get to the line 10 we trigger that function.
So here is our inner_function which points to this nested function
and so when we trigger this inner_function,
it's the same as triggering the nested_function.
And that is when we end up going into this function
and printing out what it says inside.
Have a play around with that to fully get to grips with all the things that you
can do with a function.
And once you're happy with all of this and you've reviewed it and you understand
everything that's going on,
then you've got the foundations to head over to the next lesson where we're
going to talk about Python decorators.
In the last lesson,
we had a primer on functions so that we can understand the next step
which is the Python decorator.
So we've seen that functions can have functionality, inputs,
and outputs, functions are first-class objects and can be passed around as arguments,
functions can be nested in other functions,
and finally, functions can be returned as the output from another function
without needing to trigger it. With these four things in mind,
we're finally ready to tackle the Python decorator.
First of all,
I'm actually going to create a Python decorator for you so that we can talk
about how it works.
Here's what a Python decorator function looks like.
We started off by creating just a normal function.
Let's say I call it my decorator_function.
This function is going to take another function as an input.
Now, inside the decorator_functionn, I'm going to nest a wrapper_function.
And this wrapper_function is then going to trigger the actual function that was
passed in to the decorator function.
And at the end of calling all the lines in my decorator_function,
I'm going to return my wrapper_function. But remember
without the parentheses. Now,
basically what we've done is we've created a decorator_function
which can do some stuff and it could control the calling
of the function that was passed in.
Remember that a decorator_function is just a function that wraps another
function and gives that function some additional functionality.
That's quite a mouthful, but let's take a look at an example.
Let's say that I wanted to create a simple function
which I'll call say_hello.
Now this function is going to be the simplest form of function.
It has no inputs and it has no outputs
and all it does is just going to print hello. Now,
what if I don't want to run this immediately
the moment when I hit run, what if I wanted to add a delay to this function?
Well, one way of doing that would be importing the time module
and then before we print hello,
we can go ahead and run time.sleep
and we can sleep for a prespecified number of seconds.
So now when I call this method, say_hello,
and when I run it, you'll see that immediately nothing happens.
And then after a two second delay, you can see the print
hello actually gets triggered. Now,
what if I wanted to create a whole bunch of functions
like say_bye and say_greeting.
And I wanted to add a delay onto each of these. Well,
then I would have to copy and paste this code into all three places.
Now, this is a very simple example,
but frequently we'll want to add some additional piece of functionality to a
number of our functions. So this is where the decorator comes in handy.
What we could do is before we trigger the function that's passed in to
the decorator_function, we can add the delay.
So now whenever we decorate a function with this particular decorator_function,
then it's going to delay for two seconds before it runs the function.
So let's give this decorator function a little bit more of a descriptive name.
Let's call it a delay_decorator. Well,
now what we can do is we can simply use an @ sign
and we can call the delay_decorator in front of the methods
which we want to delay. So we can add it to all three of them,
or we can only add it to some of them.
But now when I actually run my function, say_hello
for example, you can see that this one
because it's got the delay decorator
it's going to wait for two seconds before it prints hello.
But if I call say_greeting
which is the one that doesn't have the decorator above it,
then you can see it gets triggered immediately.
So this is a really nice way of adding something that you could do before you
run the function,
Right?
or adding some functionality which you can do after the function. Or
alternatively, you can modify the function so maybe you wanna run it twice.
So now when I say hello,
it's going to not only delay by two seconds,
but it's also going to run it twice.
This syntax is what we saw when we were creating our Flask
app. It's got the @ sign and it basically decorates the function below with a
decorator function.
So putting this function through a machine that could modify the function or add
some functionality before or after. Coming back to our definition,
a decorator function is simply a function which wraps another function and gives
it some additional functionality or modifies the functionality.
Now, coming back to this syntax, this @ sign, it's
what's known as syntactic sugar.
It's some syntax that you can write to make it easier to write an alternative
line of code.
So let's say we wanted to add the decorator to this say_greeting. Well,
if instead of using this syntactic sugar with the @ sign
and then the name of the function,
we could also just call the name of the decorator and then we could pass in the
name of our function, say_greeting,
and then we would end up with the decorated function as the output from this
method.
And we can now call the decorated function with the parentheses.
So now we've triggered this say_greeting function
and we've passed it through the delay decorator.
But it's much easier to see at a glance what's going on by using this @ sign
because you can see now you can just trigger this method by its own name
and because the @delay_decorator is on top of it,
then it's going to go through that filter.
I recommend spending a few minutes looking at this code
which you can access at this URL which is in the course resources,
and then trying to recreate this functionality from scratch based on your
understanding of what we just talked about. And then once you're done,
when we head back to our Flask application
you can now see that pretty much all of the code is easily understood.
We know what this __name__ refers to,,
we know that this is a decorator
which is going to make sure that we only trigger this function
if the user's trying to access the URL
that is the homepage/.
If we wanted to create another function, let's call it say_bye.
This function could also get a decorator
and this decorator will check to see well, if somebody goes to the URL
/bye, well
then we're going to be triggering this method. Effectively
the Flask framework is the one that determines which of these methods to call
and these methods are only called when the decorator says that it's appropriate to do
so. Now, if I go ahead and run this code once more,
and we go to the URL that is our server,
so this we know is the home route or the homepage,
but if we go to /bye
then we go to the bye route and this method gets rendered.
Now in order to make sure that you get a chance writing decorator functions
yourself, if you head over to the next lesson,
I've got a coding exercise for you to challenge you
to create your own decorator functions.
And it's going to be a really useful decorator function because it's going to
measure the amount of time that it takes a particular function to run.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Hey guys, welcome today.
55 of a hundred days of code today.
We've got yet another jam packed day for you because we're going to be diving
right deeper into web development with flask. And along the way,
we're going to be learning some new concepts as well,
including how to render HTML on your website that you serve up using flask.
And in addition,
how to get hold of and pass the URL that the user typed in finally,
right? It also going to be looking into advanced decorators,
so decorators where we can pass in inputs as positional and keyword arguments.
And we're going to be doing some exercises around that.
But what all of this knowledge is going to culminate into is a guest,
the number of web, right? All right. When we go to the, a home route,
so just a single slash afterwards,
it asks us to guess a number between zero and nine.
And then if we type in eight guests into the path, let's say,
we decide to guess the number three, it tells us to low try again.
So this is HTML with styling with an H one,
as well as a gift being rendered. Now,
what if we try too high or, you know, a gift? And then finally,
if we land onto the correct number,
then we get a scene that tells us we found the correct number.
So that's the goal.
Once you already heard of it to the next lesson and let's get started.
Now, one of the first things I want to tackle is getting it out.
Hold on the user typed in too, the URL,
or rather known as parsing a URL in this case,
if the user typed in ww.mysite.com and then they had a forward slash with a
path, for example,
forward slash Angela or forward slash mail forward slash messages forward slash
pictures, then we want to be able to get hold of the information in that path,
because we might be able to do something different with it and render something
specific. Based on that URL previously,
we already saw that we could change the route of our website by serving up
different information. So if the user went to the home route,
which is just the URL and then a forward slash,
then we would show them something. But if they went to a different route,
for example, forward slash hello, then we could show them something else.
This is where we left off in our previous lessons.
If I wanted to create a BI function that just simply returns by
then I could set up the route decorator.
So this is the decorator function to look for when the user goes to a specific
path, for example, for what slash buy,
remember that this is a decorator function,
which lives inside a App Object,
which is declared in the flask class. Now,
if all of that sounded like it didn't make any sense,
then be sure to review the lessons that we did in previous days on classes and
methods.
I'm going to assume that all of this is pretty straightforward to you by now.
Now when we run this website,
we can now go to the URL and we can go to the homepage,
which says, hello world. And we could go to the buy route,
which just says, buy with an exclamation. Okay. What if we want,
I wanted to have a variable in that route.
What if we want to get hold of what the user types in him, for example,
let's say that instead of just catching by and forward slash what if we wanted
to greet our user,
let's say I create a greet function that takes their name and it returns
something like hello, but then it adds the name.
Let's turn this into an F string to make that work.
The question is how would we create the route?
Would it be forward slash name or would it be something else?
Well, this is what is described in this section of variable rules.
We can add variable sections to a URL.
So basically it's the equivalent of creating a variable that URL by marking it
with this syntax.
So putting some angle brackets around the variable name,
then all function is going to receive the variable name.
Once the decorator is done with it,
and then we can use it inside our function.
So for example,
let's say that we had a route which is forward slash username,
and then forward slash the actual name of the user,
which we'll put inside some angle brackets.
This means a flask is now going to turn, whatever it is that comes after.
Use a name forward slash into a variable for us to tap into.
And that variable has the name of name.
So now when our greet function goes through that decorator,
it's going to receive that value and we can use it in this greet function.
Now, if I go ahead and rerun my code
and go back to that URL and I go to user name forward slash,
and then I'll put in a user name, for example, Angela,
then that Angela is going to be taken and it's going to be rendered dynamically
into my webpage. So it doesn't matter what it is I put here.
It's always going to respond accordingly and treat this as if it was the value
to a variable.
Now notice how every single time we update our code. So for example,
if I didn't want this to be under the route forward slash username fall in slash
name,
instead if I just wanted to put it at forward slash name,
this is not going to work as it is. It's going to give us a four Oh four,
which is not found.
And the reason for this is because we have to stop and refresh all server for
these changes to be reflected.
So I have to stop and then rerun my server.
And now if I go to here and I start typing something like John,
then this update to the route is now live.
If we are testing and developing our website, this is really painful.
Having to stop and rerun the server every single time we make a change in our
server file.
So one of the things that you might notice here is that there is something
called a debug mode, and we can set this to be on or off.
Now there's a couple advantages of having the debug mode on and it's described
in the Quickstart. It allows us to activate the debugger,
which helps us narrow down on any issues.
It activates the automatic reloader so that whenever we edit off a file and hit
save, it's going to reload our server. And finally,
it also enables debug mode on the flask application.
Let's give that a go in order to change our app to run on debug mode.
All we have to do is to change right,
the debug property to true, right?
And now if I go ahead and rerun this application,
then you can see my debug mode is now on.
And I've got this debugger is active and also a debug, a pin,
which we'll come back to in just a minute. If I go to my website,
you can see that I can go there two, a route like this,
and it still works.
But if I was to change something in my code,
for example, just adding a new word into the return.
If I go ahead and hit command S on Mac or control us on windows to save this
file, then it will right.
Reload the server because it's tech did a change in that file,
and it's going to reload our server automatically so that we don't have to stop
and start all over again. So now,
if we go back over here and we refresh this page,
then you can see that update in the code is now reflected.
This is pretty neat. But in addition, we could also do other things.
For example, if we actually need to debug an issue, for example,
let's say that here in my variable path,
instead of saying name, I quote it username.
But then in my greed function,
I'm still trying to tap into this variable code name.
So now if I hit save,
it's going to reload my server and you can see that there's actually nothing
wrong with what I've done. This is all syntactically valid.
But if I go to my website here and I hit enter,
I actually get the flight task debug view.
So it's it actually telling me in this nicely formatted way?
What is the issue? So the main issue, right, is that I got a type II error.
Yeah, it happens.
If we scroll through the bottom is that the green function got an unexpected
keyword argument called username.
So that debugger might help us to figure out that, Oh, actually,
I've named this wrong.
Now this is an issue with the path here. But alternatively,
I could have made an error in my code as well. For example,
let's say that we want to take the name that's being passed in him.
We decided that we were going to add 12, two, it for some reason or other. Now,
if I hit save so that my server reloads and I tried to refresh this website,
you can see again, I've got a type II error. And this time though,
it's telling me that I can only concatenate string,
not an integer to a string. And if we go through these files,
you can see one of these lines, the first to a file that we wrote, hello, dot.
And it tells us that online 18 in the greet function,
this is the line. That's tripping it up. Now,
one of the things I can do at this point is I can actually open up the flask,
a debugger. And I do that by clicking on this button right here.
And what this is going to ask is for that pin that I showed you earlier on,
which is in our console.
This means that if somebody else is accessing your website,
live on the internet and you happen to have it in debug mode,
they can't just go and mess around with your code.
Let's go and scroll to the bottom and copy our debugging code and then paste it
in here as the pin, and then confirm to gain access to the debugger.
Now,
what it's done is basically its open up a console that is live on this line.
So now what I can do is I can print out for example,
the variables that it could access on that line, for example, name,
and it tells me that name is Angela. I can start diagnosing, well,
why is this wrong? So if I wanted you to add name to 12,
well I can narrow it down.
And it shows me that you can only add a string to a string or an integer to an
integer. You can't mix up the types.
So that might make me realize that actually I need to change this also to a
strength. Now,
if I go ahead and refresh,
you can see there's no problems there and I've managed to fix the problem with
the help of the flask debugger.
Now just a few more things on this URL.
One of the things that we could do is we could add some texts to the path
before. So you remember that I said username slash name. So that works.
We can also add paths afterwards.
So it could be one or two, whatever it may be.
And we can now access this route by going to our URL and then going to the first
part, which was username.
And then it was the variable that we could put in.
And then finally we can add even more to the path afterwards.
So we're in our case, the path is one. So now if I hit enter,
you can see it still goes to the same page,
but it's only this middle pot that's being taken as the value to this name
variable. Now,
if we go back to the flask Quickstart,
you can see that the final thing you mentioned is there is something called a
converter on the converter,
basically converts the URL into any data type that you specify by default,
it converts that variable value into a string,
which means it's going to accept any text without a slash. Now,
if you want to keep the slash, because if you are using a path,
then that might be quite important. So for example,
you wanted to get this entire part as your variable slash Juan.
Well then in that case, instead of using this, you would have to specify, well,
the data type is going to be a path and then I'm gonna save that as the name.
So now if I hit save and I use this same URL,
you can see the rest of that path is now being rendered in my variable and it's
being pulled in for whatever it is that I may need it for.
Now, alternatively, you can also have more than one variable, of course.
So maybe this first part, I'm going to keep it as a name,
which is a string. And then the second part, I want a number.
So maybe I'll keep it as the datatype integer and I'll give the variable a name,
a code number.
So now I can tap into the name and then I can also tap into a number like,
so now coming back here,
if I change this URL with a bit and I hit enter,
you can see it's taken this and placed it here.
It's taken this and placed it here.
So that's a quick little bit on how we can extract the parts that we want from a
URL by using these variable paths in the next lesson,
we're going to see how we can control the HTML that gets rendered instead of
just letting flask render what is the default.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now in the last lesson,
we talked a little bit about how to get different routes to work by using the
app dot route decorator,
as well as how we can create variable paths by using this angle bracket syntax
and how we can convert the path into a pre-specified data type by using this
particular structure. Now,
we also looked at how to run the App in debug mode so that we can auto reload
our server and also get access to the flask debugger. Now,
in this lesson,
I want to talk a little bit about how we can render actual HTML,
because at the moment,
what happens is we're simply just returning a string and we're getting flask to
do whatever it wants with it. And what that means.
If we go into the Chrome inspector,
by going to view and then developer and then develop a tools is we can see it.
It just stuffed that whole
F-string into a body tag without any real HTML tags that gives it structure.
So that's usually not what you would want when you're creating a website.
So let's see if we can start creating some HTML. Instead.
Now the simplest way to do this is flask actually accepts HTML in the return.
So we could just a simply say,
if we wanted to create an H one by adding an H one opening and closing tag here,
and if I hit save to refresh my server and then go to my home route,
then you can see this is now inside and H one inside the body.
Now, of course you can change this to whatever target is you want,
and it should still work. Now,
once we can start rendering HTML,
we can also start using the HTML attributes, by the way,
if any of this that I'm talking about HTML or CSS or attributes or tags sounds
unfamiliar, it might be because you've skipped the sessions on each balance CSS,
which we went through a few,
Two days ago. So have a quick search for that.
If all of this is confusing and it might be a good time to do a revision on
that. Anyways. Now coming back to my H one tag,
let's say I wanted to give it some CSS, which is just inline CSS.
So I'm going to set the style and give it some CSS code. For example,
I could set the text, the line CSS property to center,
and now if I hit save and I refresh on my homepage,
my text is now center aligned,
and you can see if I select this H one,
you can see that style being applied right here.
Anything that we can do with inline styling that you saw in the CSS modules or
changing the code to any sort of HTML tag we can do in the return.
Now, what if you wanted to render more than one HTML element? Well,
that's possible as well. All you have to do is just continue typing.
So let's say we wanted to create a paragraph tag. Well,
we could simply create it like this.
So if I hit save and refresh, you can see, this is my H one,
and this is a paragraph,
and this is the updated structure of my HTML file
now because pie charm doesn't really like you going too far over and creating
very long lines of code because it's difficult to read.
One of the neat tricks that it has is if you want to split a string at any
point, all you have to do is hit enter,
and it will add in this backslash for you,
which basically is the equivalent of the same code that we had before.
But it's now much easier to read.
So you can add in as many lines of HTML as you want in this fashion.
For example, if we wanted to add a another line,
then we would go inside the paragraph quotation Mark hit enter to insert another
line. And here we can add our image element.
Our image element is a self closing tags. We don't need the closing tag,
but it does need a source.
And this source could be a image that we find online.
So let's see if we can find a picture of a kitten.
This one looks pretty good.
Let's go ahead and copy the image address here by right clicking.
And then let's piece that in here as the image source. Now,
if I go ahead and hit, save and go back to my website and reload it,
you can see that is my little cat.
Now you can add other attributes, do the image tag. For example,
you can change the width to you only 200 pixels so that it would fit in to this
site a little bit better, or you can manipulate it in any way you want.
Now, the great thing about the image tag is we can also add gifts as well,
and it'll be rendered in our browser.
So Giphy is a great source of gifts from all over the internet.
So let's find an animated kitten on him.
This one is very cute. If we go to copy link and then copy the gift link,
and we replace this URL,
that's currently inside the source with this new URL,
then we would end up with our gift of being rendered as an image. Now,
one thing to note is that as we're changing these source attributes or the style
attributes,
the tax let's going in there is going in as a string with the quotation marks.
So this will clash with any outer quotation marks.
So be sure that if you've got a return as a single quoted string,
that in the middle, if you need to have quotes,
it will be double quotes basically has to be opposite of each other.
If you have single quotes on the outside,
then you're going to be using double quotes on the inside.
If you are using the opposite,
then it's double quotes on the outside that it has to be single quote on the
insight let's hit, save and see if this worked,
go back to our home page, hit refresh,
and you can see there is a fairy cute kitten being rendered in HTML from a flask
server.
So we've now leveled up a website a little bit more. We can now render HTML.
We can put an inline styling and we can add HTML elements to our heart's
content. Now in the next lesson, I've got a little bit of a challenge for you.
And the idea is for you to practice what you learned yesterday about decorators.
It's a bit of a advanced topic, but once you get used to it, it's really,
really handy. So for all of that and more head of it in the next lesson,
All right guys. So in yesterday's lessons that we talked about,
Python decorators, and we did quite a few exercises around that.
Now,
in order to test your knowledge and make sure that you haven't forgotten how to
use it, I've got a challenge for you to apply your knowledge of decorators.
Here's the challenge in this route that I've got here,
which is just forward slash bye.
One of the things that we learnt in the last lesson is that we can turn this
into an HTML element by simply wrapping it around HTML tags.
So for example,
if I wanted to turn this BI into a bolded,
by that I could add the B tag around it.
So now if I hit save and I go to my forest slash buy route,
then you can see that this text is now bolded. Like, so
now I can continue wrapping the text around more tags.
If I wanted a turn in a tallit, then I can wrap it around some emphasis tags.
So the EMT tag, and this will make it look like this.
And finally,
I can also make it underlined by wrapping it inside a you tag like this.
So now it's bold emphasized and underlined,
which looks like this. Now, what I want to do though,
is I don't really want to add all of this using strings because it's prone to
errors and it could be making typos, and it's just a bit of a pain to edit.
So what I want to do instead is under the first App dot route decorator,
which is important to identify the route to render what's in this method.
I want to be able to add some other decorators. For example,
let's say I added a decorator that I created somewhere up there called make
bolt. And if I hit save, you can see it's done the same thing.
It's added the B tag around that text.
I can also add some my other ones that I made earlier,
like make emphasis and make underlined.
So now I can add a whole bunch of decorators to my by function.
And once that's rendered, you can see it's got the bold,
it's got the emphasis and it's got the underline.
And that was much easier because I've got the auto suggest from PI jam.
And also I've got my decorator working in the background.
So your task is this,
your task is to create these three decorators,
which each will achieve the named effect.
So either making the text bold, making emphasize, or making an underlined.
So this is a bit of a revision and a bit of a challenge.
I'll let you pause the video and complete this challenge.
And in the next lesson, I'll reveal the solution code. Give that 10 minutes,
give it a good go and see if you can complete this challenge.
Previously, we looked at simple Python decorator functions.
And the reason why it's simple is because all that we're doing when we're
calling the function in the decorator is we're just calling it straight up.
But this doesn't take into account in the cases where, for example,
we want to add a condition before we called the function or even more advanced.
What if we needed to call the function with some sort of inputs?
How would we get hold of that? If it was inside a decorator?
So let's say that we had a class called user.
Now, if you are not familiar with classes,
I strongly recommend going back to the lessons where we covered classes and
Object in great detail.
We did over several days just to make sure that you're up to date with that
before you continue. But this is a pretty simple class.
All it does is it has two properties, a name, property,
and it is logged in property.
So basically what we're trying to simulate is a condition where let's say we had
a blog website and we had these user objects and the user has a username and
also some sort of property that keeps track of whether,
or if the user is going onto the website and not logged in,
or whether if they all have already logged in.
So certain methods on the website,
you can only be achieved by users who are logged in it's. For example,
if they wanted you to create a new blog post we'll,
then that user has to be checked.
And we have to make sure that they are in fact logged in and authenticated to
create a new blog post.
If I go ahead and create a new user from the user class,
then I can give it a name, which I'll put as Angela.
And then I could create the blog post and pass in my user.
Now, when I hit run, you'll see, this is Angela's new blog,
post being printed right here.
Now what if I wanted to create a decorator function that could be used to
decorate any function on our website that requires authentication.
So it requires that this users is logged in property is set to true.
So let's say that I decided to create my decorator function right here,
which I'll call the is authenticated decorator.
And this is of course going to need to take a function as an input.
And then inside, we've got our wrapper function.
Now inside our wrapper function is where we call this function.
That's the past and right here.
And finally to complete our decorator.
We have to return the wrapper as a function without the parentheses.
Now, in order to check for the is authenticated,
what we actually want to do is we want to say, well,
if the user.is logged in is equal to true will in that case,
we're going to trigger the function. But if it's actually not true, well,
then we're not going to trigger the function. Now,
the only problem here is that this user is undefined.
We were only able to pass in the function,
but what if we needed to pass in some arguments associated with that function?
Notice here that all function create blog posts, which is what we want to add.
The decorator to accepts an input in the form of the user. Object.
If I decorate this function with the is authenticated decorator,
and I tried to run this,
then it's not really gonna work because that user is not defined.
And it tells us that the wrapper function takes zero positional arguments,
but one was given.
And the one that's given is this user right here,
this era might already be a good hint for us to figure out how to fix this.
One of the things that we talked about in previous lessons is the concept of OGs
and clogs, unlimited positional arguments.
Normally all add it in as asterix,
OGs and unlimited keyword arguments are usually added in as two Astrix and then
Crocs. So now we can have all function,
which is decorated with this decorate to function.
And when we call the function,
we could provide some inputs and those inputs can be tapped into via these OGs
and Crocs. Now, in this case,
this is a positional argument and it's the argument App positions zero.
So instead of using this user, which is what we would do,
if we were inside this function, instead,
we would use the wrappers OGs,
and then we would use the position set to zero.
So now it's going to look at the function that is going to be passed in which is
going to have some inputs.
And it's going to take that first position input and then see if it is logged in
property is equal to true.
Now that my wrapper is taking positional arguments and keyword arguments,
and I can tap into the first positional argument by using Oxy zero.
Well inside the rapt function,
I can now also use this first argument in order to give it as an input to that
function.
Remember that this function is simply this create blog post function without the
decorator. Now, if I go ahead and hit run,
you will see that nothing happens unless I change this users is logged in
property to equal. True. And now that that's true,
then it's going to be checked right here.
And then it's going to call the function because that user is now logged in this
idea of being able to pass in positional arguments,
as well as keyword arguments,
by simply adding the odds and quarks to the wrapper function,
and then using it inside the wrapper or using it to call the function itself is
one step higher in terms of understanding Python,
decorator functions.
I recommend spending a few minutes looking at this code,
which you can access at this URL, which is in the course resources,
and then trying to recreate this functionality from scratch based on your
understanding of what we just talked about in the next lesson,
I've got a coding exercise for you so that you can try out this new advanced
form of Python decorators and try creating one yourself.
Hey guys,
and welcome to day 56 of 100 Days of Code. It's Angela here
and today we are diving deeper into web development with Flask.
We're going to be covering a bunch of things,
including how to include static files on your website
like local images or local videos,
as well as how to render HTML and CSS files. Previously,
when we looked into web design
and we learned about creating websites using HTML and CSS,
we were able to create it as a separate file with the proper structure and
styling.
And we want to apply that now to our Flask applications.
And we want to be able to show the user
a HTML website with CSS styling.
Now at the very end of today
we're going to be building out a beautiful personal name card application.
It's the 21st century and we no longer have to hand people name cards.
Instead, you could create a website,
put your name on it and have all the links to the relevant pages that you
need and to show off your beautiful design
as well as give people your contact details. That's the goal for today.
Head over to the next lesson and let's get started.
Now, the first thing I want to show you is how to render HTML files.
Go ahead and create a new PyCharm project. I've called mine my-personal-site,
but you can call yours anything you like. And in the project,
we're going to create a new file which is going to be our Python server.
So I'll call it server.py. And then inside our server.py
we're going to go through all the stages of building up a simple Flask server.
This might be a good time to revise how to do that. So go ahead,
pause the video and see if you can set up a simple Flask application
which just serves up hello world to the homepage.
All right. So let's start from the beginning.
We'll import the Flask class from the flask application.
And as usual, I'm going to use my red light bulb to install the Flask package.
Now, once I've done that,
I'm going to create my Flask application by saying app = Flask.
And then inside the initialization for my Flask application,
I'm going to put in the name of my current directory.
Next,
we're going to use the route decorator to target the home route.
And when the user hits up the home route,
we're going to render the home page.
So inside this definition,
we're simply just going to return hello world. And finally,
we're ready to go ahead and check to see if the name is equal to main, then in
that case we're going to run our app. That's it.
That's all there is to it.
Let's go ahead and run this application
which is our server.py. And if we head over to this URL,
we can see hello world when we go to our homepage.
The next step is to figure out how can we render an HTML webpage
which is crafted inside an HTML file rather than simply just returning strings
or small bits of HTML elements.
Let's go into our file and go ahead and create a new HTML file.
Now,
the reason why we creating it like this is because it's going to add in all of
the boilerplate code that is required to an HTML website.
So let's go ahead and call our web page index.html.
And you can see as soon as I create it, it's added in the doctype,
it's added in the HTML, the head and the body. Now,
if this is unfamiliar to you,
be sure to check out the lessons where we covered HTML and CSS in detail.
But I'm going to assume that all of this is pretty straightforward by now.
Now the first thing we're going to change in our new website is the title.
So I'm going to go ahead and give this a title.
You can put anything you want, but I'm just going to put my own name here. Now,
inside the body,
I'm going to create a h1 and you can see that the HTML files on PyCharm has that
tag completion that we see here. In my h1
I'm just going to write I'm Angela. Pretty straightforward.
This is a complete HTML file now. Now,
if I want to render this instead of just hello world, how would I do that?
Well, how do we find out? As always it's through
the documentation. In the documentation of the quickstart for Flask
there's a section on rendering templates.
And this allows us to render an HTML file as a template.
There's a couple of requirements though. Tthe first thing is that
remember that Flask is a framework and not a library.
So it will put certain restrictions and requirements on your code so that it
will actually work. And in this case, our HTML files,
which is known as our templates, must be inside a folder called templates.
That's where Flask is gonna look for it when we try to render it.
So let's first do that. Let's create a new directory
which we'll call templates, all lower case,
and let's move our index.html into that new folder.
So there is. The next thing we have to do is we have to import this method called
render_template from the Flask module.
So let's go back to our server.py
and in addition to importing the Flask class,
let's go ahead and import the render_template method as well.
The next thing we have to do is to,
instead of returning a string or a string that contains HTML,
we have to call this method render_template and pass in the file name that we
have and then that is going to be rendered into our website.
So let's go ahead and do this. Let's delete that hello world
and instead, let's return the output from this render_template method.
And inside here, we're going to put the name of our HTML file
which lives inside our templates folder.
That's going to be index.html because that's what we called it.
Now let's go ahead and run our code. Alternatively,
let's switch on the debug mode so that it will refresh and rerun our
server every time we make a change. So let's rerun
and now let's go to our website,
refresh the main page and you can see it's now got an h1 in here and in the
head, there is now the title, which is Angela,
which is the title of the tab as well.
Imagine if you had to type all of this HTML into this return as a string.
It's pretty painful.
It doesn't have any of the assistants that you get from your editor.
Now here's a challenge for you. Back in days 41 and 42
we learned about HTML and we created a CV website that looks something like
this, which we managed to publish and upload to GitHub. Now,
what I want you to do is to go and find your own CV website
and then go to the link either on your GitHub page or find the original HTML
file and I want you to go ahead and get hold of it.
So if it's on GitHub, then you can go ahead and simply save as
and save this webpage into your downloads.
Now, if it saved as a HTML file somewhere in your system, that's also fine.
But essentially what we want to do is we want to take this file,
which is an HTML file,
and we want to move it into our templates. Now,
one of the things that you'll notice is if you downloaded this file off the
internet,
then you might have to rename it because firstly it's really long
and we don't want to have to type that into our code.
So I'm going to shorten the name to angela. And then at the very end,
you can see the file extension at least when it comes off GitHub, is .htm.
And the reason for this is because some servers don't accept four-lettered file
extensions, but it's exactly the same as .html.
So we're going to change it to .HTML and then we're going to re factor that.
So now that we've got hold of this HTML page,
we're going to try and render it instead of the index.html.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this as a challenge.
Right.
All right. That's pretty simple.
All we have to do is just replace the index.html to the new file
which is angela.html.
And if that file happened to be inside a folder for example,
if we had a subfolder inside templates which we've called, I don't know cv,
and we had this inside here,
then we would have to specify that in the file path.
If we just have it in the top level of our templates folder,
then it's as simple as what we did with the index.html.
So now, while our server is running in debug mode,
we can go ahead and hit save on this website and it should restart our server.
And now if we go back to our main homepage and reload the website,
you can see it's now rendering our personal CV site with only one exception.
What has happened to this profile picture? It looks pretty broken.
Now in order to be able to render static images,
we're going to have to learn how to render static files
such as images like this. That's what we're going to do in the next lesson.
As we saw previously when we rendered the HTML page of our CV,
one of the components is an image tag and it has a image file that it needs to
render. But it looks pretty broken when we rendered HTML.
So if we go ahead and open up the Chrome developer tool
which is under view, developer, and developer tools,
then if we go to console
you'll see that we actually get a bunch of 404 errors and they relate
to the styles.css file as well as the angela.png file.
That is what this is referring to.
And you can actually see
we get the same 404 errors when we look at the debug log in here as
well. So we're missing some stuff basically. Well, firstly,
let's see if we can recover it.
We can go ahead and save this image from the website
which I'll just call angela.png.
And then we can drag this image into our personal site.
And there it is right there. Now, in my case,
my image actually happens to be a circular one
which I edited in Photoshop,
but you might just have a square one and it doesn't matter at all.
Now that we've got our image inside our project,
how do we make sure that that image actually gets rendered in our HTML site?
Because here is the image tag and it's looking inside Angela's personal site
files for angela.png, which is not what we have here.
In fact, if we had moved this PNG file to the same
folder so they're on the same hierarchy, basically inside the same folder,
well then we could probably just change this to angela.png.
If I go ahead and restart and rerun my server after I've added in all these
files and I go to my personal site and I hit reload,
you'll see that there's still no photo. So why is that? Well,
back to the Flask documentation we go.
The reason is because, just like our templates have to be inside a folder called
templates, Flask will look for all your static files
like your images or your CSS files inside a folder called static.
So you have to put it inside a folder called static.
They made the framework, they make the rules. So inside our project
my-personal-site, let's create a new directory called static and let's move our
image into that static folder.
Now inside our angela.html, when we want to point to that image,
then the path is going to be static/ the name of the file inside
that folder, which in my case is angela.png. Now,
if I go ahead and rerun my application,
then go back to my homepage and refresh,
you should see that image being rendered.
It was able to look inside the static folder and find that image.
Whenever you create a Flask application, 9 out of 10 times
you'll need to create it with the templates folder and the static folder.
And you put all your static files like your CSS files or your images or your
videos inside that folder
and your file path is relative to that folder.
And then when you create your HTML templates,
you're going to put it inside the templates folder.
Now going back to my project,
I'm going to delete all the extra files that we created just now in the demo.
Right.
And I should now only end up with my index.html
which is our simple website. Now,
the reason why I wanna keep it simple is just so that you really understand
everything from the ground up.
And the challenge I've got for you is to go ahead and create a CSS style sheet,
and then using the style sheet
change the background of the body of this index.html website to purple.
That's the goal. You are going to have to change the server.py,
you're going to have to change the index.html,
and you're going to have to create a CSS file.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge.
Right.
All right. The first thing we're going to do is create a CSS file.
That is going to be a static file.
We're going to create it inside the static folder.
So I'm going to call it styles.css
and now I'm going to go ahead and target the body of my website to the body tag,
and then I'm going to change the background color to purple
like this.
So very simple CSS code here. Now that when it's run is going to target this body
tag which is basically the body of our website
and hopefully it's going to turn the background purple. Now,
in order for that CSS to work though,
we're going to have to add it into the head of our HTML file just as we've done
it thousands of times before when we did the lessons on CSS and HTML.
In order to add that in, we're going to create a link element
which is going to have a relationship. Now,
the relationship is going to be a style sheet.
So it's basically telling the HTML file that this link points to a style sheet.
And then the href of the style sheet is going to be inside static/
styles.css.
Now let's go ahead and save both of these files and go back to our server and
make sure that we're rendering that HTML template which is index.html.
And now if we go ahead and stop and restart this project so that it takes into
account all the new files, and then we go to our homepage,
hopefully it should show you a page that has a purple background
like you see here. Now,
one of the things you have to be careful about Chrome is that it likes to cache
your static files. So what does this mean? Well,
let's go back to the styles.css and I'm going to change that background-color
to red. Now I'm going to hit save on this file.
I'm even going to stop and rerun my file,
but you can see if I refresh this page, it's still purple.
And if I go into the Chrome developer tools and we take a look at our elements,
you can see that the body still has CSS saying that the background color should
be purple. If we go to the sources inside the static folder,
there's our styles.css. And you can see
this is an older version of our style sheet. So what's going on?
Is it because we didn't save this change? No, we definitely saved it.
What's actually happening is that to save your internet usage,
Chrome likes to cache the style sheets and other static files,
so images or JavaScript.
and the reason why it does that is because when you visit a website,
if you're visiting it on the same day,
these static files are unlikely to change.
A website is unlikely to update their CSS or their images over one day.
So once the browser downloads it,
it keeps hold of those static files.
This just means that you don't have to keep downloading these large files every
single time you hit up the same website.
That's kind of good if we are in fact visiting a real live website.
But when we're testing, it's a little bit confusing.
So one of the things you have to do is you have to get Chrome to hard reload.
And you can do that by holding down the shift key and clicking on this refresh
button, which is going to do a hard reload.
And it's going to get rid of all the cached files and pull in any new files.
So now the background changes to red. And we can confirm that by... let's change
this to blue hit save on that file, holding down shift, reload,
and we get the blue background updating.
So that's just something to be careful about when you find that your CSS files
or your other static files are not being changed or not being rendered.
All right guys,
it's time for another challenge to review what we learned in the last lesson.
Back when we learned CSS on days 43 and 44, the end project that we created
was a personal site that looks something like this.
It's beautifully designed with CSS styling,
images, gifs, and a whole lot more. Now,
what I want you to do is to take your version of this personal site and get it
to run with your Python server. And in the process,
you'll review what you learned about rendering HTML files
as well as serving up static files.
Hopefully, you've got all your files lying around somewhere in your computer.
If you don't,
you can go ahead and head over to the course resources where I've included a
link to download all of these files as a zip file.
Once you have unzipped that zip file,
you should end up with a folder that looks like this.
We've got our favicon, our CSS folder with our styles.css,
our image folder with all four images,
and you want to move these files to their respective places inside the personal
site.
Feel free to go ahead and delete the index.html and the styles.css
and see if you're able to use the files that you've got here to render it using
your Python server. Pause the video and give that a go.
All right.
So the first thing we need to do is to move the files in here to their respective
places. The index.html is going to go inside the templates folder,
but pretty much everything else is going to go inside the static folder.
So that includes the CSS, the favicon, as well as the images folder.
Now that we've moved everything in here,
there's actually nothing we need to do inside our server.py
because it's still trying to render a webpage called index.html,
which in our case, it's still called index.html. Now,
the thing that we do have to change though is inside our index.html
it's pointing straight towards css/styles.css,
and also for the favicon, it's pointing straight to the favicon file.
What we need to do is to take into account that it's now living inside a folder
called static.
So we're going to have to add the full file path to anywhere where we have a
local static file being used.
So that includes the CSS,
that includes the favicon, also any of the images that we're using in here.
And if you want for sort of convenience sake,
you can actually just copy this part
which is the source of the images and then you can hold down
Command+ R on Mac or Control + R on Windows to bring up the find and replace.
And we're gonna replace this with static/images/. So we're basically
adding static to this images/. And if we go ahead and replace it in all five
places, then we should now be done with all of our refactorings.
Now let's go ahead and restart our file so that it looks at all of these new
image, and let's go to our website
which is being served up by Python
and hopefully you have the same result as I do
which is the same personal site,
but now served up with our Python server.
Now this process has been pretty pain-free
I would say. We simply moved in the required index.html,
the CSS images and the favicons,
so all the files that make up a particular website.
And we simply added it to our Flask project.
Now,
what you can also do is you can get templates of HTML and CSS files from the
internet. For example, a website like html
5up.net,
where they have beautiful free templates that you can tap into.
Now consider if you were creating your own personal site,
then you can pick from all of these beautiful HTML templates
which you can then update and personalize. For example,
if we take this first one, we can go ahead and see it as a live demo.
So we can see this website as it is, and we can see how cool it looks.
It's got buttons, it's got JavaScript, it's got beautiful CSS styling,
and this might be a really good website for say, keeping track of our portfolio,
like the website's that we're building; to have images of the websites,
a link to the website, some brief description.
And then we could just put this up online and whenever we want to get hired as a
web developer, we could point people towards it.
So how do we make this work with Python? Well,
the first thing we have to do is simply hit download,
and it's going to download all of the files that make up this website.
Now remember that because we're getting it for free,
we need to attribute the designer who created this website.
If you don't want to attribute it and you want to use it for commercial use,
then you can pay just $19 and access all of their templates as well as support
from the creator. Now compare that to a service like Squarespace
where you're basically getting the same service templates for your website.
But in this case,
you're going to be paying anywhere between $10 to $30 per month
which is a lot more expensive, but it's great if you don't know web development.
But we're not going to be in that camp anymore.
Let's go ahead and unzip that file that we just downloaded,
which was called paradigm shift.
And we're going to try and transfer these files to our website over here.
So again,
I'm going to go ahead and delete all of the previous files that's inside my
static and templates folders,
...
and I'm going to try and move the relevant parts of this new website over.
So here, they've got an index.html,
a read me text and a license text.
So all we need is to move our index.html to the templates
and the images and assets over to the static folder.
Right.
Now, one of the things to note is when you're looking at the demo,
there's all of these beautiful pictures,
but of course the designer doesn't have the rights to these pictures to
distribute. So you'll notice that all the images inside the images folder
are these sort of gradients.
So don't be worried if when you run your website,
you just see a bunch of blurry gradients. It's not a problem.
Now what we want to do is we want to see if we can get this index.html to
work when it's being served up by our server. Now,
the first thing we can do is simply just restart our project,
rerun it and see what it looks like.
So let's refresh this static page and you can see it's got all of the HTML,
but no styling and no images.
So that is probably because we're not specifying the static folder in the path.
So here we've got our assets,
and here we've got an image, but they're both inside the static folder.
So we can do that quick trick with find and replace.
So for anything that's inside the images folder,
we're going to replace it with static/images and for anything that's
inside the assets folder,
we're going to replace it with static/assets.
Right?
And now if we go ahead and hit save and refresh this page,
you can see it's now rendering the images as these sort of gradients
and it also rendering the styling and CSS. Now,
how would you edit this? Well, the easiest way is of course,
to actually just edit this raw HTML.
So you can take any of this HTML and you already understand what most of it
does. You've got tables, you've got headings, you got h1s,
all sorts of tags in here.
And you can edit it just like that. For example,
if we scroll up to very top,
we can change the title to a name for example,
Angela's portfolio. And we can change the h1
which says paradigm shift to our own name for example.
And now when I hit save and I refresh over here,
you can see all of that being reflected.
Now there's an even better way of editing HTML in Chrome.
All thanks to the Chrome developer tools.
If we open up the Chrome developer tools and go to the console,
we can actually type a little bit of JavaScript to make anything on our webpage
editable. So to write this, we tap into the document
which is this entire HTML document, and then we tap into the body
which has everything inside the body tag, which is the content of the website.
And then we can call on a property called contentEditable,
and we can set that to true. Now note here that in JavaScript,
the true booelan is spelled out with a lower t, not capital T like in Python.
But the rest of it is pretty standard code
and we can all understand that. Now once I hit enter and that goes through,
I can close down this pane and now watch this.
I can now edit anything that's on this website.
Cool.
All of these paragraphs or any bits of text is now completely editable.
Now, what if you want to delete some of these elements,
what would be the easiest way to do that? Well,
you can simply open up the Chrome developer tools,
and then we can use this little button here to select any element.
So maybe we want to get rid of this paragraph here, select it,
it locates it in the HTML and I can just hit backspace. So I can select any part
of the HTML elements that I don't like for example,
if I want to get rid of this whole section well I would select it and then
delete it.
Maybe I could delete some more sections and make this a lot simpler.
Now you can see this website just has two sections,
my name and my contact details.
One of the unfortunate things though,
is that all of the changes that you're making here, even though you can see it
and it's great, as soon as you hit refresh,
all of those changes will disappear.
And the reason is because when you hit refresh,
what's happening is your browser is going to your server at this address and
requesting all of the HTML and CSS files,
which of course comes from over here.
So this is unchanged by what we've done just now,
it's completely not changed at all.
So if you want all of these changes that you've made in the HTML,
then what you have to do is actually save this webpage as it is.
And then you can move this HTML into your templates
and you can see that this is now a lot shorter with all of the changes that we
made previously.
And you can replace this with what's inside your index.html.
This is probably one of the easiest ways of modifying a prebuilt template.
And you can see that there's plenty of templates for you to play around with.
In fact, in the next lesson, when we're creating our final project,
you're going to be editing this identity template completely from scratch.
And you are going to be creating a digital name card.
So have a play around.
And once you're done, head over to the next lesson and complete the final
project.
All right, so let's go ahead and run through the solution.
The first thing I'm going to do is to head over
to the website and download the template.
Once I've downloaded the template,
I'm going to unzip the file and get access to all the files inside.
Now I've already set up my Flask server
which is pretty simple by now. I've created my app,
I've set up the home routes and I've set my app to run on debug mode.
Now I have to create the necessary directories.
So I'm going to need a directory called templates,
and I'm also going to need one called static.
With those two folders in place
I can now start moving over the relevant parts of these files; index.html
goes into templates, assets
and images go into static.
Right
Now,
one of the first things we're going to try and do is just to see if this works.
So we're gonna start up our server and try to render that index.html.
And if you've got another project running in the background
which is using our server address,
then you are going to get an error that says address already in use.
So just make sure you stop any other files from running and then run this again.
So here's our webpage with just the HTML. It's very,
very simple, and it doesn't have any of the styling or the images.
So we're going to have to fix that by going into the index.html and figuring
out which parts of it need to be changed.
Now notice that in the download, we got two folders;
assets and images which are now both inside static.
So we're going to have to find and replace anything that is assets and change
that to static/assets,
...
and also do the same with images,
right?
There's actually not a lot of code in here.
You can pretty much scroll from the top to the bottom and you can see there's
not a lot of stuff here.
So now that we've fixed those paths,
let's see if we can hit save and go back to refresh our website.
Now, if you are getting what I'm seeing here
which is the CSS file being rendered from the previous project where we got hold
of the portfolio site, that remember is because the CSS file is a static file and
it's being cached by the Chrome browser. So as I mentioned before,
you have to hold down shift and hit refresh in order to get the new static files
to come over. So now that we've got all of this,
it's time to actually edit the text and the links. Going into here,
we can see that here is the h1 which we can change quite easily,
...
and you can of course add your hrefs to these links for Twitter,
Instagram, Facebook,
copy your Twitter URL and change the Href here to that
if you wish.
And you can change the footer as well. Now,
remember because we didn't buy these templates and we're using it for personal
use, we should really attribute the source where we got it from.
So I'll just leave that as it is. Now, if I hit save,
you can see I've pretty much updated all the text to what I want.
And you can see that this avatar image has disappeared
and the reason is because when I was doing the finding and replacing,
I wasn't careful enough
and I didn't add in the final trailing slash
which should in fact be right here.
So this is going to now render the avatar image.
But of course at the moment,
it's just this blank gradient image inside the images folder.
So what we can do is we can simply replace it with our own image.
So, here in my downloads folder, I've got an image called angela.png.
So I'm going to move my own image into the images folder and refactor that.
And then back in our index.html,
I'm going to point towards that image by changing this file path.
So now I can go ahead and delete this avatar image.
And if I hit save and go back to my website,
you can see my photo now shows up inside the image.
The next thing I want to add is a background image under this gradient here.
So one of the best places to find great images for commercial use is a website
called Unsplash.
So if we look for some sort of image that we could put as the background,
maybe a beach or a sea,
you can see there's thousands of images that you can choose from.
And they all look incredibly beautiful, and they're all large, all HD.
I've decided to go with this picture of the seashore.
And if I go ahead and click on download free,
it should download the large JPEG image onto my computer.
So now I'm going to go ahead and rename that image to
the same name as the original background image
which is just a bg.jpeg.
Right.
Like that.
And now I can delete this file and replace it with my own background.
So remember that the background image here it is actually being rendered from
the CSS files.
And if you look inside the main.css you can see here where it sets the
background image,
it's actually generating a gradient and it's overlaying that on top of something
inside the images folder called bg.jpeg.
So instead of changing it all over here,
all we just did is just name our image the same as what they had before.
Now, if we go ahead and rerun our website,
go back to our website and hard reload,
remember by holding down shift and clicking on the reload button,
you can see that image has now been brought in behind this gradient.
Now the last step is to change that title so that it says our name instead of a
placeholder text. So let's go ahead and change the title
...
to our name and there we have it.
We're now serving up this beautiful website
which we got completely from a template that somebody else's developed.
And all we needed to do was to have enough understanding of HTML,
CSS and how Python servers work in order to customize it for our own purposes.
I hope you enjoyed building this with me
and I hope you'll look through some of the other templates and start messing
around with some of them to create your own custom websites.
Hey guys, welcome to day 57 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be digging deeper into building more advanced Flask applications.
And in order to do that, we're going to be learning about URL
building and templating with Jinja.
So very often when you're creating a website,
you'll get cases where you actually don't want to create the page entirely from
scratch. For example,
if you had a blog and you wanted to have several different posts in the blog,
you don't want to create a separate HTML file for each blog post.
So in that case,
it's really helpful to have a templating language where you can replace bits of
that blog with dynamic content.
And that's where Jinja comes in.
This is a templating language built for Python,
and it's going to allow us to create the general layout of our blog,
the styling and the structure, and then to replace the content, for example,
the title or the subtitle or the body with dynamic content
that's generated each time we load a specific page.
And by the end of today,
you will have built a very simple blog with a number of blog posts.
So here we can see the title and subtitle.
And then when we click on read to see the blog post in detail,
we go to a different page.
And depending on which of these blog posts we've clicked on,
you can see that we're rendering basically the same layout,
the same styling and the same structure,
but each time for each of these pages,
we're getting some different content. So that's the goal.
And once you're ready, head over to the next lesson and we'll get started.
Now to begin, all we need is a simple Flask application.
You can either write this out from scratch for practice,
or you can head over to the course resources and you can download this file as a
zip file. Once you've unzipped it and opened it in PyCharm,
you should see a server.py file
which contains all of the basic code that is required to render hello world onto
the screen.
So if we go ahead and just run this file and go to the local URL of our website,
you should just be able to see hello world. Now,
the next thing I want you to do is to create an HTML file
which you'll call index, and inside this HTML file,
we're going to give it a title of just my website and the more important part is
going to occur in the body. For practice,
go ahead and see if you can create an h1 that says hello world
instead of returning just a hello world as text, and render this index HTML onto
the screen instead. Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right.
So the first thing we have to do was to create an h1 that said hello world.
And once we've created our index.html,
we want to render it as a template instead of just returning this text.
So to do that, we're gonna need this render template function at the top.
So if we're going to say render template,
and then the template we want to render is called index.html.
But one thing you have to remember is that this file has to be inside a folder
called templates because Flask has specific requirements for things like
static files and templates.
So now we should be ready to rerun our app so that it will take into account the
new files and then go to our website and you should see this hello world is
being rendered from our index.html. Now,
one of the things you might be wondering is why is this a template?
Why are we rendering a template
when in fact what we're doing is just sending over an HTML file?
Well, the HTML files can actually act as a template
as long as we know how to work with a templating language.
The templating language that we're going to use is called Jinja
and this is specific for Python.
It allows us to use some syntax like these curly braces, percentage signs,
or double curly braces in order to specify inside the HTML file
which parts should actually be evaluated as Python code.
Let me show you something.
We've already seen that just by putting this text in between the h1
we get this rendered as text in the h1.
And if I go ahead and I wrote something like 5 * 6,
what would you expect our website to look like? Well,
if I go ahead and hit save, and because we're in debug mode,
then our server should allow us to refresh the page and you see,
it's just the plain text of what I wrote right here. Now, however,
if I go ahead and add two curly braces around this expression,
then this now suddenly becomes evaluated as Python code.
So let's hit save again and let's hit refresh and you can see now
instead of 5 * 6, I get 30.
So this is actually being seen as Python code
and the calculated outcome is being put into this h1.
This is why this is known as a templating language,
because it means that we can have an HTML
which acts as the template where the title doesn't change, the head doesn't
change,
the styling doesn't change, and only the parts which we specify inside these curly
braces actually get evaluated as Python code and inserted into the template.
I'm going to add back the hello world inside an h1
and also our Python expression inside this Jinja markup so that you can see
both versions.
The next thing I want to do is what if I wanted to generate a random number?
Let's say I was to create an h3 and inside here
I wanted to generate a random number. How would I do that?
Well, when we're working with something that requires an import, for example,
to get a random number, we're going to need to import the random module,
then it's best to write our code inside our Python server.
Let me show you how this works.
Let's go ahead and import random so that we can generate a random number.
And I'm going to do that inside this home function. Now,
in this case, I'm just going to generate a random number between 1 and 10.
But the most important thing is I want to be able to send this random number
over to my index.html and incorporate it into this template when I render
it. So what I can do after the first parameter
which is the name of the template file,
I can add as many keyword arguments as I need.
If we take a look at this render template,
you can see that after the name of the template,
the next parameter has the double star context.
This is basically the same as when you see the double star keyword arguments or
kwargs.
Basically it says that you can add as many keyword arguments as you want
and each of these keyword arguments need to have a name for the variable and a
value for the variable.
And the reason why they need have a name and value is because we can refer to
that variable by its name inside the templated HTML file.
So for example, if I go ahead and send over a variable
which I'll call num and then set it equal to this random number we've generated
here. Well, now, once this template gets rendered,
it's going to pass over this variable with this name and with this value.
So now in our index.html, I can tap into that variable name
which is num
and I can insert it using these double curly braces into the position that I
want it to be. So that's going to go inside that h3.
And now if I hit save and go ahead and refresh my website,
you can see I've got this random number and then a number show up.
And every time I hit refresh,
you can see that number changes to a different random number between 1 and 10.
So we've seen how we can render an HTML file just by using render
template, but we've also seen that inside the template,
we can use these double curly braces in order to create single lines of Python
expressions
which can be evaluated and then inserted into the position that we desire.
Now, we've also seen that we can pass over any variable
we desire as keyword arguments after the name of the template.
So now I've got a challenge for you. On a lot of websites, for example
if you go to the Jinja website which you'll find in the course resources
and you scroll to the very bottom, there's usually a line of copyright text.
So it will say copyright and the current year
and then the name of the creator or the company.
Now that year is supposed to be the current year to say that this website's
copyright is valid in this current year.
But very often, even Jinja included,
they don't actually update their footer because it's probably just some hard-
coded text, as you can see right here. Now,
this is something that annoys a lot of web developers and web designers.
And they are outraged by the idea that people would have just some plain text
as their copyright. We're programmers, right?
We should be able to update our footer dynamically by using code.
And this is a website which has a pretty much a sort of campaign against
websites with outdated footers. And if you take a look at their footer,
you can see that this is not just a piece of plain text.
This is actually a script using JavaScript to work out the value of the current
year. And so it's always going to be up to date no matter what year it is.
So we also want to have a dynamic footer year,
but we're not going to be doing it with JavaScript and definitely not with PHP.
We're going to be doing it with Python.
So this is the challenge for you. Using what you've learned in this lesson,
see if you can create a footer element so we can put it inside a footer tag
like this. And inside this footer tag,
I want you to create a paragraph element that can say any piece of text
as long as it contains the copyright year, which should be the current year
worked out programmatically using Python.
Pause the video and have a think about how you might solve that challenge.
All right.
So the first thing we're going to do is create our paragraph and we're going to
say something like copyright and then the year
and then we're going to say, um,
something like built by... This is a pretty common footer.
Now what we want to do is we want to replace these YYYYs
with the actual year. So, as you can imagine,
I'm going to be using these double curly braces to insert the year into here.
But first I have to generate that. So going back to our server.py,
I'm going to import the datetime module
which you've used many times before to generate the current date and time.
And we're going to use it specifically this time though,
to generate the current year.
And it's going to be done using the datetime module, the datetime class,
and then we're going to call the now method in order to get the current date
time and then we're going to tap into the year property.
So now in addition to passing over that random number as num,
I'm also going to pass over a new variable with the name of year and the value
of the current year that we just worked out from here.
So now when this template is rendered,
it's also going to receive a variable called year
which we can insert right here into the copyright like that.
So now if I go ahead and hit save, go back to our website,
hit refresh, you can see our footer show up copyright 2020,
which is the current year I'm living in, and it has the rest of the text.
So now no matter which year it is
we will never need to update our footer ever again because it's being automatically
updated using code.
Now that you've seen that we can write code in our server,
work out some sort of value or get some piece of data,
and then we can send it over to our template to be rendered,
I've got a challenge for you to test some of the things that you've learned from
previous days as well as what we've been doing with Flask
over the last few days.
I found a pretty interesting API called the agify
and there's also genderize. This is a really simple API.
It doesn't require you to sign up and it doesn't require any authentication.
What you can do with it is you can hit up the URL of the API and then you can
pass over a value for name.
And it's going to predict the age of a name.
You can go ahead and hit try me to see what you get.
You can see its a very simple JSON that you get back.
And this describes the name that you entered, the estimated age of that person
with that name,
and also how many times they've sampled this name when they were calculating
this data.
Now another one is genderize where you can pass in a name and it'll give you the
predicted gender.
So I have to say from testing that I think genderize is a lot more accurate than
agify,
but maybe I'm just a little bit upset because it says that people with my name
on average are 63 years old. But hey, you know,
I'm doing pretty well for a 63-year-old. So, I can't complain.
Now,
what I want you to do is to turn this into a dynamic Flask application.
We're going to set up a new route in our application and it's under the
/guess route. Now after /guess
we're going to put in a name. So for example,
/guess/Angela and what it should give us is
Hey, and then the name that was entered into the URL.
And then it should say, I think you are
and then the predicted gender from genderize.io.
And then it should tell me how old it predicts that name to be.
Now this works for any name so I could change it to James or Katie.
And it doesn't really matter what I enter here.
This piece of data come from these two APIs.
Now you might have to think back a little bit when we learned about
how do you use the requests module to get hold of the data that we want from an
API. And then you're going to incorporate it into a website that you can design
however you want,
but be aware that the first line needs to have the name that was entered into
the URL and the name should ideally be capitalized into title case like this,
and then it should have the predicted gender and the predicted age.
So this is your challenge and it might take you a little while to work out all
the components, but I think you can do it.
Pause the video and spend at least 15 or 20 minutes working out this challenge
and see if you can complete it.
Remember that you've always got the help of the documentation.
So there is the Flask documentation, there's the Jinja documentation, well
also there's the documentation from the agify and genderize.io.
And if there's anything else, you can always search through the course for the
part where we dealt with APIs and getting hold of data from APIs,
as well as using Google and Stack Overflow to help you achieve this.
Don't just give up. If you get stuck,
try to work like a real world developer and work out the solution to your
problems. All right.
So the first thing we have to do is set up this /guess/
name route. Back inside our server
after where we've defined our home route,
let's go ahead and create app.route
and here we're going to target /guess and then /name.
Now because we need to pass the URL to get hold of the name that the user
entered, if we take a look at the Flask documentation,
you might remember that yesterday we covered this idea of variable rules and
passing a URL.
The way we do it is by adding some angle brackets around the part of the URL
which is going to be taken in as a variable. And here's their example.
So in our case,
we're going to put this name part of the URL inside some angle brackets to turn
it into a variable. And then we can create our function
which I'll just call guess. Um, it doesn't really matter what you call it.
And then inside this guess method, I'm going to put in this name.
So essentially when my guess function goes through this decorator method,
it's going to give it a value for this name variable,
and then I'm going to catch onto that name and I'm going to send it over when I
render my template.
So let's go ahead and create a new template to render.
So it's going to be an HTML file which I'll just call guess.html.
And I'll leave the title as guess. Now inside the body
I want to be able to type the name.
So it was Hey, and then the name.
And then it was, I think you are and then the gender,
and then finally it was, and maybe and your age.
So something like this. Now we just need to replace the name,
the gender and the age.
So I'm going to keep those names and I'm just going to wrap them like this.
Now remembering the names of these variables,
I'm going to go back to my server and I'm going to try and render my guess.
html. So it was render_template,
the name of the template is called guess.html,
and then I'm going to add a bunch of keyword arguments.
So the first one was the name,
so this is the name of the keyword argument.
And then the value is also going to be name because it's going to come from
this URL. If you find that confusing,
you can always change this. For example,
you could change this to person_name
and we could use that right here.
Now you might be able to see that this name comes from the URL
which gets passed through the input, and this person_name is the one that we use
when we put it into the template. Let's go ahead and test this out.
Let's comment out these two lines of code by hitting command forward slash or
control forward slash and then hit save and run the code
and let's try going to this URL. So you can see it says
Hey, and then it says whatever it is that we typed after guess.
So if you type a whole bunch of gobbledy goop,
then that's also what we're going to see right here. Now,
one of the things about the name is it will be nice to have it in title case.
So we can change things to title case by using the Python title method
where we simply just say txt.title.
We can do that inside our guess.html
because we know that we can evaluate Python expressions in between the double
curly quotes. We can say person_name.title
and then it's the parentheses.
So now, if we save that, coming back over here and we go back to our Katie and hit
enter, you can see it's now capitalized
that K and the first character is always now going to be capitalized.
We've solved the first part.
Now we need to figure out the gender and the age. And to do that,
we're going to need the help of these two APIs; genderize and agify.
So the API is probably the simplest API you've worked with.
You've worked with a lot more complex APIs in the past.
So there shouldn't be too hard.
Now what we want to do is we want to replace this part that says Peter
with whatever it is that the user typed into the URL right here.
We're going to need to take this entire string and we're going to paste it in
and this is going to be the URL.
Now we're going to replace this part by an f-string.
So we have an F in front of the string, and then inside the curly braces,
we can put in the name which got passed from the URL.
So that's the gender URL.
And in order to get the data from that URL,
we're going to need the requests library.
So let's go ahead and import requests
and install it if it's red and squiggly.
Right.
Now, once it's installed, we can now use requests.get
and we can get hold of the data at this gender_url.
And this is going to be our gender_response.
Right.
Now, from this gender_response,
we can get hold of the gender_data and we want it in JSON format.
So we can say gender_response.json.
I'm not going to explain this too much because we've gone into excruciating
detail before on how to work with JSONs,
how to work with APIs, and how to work with the requests library.
I'm hoping that this stage
it's just a bit of revision and you just have to look up some of the methods,
but you've already seen this before and it should be quite familiar.
So now finally, from the gender_data,
we want to extract the part of that dictionary that is interesting,
which is actually just the one under the key gender.
So let's go ahead and add our square brackets and then put gender in here.
And this is going to be equal to our gender.
And that is what we're going to pass over.
So we're going to say gender = gender.
And that means that once we get into the guess.html,
it'll be able to put the value into this placeholder. Now,
all that's left is to work out the age.
So let's get our agify URL.
Right.
And this is going to be pretty straightforward because it's going to be pretty
much the same as what we did for the gender.
Yeah.
And if you take a look at the JSON you get back from calling this API,
the important piece of data is inside that key age. Now,
all we need to do is pass over a new variable called age
and the value is going to come from right here.
Cool.
So now if we hit save and we go back to our website and we hit enter,
it should say, Hey, Katie, I think you're female. And maybe 32 years old.
Why is Katie younger than me? Anyways. I hope you managed to get that to work.
If not,
take a look at the final code in the course resources and see where you went
wrong and maybe revise the section in the course on APIs.
In the previous lessons,
we've seen how we can use the Jinja markup in order to insert bits of Python
code into the HTML template. Now,
in this lesson, I want to demystify some of the other markup
like the {% and some of these keywords.
Now,
what we've been able to do with this markup is to specify single line
expressions in Python.
But what if we wanted to create multiline statements like an if statement or a
for loop? Well, we would have to use some slightly different markup.
I'm going to go ahead and create a new HTML file which I'll call blog.
And this will have the title of blog and in the body
what I want to do is to render all the titles of all the blogs I have. Now in
order to get hold of some data for our blogs,
we're going to use a service called endpoint. And this is a really neat service
which just acts as JSON storage bin.
So basically you can create your own API with your own JSON data
and you don't even have to log in. It's as simple as clicking on,
create JSON bin, and then here you can create some, um, keys,
some values or a list of values.
And once you've done that,
you can go ahead and access this bin at this particular API
and you can see it sends you that JSON back.
So you can update anything in here and you can get that data coming back to you
via this API.
That means that I could create some blog posts where each blog post has an ID,
a title, a subtitle and body.
And I've only got three blog posts in my list.
But you can now use this as if it were an API simply by heading to this address,
which you'll find in the course resources. Now,
what we're going to do is we're going to pull down these blog posts as if it was
an API,
and we're going to try and display all of the titles and all of the subtitles.
Inside our server.py,
if we go ahead and set up a new app.route,
and this route is going to be /blog, then here
we're going to create a blog function
which is going to fetch all the blogs from this URL.
So I'm going to copy the URL of my API
and you can do that in the course resources.
And then we're going to put this as the blog URL.
Now I'm going to use requests.
get to get hold of the data at that URL,
and then I can tap into the data by saying response.json
and this will give me all of the blog posts.
So we'll call that all posts.
And now I'm going to render my blog.html
and I'm going to pass in all the posts under a keyword called posts... like this.
So I've fetched all of those posts,
I've passed it into a variable called all_post,
and I'm sending that value over to the blog.html under the name posts.
So now going to my blog.html, I should be able to catch that post.
And if we were just writing Python straightaway,
then we would be able to say something like for blog posts in posts,
let's go ahead and create an h1 where we have the blog post title,
and let's create a h2 where we have the blog post subtitle.
And it would, in an ideal world, loop through all the posts it received and for
each of the blog posts, render
an h1 for the title and h2 for the subtitle. Now, in fact,
using Jinja, we can pretty much do exactly this,
but we have to alter things a little bit. Firstly,
when we have a multiline statement,
we're going to have to add a curly brace and then a percentage sign for each of
the lines. So not just from the beginning to the end,
but for each of the lines that's Python code that spans multi lines
we have to enclose it inside this kind of markup.
So notice the direction of the curly braces and also notice the presence of the
percentage signs. Now inside the part
where we insert it into HTML elements,
we can do just as we did before, pass through the blog post and render it as a
single line expression like this.
But because we're working inside an HTML file,
we also have to specify when our for loop actually ends.
And that very end is also going to be enclosed inside one of these percentage
curly brace.
And there's a special key word that comes from Jinja
which is called endfor in order to specify at the end of the for loop.
We'll just have to add it in like this. Now,
if we go ahead and hit save,
and now if we run our code and try to bring up our blog website,
you should see that it's pulled in all of the articles in our fake blog,
the life of cactus,
top 15 things to do when you're bored, and introduction to intermittent fasting.
It's a really random blog that we're starting and it's created an h1 for
each of the titles and h2 for each of the subtitles.
And it's done this without us having to pass out each of the title, subtitles.
We've actually been able to do all of that just with a
for loop inside our template.
Now you can do the same thing using an if statement.
All you have to do is to, again,
enclose every line in the statement with {%,
and then at the very end of your block of code, of your statement,
you have to add the endif keyword as well.
See if you can modify this so that we only print out the title for the blog
post which has an ID of 2.
All right, in this case,
all we have to do is add an if statement down here.
We're going to say if the blog post that we're currently looping on has an ID
that's equal to 2, well, in that case,
we actually want to render the title and subtitle,
but otherwise, we're not going to. All we have to do is add in the markup.
So starting at the first if statement,
we add the {% at the beginning and at the end, and at
the very end of the if statement
we add the {% and that keyword endif
to say that this is the end of the if statement.
So now if we hit save and we go back to our blog,
you can see that it's only going to show the second article,
the one with ID of 2.
So now that we've seen some of the things that we can do with templating and
Jinja, I want to talk to you about something called URL building.
And this is a way that allows us to direct the user to a specific page in our
website and web app. Now, what that means is that for example,
on our main homepage,
we could actually have a link to the blogs page.
The way that we would do that is in our index.html here, we could create a
anchor tag, for example, in the body here. And we could say
Go to blog.
And then for the Href of this anchor tag,
this is where we're going to use the Jinja template to build out the href.
So we're going to add the curly braces in and dynamically work out the href. And
in every Jinja template,
we have access to a method called url_for.
So we can say url_for, and then because this is Python,
we can add some parameters when we call this method.
And what it's expecting is the name of a function in your Flask server.
So you could, for example,
hit up home or guess or blog.
And in our case, this blog is what we want.
So to make it right a little bit more clear
because we've got the route which is called /blog, and we've
got the function which is called blog.
I'm going to change this to get_blog.
So once you render this blog page, we can call this method
get_blog by saying URL for, and then passing a string.
So because we've got some quotation marks around the outside,
we're going to use some single quotes on the inside. And in between a single
quotes is the name of that method, get_blog,
like this. Now,
what it's going to do is it's going to generate a hyperlink
that's going to be based on what it takes
to get to this particular route and call this particular method.
So now if I go ahead and update this and go to my homepage here,
you'll see there's a new link that says go to blog. And when I click on it,
it takes me to the blog page. Now,
another thing that you might want to do is when you navigate to a URL inside
your web app, you might want to add in some parameters.
You can add parameters when you are using url_for in the same way that you did it
when you did render_template. So that you can create the name of the parameter
and the value
and it is a keyword argument that comes after the first parameter.
So here we could say, for example, url_for get_blog,
and then we could just say a number equals three.
So now when the user clicks on this anchor tag,
it's going to look for a method called get_blog on our server.py
which is right here,
and then it's going to pass over any subsequent keyword arguments as parameters.
So we can catch those parameters inside the app route.
So we can say / and then we can use our angle brackets
which we've always done to give parts of the URL a identifier,
and we can call this num or number, whatever you like.
And we'll also need to add that to the input to this method
and just to prove that it works, I'm going to print it out.
So now let's go ahead and rerun our code.
And if we go back to our homepage and I click on go to blog and it goes to the
blog website and it inserts that three into that part of the URL,
and if I take a look in the console, you can see it printed out that number
which got passed all the way from the index.html to the server.
And finally, inside this method
it was caught and it could be printed. And it could also be further propagated
into another template if need be.
So now that we've done all the theory, in the next lesson,
it's time to tackle the final project and we're going to be building out our
blog website with styling and also with templating.
So for all of that and more, head over to the next lesson.
Hey, guys.
In this section we're going to be learning about the bootstrap framework.
And this is one of many external CSS layout systems, but this is probably one of the most popular and
the one that you'll most likely to come across out in the wild.
Bootstrap, as I said, is a CSS framework created in 2010 by two Twitter developers Mark Otto and Jacob
Thornton.
Now the power of Bootstrap and the reason why it became so popular is it contained pre-made CSS files,
which you can simply include into your project in order to use their pre-built components and styling.
For example, if you wanted to have some tags in your website, you could create a look like this by
simply adding a few classes to your HTML.
On top of that, one of the biggest reasons why bootstrap took off is because of their 12 column layout
system built on top of Flexbox.
That makes it really easy to create responsive websites and websites that simply just work and look
great on mobile as well as desktop, the so-called mobile first approach.
So how exactly does it work?
Well, let's say you had a button which just said home.
You can see that the standard button rendered from HTML doesn't look fantastic.
But if we included just five classes which come from the bootstrap CSS, so we include the pre-built
CSS into our project and we add the styling and the components by adding these classes to our HTML.
Then all of a sudden what you'll end up with is something that looks beautiful and pre styled like this.
And because we don't have to worry about writing all of the CSS code, all we need to know is which
classes we need to add to our HTML.
Then it makes everything so much easier and so much quicker when we want to build components into our
website.
Now, as I mentioned, bootstrap is a type of CSS framework.
What exactly are these?
Well, they're pre-made CSS files which you can include into your projects.
If we had a look at the bootstrap GitHub and because bootstrap is completely open source, then all
of the code is visible and you can see it's got styling defined for all of the different components.
For example, this is inside the card component and it's got classes that define what a card body should
look like, what kind of layout it should have, what kind of color it should have, as well as what
the card title should look like, subtitle.
And it's got all of this predefined CSS, which we can simply insert straight into our HTML.
Now, the two most popular external CSS frameworks are bootstrap and foundation, but there are lots
more like MUI and Tailwind and a whole bunch more.
And the reason why they're so great is because they allow us to add in pre-built components and develop
websites quickly and efficiently.
If we look at the usage percentages across the Internet, you can see that the biggest CSS external
framework is still bootstrap with close to 80% of the market share.
But just because we learn about bootstrap, it doesn't mean that everything we learned about CSS is
null and void.
In fact, if you look at the top here, when we look at the absolute usage percentages of all of the
different frameworks across the Internet, you can see the largest percentage are still websites that
don't use any external CSS frameworks.
What does it mean when there are no CSS frameworks being used?
Well, it means you're probably using native CSS like Flexbox and Grid and Float and all of the great
things that we learnt before.
So bootstrap doesn't replace any of that knowledge and in fact we should be in a situation where we
don't actually need to depend on any sort of external framework, but they are really useful when we
want to develop websites quickly and easily and we don't want to spend a ton of time designing our websites
because it comes with all of the pre-made styling and all of the styling rules that we can easily conform
to by using their components.
So what are the pros of external CSS frameworks?
Well, they're easy and they're fast to use and you get a ton of pre-built components like this pricing
plan, which took us ages to build ourselves.
And you also get really consistent styling across your website.
It's almost like you hired a professional developer who kept everything looking on brand and finally
you have really good browser compatibility because they've tested all of the different browsers Safari,
Chrome, Brave and whichever browsers that.
Your user might be using.
So you don't actually have to do all of this complicated testing.
You can just trust that it works out of the box.
Now, what are some of the downsides of frameworks?
Well, one of the biggest downsides is something called class bloat.
Remember previously we mentioned that it's a really good idea to separate structure from style where
we said that HTML is for structure.
So adding in elements that describe what the purpose is and CSS is for style using external CSS frameworks
because we're adding everything into the classes, then very quickly you end up with what's called class
bloat, where you have a lot of styling going into the actual HTML file and it looks a lot less clean
than if we had just use something like Grid or Flexbox where we have all of our predefined classes and
we go easy on the classes that we add in to our HTML file.
The other downside is customization.
If you want to build a website where you want to have full control over every pixel and layout and everything
to be exactly the way you designed it, then external CSS frameworks is probably not the way to go because
in order to customize each and every component, it can be really time consuming.
So when should you use the CSS frameworks like Bootstrap and when should you not?
Well, when you are building a mobile first responsive website that you want to put online very quickly
and access beautiful components designed by professional designers, keeping everything on your website
looking slick and uniform, then you probably want to consider using bootstrap.
But if you're building a very simple website where you just need HTML and CSS and you can quickly throw
it up, or if you're building a really complex custom design website and you want complete control over
the design, then it's probably not a good idea to use an external CSS framework like Bootstrap.
So we've spoken so much about the pros and cons, when to use, when not to use, but how do you actually
use it?
Well, one of the easiest ways is to include it via a link.
We've seen how we can use the link tag in order to add our stylesheets.
And in a similar way we can use these link tags that simply gets hold of the stylesheet from an external
resource.
So in this case it's through CN, which stands for Content Delivery Network.
And what these are is little hubs all across the entire world and it knows where your users are located.
So when they load up your website and try to access this particular CSS file that contains all of the
bootstrap code, then it can find the closest location with the shortest distance to the server that
has that content.
And that just means that even though this has to be downloaded from somewhere, it can be delivered
to your user and rendered very, very quickly.
And from our point of view as developers, all we need to do is simply include this link into the head
section of our HTML.
And if we want any of the functionality like dropdown menus or clickable buttons, then we want to include
the bootstrap script just before the end of the body section.
So somewhere right about here.
Now let's go ahead and try an exercise and see if we can upgrade our website quickly by using bootstrap
download 11.0 Bootstrap intro and if you open it inside of vs code, open the index.html, you can see
there are four to do's for you to complete.
And once you've completed all of these four steps, you should end up with a card that displays a sunflower
image.
And this is one of the pre-built bootstrap components.
Now how are you going to do this?
Well, firstly, you're going to head over to Getbootstrap.com, which is the main bootstrap website,
and then I want you to include the bootstrap files using CDN.
You only need the CSS file through this link element for now.
And then I want you to go into the documentation if you want to look up anything regarding the card
component, which is all the way down here in components under the card section.
Now you know what the goal should look like.
You've got all of the resources to get started and you should be able to work through each of the to
do's one by one.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right.
Hopefully you've given that a go and you've seen that the bootstrap card has some example code, which
you can straight up just drop into your file.
If you haven't given this a go, pause the video now.
Don't continue because things will get harder and harder as we go on in the course.
And if you just watch the videos, eventually, at some point things are not going to make sense because
you haven't had the practice.
Make things easy for your future self by putting in lots of effort and practice now.
All right, enough said.
First thing, let's walk through the solution together and hopefully you can check it against your work.
Now the first thing we're going to do is add the bootstrap link, which comes from the homepage.
And we just want this first link that is going to include the stylesheet.
And you can see this is a link with a relationship of stylesheet.
So instead of using our own stylesheet, we're now using the bootstrap CSS.
And if you're wondering what that min stands for, it's basically a file where all of the spaces are
taken away so that it's as short as possible.
So it loads up quicker because there's no spaces and everything's all jumbled, which is impossible
for humans to read.
But it works just fine for the computer to do.
Number two is to add the bootstrap pre-built card.
So if we go into our docs and find our card component, you can see the first example is pretty much
the card we want to build.
If we look at the goal, we've got our card title, some example, text, a button and an image, and
this is exactly the same as this example.
So let's copy the HTML and paste it into here under to do number two.
Now let's check our work, let's show it in preview and see what it looks like.
It looks pretty good.
Other than the fact that the image is pretty much completely broken.
So step three is to change the image source to display the flower JPEG image.
The image is right here and right now the source is completely empty because it's an example.
Let's go ahead and change it to our image, which is flower jpeg.
You see it show up immediately and as always with images, let's add a alt text so that people with
screen readers know what it's all about.
All right.
Now the final step is a little bit of a revision step because I wanted you to use Flexbox to center
the card in the vertical and horizontal center.
If we take a look at this URL on our browser, you can see it's stuck all the way to the top left,
which is default layout.
But if we want it right here in the middle, then we're going to need to use some Flexbox magic and
we're going to do that inside an internal style element right here under to do number four.
What do we need to target?
Well, we need to target the entire card.
And the topmost level is this flex container.
The reason why it's of class flex container is because this comes from the bootstrap CSS and it's got
some styling in there that defines that container.
But we can always override it.
And this is really, really important when we want to override a particular bootstrap style, we have
to make sure that it's more specific.
So either it goes inside an internal style element or it goes inside an inline style property, or if
we're using our standard external CSS and we use a link linking to, I don't know, say forward slash,
forward slash style.css and we have a style CSS file somewhere in our project, then you've got to make
sure that your custom CSS file occurs below the bootstrap link.
That way this is first looked at and then the browser looks at your custom stylesheet and you can override
any of the classes that come from bootstrap.
So this is an important point to remember for the future when you're creating your own custom style
sheets.
All right, so now in order to override the style here, now we might be building on top of existing
bootstrap styles or we might be specifying something they don't even care about, and it's not defined
in the bootstrap CSS at all.
In our case, we want to change this flex container to display flex because we know that this is one
of the simplest ways to center anything in CSS.
And the first thing we need to change is the justify content set to center.
And the second one is align items set to center.
And finally, we need to make sure that the entire container takes up the full height and not just some
proportion.
Portion of the height.
That's enough for the content.
So let's set the height to 100 viewport height.
And now you can see our card is perfectly centered in the middle using Flexbox.
It's a component that we've borrowed and customized from bootstrap, and you can see how easy it was.
And quick to create this layout by leveraging the power of bootstrap.
In the next lesson, we're going to dive deeper into bootstrap and we're going to look at how the bootstrap.
12 column layout system actually works in practice.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.
All right.
So now that we've had a little bit of a taste of what Bootstrap can do, let's dive deep into one of
the most powerful features of Bootstrap, which is the 12 column layout system.
The 12 column system is made of three components.
Firstly, we need a div that has a class of container and this is going to be the starting point.
Next inside that container we need another div which is going to be of class row and inside the row
is where we will have our items and they will be laid out using the column system.
So what does this look like in code?
Well, it's pretty simple.
We have a container that contains a single row and then within the row we can have as many items as
we like.
And they're laid out using the column class.
Pretty simple so far.
And you're probably thinking, well, there's nothing very groundbreaking here.
Now, the interesting thing starts happening when you have multiple columns laid out inside these rows,
because automatically Bootstrap will try to give every column inside the row equal spacing and space
them across the entire width of the container.
So if you had a container which included a row that had one, two, three, four, five, six divs in
there, each with the class set as call short for column, then it will divide up the entire width by
six.
And if you had three of them then it would give each of them a third of the space.
Now the bootstrap container is responsive.
So by defining a div with the class of container, you're actually telling it to have a different size
on different sized screens.
If we had an XL or an XL screen, so like a desktop or a TV or something, then that container is going
to be this size and you can see that there's several breakpoints that are responsive to the different
device screen sizes.
On mobile, maybe the container would be 540 pixels on an iPad, maybe it would be 720 or 960 pixels.
And on desktop, maybe it would be about 1000 pixels.
You can use the dash plus these different letters to specify at which point you want your container
to be.
100%.
Container is the same as the normal container, but container MD or medium means that on small screens
the container would already reach 100% of the width of the screen.
And again, remember, all of these sizes here are referring to the width of the viewport.
So only this dimension.
And then as we go down the line, we're starting to specify a 100% width on larger and larger screens
until we reach this container fluid, which basically says that on all screen sizes, we want it to
reach from edge to edge, which is 100% width in most cases.
You will see these two being used quite frequently because the container gives a nice sort of margin
around the left and the right.
And the container fluid is when you want that edge to edge behavior.
The layout system gets more interesting when we start using sized columns.
Instead of just writing Col as the class, we can actually set the class as for example, Col dash two
or cold dash four.
And what this is saying is if we think of each of our rows as having 12 columns and we split them all
up into the 12 equal size columns like this.
So if you count this is actually a total of 12.
Then when we create a div we can specify well how many of these columns do we want to occupy?
In this case this div wants two of those columns and then this one wants four of them and then the final
one wants six.
Based on the classes that you choose, Bootstrap will know how much space to allocate each div on a
percentage basis.
So you could view the COL six as a 50% and the col two as one sixth of the entire width and so on and
so forth.
So you can use all of the numbers col one all the way up to col 12 and you can split up the proportion
of your screen and the content inside.
So maybe you would have a navigation section on the left that you only want to take up two out of 12
width and then the main content here maybe could take up ten out of 12 of the width and so on and so
forth.
And this is a really, really easy and intuitive way of sizing your content using bootstrap, and this
is what the code would look like.
So we have three divs and we're giving this one two out of 12, four out of 12, six out of 12.
And this is the layout that we end up with.
And we didn't have to write any CSS.
All we had to do was add in the pre-built layout classes.
Again, it's really important to know that Bootstrap has predefined breakpoints and these dimensions
are defined based on common screen sizes.
And even though these numbers are constantly changing, generally I would say that small is for mobile
devices, medium is for tablets and iPads.
A large is for laptop, extra large is for desktop, and extra extra large is for anything crazy like
maybe a TV or something.
An extra small is for devices that are maybe longer than they are wide.
So maybe foldable phones and even really narrow phone screens.
Now, one thing I want to draw your attention to is the directionality of the signs here.
All of these breakpoints, which will often use, for example, coal dash, SM dash two.
This section refers to the screens which are greater than this dimension.
So that means the small breakpoint is between here and here and covers the range between 576 and 768,
and each of them always go up.
So this is important point to keep in mind when you're dealing with the bootstrap breakpoints.
Now, one of the great things about bootstrap breakpoints is we don't really need the media queries
as much because this covers pretty much a lot of the different device dimensions and we don't have to
manually write all the pixel sizes and add media queries into our CSS.
We can target the different sizes and make our website responsive by using the pre-built breakpoints.
Here's an example of the bootstrap breakpoints here.
We're saying that on a small screen and above we want the dimension ratio to be two, four and six.
So this means that on desktop, on laptop, on TV, it's all going to have this size.
And even on mobile as well.
But below the size of mobile, it is not defined as having these proportions.
So it will default to giving each of these divs 100%.
And similarly, if you don't add a number here.
So we could for example, here it's 12 columns, 12 divided by three.
So these are actually call fours.
But if we don't define a number, you remember that they will automatically distribute.
But what would it look like if we reduce the screen size to less than a mobile size?
Well, all of these divs will go to 100% width when the overall width is less than 576.
Then all of these items default to as if they just had a column defined.
So call as the class and the call class by default is going to take up 100% of the width in the small
sized screen.
Now in a single div, you can actually also have multiple breakpoints.
So in this case, what it's saying is on the large devices and above, then it should take up four out
of 12 of the width.
On medium sizes and above.
Well, because the above is already defined.
So then this case is only on medium devices, then it should take up eight out of 12 of the width and
on small devices it should take up 12 out of 12.
So full width.
Here we're simulating a large screen.
So maybe on a laptop or a desktop, then it's taking up four out of 12.
It's this kind of proportion.
And then we go over to the next size down.
So on an iPad, then it's going to take up eight out of 12 of the screen.
And just for example, sakes, let's go down even further to a mobile size where we want it to take
up 100% or full width of the screen.
Because as you imagine, when we have more screen real estate, it's easier to see things.
And when we're working on smaller screens, we want to make things generally a bit larger so that it's
easier for users to see our content.
In addition to having multiple breakpoints in each div, you can also mix and match the types of definitions.
So for example, here we've got two sized columns, call two and call four.
So it's always going to take up two out of 12, the Section four out of 12 here.
But this last one, notice how we've just left it as the column class.
Now this means that it's going to automatically adjust in size in order to take up whatever proportion
remains.
Bootstrap layout is a little bit complicated when you're first working with it, and it's really important
that you read the docs and also have plenty of practice before things start to make more sense.
So in order for you to practice, I've created a website at github.io forward slash bootstrap dash layout,
and if you go to this website you'll see that I've got three exercises in total for you.
The idea of the exercises is that at the top there will be a demo area, which is the effect that you're
trying to achieve.
For example, in this case we want these Divs to be 50% on desktop and 100% on mobile.
So as I reduce the width, you'll see that it gets to a point where we reach that breakpoint where it
goes into 100% width.
As you scroll down, each of the different exercises will have different proportions.
And what you want to do is to modify the HTML code inside here, which is responsible for the styling
of the area that you control, which are the divs underneath the examples.
And I want you to add the classes for using the 12 column layout system so that your area behaves exactly
the same as the top area.
When you reduce the size and hit the various different breakpoints.
If you get stuck, be sure to check out the layout section of the bootstrap documentation and here you'll
see the different bootstrap breakpoints.
Also, you can read up more on how the columns work, how the containers work, and how the grid system
works.
Pause the video now and give this challenge a go.
So hopefully you've given this a go and you've managed to get everything to work correctly.
Let's go through the solution together.
The first example says it should be 50% on desktop and 100% on mobile.
We know that the desktop breakpoint is the XL, so we can define column dash XL dash six and six out
of 12 is of course 50%.
Now in order to get it to be 100% on mobile, we could say column dash dash 12, which is 100% and we
can add that to both divs.
Now if I go ahead and set apply changes, you can see now when I reduce the width of the window that
it's going to hit that breakpoint where below which it's no longer going to be 50% and it's going to
start taking up the full width.
Now, you might remember from previously we said that the bootstrap breakpoints, target sizes, this
particular size and above.
So when we define Column XL six, we're saying anything that's above the XL breakpoint, which is greater
than 1200 pixels, should be 50%.
You might have realized that you don't actually need to define this because everything else is going
to default to 100%.
So if I apply changes again, you can see that my purple example still behaves the same as the green
example.
And I've only changed the behavior of the XL size and above and changed its layout.
All right, so let's go to exercise number two.
And in this case, I haven't given you exactly what they should do or how they should behave.
And instead, I wanted you to simply just reduce the width of the screen to see how it changes through
the different sizes.
The first one's easy.
Pretty much all of the larger sizes, all the way down to the large breakpoint takes up the full 12
width column and you can take out a ruler if you want to measure the screen.
But we can see that column one is roughly half of the width of the row.
Column two and three are pretty much equal size, so it's probably going to be six, three and three.
Let's modify this so that we target the large breakpoint first.
So we'll say Col Dash, LG Dash six for the first column.
The second column is going to be called Dash, LG Dash three and the same for the third column.
So now if I click apply changes, you can see it's now taking up the same proportions.
But when we hit this breakpoint that's below the large breakpoint, our columns by default go to 100%,
whereas the example actually does something different.
The top column takes up 100% and the other two take up half of the width.
And you can see that behavior continues all the way until the very small size.
So that means that we've got an SM breakpoint there defined.
Now, once you've worked with this for a long time, you can spot each of the breakpoints pretty much
by eye.
But initially you can always just switch around, try different ones, try the SM, try the XL and see
which ones actually behave like the example.
There's nothing wrong with trial and error when it hits the smaller screen size.
Our column one is going to take up the full width of the row and then the other two on the smaller breakpoint
are going to take up half of the width.
So call SM six.
And similarly, the third one does the same thing.
So let's apply the change.
And you can see now at this breakpoint, they also behave exactly the same.
So now all we have left is the final one, which is just the smallest breakpoint for the columns.
And here what's actually happening is each of these columns are taking up ten out of 12 of the columns.
Now, I can spot that by eye, but also I created this exercise, so I know.
But if you try some different numbers, you'll probably get there as well.
So if we define the smallest size as column, let's just try an eight to start with so I can show you
this trial and error process.
And we know that all the columns behave the same at that breakpoint.
If we click apply changes and we go here, we can see, well, eight is clearly too small.
So let's go up a size and let's change to ten out of 12.
And once I hit apply changes, you can see we now have both sets of columns behaving exactly the same
at all the different breakpoints.
This one was a little bit harder, admittedly, and it required a little bit more thinking and probably
trial and error on your part.
But hopefully by the end of it you will understand a bit better about how these different breakpoints
work and at which points they hit.
So now for the final exercise and this one, we've got two columns.
Initially they start out in one line taking up a particular proportion and then we hit a certain breakpoint
and it changes the proportion.
Column one gets a little bit wider, takes up more space compared to column two.
And then if we reduce a little bit more, that changes again at the next breakpoint and then again and
then finally taking up full width.
So let's start with the largest breakpoint we know, which is the XL.
Let's say that coal dash XL.
And let's define as one out of 12 and then give the other half.
Um, 12 minus one is 11.
And now let's apply the change and you can see that is the correct proportion.
Again, this might require trial and error on your part.
Don't be too hard on yourself.
If you didn't manage to get it first time, I wouldn't be able to either.
If it was somebody else's exercise like this.
Now let's hit the next breakpoint just about here, and this is going to be the next breakpoint down.
This is the XL.
We've just hit 1200 and a tip for working with responsiveness.
When you're wondering how do I know that it's the 1200 pixel breakpoint that got hit?
If you go into the Chrome developer tools and click on this button to toggle the device toolbar and
change the dimensions to responsive, then you can click this drag bar and look at the top here.
This is the important width that we need to look at once I expand it to 1200, you can see that jump
in size happen just around there.
So we know that the 1200 breakpoint is the XL breakpoint and you can work this out this way as well.
So just a tip for the future when you're working with any kind of responsiveness.
This is really useful to know, but most of the time I would judge responsiveness just by eye when you're
designing the layout to see what looks good.
All right, so let's hit the next breakpoint at the XL size 1200 pixels.
So this is called Dash XL, and I reckon this is a ratio of 2 to 10.
So let's do call XL to call XL ten, let's apply our changes and that's pretty good.
So now let's keep reducing until we hit the next breakpoint and this is going to be the next level down,
which is large.
LG And I reckon this is probably 4 to 8.
So call Dash, LG Dash four and the next one will be called LG Dash eight.
And notice that each of these always add up to 12 because you can see in the example layout, they're
only taking up one row.
If it didn't add up to 12, then it will go to the next row in order to take up the amount of space
that we specified.
Now we have the next breakpoint, which is the cold dash.
MD And this one's easy to spot because it's half half, so it's going to be six.
And finally we have the rest are by default going to take up 100%.
So you could define the SM, but that's also the default behavior.
So you could also leave it out.
There you have it.
That's the final solution.
Code for exercise three and exercise two and exercise one.
Hopefully you manage to get there in the end, even if there was a little bit of trial and error and
some difficulty.
But once you've used bootstrap layout.
A few times.
You'll get used to this idea.
And it's a really intuitive way to lay out our screen.
And it's really easy to manipulate and to create different layout designs.
Now, in the next lesson, we're going to be talking through the different bootstrap components.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Hey, guys.
In this lesson, we're going to be learning about one of the most powerful features of Bootstrap and
one of the biggest reasons why we would be using bootstrap in our project in the first place.
And that is the concept of the bootstrap components, the pre-built pre-styled components like buttons
and cards and carousels and a whole load of beautiful things that we get access to simply by adding
in a bootstrap class into our HTML.
Let's start with one of the most commonly used components, which is the bootstrap button.
And this is a really good place to start because you also see the default bootstrap styling and the
color scheme in most of the components that you'll get access to through bootstrap.
If you want to give it a particular color.
It's really easy to access all of these default colors by simply using their name in most cases in a
bootstrap design website, the primary button, the go to, you know, the buy or the contact us or
download whatever will be this blue color and you can access all of the other colors through each of
their bootstrap names and they give you a little bit of a hint as to what they're used for.
So success is usually like an okay button danger.
Maybe if you click this button, something really bad happens or warning, etcetera, and you get access
to this button and this button styling simply by creating a button HTML element, giving it the class
BTN for a bootstrap button, and then adding the class for the color scheme from this list that you
want to choose.
Let's try this out.
Go ahead and download the starting files from the 11.2 bootstrap components zip file and once you've
extracted it, open it inside vs code.
Head over to index.html.
Now here you'll notice that I've already added in the bootstrap link, we've got a style section which
we can add custom CSS to and in the body area I want you to use the bootstrap documentation.
So if you go to the bootstrap main website at getbootstrap.com, go to docs and then scroll down to
the components, find the buttons, and I want you to put in a green button that says, okay, somewhere
onto this website.
Remember, you can preview it in real time to see if it's working and pause the video now and complete
this challenge.
All right.
So this is pretty simple.
We have a button which we said is going to say, okay.
And in order to style it using bootstrap, the first thing we do is add the BTN class and you can see
automatically the font changes, the background color changes.
And then we said we wanted to have a green button.
So the green button is BTN success.
So let's go ahead and add BTN success.
And once we're done, you can see we've got a beautiful green button with a hover animation with nice
styling, a good size, rounded corners, all of that goodness without doing a lot of work at all.
It was super, super simple to create this, and this should give you a taste of what's yet to come.
The next component I want to talk about is a really useful one, which is the card which you already
saw in the previous lessons exercise.
And as always, all we need to do is go to that particular component's page and then we can simply copy
the code, paste it into our website and replace certain parts of the code, such as the image source
or the alt text.
Now, one component that you're probably going to be using whenever you're building a website is a nav
bar, and the bootstrap nav bars are some of the best designed nav bars I've seen.
And it also is super easy to include simply using their example snippet codes.
If you head over to the nav bar, you can read on how it works And also what's some of the examples
they have are for example, this one with a search bar with some dropdowns, and this one which describes
how you can have the brand at the top left or if you want an image, image and text brand and you can
scroll through this to find the kind of nav bar you want to create and to use the example code.
Now another area for the nav bars is if you head over to examples and you go to the header section,
you can see some even more Fancily laid out nav bars over here in order to show you some of the different
types of components and how they can be used in real life.
We are going to be building a moving startup's website.
They're called Move It, which is pretty simple and it's got a one page website with many different
sections and I'm going to show you just how easy it is to build this entire fully fledged website using
just bootstrap components.
So the first thing we need is that nav bar, and you'll notice that I've taken the nav bar that is pretty
much this standard one.
So it's got a field which you can search for, say the postcode.
If our company works in your area, it's got some dropdown menus, it's got some other little areas
which you can click on.
So let's go ahead and copy the code for the starting point of our nav bar and let's paste it into the
body of our code.
So you can see as soon as I've done that, I've got my nav bar show up.
But one thing you'll notice as soon as you start playing around with it is when a bootstrap nav bar
is in a smaller width, it will automatically show a hamburger menu and that menu should have a dropdown
with all of the buttons from the navigation bar.
Now why is our button not working?
Now remember previously I said when we get started with Bootstrap there's two links to include via CDN.
The first one is the style sheet and that gives us all of the styling.
But the second one is the scripting code that gives us all of the functionality because this gives us
access to the bootstrap JavaScript code.
Now we don't need to understand anything about JavaScript just yet in order to use it.
All we need to do is copy that link and go to right at the end just before the closing body tag and
paste that script link in there.
And you can see as soon as I've done that, my buttons now work, my dropdowns work and all of these
clicking functionality bits start working and this again comes straight out of the box from Bootstrap.
Let's take a look at this website in a larger format.
By opening Inside Chrome, you can see that for the most part, these two nav bars look pretty similar.
All I did is got rid of some of the components and changed some of the other things.
For example, this button is disabled so that users can't click on it.
And in our version we actually just got rid of it.
We can do that quite easily by finding that button.
And you can see the reason why it's not enabled is because it has this class of disabled.
So if we get rid of that, then you can see this button is now active once more, but we don't actually
want it at all.
So let's delete that entire list item.
And now.
We only have three links.
Home link and dropdown.
So let's rename those links to about and services.
And again, because this is just a simple anchor tag, you know exactly how to work with this.
So the first one is link.
So we'll change this to about and the dropdown instead of reading dropdown will say is called services.
And you can imagine in the future we would have our different services in the dropdown, like moving
with a van, moving by, hauling everything yourself or something else.
But this is just an example of how our nav bar could look.
Now the first part of the nav bar is the nav bar brand and we can see that right up here.
We've got an anchor tag which is called the NAV Bar brand, for example.
If I change it to move it, then that's going to change our brand text.
In addition, we can also have a image in here so you can simply just add an image, give it a source,
maybe let's use one of the images we already have in our folder.
For example, the dog dot JPEG.
Now, because this image is super, super large and we haven't really resized it, then it's not really
going to work in the nav bar, but you can always change this.
So let's change the height to just 20 pixels.
Then you can see our nav bar brand image show up right there.
Now in our case, we're not going to use an image.
Instead, I'm going to delete that tag and I'm going to use an SVG.
This is a good time to show you the Svgs which are available through Bootstrap.
So if you go back to the home page and you click on icons, you can see you got all of these free icons
for you to use in any of your websites, paid, monetized, whatever.
And it's really hard actually, sometimes finding well-designed icons that you can simply add to your
project without having to pay royalties and buy it from a designer.
So this is also really, really neat and you can search through the different icons by using the filter.
So the one that I found is actually this box with seams on it, which looks very much like a moving
company box to me.
And you can either simply just copy the SVG straight up into your HTML.
So if I paste it in here, you'll see it show up right there.
Alternatively, you can also include it as an image and you set the source to the SVG that you have
saved in your folder, which is right here.
I'm going to use the image in the folder by setting it as a source and I'm going to set the alt text
to move it brand icon, and then I'm going to change the height to, let's say 30 so that it's a little
bit bigger.
And we now have a nav bar that looks the same as the example.
Now on the right hand side, there is a form here and I know we haven't spoken much about forms that's
all yet to come.
When we learn more about how to have the actual form functionality later on, especially in the back
end section, this is all going to come in really, really handy.
But for now, we're just going to change this search bar from search to say, post code and check.
So that's pretty easy to find.
You can either use command F to find those words or you can scroll through your code to find it as well.
Let's change the button to say check and let's change the placeholder for that search bar into, say,
a post code.
There we go.
And now we've completed our nav bar.
And if you had a design, all of that from scratch and all of the CSS that's included and you can see
just how much CSS there is actually, if you click on one of these items, you can see the nav link
that I just clicked on has all the padding defined, has all of this defined, has toggle styling.
And that's just one part of this entire nav bar.
So you can see just how much time we're saving ourselves and we're able to leverage a professional design
and create something that looks really contemporary and beautiful.
Now let's move on to the next section.
And this entire section is made up of different components.
So maybe an H1 heading, a paragraph, two buttons and an image.
But if we want to just take this layout, I actually got it from the examples.
The examples area is really, really good for taking bits and bobs of the different code snippets,
the different components that they've already styled and created for you, and simply putting it into
your website where it makes sense.
So this is a hero.
And as you can see, it's this one.
It's pretty much exactly the same title text, two buttons and an image, and everything is styled beautifully
already for you in order to use it.
All we need to do is right click.
On inspect.
And now we want to expand our elements area.
And what I tend to do is just to go upwards on the hover until the highlight actually highlights the
area that I want, which is this div right here.
Let's go ahead and copy this div and put it into our code just below our nav bar.
Now once I've done that, you can see we've got our centered screenshot text button and image.
Let's first fix that image so we can see what things should look like.
And their source is from the bootstrap docs.
But instead we want to use the one of the moving van so that we can show our users what our services
are all about.
And now all we have to do is just to replace the text.
If you look inside the starting file folder, there is a file called Website Text, and here you can
simply copy all of the website text and replace the relevant parts.
The H1 should say move with joy and then we've got a long bit of text which we're going to replace with
our paragraph.
So let's just copy everything in that paragraph element and replace it.
And then our buttons should say, get a quote and contact us.
And now we have a hero section done in two seconds.
Okay, maybe it was a little bit longer, but you can probably see just how powerful this is.
So now let's keep going.
In the next section of our example website, we've got some features and this is where you would usually
tell people what's so special about your particular startup?
Well, our startup is really professional.
We are available countrywide and we have a personal touch.
And you might have guessed this comes from the Bootstrap Examples page.
They have a section called Features, and this first feature is perfect for our needs.
And I think a lot of bootstrap design kind of comes from Apple because when you look at the Apple website,
a lot of the buttons, the shading, the kind of fonts, they all look really, really similar to the
bootstrap components.
And I think this is probably one of their design inspirations and we can get that simply with some copy
and pasting and a little bit of customization.
Again, let's go into the section of the features that we want and then we're going to keep hovering
up until we find the div that contains all the things that we want, right click, copy, copy element,
and we're going to put it below the previous section.
Now let's take a look at our good work.
We have our columns with icons and we've got three features.
Let's change the text of all of this.
First, and I'm going to fast forward through this section so you don't have to watch me copy paste.
And there you have it.
We've now got all the text replaced and we should have all of our copy, which is the text for your
website inserted into the relevant parts.
Now, one thing that you'll notice is very obvious is that this part does not look like this part.
And it also doesn't look like the part that we copied the code from.
So what is going on here?
Well, as I mentioned, most of the bootstrap styling and components come from bootstrap classes.
For example, this one looks like this because it has a class of icon link.
But sometimes sometimes we might want to customize the styling that we get so that we have some of our
own design features on top of what Bootstrap already addresses.
If we right click on these styled squares from the example website, and if you scroll up to find the
div where it highlights the entire square, you can see that this div actually has some custom styling.
Now the reason why we know it's custom is because all of the default bootstrap classes come from something
like utilities dot CSS, for example, the background gradient, for example, the margins, the align,
etcetera.
But the parts that come from custom CSS for this page is going to have a file that looks like this.
So for this features page, they've created some custom CSS and in that custom CSS file they've got
little bits of CSS just to make things look a little bit more custom rather than coming from bootstrap.
So the part that we're missing, as you can see, is something called feature icon.
So if we copy all of this CSS and put it into our CSS here between the style tags, then we look at
our website, we can see those squares styled the way we want.
Now what we're going to have to do is to remove the SVG in the examples and replace it with our own
svgs that we've downloaded.
So let's go ahead and find the first one which is here.
Let's go ahead and delete this and simply add an image with the source set as the first one, which
is the briefcase, because we're saying how professional we are.
So let's change the alt text and the second SVG will replace with the image that is the bus front.
And this is because we're saying that our services are available countrywide.
And then for the final feature icon, we're going to change it to the chat square.
Hard to say how much of a personal touch our company has, and now we should have all of the icons set
up, but they're a little bit small.
So in order to get it to the right size, we'll do the same thing that we did with the icon up there.
We'll give it a different height.
So let's go ahead and add a height of 30 to each of these svgs and now they are all correctly sized.
And while you've been doing the copy and pasting, you might notice there's another SVG here, which
is the Chevron, right?
Which is this little forward button here.
We can also replace that with our images, which is the Chevron, right?
And we'll give it an alt text and copy and paste this to all three places where they exist.
Now, the reason why the svgs that we copied from the features section doesn't work on our website is
because svgs can be installed in many different ways.
We can download it just as I have done and put them into the project folder and you can access it through
the SVG element or through an image element.
Alternatively, you can simply copy the entire HTML code for a clean look.
I've simply downloaded each of the Svgs into our resources folder and added them as images.
It really is up to you how you want to do it.
Now that you've seen a little bit about how we can use the different code snippets from the bootstrap
components or from bootstrap examples, I've got a exercise for you.
We know that the next section after features is our carousel and it's simply a component that allows
you to scroll through different pages.
Now the one that I've chosen here has an indicator at the bottom, so you can easily switch to whichever
page you want.
It's got the side buttons here so you can go left and right and all it has are just three large images,
but be aware that the images don't go all the way to the edge.
Instead, they are aligned with the rest of the content.
So have a think about what you've learnt before.
Have a read of the carousel documentation.
Find the example that you think looks the most like the outcome and see if you can complete this challenge.
Pause the video now.
All right.
If you completed this challenge successfully, we've now got another section here, which is a bootstrap
carousel, which is really neat when you want to display some gallery images or maybe you have some
testimonials you want users to be able to flip through and maybe you want to show all the members of
your team.
And if you look inside the carousel example here, you can see there's an example with different text,
but the example that I use is actually even simpler than that.
It's in the docs inside the components.
So going back to the components now, we can take a look at how the carousel works if you want to have
a read.
But I've chosen one of the basic examples which has an indicator where you can toggle to different pages
and we simply have a big image covering the entire carousel.
Let's copy this code and paste it into our website.
Now when you paste it, you won't see anything happen at all.
And the reason is because there's no images, the images are broken and that's because the images have
no source set by default.
So let's go ahead and set our carousel image source.
So the first one we're going to set to the couple and.
The second one we're going to set as the dog.
This is almost like an evolution of a family going from a couple to a dog to a family.
And finally, we have all of our photos set up.
And now if we take a look, you can see our carousel is showing and it's working, but it's maybe a
little bit too big.
It's kind of taking up more than the height of the website.
And that's because this is set to cover the entire width.
If you remember from previous lessons, one of the best components to size everything evenly is from
the layout section, and it is our container.
We know that we're going to get a uniform look if we put things inside a container div.
So that's exactly what we're going to do.
I'm going to create a div and I'm going to set it to class of container and I'm going to move the final
closing div just below the carousel.
And now when we go back you can see our carousel is nicely enclosed inside the container and you can
see that no matter which size I change to, we've always got a consistent look with that container responsiveness.
We're now ready for the final section of our website, which is just the footer.
And I haven't done a lot of work on the footer.
I've simply gone into the snippets, found the footer section, picked one that I liked and then hit
inspect to find the starting point of the footer and pasted that code into the correct position.
I'm not going to modify this too much because you already know how you can do that, but just look at
how easy it was to create this beautiful website in a matter of minutes using bootstrap components.
The components are really, really handy, as are the snippets and the example code because they allow
you to pick a style out of their palette that you like and simply add it into your website.
And this makes it super easy to build well-thought out designs very, very quickly.
In addition to the layout classes, that Bootstrap gives you the component classes, there are also
utility classes and helpers.
And one really important aspect of this is spacing.
Very often when we're designing websites, we want to add margin, we want to add padding.
And this is all spacing, right?
As you might remember from previous lessons, padding sets up the part between the item and the containing
div.
So this part and the margin sets up the spacing between the outline of your item and any other components.
So you can set all of those values using very simple bootstrap notation.
So let's run through this quickly.
It's a format where you have the property, which sides you want, a dash and then the size.
And this is really easy to figure out.
So for example, if I wanted to set margin only to the top of my element, then I can say m T So.
M For classes that set margin.
T that sets margin top or padding top and then using a dash, I can say how much margin I want.
So zero is eliminating the margin and then we can add a little bit more, a little bit more, a little
bit more.
So if I had margin top five, that's usually the maximum that you'll need.
And then there's this concept of X and Y.
So if you want to set the margin for both the top and the bottom, you'll use the x axis.
And if you want to set the margin or padding for the left and the right, then you can use that y axis.
So maybe you'll have MY-3.
It looks like my three, but it actually says set the margin for the y axis to a size of three.
It's relatively easy once you understand it, but when you just see it in the code, it can be really,
really confusing.
But now you should be able to see that in our footer we've got MB-2 and that of course stands for adding
margin to the bottom.
And it's a size of two.
That's how we can decode all this.
Now, the final neat trick I want to show you in this lesson is how you can add dark mode to your website,
flipping the colors around by simply adding one property into your HTML tag.
If you go into the customize section, go into color modes, you'll see that Bootstrap now supports
dark mode and it can flip the entire.
Project's theme to the opposite color simply by setting the data bootstrap theme to dark.
Let's try that out on our website.
Let's go all the way up to our HTML after the language is set.
Let's change the theme to Dark and you can see our entire website has now been reformatted to a dark
theme, which is super neat.
If this is the design that you want or if later on when we learn about JavaScript and we can put in
buttons to change the theme of our website to whichever the user prefers so that the user can change
that theme to whichever they prefer.
So now you're starting to see how powerful bootstrap can be using these examples, using snippets,
using the pre-built components and styling as well as the layout system.
But if you've tried to build websites before, you've probably come across full page themes completely
built out for you.
For example, with Squarespace.
The catch, though, is you're going to have to pay something like 12 a month or $10 a month in order
to just be able to use these templates of theirs and to have your website on the Internet.
What I want to show you is that with Bootstrap there are a whole bunch of free themes and paid for themes
that you can use that are one off costs for you to build beautiful websites and simply customize the
themes.
Now that you know all about bootstrap, one handy template is from W3 schools and they have some of
the most common website layouts like a blog.
You might have a sidebar main, a footer or what a portfolio might look like or what a web page might
look like.
A social website.
ET cetera.
And they've built these simple examples for you to be able to simply take the code and customize in
order for you to use their examples.
You can simply do, as we have done, find a template that you want to replicate and then customize
it and maybe add some more custom CSS in order to achieve the look that you want.
If you think that these are a little bit basic because they are, the idea is they're mostly for layout,
getting the big structure done using the bootstrap layout system.
There are a lot of other beautiful bootstrap themes that are more complete in a way, starting with
the official bootstrap themes itself.
If we head back to the main bootstrap website, click on themes.
You can see that they've got these professionally designed websites and many of them look absolutely
incredible.
So depending on what it is that you're trying to build, you could use one of these templates.
But the only downside to this is they are in fact all paid for because there's a lot of work that's
gone into it, right?
But these are mostly one off costs.
And if you don't want to pay to get a theme, you can always search through Google for free bootstrap
templates and you'll find a whole range of websites that have free and paid for bootstrap websites.
And again, you can do the same thing as we've been doing so far in this lesson.
Just getting hold of the components you want, customizing it and getting the design that you're looking
for.
So hopefully in this lesson you've seen that bootstrap can be incredibly easy to create components and
features in our websites very, very quickly, and it has consistent and beautiful design to boot.
And if you've really taken to bootstrap and web design, you can even create and sell your own themes.
If you really enjoy working with bootstrap and designing websites and creating websites using the bootstrap
components, you can create the templates yourself and put them onto marketplaces and sell them as a
potential source of income.
So have a play around with the other components, see what bootstrap themes are out there.
And in the next lesson, we've got the final project for this section where you're going to be building
a fully fledged startup website or by yourself using your knowledge of bootstrap.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
All right.
So now that you've learned all about bootstrap, it's time to apply what we've learned and build a project.
I want you to imagine that a startup has approached you to build their landing page.
So the company is called Tin Dog, and they make basically tinder for dogs, helping dogs meet new and
interesting dogs nearby.
Obviously this is a fake startup that I've created.
Now, if you want to go ahead and steal this idea, then I fully support you.
But essentially the idea is very simple.
You have a dog, you want your dog to have friends, so let's use tin dog.
Now our website is pretty fully fledged and if you want to look at what the finished product looks like,
head over to App Github.io forward slash tin dog.
And this is what you'll see.
It's a really simple startup website with a animated gradient background with buttons to download the
app as well as features testimonials, pricing and a footer.
We're going to be creating this beautiful website, and the way we're going to do it is through the
use of the different snippets that are provided by bootstrap as well as the different components and
using bootstrap layout to get it responsive and looking beautiful on desktop and mobile straight out
of the box.
To get started first download the Tin Dog project, unzip the file and open it inside vs code.
Now here I want you to open up the index.html and you can see I've provided some comments and some section
HTML elements.
These section elements are mostly used to separate different sections of a website, so it's just a
group or area of the website.
And in modern websites you'll see very often these sections.
So this one is a section, this is a section, this is a section and it keeps the code nice and organized
and you're going to be writing your code in between these section elements in order to create each of
these areas.
Now, what are you aiming for?
Well, you can always refer to the live website at GitHub.com Forward slash Tin Dog to see what everything
should look like.
But I've also provided goal images for each individual section that's marked up to point you to certain
areas that need more attention.
For example, what's the name of the image that's going to be displayed here?
Well, it's iPhone dot PNG and you can find it inside the images folder, but also things like this
little Apple icon is actually an SVG and you can find those inside the README.
So I've included all the SVG code in here and I want you to be copy and pasting these svgs because some
of them have different heights, they have different sizes and instead of getting it from the bootstrap
website, which this is from, I want you to use this version.
So just copy and paste it into your code.
Also, if you scroll down, there's the text copy that you'll need on your website and so you can either
copy it straight from the final finished website or you can use the text from the README and just copy
it from here.
If you're working as a web developer, this is a very common workflow.
You'll want your client to create the text copy because they know the most about what they want on their
website, and all you have to do is just place it and style it in the right ways.
Now, the final thing I want to mention is if you look inside the style.css, this is going to be your
CSS style sheet for the website.
You can see that already in there.
I've got a class called Gradient Background, and this code comes from a codepen by Manuel Pinto where
he created a pure CSS gradient background PSD, and we're simply just using this code but defining some
unique colors of our own.
And you can see in here we are having our animated gradient hovers between these three colors, a blue,
a red and a sort of peachy color.
And that's how we're going to get this gradient background similar to other things you've been doing
with Bootstrap.
In order to get this gradient to show, all you have to do is to add this class to your HTML element
and then it will automatically animate with this beautiful color scheme.
This project is going to require a little bit of exploration, a little bit of looking around the bootstrap
example, seeing which ones might work and comparing them, for example, which of the heroes might
be the one that we could use, or which of the features might match the one that we've got here and
customizing it and checking its CSS and.
Making sure that things look pretty much the same as the final outcome.
Now it's time for you to pause the video and give this challenge a good go.
You might have to spend half an hour, an hour on it.
Just give yourself lots of time to make mistakes.
Try things out.
Don't be too harsh on yourself.
This is a big project, but I believe in you.
I think you can do it.
Pause the video now and see how you get on.
All right.
Hopefully you've completed this challenge and you're just here to see how I'm doing it.
If you haven't given this a go, I really recommend you to stop, pause the video and actually try it
first because you can listen to me all day long, but you're not going to learn until you actually take
the first step and write the code yourself.
I know it can be really, really tempting, but I promise you this is the only way you're going to be
able to move on to harder things in the future by struggling through each and every single step.
Because once we start moving on, I'm going to assume that all of these things are in your tool belt.
So make sure you practice, practice, practice.
And this is a perfect opportunity.
All right.
Pep talk over.
Let's go ahead and build out this website.
Now, the first thing I'm going to do is build out this title section.
So if we take a look at the title goal, we can see it's pretty much what we call a hero section.
If we take a look inside the the bootstrap examples and we look inside the hero's area, you can see
it looks incredibly similar to the layout here.
It's got some big text, some buttons and an image to the right, which is pretty much what we have.
So let's go ahead and right click, inspect and scroll up to the top level that contains everything
just after the divider and let's copy the entire element.
I'm going to paste that element into this section area and let's hit save and see what it looks like.
So I'm going to show preview just to get this URL and I'm going to open it inside Chrome so I can see
it in full screen.
Now you can see this doesn't look like bootstrap at all.
The text is not the right font.
The buttons are not styled.
This is just pure HTML.
This should give you a big hint as to what is wrong.
And that is because we have not yet added a link to the bootstrap CSS.
So let's go ahead and do that now.
So if we go back to the main bootstrap docs and go to the home page, we should be able to grab hold
of the link and we can paste it into our project.
So now let's hit, save and go back to our tin dog.
We should see that we have what is closer to the example that we saw right here.
There's a couple of things that we will need to fix.
First, let's go ahead and get rid of this broken image and put in the image that we want.
Here is the image.
So let's go ahead and change the source to our image, which is inside the images folder.
And it's called iPhone dot PNG.
And let's change the alt to app demo.
Let's hit, save and go back and we can see this is absolutely massive.
So now we're going to have to adjust the size.
So here it's set to width, 700 height, 500.
I'm going to keep the aspect ratio.
So I'm going to delete just the width and hopefully it will adjust proportionally and I'm going to change
the height to 200 pixels.
And this looks more or less the right size.
Now yours might be a little bit bigger, a little bit smaller.
It doesn't really matter as long as it looks good to your eye.
Now the next thing we're going to do is let's change all of this text so that it reads the same as the
final copy.
And to do that, I'm going to find the text inside my readme me, go ahead and copy and paste it into
the right areas.
So we've got an H1 and that's where we're going to replace with our big heading meet new and interesting
dogs nearby.
And then I'm going to delete this paragraph element because we don't actually have it in our final design.
And I'm going to change the two buttons to both say download.
In addition to the download, there's obviously two svgs as well, and these are the icons from Bootstrap.
But remember I mentioned that you can get hold of these svgs in the README file, so I'm going to wholesale
just copy this apple SVG and paste it into here.
Add a space between the SVG and download and now hopefully we have a good looking apple symbol in the
download button and I'm going to do the same with the Google Play logo.
Hit save and that's it.
There it is.
We're going to change the color scheme here a little bit.
We've got a button light and we've got a button outline light so that it would look the same as the
final design.
Now, right now, this button is a button primary, so we're going to have to change that to light.
And this one, is it a button outline secondary.
We're going to change that to button outline light.
Let's hit, save and see what we have.
Now you'll notice that this button is almost completely disappeared if not for this rollover effect.
And the reason is because it's more or less a white outline.
In order for this to show we need a background.
So let's go ahead and set it up with this gradient background.
Remember I mentioned that if you look inside the Style.css file, there is already a class called gradient
background, which we can add into our HTML for it to show up.
Now where do we add it before we can add it?
We need to import our CSS and as always, we put our custom CSS after the bootstrap.
So in case there are any collisions in terms of targeting the same selectors, the final one wins out,
which hopefully is our CSS.
So I'm going to link to the style CSS and then I'm going to put that class gradient background into
my title section.
So where do I put it now?
If I put it inside the container, you'll see that it's only inside the container and the container's
got these big margins on the left and right.
So this is not the look that we want.
Instead, we're going to put this inside the section.
We can't put it into the ID because it's not an ID, it's actually a class.
So make sure you've got it set inside the class property.
Now let's take a look.
And this looks pretty good.
Now, the only difference between what we have and what we're aiming for is a lot of padding.
Now, the reason I can tell this padding and not margin is because padding extends the background.
So if this was an extra margin, then this area would be white.
But instead it's actually the same as the background color.
So where does this margin come from?
Let's go ahead and hit, inspect and make this just a little bit smaller so we can see this padding.
And if we scroll up until we see the padding show up, you can see that orange down there when I hover
over it.
Well, that is what we need to get rid of.
So you can see we've got padding top and padding bottom.
And if we get rid of the top and bottom, it will look a little bit too much.
So if we just target the bottom, then we've got more or less the right layout.
So let's go in here and find that P five for the container which is right here.
And remember, the P stands for padding, the Y stands for the Y axis.
So it means it's adding padding to the top and the bottom.
So if we want to change this to only have it on the top, then we change this to padding top and then
we've got another div that has the padding on top and bottom as well.
So let's change it there.
And then when we go back we should see that we have pretty much the same layout.
And now if we compare our layout to the final outcome, it looks pretty much exactly the same.
So we can now move on to our next section, which is the features section.
If we open up our features goal, you can see that we've got three different areas with all of the features
that we want to show off, and we've got this sort of rough layout.
If we go back to the bootstrap examples and if we look inside the snippets at the features, you can
see this is pretty much the same layout as what we're aiming for.
So let's go ahead and inspect and find that row that we need to get hold of.
Let's copy the element and put it inside our index.html.
Now once we paste it in, let's hit, save and see it.
You can see this is occupying pretty much the entire full width, which is not quite what we want.
We actually want it all to be roughly along the same vertical line.
So why is this?
Well, it's because the top level here is a bootstrap row.
If we want it to be contained, then we need to add a container.
So let's add that container class and then let's move this closing tag to wrap it around all of this
hit save.
And now you can see we've got that perfect alignment.
The next thing we need to do is.
Is that we need to get rid of all of these buttons and that is pretty easy.
They're just these anchor tags.
So there's one there, there's one here and there's one up here.
So now we're pretty much on the design we're looking for.
All we need to do is replace the text.
This is probably a little bit boring, so I'm going to use video editing to speed things up a bit for
you.
All right.
So now that we've got all of our custom copy in, the final thing we need to fix are these svgs.
So let's go ahead and replace the svgs that are in the example with the ones that we want.
So the first one is going to be the check mark SVG Let's copy and paste it in.
The second one is the graduation hat.
And the final one is the heart with an arrow through it.
So now that we've replaced all of our svgs, you can see them show up, but the background doesn't look
quite the same.
It should have these rounded corners, it should be a little bit larger.
And we will look on the bootstrap example where we copied our code from.
They look perfect.
But why is it that when it's in our website it doesn't quite look the same?
Now this might be something that you got stuck on, but in order to figure this out, the easiest way
is to inspect on it.
In Chrome, you can see right now I'm highlighting the SVG, but if I go one level above and hover on
that div, that is the one with all of that fancy styling.
And if we look inside the styles, you can see there's actually some custom CSS in here because it's
not in the utilities which comes from bootstrap.
This is actually custom CSS just for this feature section.
So what we need to do is we need to copy all of the CSS and put it inside our style.css.
So now this icon square, which is the class for this div, can be activated.
And when we look at it now, you can see that they all have the right styling that we expected.
So the final thing we need to sort out is just to add a little bit more margin in this features section
and then we're pretty much done.
So if we look at the features goal, you can see I've given you a hint that it's actually margin top
five.
If we want to add some margin to this entire container, then we can go up to the div class where we
have the container and then we add margin top five, empty dash five.
And now we should have enough space between that top title section and our feature section.
So we're now ready to move on to the testimonial section.
Again, let's take a look at the goal that we're looking for.
So the first section is an H2 with an image and some paragraph text.
This area comes from this Jumbotron section, and if we scroll down, we can see this full width jumbotron
right here.
So let's go ahead and inspect on it and let's take the entire section just after the divider.
So let's copy the element and paste it into our testimonial section.
Let's take a look at what that looks like.
It looks pretty good, but we need to modify it for our purposes.
So let's change the text inside.
If we go over to our README, we should see our quote here from Pebbles and we can replace the text
inside the H1.
Remember from our HTML classes we should only have one H1 per website.
And remember at the beginning in our title section we've already got our big heading.
So here it should really not be an H1.
Let's turn it into a subheading by changing that to an H2.
Now this paragraph element, I could delete it, but I'm actually going to keep it and use it for showing
the name where the quote comes from, which is Pebbles from New York.
And all I have to do now is add an image in between, and the image is going to be our dog image and
I'm going to add the alt text as well.
Let's take a look at what that looks like.
It looks great.
Other than the fact that this should be rounded and it should be a little bit smaller, if we look at
the goal, we can see it should be 100 pixels high and it should be circular.
So how do we make it custom?
Well, we're going to need to create some styling, right?
So let's create a class called profile Dash Image and let's set it to have a height of 100 pixels.
And in order to make it circular, remember, we need to set the border radius to 50%.
Now, if we apply that class to our image profile dash image and we look at our website and you can
see that looks pretty much perfect and similar to what we've got here.
Now, the only thing we need to add is just a little bit more margin.
We should have a margin of five between these two sections and a margin of two between these two sections.
So I'm just going to add some margin top to the image.
So a size five margin to the image so I can hit space on the class and then do margin top dash five.
And then for the text, I'm going to do a class of margin top dash two.
And now we should have enough space in between everything and it looks pretty much the same as the example.
Now we need to add in all of these outlets that have featured our startup, and you can see from the
goal image here that we've got a 12 column grid here from Bootstrap and they're each occupying a fourth
of the space.
But notice here where I've said it should take up three columns on desktop, but a full width, 12 columns
on mobile.
So it should be responsive and we can find all these images in the images folder.
Let's go ahead and add that below this container in order to create the bootstrap 12 column layout system,
the first thing we always need is a container.
So let's create a div of class container and inside here is where we need our div that has a class of
row.
So now we're ready to create our columns.
Each of the columns are going to be three columns in the desktop format, so that's called Dash Large
or LG and it's going to be dash three, but on mobile.
So call Dash, SM Small is going to be full width.
So 12 and inside here we can place our image which is from the images folder and we're going to start
off with TechCrunch and I'm going to add the alt text as that.
Now I'm going to copy this and paste it three times and now I'm just going to replace each of these
images with the ones that we have here.
So Mashable, Business Insider and TMW.
All right.
So now we should have all of our images, but they are a little bit large.
One thing we can do is we can limit their height so that they are all equal in height instead of having
this uneven start and end line.
So I'm going to set the height to 30 and that should be enough height to be visible, but not so much
height that it takes up too much space and that looks pretty good.
So now we're done with our testimonial section and we are on our penultimate section, which is the
pricing plan.
And as you'll remember, Bootstrap has the pricing plan section right here.
And these three cards are the ones that we want to get hold of.
So let's inspect on that and find the area that we need, which is probably this div row.
So let's copy it and put it inside the pricing section.
But as you remember, a div row needs to go inside a container.
So let's go ahead and do that.
And if we look at our pricing table then it's already in and looks pretty good.
The other section we need is a title for the pricing table, which is this area right here, and this
is the div that contains all of that content.
So let's just copy it and put it at the beginning of our container right here.
So now we've pretty much got the pricing table down.
We just need to update all of the text here to the ones that we have in our copy.
So I'm going to do this again quickly.
I'm going to fast forward and replace all the text.
All right, so now all the text has been replaced and you should see all of that text inside the pricing
section.
So now we need to update the design a little bit.
And the main difference is the color scheme here is all using the bootstrap primary color, which is
this blue.
But we need to change it all to the dark kind of color, which is this kind of black color.
And if you look inside the pricing goal, you can see the parts that we need to change.
This needs to become outline dark.
This needs to be button, dark, button dark.
And this also needs to be dark.
A shortcut here is to simply use the control F on windows or command F on Mac in order to bring up our
search bar.
And if we search for the word primary and we replace it with dark, then we can actually go through
each of these examples and see if we want to replace it.
What I recommend doing is to actually do this one by one.
So instead of doing replace all, because that way you can see which parts you're replacing.
And many times I've done replace all only to find out that I've messed up the entire project in some
big way.
So just a word of advice.
Go through it one by one.
Make sure that it makes sense and it's the right area that you're changing.
But hopefully when we go back to our website, we can see we've now updated all of the right places
to this dark color scheme.
Coming back to our pricing goal, we can see that this title needs to be an H2 and this subtitle needs
to be a paragraph element.
So let's go into our section and make sure that is the case, because when we copied it over, it actually
gave us an H1.
Now the styling is not going to change because it actually comes from the display for class.
So you won't see the size change that much or the color scheme because it is actually not dependent
on the HTML element.
And this happens very frequently with bootstrap, so we're able to adjust that pretty easily.
And now we're ready for our final section, which is the footer.
So let's find ourselves the footer snippets and let's find the one that looks like one that we want,
or one that is similar to the one in the example, which is this one right here.
And let's find the container that we can copy and put into our footer section.
So now straight up we can see our footer section show up and all we need to do is to adapt it to our
design.
Firstly, you'll notice there's this area that you can't really see, but when you hover it, it seems
to be clickable.
And if we refer to our code, you can see this is actually a link that links to the bootstrap logo.
So let's go ahead and delete that.
But let's change this paragraph class to copyright and then the name of our company, Tin Dog.
And I'm going to leave these links alone because I don't know, maybe in the future you'll want to use
this website and put in some different links to different sections.
But for now it just kind of looks more or less the right kind of style that we would want on a startup
website.
So let's leave that alone, but let's get rid of this border line here.
And this border came from the footer.
So there should be a hint in here.
If we look at the footer element, you can see there's the border top class, which again comes from
bootstrap, but it's a really simple way of adding some borders to the top left or right.
But once we delete it and that's completely gone.
So the final thing we need to do is just to add that gradient background to the footer area and then
we are pretty much done.
So let's take that section footer and add the class gradient background and now hit save.
And we should see that we have almost the same website as the final result.
The only thing that we need to do now is to get rid of this little bit of space at the bottom.
And the fact that it's white should give you a hint as to what it is.
If we select our footer section and we go into the section, look inside the container, at some point
our hover is going to show us where that margin comes from.
And right here you can see that orange box showing that margin at the bottom.
So if we select it, we should see there are some margin classes applied.
So there's a margin top, which I think we should probably keep because it adds a good amount of spacing
between the different sections.
But the margin bottom we could probably get rid of so that we don't have that white space down there.
So let's find this.
Y-5 class in our footer element and it's right here and let's change it instead of y to just having
it on top.
And now let's hit, save and refresh.
And you can see we have now completed our design for our website.
In less than half an hour.
We've managed to build a incredibly complex and beautiful website for our tin dog startup.
I hope our clients will be pleased because we've created this amazing, incredibly modern looking website
for them and we should be pleased because it only took us so little time to do by leveraging the power
of the bootstrap components and using the different helper classes, utilities, as well as snippets
that they provide.
Hopefully this gives you an insight into how we can use bootstrap to create beautiful, complex websites
quickly.
And also you see the difference between what CSS grid, Flexbox and Bootstrap are all good for.
They all have different strengths and weaknesses and I think bootstrap is really good for throwing some
components down and creating something that looks incredibly modern very, very quickly.
Whereas Flexbox and Grid are great when you want to get into the nitty gritty of creating a very, very
custom layout for your website.
So well done on completing this section.
And in the next section we've got the Capstone project for CSS.
So once you're ready, head over to the next section.
Hey guys. In this module I've got something a little bit different for you. Now,
up till now we've been working on how to build websites that have great functionality and how to use
CSS, HTML, to build up the structure of the website.
Now today I want to talk about something a little bit different namely how to design websites so that
not only does your website have great functionality but it also looks beautiful.
The most important thing to making a website loved by users is pretty much the design.
After all, think about it.
When was the last time you heard somebody tell you, "Hey I came across this great website.
It worked really really well.
So smooth and no bugs."
Nobody ever says that right?
They say things like: "It looked so beautiful. It just worked like I wanted it to."
So today we're going to talk about design and I want to show you some of the different aspects of design
when it comes to websites.
Now more often than not, you've heard the saying right?
"Don't judge a book by its cover."
Now at the same time, you might have also heard of this saying: "You only have three seconds to make a
good impression."
Now when it comes to web design, the latter is probably more accurate.
It's just like a job interview or a first date, your website has a crucial few seconds before the user
is going to judge your company, your brand, your product.
So take a look at this example.
This is a website called Penny juice and it's a company that sells children's juice cartons.
Now look at the design of it. There's clashing colors, there's different typefaces, there's different colors
for the text and they have different fonts and it's all, to be honest, a bit of a mess.
So this is a question I often ask students at this point.
Take a look at this website and ask yourself if you were to buy a product from this company,
if you were to buy a carton of juice, how much would you pay for it?
Now take a look at this website.
This is the same website reimagined by a professional web designer.
Look at how the color scheme is now consistent, how the fonts and the typefaces now look a lot better.
And ask yourself again, how much would you pay for a single carton of juice from this website.
Now I've asked this question to a number of people and this is the result I got.
People are willing to pay anywhere up to only a dollar for a carton of juice from the first wesite
but anywhere up to $3 for the second website.
Now I run a startup and a lot of friends and colleagues of mine also work on their own businesses.
And we usually spend a lot of time brainstorming, how can we make our product better,
how do we make our brand stronger.
And there's very very few things that we can think of that can actually produce a three times improvement
in the value of your product or in the value of your company.
So design is really really powerful.
It's one of the cheapest ways to make your company or your product look expensive because it's elevating.
And it doesn't take a lot to get good at design as you'll see in the coming lessons.
So we're going to be exploring some of the principles of web design in this module.
And I want to take you through everything from color theory to typography to user interface design and
user experience design.
These are the four pillars of good web design.
So once you are ready, head over to the next lesson and let's get started.
Now one of the first things I want to talk about is Color Theory. And color theory is the art and science
of creating the right palette for your website.
So take a look at this example.
Now let's say you had a logo where you have flowers which are brown, paintball which is pink.
It looks all very weird and very inconsistent.
And take a look at the actual logos. Like what are you thinking when you see these color palettes on
the words. The color of the flowers looks a bit like dirt I guess but it also looks a bit like something
else. And the paint ball being pink
I'm not really sure who that target audience is. But take a look at this.
If we flip the color palette, it suddenly all looks like it's meant to be like this.
It suddenly all looks a lot better right?
It looks consistent with the actual message.
So when you're picking colors you have to be aware of the mood of your color palette.
So the predominant color that is going to be in your design really tells a story and it conveys a message
to the user.
For example, Red conveys love, energy, intensity. Which is why you see a lot of car adverts which have a
red car on a red background.
It's because they're trying to tell you,
"Hey buy this car and you'll feel energetic
and the intensity of this car even if you're 89." Now yellow is more about joy, intellect, attention.
And the most important thing about yellow though is how attention grabbing it is because it's almost
impossible to not look at something that is very yellow.
For example this ad. Now a few years back
this ad caused an uproar because it has this lady in a yellow bikini
and it says, "Are you
beach body ready?"
And a lot of people got really really upset about it.
They took to the Internet,
they raved about it.
And I remember thinking to myself at the time, "You know, this is not so different from a lot of the other
ads that are trying to tell women how to look."
And it's not a great message.
But why is it causing so much anger and causing so much attention drawn to it?
And I think the reason is because it's actually bright yellow.
It's impossible to ignore this advert when you come across it.
So when you're creating a logo or when you're creating some sort of headline, then yeah yellow is a great
choice. But when you're creating something that's designed to be looked at for a long period of time
then yellow can be too attention grabbing. It might actually hurt your user's eyes
if you tried to read a whole article that's backgrounded in yellow.
Now the next color that we're going to talk about is green which is all about freshness, growth, safety.
And that's why you see a lot of grocery companies like Hello Fresh or Amazon groceries use this color
as their predominant color palette. Because it's trying to tell you, "Hey look! This thing is edible.
This is what we're selling."
And so if you have a company that has anything to do with food, this is usually a safe bet to go with.
Now Blue is about stability, trust, serenity. And so you see a lot of companies which need to convey that
"Hey, we're really trustworthy"
use this color. For example,
look at all the financial companies, look at companies like PayPal or the cryptocurrency companies like
Coinbase. They all choose this color because they want you to know that they're not going to run away
with your money.
In fact, there was a really interesting psychology study where they compared interviewees wearing different
colored shirts.
So for example, a group of them would wear a green shirt,
another group would wear a blue shirt and they compared how they were perceived by the interviewers.
And it showed that just by changing the color of your shirt to a blue one you vastly increase the amount
of trust in you
that's given by other people.
So have a think about that the next time you're going for an interview.
Now the final color is purple and it's meant to signify royalty, wealth, femininity. And strangely enough
I've come across a number of payday loan companies which use this color palette especially ones which
are targeted at women.
So, the important thing to think about is that you're making a conscious decision when you're choosing
a color palette.
It's not just whichever color you like or your favorite color. But it's actually 'what message am I trying
to convey to the user' and then picking an appropriate color. Now, usually you're not just going to be
using a single color for your design. You're probably going to be using two or three.
So at some point you have to think about which different colors to combine.
And this is probably the most scientific part of color theory.
Now very often, designers will rely on scientific ways of combining colors. For example taking two colors
that are right next to each other on the color wheel.
And this way you create what's called an analogous color palette.
And these designs look incredibly harmonious and they really work well together.
So this color palette can be really good for things like navigation bars and the body of your website
or things like a logo and it's background.
Now, what it's not so good at though is standing out. If you really want your design to pop, you're better
off taking two colors from opposite ends of the color wheel creating what's called a complementary color
palette or a clashing palette.
Now this complementary color palette really creates that pop.
And it really brings out each of the colors.
So the next time you go to a supermarket, I want you to take a look at the meat aisle and see if they've
used this complementary color palette to make things pop.
So, one of the things that you often see is they'll take these fake plastic bits of greenery like fake
grass or fake bushes and they'll put it in between the meat. And because the green and the red are complementary
colors it makes the red meat pop out a lot more and gives you this idea of freshness
even if it's a little bit past the best dates. But what you shouldn't do with clashing colors or complementary
colors is to try to style text and text background with it because it actually looks very very jarring
and you can feel your eyes sort of getting a little bit fuzzy
looking at this particular combination. So don't do this when it concerns text.
Instead, keep it to things like logos or icons or things that you really really want to stand out from
each other.
Now, there's a lot of other ways that you can combine colors like drawing an equilateral triangle to
create a triadic color palette or drawing a perfect square.
Now if you want to, you can head over to a website called Adobe color which lets you mess around with
all of these different color combinations. So select a triadic color palette or a square color palette
and then drag it around the color wheel so that you get different combinations of colors.
And once you come across a palette that fits the mood of your project, then you can pick the hex codes
and just put them straight into your website.
Now if all of that sounds like it was a little bit too much work ,then I got you covered.
You can also use a website called colorhunt.co.
This is a website where professional designers have curated some of their favorite color palettes
and you can nab the hex codes straight off the website.
So take a look at the hot and popular sections of this website and use it to guide the pilot scheme
for your next project.
Now when you create a website that has a beautiful consistent color scheme like the one for the LIEBE
yogurt, you can see how much it makes the design stand out and it becomes really colorful and really
playful and you can convey different messages using your choice of colors and your color scheme.
So think about your color choice and your color palette
the next time you design your website to make sure that it is consistent with what your brand is about
and what your product is about and it conveys the message you want to convey.
All right.
The next topic I want to talk about is typography.
Now, I know a lot of students always say to me
"But why do I need to learn about typography?
I just open up Word, click the dropdown,
find Times New Roman,
my favorite font.
And then just put that on everything. It's done right?"
Well let's think about this.
Well let's say it's Valentine's Day and you decide that you want to write a letter to your beloved Valentine
and you change the font to something cursive like this.
"You'll always be mine."
I don't know if she or he will be
but you have a good chance.
Now let's say that you chose the wrong font.
That's a bit of a problem.
Not only do I not think your Valentine is going to take very kindly to this,
you might also have the police on your back which is a bit of a problem.
So fonts really do matter and it's important to consider not only their mood but also how to combine
different fonts.
And it's a really really easy way to make your designs look very professional and really slick. Out of
all of the fonts in the world
there's pretty much two large families that you should really know about.
One is the Serif family where they have these little feet at the end of their central beams.
And the reason why they have these old feet is because the Serif typeface were inspired by the marble
carvings of days of yore.
So if you next go out and you take a look at the buildings around you especially if you're in a historical
area, take a look at places where they've carved into stone or marble and you'll notice that they also
have these little feet at the end of the central beams.
So why is that?
I don't know how many of you carved marble in your spare time but if you did you would know that once
you chisel has gone into the Rock and you need to exit your engraving it's actually not possible to
create 90 degree angles when you're carving into rock.
So this is where the Serif typeface gets their inspiration from.
And this is also the reason why when you're choosing a Serif typeface you're making your design look
more serious, more authoritative and also a little bit older as well.
So it's really good if you're designing something like a letterhead for a legal company or a magazine
for architectural design.
But when we take a look at the big family of Serif typefaces
they're actually further subdivided into smaller sub families like Old style, Transitional, Modern and
Slab-Serif.
Now the really interesting thing is you can actually tell how old a typeface would look by looking at
the difference between the thickest and the thinnest parts of each letter.
So compare the Old Style 'o' versus the Transitional
'o' versus the modern
'o'. And look at how that difference between the thickest part of the letter and the thinnest part gets
more and more exaggerated as you get towards a more modern font.
So if you want something that looks authoritative but modern then maybe you want to go for a modern
Serif typeface like Didot. But if you want it to come across as a little bit older, a little bit more aged
maybe you have a winery, maybe you want to go for an Old Style Serif instead.
Now just as different colors have different moods and emotions, different fonts also have different moods
and they also convey a different message to a user depending on which one you choose.
So the Serif family generally come across as traditional, stable, respectable, authoritative.
These are the words that get thrown around by designers when they're thinking about the Serif typeface.
So for example, the next time you go to a magazine rack pick up the Vogue magazine.
Take a look at their title and see how it's a modern Serif typeface.
It's got hugely exaggerated difference between the thick and thin parts of the lettering and it looks
authoritative and it knows what it is talking about.
Now on the other hand, if we think about the San-Serifs, they're kind of a different family because instead
of having the Serifs or the little feet at the end the central beams, they have perfect right angles.
And it's this right angle that makes the San-Serif family look so much more friendly, more approachable,
more novel and more contemporary.
So for example, you will tend to get words like sensible, simple, straightforward. And this is why a lot
of startups love using the San-Serif typeface in their websites.
For example, a Humanist typeface which is a subfamily of the San-Serifs. It's something that is known
as a highly readable typeface. And in fact, even within the Serifs and the San-Serifs, you will tend to
see designers going for the San-Serifs if they want to write body text which needs to be more legible
and more readable.
Now within this sub family, there's even differences in terms of legibility and readability.
So how easy are the words to read and how pleasant is it to read the letters.
There was a really interesting study done by MIT a few years back where they took two groups of users,
one they put them into a car which had a dashboard made of a Humanist typeface and the other car had
a dashboard which had a Grotesque San-Serif typeface. And what they did is they tracked the pupils of
the people who were driving the cars and they tested how long each driver needed to look down at the
dashboard before they got enough information from the speedometer or the odometer and before they could
come back and look at the road again. And really surprisingly they found that just by changing the font
from a Grotesque San-Serif to a Humanist San-Serif, they could save the drivers somewhere around
30 to 40 percent of the time that's required to understand the information.
So imagine that car is on a freeway that's driving at 60 miles, 100 miles an hour.
That difference in the amount of time the user needs to look down at the dashboard could be the difference
between life and death.
And as designers, we rarely get to make that kind of difference in the world right?
So knowing that the Humanist typeface, all of the fonts that belong in that category like Gill Sans,
Tahoma, Verdana, these are highly readable and highly legible fonts which you can use in the body types
for example of your sales pitch.
Now, even though we're not saving lives with our sales pitches,
if you manage to get the user to read through more of your sales copy then they're probably going to
be more convinced and more likely to buy your product
right?
So readability and legibility when you're choosing fonts is incredibly important. And the things that
you're looking for in the letters when you're looking for legibility are open shapes and a lot of space
between each of the letters and also the forms look unambiguous so they look different
for example here the 'g' and the 9 actually look different on the second line. And finally, varying proportions.
So having an 'O' that's very wide and a '0' that's a bit more narrow so you can actually tell the difference
between the two.
Now while we've talked about using fonts it's often that you see people go a bit overboard where they
choose 10 fonts in the same design. And that makes your design look very cluttered and very unprofessional.
I recommend actually sticking to just two fonts in one design.
So if you're making a poster keeping that to two fonts. If you're making a section of your website keeping
then again to two fonts. It just looks a lot cleaner and a lot tighter.
And when you're combining these two different fonts you want to try to go for similar moods. So find
fonts that have a similar mood to each other and also a similar time era.
You don't want something that looks ultramodern with something that looks like it's from the days of
yore combined together. It looks a little bit weird.
Now the things you want to contrast are the serifness.
So for example you on the heading to be a Serif and the body to be a San-Serif or the opposite way
round. It just creates more interest in your design.
And similarly, you can also create interest by just changing up the weights between the heading and the
body. So making the heading really really bold or even using a black typeface and making the body text
using something like thin or regular or light. These different weights can create contrast in your design.
Now if you don't remember anything from this talk on typefaces, I just want you to look at these six
fonts and try to wipe them from your memory because it is very very difficult to make these designs
look good unless I guess if you're running a lemonade stand.
But if you want to look professional, if you want to look designs, try to use one of the other fonts that
we've talked about and try to ignore these ones which are difficult to read and have moods that are
difficult to fit in in a professional setting.
The next time you're designing a website think about what typefaces you're going to choose.
Think about what you're trying to convey with those typefaces and then pick a font from the San-Serif
or the Serif family and maybe try to combine them
so you have a heading that's a San-Serif and a body that's a Serif and try to create contrast in your
designs.
So keep this in mind and hopefully they'll make your designs a lot more interesting and a lot more professional.
So now that we've talked about some of the fundamentals of design like Color Theory and Typography, the
next thing I want to talk about is User Interface Design.
Now take a look at this picture.
In most cases, 99% of you would have read "YOUR EYE HERE" first, "then here" then
"Isn't that fascinating?"
So this is just a way that our brains work.
We're always drawn to the bigger bolder square of things.
And As designers, we can use this knowledge to define hierarchy. So let's say that you were to write a
birthday invites to Jane.
You could write it like this. But all of the information has equal weighting.
So as a reader, I have to go through the entire paragraph and I can't just skim through it to get the
important bits.
So it's gonna take me a lot longer
right? Now on the other hand if I apply the rules of hierarchy then the most important information gets
conveyed over first and I make sure that Jane actually knows whose birthday party it is, where it is
and when they should go.
So we can establish hierarchy in a number of ways.
The most obvious is through the use of color.
So colors that really pop and stand out and have contrast with that background tend to be used for high
hierarchy.
So for example in this case if all the colors were the same, then it feels like they all have equal importance.
But on the other hand, if we have something that's very bright very standoutish versus something that's
a bit more grade, a bit more muted, then we know exactly where our eyes will go to first.
Now if you take a look at this example this is the ASOS website. And their predominant color palette
is the sort of gray and white color. But they've really cleverly used their accent tone, this green and
red, to really tell the user what they think you should really look at.
And it seems like ASOS really cares that you know that they have an outlet and also that you add your
product to the bag so that they can actually make money off you.
So, in this case, they're using that green accent tone to really pull the eyes to that button and make sure
that the user actually completes their transaction. Now in addition to color, you should also think about
size because as I said, the bigger items often draw your eyes to it.
So, for example, if you look at the Coinbase website which you can use to buy cryptocurrency, we can see
the first thing they want to tell you is you can use this website to buy and sell cryptocurrency.
Now the next biggest thing on the page is this huge email input and a button that says "Get started".
So because a lot of these companies run ads and they're paying for users to land on their page, it's really
important for them to capture the emails.
This is kind of what this design is representing
right?
As long as you land on this page, you're probably going to want to look at this place where you put in
your email address and get started so that the company can capture your information.
Now in addition to establishing hierarchy in terms of user interface, you should think about the layout
of your website.
You can of course, on one hand, have this big block of text which is just your website where everything
is all laid out in the same kind of way
or you can create more interest by creating a block of text and then interspersed with pictures and
then create some different sizes and different shapes and different hierarchies to make your design
look more interesting. Now the Wikipedia pages are a example in bad design because just look at how bland
it looks.
It really is trying to be an encyclopedia but it doesn't have to be like this. Now
one of the most noticeable things about Wikipedia is just the length of each block of text.
Just look at how long each line of text is.
It's very hard for a user to keep their eyes tracking along the same line.
And in fact, in terms of user interface design, there's an optimal line length. Too long and it gets a
little bit tedious to read. But too short it feels a bit too choppy and it's a bit awkward to read.
So you want to aim for something around 40 to 60 characters per line so that it feels comfortable to
the user and they'll be able to get through the information and still be interested in your website.
Now when you have good layout like Grammarly's website, it's not only interesting but it also chops
up the content into smaller pieces so that you actually get through more of the website and you take
more of it in.
Now another thing I want to talk about is alignment.
This has to do with how you position each of the elements on the screen relative to each other.
So take a look at the example on the left. The top title is center-aligned whereas the body text is
left-aligned. And it makes it look a little bit awkward like they're not really meant to be together.
Now on the right however just by shifting the alignment so that both starting points are the same for
the title and the body, it suddenly looks a lot more consistent and a lot more designed.
Now one of the easiest ways of making any sort of design you create look professional is just to reduce
the number of alignment points.
So let's say that you're creating a slide deck for your next presentation or you're creating a poster
for your birthday party,
take a look at all the things that are on the design and identify a line which goes through the beginning
of each item.
Now if you can reduce the number of lines like we have done here on the right then suddenly the design
looks a lot more coherent like all the pieces are meant to be together.
And it just looks a lot more professional.
So use these grid lines in your designed to help you visualize where the starting points of each element
is and try to line them all up.
Because even if you do nothing else but just alignment, you can see in this case the left looks a lot
more sloppy and the right looks a lot more designed and more professional. And all that's changed, there's
no change in the color, there's no change in typography, it's just the alignment. Now a really important
concept in all design is White Space. And white space refers to the empty space that's around text or round
your elements.
Now sometimes when I'm on the high street I come across one of these luxury handbag or shoe shops and
I look through the window.
Now here's an experiment.
Take a look at this shop that sells handbags and take a look at this one.
Now how much are you willing to pay for a handbag from this shop versus this one.
Now this is really a use case for white space.
A lot of luxury shops, luxury designer stores,
one of their simplest tools is just injecting white space around their products, space things out and it
makes everything suddenly look a lot more expensive. Whereas when you have everything all tightly crammed
together and you have a lot of product on show, it makes it look like it's some sort of discount store.
And the same principle applies when it comes to digital design as well.
Let's say you have an ad for noise cancelling headphones.
If you have loads of things on screen, there's "New", "Only $20", "100% noise cancellation".
It makes the product look really cheap. Whereas if you injected some white space, all of a sudden it looks
like Apple made it right? Just by adding that space around each element on the screen
you can make your design a lot more minimalist and at the same time elevate it.
Now the last thing on User Interface design I want to talk about and probably the most important is
design for your audience.
A lot of things I've said, including not using comic-sans,
it really depends on your audience.
Let's say you're designing a children's concert poster, the one on the right looks like something that
children might actually want to go to. The one on the left looks a bit like a funeral advertisement.
It's so serious. It's so black and white and it's so severe looking that no child is kind of want to
go to that concert.
So think about your audience.
Think about what would appeal to them and what's important to convey to them. That it's going to be a
fun concert or that it's going to be boring adults who are going to be reading newspapers and some sort
of classical band in the background. When you're designing websites design it for your audience even
if it's something a little bit messier, a little bit bolder in terms of color, as long as it fits your
audience and that's perfectly fine.
So have the flexibility in your design so that you're not just creating one style all the time. You're
creating one style for a particular audience like teenagers who want to buy clothes and you're creating
a different style for people who want to buy and sell cryptocurrency or have a medical website.
So the flexibility in your design skills is really important when it comes to User Interface design.
But keep in mind those five things: hierarchy, layout, alignment, white space and your audience and you'll
be well on the way to creating more beautiful user interfaces for your websites.
Now, so far we've talked about the three pillars of web design: Color Theory, Typography, User Interface
design and now I want to talk about the last pillar, User Experience design.
Now a lot of people often get confused about what exactly is UX or User Experience?
And one of the best ways I've heard it explained is through the story of the renovation of a college.
So this is a picture of Reed College in the US and let's just use it as our imaginary backdrop.
So this college decided that it needed to undergo serious renovation. Tearing down the buildings, building
new ones and completely reform the campus.
So they invited this well-known architect who is very respected in his field.
He came and he did a great job with all the buildings and the provost was really really happy.
He was like "This looks great."
But he had one question.
"Hey Mr. Architect. It seemed like you've just left lawn across the entire campus. Where are all the path that
people are going to walk on to get between the buildings?" At this point
the architect says "Don't worry. I'll come back in a year and all will be revealed."
So in a year the paths where people need to naturally walk becomes trotted down and the grass gets worn
down revealing these paths that people need.
And it's at this point when the architect actually lays down all the tiles and paves these paths.
So this is kind of the difference between user experience and design. Design
we often think of having an aesthetic, what we think looks good and enforcing that on the user.
Now user experience is meant to be invisible.
If you have a good experience with a website it's meant to be unobtrusive and it just lets you do your
thing and it feels like as if everything is easy and everything is effortless.
So this is what we're aiming for.
And in order to do that we have to think about again five things.
The first is simplicity. Keeping things simple is always better than making it more complex or more cluttered.
So this is a website called Sina and it's one of the biggest News websites in China.
Now every time I look at it though I get a headache because it is just so dense.
There are so many links and my brain gets overwhelmed and I say "Nope, can't do it."
So take a look at this alternative.
This is Monocle, which is also a News website.
But look at how they've managed to chop up the content, provides some interest for the eyes.
There's a little bit of dialogue, some images, some videos, a little bit of text.
It's never overwhelming.
And with that consistent color scheme and typography, it's really delightful to actually read rather
than this experience of sort of hurting your eyes with design.
This is a much nicer user experience because it's simple.
So whenever you're having to choose, should I make it more complex or should I make it more simple,
always try to pare it down.
The second point is consistency.
Keep your designs consistent but also keep the functionality of your product consistent.
So here's an example.
This is the webpage for Xfinity. Xfinity is a really big communications company in the US and they
are responsible for various things like providing TV and providing internet.
Here are three screenshots from various parts of their website.
One is their home page,
the second is their TV offerings and the last one is their News site.
And if you take a look at the top navigation bar not only do you see that they've changed up the design
of the navigation bar between the different parts of their website,
they also made it work a little bit differently.
The buttons are not all in the same place, the search bar moves around.
And that inconsistency means that a user is going to be confused when they go from one part of the website
to another, having to re-learn how to use your website.
If you think about the target audience of this company Xfinity, a lot of them are going to be a little
bit older right?
And having this inconsistent functionality and inconsistent design will really make those users have
a bad experience with this website.
Now the next thing to think about when you're designing your website is to take into account people's
reading patterns.
Now they've looked at how human eyes track a webpage and which parts they look at when they're browsing.
And one of the most common reading patterns is what's called the F-pattern where the eye starts at the
top left of the corner and then it tracks the right and then it flips back again
browsing down the left gutter.
So you have often things like bullet points or pictures or icons, buttons, they're all on the left.
So you can design for this by using the F-layout.
So have the most important parts of your content on the left gutter, have the logo at the top and have
everything follow this pattern.
For example like this website for Bigcommerce.
See how the eye is being naturally accommodated going from left to right.
Now another really common pattern for reading is the Z-pattern where our eyes go from left to right and then
zigzagging down all the way the website.
Now this of course depends on the type of website.
So you have something that's more sparse with more video content or if somebody is trying to browse
a website a little bit faster,
you see them using this layout. And this layout is used pretty famously in the Facebook website
using that Z-pattern to accommodate for people's natural reading pattern.
So have a think about this. Have a think about how people naturally looks at the page and place your
content in that pattern to make it easier for people who are using your website.
Now in today's day and age, it's really important to think about All Platform Design.
It's not enough anymore to just design a website that's meant to go into a desktop computer.
Instead you have to think about mobile as well.
So having a website that scales up nicely onto mobile, what we call mobile responsive, is really important.
You don't want a big website that's designed to take up a landscape kind of screen to be crammed into
a phone
that's actually more like a portrait shape.
This looks really bad.
It's very hard to read the individual links and, more often than not, my fingers are actually too big to tap
onto the length that I want.
So this is a really bad user experience.
Now this can happen the opposite way as well.
So a design that looks much better on mobile but then when it's rendered on a desktop with a wide kind
of screen, it doesn't use up enough of the screen real estate. For example,
this is the Facebook latest redesign of their website.
And you've got all of this empty space that's not being used at all and everything is crammed into the
middle.
This is not very efficient. So have a think about how you're using the available space and make sure
that your website rearranges itself when it's being rendered on a portrait smaller screen vs. a larger
desktop screen. And try to avoid one of my pet peeves in terms of design which is having so many banners
on your website that show up on the mobile version that your content becomes impossibly small.
And even when you're scrolling it's like you're scrolling it on an Apple Watch or something.
Whereas all of this extra content is taken up by warnings and banners and cookies and it's just not
a very good user experience.
But on the other hand, don't go crazy either.
Don't make your entire website just one part like a picture or a piece of text scaling it up massively
like this is also very very awkward because then I have to just keep scrolling until forever before
I can actually read and take in all of the content.
So strike a happy medium.
And most importantly test, test, test.
Give it to other users.
You can employ professional testers to try out your website and give you feedback.
Now if you can't afford that, just use your family and friends. And bake some cookies for them,
get them to test out your website and start getting some feedback on how you can improve the design.
Now finally we've talked a lot about user experience and how to get people to have a good time.
Now some designers though use the knowledge they have about human psychology and User Interface and
User Experience design to do bad things.
And in the design world, we call these dark patterns. So patterns which get a user to perform an action
or behavior that is beneficial to the company or the designer
but it's not necessarily what the user wants.
And this I would say is another form of bad user experience.
So let me give you some examples.
This is a real life example. Let's say that you walked into Waitrose which is a big supermarket in the
UK and you bought yourself a sandwich.
Now when you look at it at the point when you're buying it, it looks like this sandwich is going to be
full length from edge to edge
right?
But then when you rip open the packaging you're disappointed when you find that actually all that's
in the middle is just air and your sandwich turns out to be a lot smaller than you initially thought.
It is the worst feeling in the world.
This is a feeling that I can't stand when my food suddenly gets reduced in size.
It's like as if somebody came along and took food out of your plate. In the digital world,
people do the same thing. The same kind of trickery that's meant to get you to perform an action that
you don't necessarily want and you end up feeling really disappointed and really upset. With Amazon every
single time
I have to re-click the free delivery button which I've earned by buying so much product from them.
But they still try to trick you using the things that we've learned about hierarchy
for example. Here the button that makes the more money "Express delivery" is highlighted in orange.
It pops out a lot more.
It's a lot more likely that you'll want to click on it.
But in all likelihood, you're probably happy with just normal delivery and you're now tricked into paying
more for this delivery.
Now here's another example
that's actually true the evil.
This is a Snapchat ad for some shoes.
But what the designer has cleverly done on the advertising is they've placed a one pixel curved line
on this ad which makes it kind of look a bit like a hair is on your screen. But when you go into that
screen and you try to get rid of that piece of hair, well you've tapped on an avenue.
So the ad takes you to the website and the advertisers make money off each click.
And this is truly a dog pattern because it's just tricking you to do something you didn't want to.
Whereas good design is about helping people do what they want to do and giving them a good experience
while they're at it.
Now the king of dog patterns is RyanAir and it's a low cost airline in Europe which is really known for
sort of charging you for every single little thing.
I wouldn't be surprised if tomorrow they suddenly charged you for using the toilet on the plane.
But here's what the website looks like when you tried to buy an airplane ticket. In order to buy your
airplane ticket you have to go through all of these extra add ons including saying "No I don't want to
buy travel insurance." But look at how they've hidden it inside this big dropdown list and it's not even
at the beginning of the list.
It's actually sorted alphabetically below Denmark for some reason.
And this just makes it so much harder for you to find that option
and for you to actually accidentally end up buying travel insurance.
Now the final example and probably one of the dog patterns I dislike the most is these checkboxes. You
know right below you filled in a form,
you get these checkboxes and sometimes the wording is so confusing that I really don't know what I'm
signing up for.
Like this one: If you would like us to no longer continue to stop not sending you special deals and offers
every week, please indicate you are inclined to yes
by not checking the box. I have no idea what clicking that box does.
I really just... I don't know.
I might click it, I might not.
I don't know what it does. But it's horribly confusing and it's not a good user experience at all.
I will bet you that after I sign up I'm never going to come back to this website again
right?
Are you with me? Now
we've seen what good websites look like.
We've seen what bad websites look like.
We've even seen what evil websites look like.
But it's time to put our knowledge to the test by designing our own website from scratch and applying
these four pillars of web design to this project.
So have a think about what you've learned so far and head over to the next lesson where we're going
to design a hotel website from scratch.
Now that we've learned about some of the principles of web design such as Color Theory, Typography, User
Interface design and User Experience design, the four pillars, it's time to apply what we've learned and
build a design together.
Now there's a website called Daily UI which gives you a task to design every day for 100 days.
It's free to sign up and it's something that really does improve designing skills by just that repeated
practice.
Now if you take a look at a website called Collect UI you can see they've collected together all the
designers attempts at designing each of these daily challenges and you can see examples what each of
these challenges are.
For example, anything from creating a sign up screen to a flight website to a hotel booking website.
So we're going to take some of these ideas as inspiration and create our own website design
applying the four pillars that we've learned in this module. The first thing I want you to do is head
over to a website called canva.com.
Now this is a online graphics editing program and you don't have to download anything and it's completely
free to sign up.
So sign up for a new account and then go ahead and create a new design.
So we're going to pick custom dimensions and I'm going to choose 1400 pixels by 800 pixels high.
Once we're inside our design we're going to take this as the first screen that the user sees in our
website.
And then when they scroll down they'll see the next page and then they scroll down and see the final
part of our website.
So let's design the first title screen.
Now I'm going to choose this free template which gives me a backdrop already but I'm actually just going
to use it for some texture. I quite like the way that this pattern looks.
So I'm going to apply the pattern and then I'm going to change the background.
Now I think the background looks a little bit bland with just a single color.
So I'm going to choose a photo instead and I'm going to search for a beach, like this one.
So now that I've got my image I'm going to drag it out so that it's sized as large as it needs to be.
So going all the way to each of the edges. And then I'm going to reposition it so that it fills up the
entire screen. Like this.
So now I have a background image, some sort of texture on it
and I can go to the elements to keep adding to this design.
Let's take a look at some of the gradients here.
And I'm going to pick something that'll fit in with this theme.
Now, of course, how you design this is completely up to you.
And I'm just providing an example of how I go through this process of designing.
So now I've got a circle here.
I'm going to add some more shapes maybe a square of some sort. We can click on see all to see all the
other ones.
And then I'm going to put a square which I'm going to make it so that it goes right to the end of each
of the sites.
So here and then we're going to make it line up with the center of the circle roughly like this.
And let's just change that color to white.
Now we have this nice white border, some abstract shapes and patterns and an image.
Now I'm going to add a heading text. This heading text is going to be the name of our hotel.
After all we're designing a website for this unknown Hotel which I'll call "A Hotel".
A really easy way of making something look authoritative and like it's been around forever is by changing
the typeface to a Serif typeface.
So I'm going to highlight this font and I'm going to click the dropdown and find a serif typeface like
this one cardo.
And notice how instantly our hotel looks a lot more established like it's been around for longer.
Now I'm going to change the color of this also to white.
So notice how we're starting to establish a color palette of greens and turquoise and blue and white.
And we're going to increase the font size to maybe something really large like 120 or 144. And
I'm going to change this so that it's all caps like so.
So that's actually a little bit too big
so let's drop it down a notch. And I can increase the spacing of the letters to again make it look more
fancy, more expensive and more authoritative.
Here's the name of our hotel, A Hotel,  centered in this box.
And now I'm ready to add a subheading and my subheading is going to be some sort of tagline
right?
And I'm going to go with something really obnoxious like "Lose Yourself to find yourself".
I feel like I'm ready to open a hotel tomorrow.
Let's Now contrast this serif typeface for the title with a San-Serif sort of body or subtitle.
And this is what we learned about in the typography section.
It creates contrast in the design.
So I'm going to pick this Glacial indifference typeface and I'm again going to choose white and then
make both these lines left-aligned so that I can align them to the same position.
And that is how when you drag elements around on canvas it automatically gives you these alignment grids
so that you can more easily position it so that they are actually all aligned together.
And notice how big a difference that looks
just having it off alignment and then on alignment. It's suddenly just looks a lot more proper
right? Now I'm more or less done with my title page.
I'm going to move on to the next one which is going to be a page for selling the features of the hotel.
Let's start off by adding some images. And I've got some that I've already found before.
I've got a picture of a bedroom which I'm going to make it a little bit smaller like so and then I've
got a picture of a breakfast of some sort.
So you've got food at this hotel.
You're not going to starve.
That's pretty important for people to know.
And I'm going to size it so that it's actually the same size as the other one.
So I'm just going to put it on top.
Now the last one is going to be a pool.
So you've also got a pool.
You don't get bored if it gets too hot.
You can always just go into the pool.
This is turning out to be a great hotel
by the way, I really want to stay here.
Now the goal of our features page is to have three images which are probably going to be about the same
size.
So I'm actually going to need to crop this last photo so that I get rid of maybe a little bit of this
right edge but have it just about the same size as my other photos.
And now I need to resize each of these photos so that it actually can fit onto this page.
So I'm just going to throw them one on top of the other and resize them
so they're all the same size.
And now I can place them around this web page.
So when you move towards the edge of each page you can see this grid show up.
So I'm going to line up the left with the left side of the grid the right with the right side of the
grid and the middle right in the middle.
So now these three are evenly spaced apart and I can now add some more design features to it because
it's looking a little bit bland just as photos.
Now one of the easiest things to make photos look nice is to just jazz it up with a frame.
Now because all hotel is very modern, it's contemporary,
it's been featured in Vogue,
I want to make sure that the framing also looks equally contemporary.
So I'm going to find a circle and I'm going to put this circle around this square image which is going
to make it look quite nice and contemporary. And then I'm going to give it a background color like that.
And we've now framed our picture.
So now, all I have to do is just copy it and put it onto all the other images like so.
And now I've got three features.
You've got a bed, you've got food, you've got pool.
What more do you want? The next part is probably going to be some sort of explainer
right?
So add a subheading of these sections and the subheading is going to be something like you get beautiful
food, you have beautiful rooms and you have a beautiful pool.
So three things that we've got. And I'm going to left-align
each of these again so that I can make it aligned with the left edge of each of the pictures like this.
So all three of these pieces of text are on the same horizontal level and they're also vertically aligned
with the start of each image.
Now each of these will need to be designed so that they have the same typeface as what we had in the
title page so that it's consistent
right?
We're reflecting the same thing that we saw before.
So I'm gonna change that again to Glacial indifference and do the same for all three bits of text.
And now we can afford to increase the spacing in the text a little bit to make it look a little bit
more roomy. So I think I had 18
on the other one so I'm going to put 18 here as well and 18 here as well.
There we go.
So we've got all three bits of text and now all we need is just a little bit of body text. For the bod
text
I'm going to use a Lorem Ipsum. So I'm going to use one of these generators and just get some text generated
and I'm going to copy a little bit of it and put it into my design. Replace that text with this
and that's a little bit too much.
So let's make it a bit smaller. And we're going to have some text which is going to go just below this
section.
So it's still a little bit too much.
Let's get rid of the last sentence. That looks pretty good.
Now again we want to keep our design consistent.
So we're going to make sure it's again left aligned using the same font as before.
And we've now got a bit of body text which I'm going to further style by changing the color of each
of these.
So I want to go for maybe like a dark-grayish like one of these and the same for the body text.
That way it doesn't sort of stand out so much.
And I'm going to copy this
so that I put it on all of the other features.
Notice the alignment here.
I've got all the pictures aligned with each other,
all of these circles center-aligned with each picture,
I've got all the text lined along the left and this just makes the design look a lot tighter
and a lot more consistent.
And notice how with the layout I've tried to keep it interesting by having some pictures that break
up the text and making sure that each body of text is not overwhelming. It's not too long
like a big long sentence.
But instead it's short enough to be easily read quickly.
Now, the other thing you'll notice is that there's a degree of hierarchy that's being established here
right?
Clearly the thing that I really want people to know is that my hotel is called A Hotel.
But in addition, I've also got beautiful food being more important than the body text
that explains that paragraph.
And each of these images also being more important because, let's face it, most people look at the pictures
and don't read anything right?
So that's our second part of the website
done.
And we're now onto the last part which is going to be the contact page.
So this contact page I'm again going to search for maybe a photo of something that's quite fashionable,
contemporary, tropical.
Maybe we can just find a picture of a pineapple.
And this one looks pretty good.
Let's go ahead and position this photo so that it's the same size as the design.
And now I can move it up so that only the bottom shows up my pineapples.
So there we go.
We've got 1, 2 and 3 and the last part is just a contact me page. The contact me page is also
going to need some titled text.
Let's just call that Stay.
So when they want to stay they can take a look at this section. And we're going to again copy this style
that we had from before so that we can actually replicate it down here
and we keep our design again consistent.
It has the same theme, the same color palette, the same typography.
This is a little bit too big though. So let's make it a bit smaller so it fits onto this page.
And again I'm going to be consistent with our geometric shapes which is lending that sort of modern
feel. I've got a sort of rectangle, a circle, more circles.
So let's pick another shape from here. Maybe some sort of a hexagon. That looks pretty good.
Let's add the hexagon,
make it a bit smaller, we can maybe move our pineapples down a bit and change this so that it's white
and make it even a bit smaller.
I think something like that would do quite well.
So now the final thing I want to add is some sort of mailing address, email address, phone number, which
is going to go in here and it's going to be nicely aligned with this word stay.
So let's go ahead and take this word and make it right aligned so that this line pops up when I try
to align it like so and let's just make sure that it actually still fits in.
So maybe we have to move this text up a little bit, reduce the spacing a little.
I think a lot of times you do have to play around with your design just so that it starts looking good
to you.
You might have to shift things a little bit and be flexible with those rules that we've talked about.
So now all we need to make sure is that the word is right-aligned and our text is also right-aligned
so that we can actually line them up together so that they actually look like they're on the same vertical
alignment.
Now, if we can just mess around with the size of the hexagon and make sure that everything is still within
the hexagon and we've pretty much finished our design now. What did that take? Maybe 20 minutes. And
we managed to apply a lot of things that we've learned from User Interface design or User Experience
design, Color Theory and Typography to create this 3-page very modern looking website for A Hotel.
So at this point, there's a really cool feature in Canva which lets you just publish the website.
So if you click on this publish button and you scroll all the way down and you click on website then
you can actually select the Web style as standard and then open this as an actual web page.
Notice how it's placed my three pages together into an actual web page
and I can scroll down and also navigate to it through the navigation bar.
Now of course we don't have mobile optimization,
we don't have any code that has any functionality, we can't add javascript to it. But at least we can quickly
throw up a design, visualize it and share it with other people to see what they think.
And this is probably one of the best ways of building up your design muscle.
Just practicing again and again until you get to a point where pretty much unanimously everybody thinks
that your design looks great and people start asking you to actually build websites for them.
So study a lot of the websites that you come across,
the ones that you think look really good. And think about what makes them good and then try to take some
of those aspects along with everything you've learned in these lessons to create designs that humans
love.
So I hope you'll take a moment now to pause the video and have a go at creating your own hotel website.
So use the same tools that you saw me use on Canva and try to design a slightly different type of hotel.
What if it had to be a more traditional hotel that was around the time of Henry the 8th or something? It's
like some really old hotel and they want to show how decadent they are, how glamorous they are, and trying
to design a different type of website.
So pause the video, give that a go and then try to apply everything you've learned in this module into
that design.
And once you've created your design share this link that you can see at the top of Canva so that we
can all see your design and we can comment on how beautiful it looks.
So have a go at doing that and make sure that you let us know what it looks like in the comments below
and have fun doing it. Now I hope you really enjoyed this module on web design.
It's a little bit different from what you've been used to so far.
There's no coding in this module but instead we tried to get you to think about all of the design principles
that actually ends up creating beautiful websites, websites that people will love. And hopefully
you'll take these pillars and this knowledge through the next time you build your product or you build
your website and you'll apply it alongside with your code so that you have beautiful features and beautiful
interface.
Now once you've created your own designs and you've shared it with us then it's time to get back to
the coding and
we're going to continue tackling more web development. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you there.
All right, guys.
So in this module, we're going to learn all about how to build your very own RESTful API.
Now, in previous modules, we've seen and used APIs that other people have created, and we've also
started to build up our server to allow get requests and post requests.
But in this module, we're going to do it from beginning to end and we're going to build our very own
complete RESTful API.
Now, the first question you might have is what exactly does REST mean and what does it mean to make
an API RESTful,
right?
Well, REST is not lazing on the couch and watching Netflix, but it actually stands for REpresentational
State Transfer, which is quite a mouthful.
But in order to understand it, we have to backtrace a little bit and we have to go back to that classic
architecture that we already looked at, which is the client and server architecture.
And this is the architecture that the entire Internet is pretty much built on.
So let's just review it quickly. So the client makes a request to the server.
So what exactly is the client?
Well, if we were in a restaurant, the client would be, well, the client who's paying for the meal,
right?
And the server would be the server staff at the restaurant.
So when our client makes a request, say, I'd like a pizza please, then the server has to check
to see if this is something that the restaurant can fulfill.
And if so, he will smile graciously at you and fulfill that request.
But if the client requested something that they didn't have, for example, a sausage, and it's not on
the menu, then the server would give you a error code, a classic one, of course, being 404, which
is resource doesn't exist.
We don't stock sausages. Now when the client makes that request to the server classically on the Internet,
this is done through a HTTP request, hypertext transfer protocol request.
And the analogy for this is it's kind of like the language that you're using to make the request, say
you're saying I want a pizza,
right?
And if you're in France, you would have to say that in French, although I'm not sure what you're doing
eating pizzas in France. But the server would be able to understand your request and give you back
the correct result.
Now, the thing you have to remember is that HTTP, this hypertext transfer protocol, is not the only
language that servers can speak,
right?
Another one that you might have heard of is, for example, the FTP request, which is the file transfer
protocol request.
So if you use the wrong language, you might not get back the result that you're looking for.
So, for example, if a server speaks French in France and you try to speak to him in Italian, that
probably won't work.
So we have to make sure we've got the right language for making our request.
Now, at this point, some students might say, well, what about that other thing that HTTPs
request?
What does that
s stand for,
and is it a different language?
Well, HTTPs stands for HTTP secure request.
So remember that all your requests and responses are going across the Internet and can be potentially
tapped in by lots of people.
So if you wanted to make it secure so you don't want to be on a website entering your card details and
it's just going through, you know, a bog-standard HTTP request because somebody might hijack that
along the way and that's not very secure.
So we can also use cryptography and encrypt our request
so if anybody does intercept the request, they won't be able to know what it says.
Now, this is kind of equivalent to having like a secret code language.
For example, if both you and your waiter speak Klingon, then you could communicate securely
and it doesn't matter if you're overheard in the restaurant because nobody else will be able to understand
what you're saying other than yourself and your waiter.
Now, let's say that the client has successfully made the request to the server and this is something
that the server can serve up,
so it sees it as a valid request instead of a 404,
then in this case the server should respond with the results of what it is that you requested.
So in the restaurant, that might be your pizza. But on the Internet, that might be the web page HTML
or resources such as images or data.
Now, in order to give us that result, the server might do one of two things.
It might do some computation, run some code to work out the result that you need
for example, if our server was a simple calculator web application, or the server might need to communicate
with our database in order to grab
the relevant pieces of data that the client requested. So depending on what kind of request that the
client made, what kind of resource they wanted, the server might do one or both of these things.
So we've seen that the client has to talk to the server using an HTTP request, a specific language that
the server can understand.
But also, there's only a certain amount of things that the server can do, right?
Say at a restaurant, you would have a menu of items that this particular restaurant would serve.
And it's exactly the same on the Internet.
The server will have a whole bunch of APIs which are services that it can expose for clients to be able
to tap into.
And so when we're building an API
we're kind of like building the menu of things that our server can respond to when a client makes a
request.
So now that we understand all three components, what does it mean to make our API RESTful?
Well, REST is essentially just an architectural style.
So just as you have different buildings that have different architectural styles, for example, the
Baroque architectural style with the nice arches or other buildings might be built in the Gothic architectural
style with flying buttresses and these imposing beams.
And my favorite, the Neoclassical, have these incredibly geometric shapes and columns that really
remind you of old Greek architecture.
So these are architectural styles for designing buildings.
Well, REST is an architectural style for designing APIs, and it's definitely not the only architectural
style.
So the other really, really popular one before REST became the dominant style was SOAP.
And there's also GraphQL or FALCOR and there's a lot of other architectural styles.
But the gold standard for Web APIs is REST.
So that's what we're going to be looking at.
And REST actually came about really quite recently as a part of this guy's Ph.D.
This is Roy Fielding and he did his PhD in the University of California.
And as a part of his doctorate, he researched and came up with this architectural style that we now
call REST.
And it proposes a set of rules that web developers could follow when they're building their APIs.
And he came up with this idea that all websites across the web would use the same structure for building
their APIs.
I mean, imagine if you had a whole street and all their buildings had the same layout.
For example, the toilets for men and women are always on the same floors, in the same position,
then you would never get into a situation where you're trying to find the toilet.
So my personal struggles aside, essentially in his Ph.D. he proposed that the Internet could do the
same.
If every Web API was built using the same common guiding principles, then it would be so easy for everybody
to work together and be able to use different APIs quickly, easily, and efficiently.
So pretty neat for a PhD project, right?
There's definitely some PhD projects
that are a lot worse like the guy who had to look into the propulsion parameters of penguin poop.
But maybe if you really like penguins, that's OK.
So how exactly do we make our API RESTful?
Well, there's a lot of rules that an API has to follow to be RESTful.
And just as you have rules that you might follow at your workplace or your school, you might have a
uniform, no shorts, no singlets, don't smoke in the building,
you also have a whole bunch of rules for making an API RESTful.
But the two most important ones are using the HTTP request verbs,
so using that HTTP request language, and also to use a specific pattern of routes and endpoint URLs.
And these two things are probably the most important parts of making your API restful.
And we're going to look at each of them in detail.
So first, what exactly are the HTTP verbs?
Well, you've already seen some of them.
First is GET, then is POST, PUT, and PATCH. PATCH came relatively recently in 2010 and it was added
to the HTTP request language essentially very recently.
But it's kind of a neat twist on how we update data
and we're going to look at that in a little bit as well.
And finally, you've got DELETE.
So these are the five HTTP verbs that you should be using in order to make your API RESTful.
And you
might realize that they have a lot of similarities to something that we covered previously in the database
module, which is when we looked into CRUD, right?
Create, read, update and delete.
So we're going to look at our REST HTTP request verbs alongside our database CRUD functions and we're
going to see how each of these verbs work in practice.
So now that we've looked at the HTTP request verbs and we can see how they're used, the next thing
to talk about is the specific pattern of routes and endpoints that you have to use in order to make
your API RESTful.
So just as when you go on a safari, there are different routes that you would use to reach say
the elephant area or the camels or the hippos, in our server
we can specify specific routes or URL's in order to access certain resources.
So you might have, you know, www.google.com/elephants, then that would bring up all
of the elephants and /camels would be for the camels and hippos.
So these are routes and we've already used routes before in our server code.
But in order for our API to be RESTful, we have to have a specific pattern of endpoints and routes.
So, for example, if our API was the Wikipedia API, right?
And in our database, we had a whole bunch of articles.
Now the route for /articles applies to all of the articles.
Now, if we created a route for articles, then when a client makes a get request to /articles,
it should fetch all of the articles.
And when they make a post request to the /articles route, then it should create a single
new article
and add it to our database of articles. And when we make a delete request to /articles, then it
would delete all the articles in our database.
But RESTful routing also has rules for individual resources.
So within all of the articles, we will have specific articles,
right?
Say we had an article on Jack Bauer,
then if the client was targeting /articles/Jack-Bauer, then if they made a get request,
that would fetch the specific article on Jack Bauer from our database.
And you can also use put and patch to update that specific article on Jack Bauer
and you can delete the specific article as well.
Now, a little bit later on, when we create all of these routes using the HTTP verbs, it's going to
be a lot more clear how each of these work.
But for now, I just want you to get an overview of what RESTful routing actually looks like before
we get started.
So now that we've seen how HTTP request verbs work and the pattern of routes that make your API RESTful,
the next step is to get started and actually build our very own API.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
So what is the difference between put and patch?
Well, here's a good analogy.
Recently I went onto Amazon and I found a really nice looking bicycle.
And because I really wanted to poison my lungs by exercising around London, I clicked on the Buy Now
button.
So there I was, super happy, super excited for my bicycle to arrive.
And then on the day of arrival, I opened up that box and my bicycle was really messed up.
The whole front wheel was broken.
So I'm not really sure what happened at the Amazon warehouse, but I got in touch with them and I wanted
to try and figure out how we can solve this problem.
So there were two ways that they could fix this problem.
Option one was they send me an entire new bike.
So this is the equivalent of put. You're updating your database by sending an entire entry to replace
the previous one.
Now, the other option Amazon offered was for them to simply send me a new tire.
That was the only thing that was broken,
the rest of the bike was fine.
And in order to save the world from carbon emissions, shipping a wheel is much better than shipping
an entire bicycle.
And this is the same as Patch.
So when you're sending a patch request to the server, you're only sending the piece of data that needs
to be updated. Instead of the entire entry that will be replaced,
you're simply just updating the thing that needs to be updated.
So when we see this in practice, I want you to think back to this bicycle analogy and maybe it'll help you try
and understand the difference between these two words.
All right, guys, welcome to a brand new module.
And in this module, we're going to tackle the topic of authentication.
And it's something that is often thought of as incredibly complicated, but it doesn't have to be.
And we're going to take it step by step from beginning to end so that you get an overview of the entire
process of setting up authentication from scratch.
So why do we need to authenticate?
Well, as we're creating our website or web app for users to use, then these users are going to start
generating data in the website.
They might like certain posts,
they might interact with other users,
there might be messages created or recipes created.
There's always going to be some user data created.
And in order to associate those pieces of data with individual users, we need to create an account
for each user. So that they would sign up to our website using a username and a password
and we would essentially create kind of like an ID card for them to uniquely identify them on our database
and to save all of the data that they generate onto that account.
So the next time that they come back onto the website, they'll be able to use their username and password
and log in to our website and be able to access all of those possibly private pieces of information.
So this way, you don't end up with everybody being able to see, you know, what private messages you're
sending around on Facebook or see your direct messages on Twitter.
So that's pretty simple.
Now, the other reason why you might want to add authentication to your website is to restrict access
to certain areas of the website depending on the status of the user.
So, for example, if you were Spotify or Netflix and you charge a subscription for accessing certain
parts of the website, then once the user pays, you have to update their account in your database to
say that they have paid and they'll be allowed to access the TV shows or songs that they're entitled
to.
So those are some of the reasons why you might want to add authentication to your website.
But authentication can be done in a number of ways.
Creating a website where we sign up and log in users seems simple enough, but the difficult part of
authentication comes from how secure you're going to make your website.
But so we're going to learn how to progress from essentially a website that's basically secured with
a Cheeto to something that is a lot more serious and more consistent with industry standards of good
security on a website.
So the structure of our website is really, really simple.
It has a homepage which has two buttons that allows you to either go towards register or go towards
login.
And once the user has been registered or logged in and they have been authenticated, then they are
able to access the secrets page.
So I've kept the remainder of the website pretty simple because we're going to be focusing on a pretty
complex topic.
So I've created some starting files for you to download so that we can focus our efforts on learning
authentication and not get distracted by things like bootstrap and styling.
So once you're ready, head over to the next lesson and download the starting files, and then we're going
to get started with authentication.
So I'll see you there.
All right, so we've taken a look at level one encryption, which is basically just storing the password
as plain text in our database.
So maybe it'll be a little bit difficult for people to get access to our server and access our database.
At least you can't just simply
right-
click on a website to view page source and be able to see it in the HTML.
At least it's stored at server level. But that's not really good enough.
So let's go ahead and see what we can do to improve the security for our users on our website.
So let's increase to level two authentication. And level two authentication involves the use of encryption.
So what exactly is encryption?
Well, basically all it is is just scrambling something so that people can't tell what the original
was unless they were in on the secret and they knew how to unscramble it.
This is exactly the same as if you and your friend were sending each other secret messages and you had
a key to encode the message that you both knew that so that you could decode the message.
Now, on a bigger scale, if you've ever watched The Imitation Game or read about the Enigma machine,
well, that is basically a form of encryption.
And the Enigma machine, if you don't know, is just simply a machine that was used during World War
2 when the Germans would send each other messages,
they would use the machine to encrypt those messages so that when the messages are intercepted, say,
over the radio, unless you had the same Enigma machine and you knew what the decoding key was or what
the settings were for the machine, then you wouldn't be able to tell what it is that they were trying
to communicate with each other.
If you're interested, I really recommend watching two videos that were done by Numberphile on YouTube and
I've linked to it in the course resources list.
But it explains the Enigma machine and it talks about the flaw in the Enigma machine that led Alan Turing
and other people at Bletchley Park to be able to crack the code and create what was very much a specialized
computer to be able to decode those messages and helped the allies win the war.
And if you ever visit London, be sure to go and check out Bletchley Park and they have a computer museum
next to it as well, which is super fascinating.
Anyways, I digress.
So back to
ciphers and encryption, one of the earliest ways of encrypting messages that we know about is the Caesar
cipher.
And this comes from Julius Caesar, who was one of the generals in the Roman Empire.
And what he did is he would send messages to his generals and he would encrypt it
so if his messenger got murdered along the way, then his messages would be kept secret.
And this is one of the simplest forms of encryption we know about
and it's very simple.
Let's say we have the alphabet, right? ABCDEFG. All that the Caesar Cipher does
is a letter substitution cipher.
And the key for the cipher is the number of letters that you would shift by.
So if you knew what the shift pattern was, then you could really quickly decipher the message.
So if we were to encrypt the word hello, there's a really neat tool online that can help us do that.
It's called cryptii.com and it's got two 'i's at the end.
And you can basically choose the kind of cipher or encryption that you want to use
and then you can specify the shift and we're going to say a shift of three, let's say.
So if my text was hello, then it becomes shifted into khoor. And to an unknowing person and a non-cryptographer,
it can be quite difficult to see at a glance what exactly this is trying to say. Now in modern days and
with modern cryptography, this is overly simplistic and it's very, very easy to crack.
But there are other forms of encryption which are a little bit more complicated and it involves a lot
more math to make it more time consuming for somebody to crack.
But essentially all encryption works exactly the same way.
You have a way of scrambling your message and it requires a key to be able to unscramble that message.
All right.
So now it's time to level up to the next level of security.
And in this lesson, we're going to cover something called hashing.
Now, previously, we've already looked at encryption, so taking the user's password and securing it
using an encryption key, and then
using a particular cipher method, be it a Caesar cipher or the Enigma cipher, no matter which way
we chose, we always had a password, a key, and we ended up with some ciphertext which will make it
hard for people to be able to immediately guess what our user's password is.
So, for example, if we took a password like qwerty and we use the Caesar cipher method and we decided to
shift it by one, then our encryption key is the number one.
And that creates the ciphertext where every single letter is shifted up by one.
Now, in order to decrypt this, all you have to do, as long as you know what the key is, then you
can simply shift all of the ciphertext down by one and you end up with the original password.
Now, the Caesar cipher is a very, very weak encryption method.
It's incredibly easy to figure out what the original text was, even if you didn't have a key.
And just to illustrate what bad things can happen when you have a weak encryption system, I'm going
to tell you a story from history that tells us why we should not be using a weak encryption system.
So back in the 1500's on this island that we now call the United Kingdom, there used to be two large
areas.
One was Scotland and the other was England.
And they were ruled over by two Queens.
Scotland was ruled by Mary Queen of Scots, who was a Catholic, and England was ruled over by Queen
Elizabeth the first.
Now, these two ladies between them controlled the land that we now call the UK, but they each wanted
to have more power and more land.
So what did they do?
Well, Mary Queen of Scots who ruled over Scotland decided to plot with her friend, Lord Babington,
to try and assassinate Queen Elizabeth.
That way, she would be the legitimate heir to both the English and Scottish throne,
and it was kind of a Game of Thrones kind of situation going on back then.
But in order to mobilize their forces or try to come up with some sort of secret plan, they decided
to send letters to each other using ciphertext.
So they came up with a system to encrypt their letters to each other such that if it fell into the wrong
hands, the subject of the letter wouldn't be revealed and they wouldn't end up being tried for treason.
But the problem was that the encryption method that they used, which was a letter substitution method
similar to the Caesar cipher, was a very weak form of encryption.
And Queen Elizabeth had a chief decoder who ended up deciphering their letters and figuring out what
their encryption key was.
So he decided to take this encryption key and write a letter back to Lord Babington to try and get him
to reveal all of the co-conspirators.
And what was the end result of having their weak encryption system?
Well, Queen Elizabeth decided to accuse Mary Queen of Scots of treason, and hence she ended up having
her head chopped off.
So this is not what you want to happen to you or your website.
So weak encryption systems can end up putting user passwords at risk and your company might end up metaphorically
decapitated, such as in the case of companies like TalkTalk or Equifax, where they ended up getting
hacked and lost a lot of the trust of their users.
Now, if you're interested in more stories like this and to learn more about cryptography and encryption,
there's a really great book recommendation I would make called The Code Book by Simon Singh.
It contains stories like the one that I just told you and more.
So if you're interested in this, go ahead and read more about it.
Now, how can we make our password more secure Now,
at the moment, the biggest flaw in our authentication method is the fact that we need an encryption
key to encrypt our passwords and decrypt our passwords.
And chances are that if somebody is motivated enough to spend time and hack into your database, then
it's probably not that difficult for them to also be able to get your encryption key, even if you've
saved it in environment variable or somewhere secure on your server.
So how can we address this weakest link, the need for that encryption key?
Well, here is where hashing comes into play. Whereas previously with encryption we needed that encryption
key, hashing takes it away and no longer requires the need for an encryption key.
Well, then you might ask, well, if we don't have an encryption key, how can we decrypt our password
back into
plain text? Well, the secret is you don't. Let's say a user registers on our website and they enter
a password to register with, we use something called a hash function to turn that password into a hash
and we store that hash in our database.
Now, the problem is that hash functions are mathematical equations that are designed to make it almost
impossible to go backwards.
So it's almost impossible to turn a hash back into a password.
How is this possible, you might ask?
How is it possible that you can turn a password into a hash very quickly and easily, but make it almost
impossible to turn that hash back into a password?
Well, here's a question.
Let me ask you, what are the factors of 377 other than one and 377?
So basically, I'm saying 377 is not a prime number.
Not only can you divide 377 by 1 and 377, but there's also two other numbers that you
can divide it by.
Now it's your job to figure out what those numbers are.
So, what might you do?
Well, you might divide it by two.
OK, so that becomes 188.5.
That's not a whole number
so 2 is not a factor.
What if you divide it by three?
Well, that becomes 113.3 recurring, which is also not a whole number.
So three is not a factor either.
And you might go through this process for a long time, tediously going through number by number.
Well, then you might arrive at the point where you divide 377 by 13 and you end up with
29.
So 13 and 29 are the answers to this question. They are the only factors of 377 other than 1 and
377.
And as you can see, that process of getting to this point of finding those two factors took us a while,
right?
It wasn't that easy.
But consider if I asked you a different question.
If I said to you, can you multiply 13 by 29?
Well, you would be able to do that really quickly and easily.
It would take you almost no time at all to figure out that the answer is 377.
So here is a very, very simplified version of a hash function.
So going forward, multiplying 13 by 29 is really quick and easy, but going backward, trying
to get back those numbers
13 and 29 starting from 377 is very, very time consuming.
So this is essentially how a hash function works.
Just add a little bit more complexity and you end up with a real hash function.
So they're designed to be calculated very quickly going forwards, but almost impossible to go backward.
And by almost impossible
I simply mean that using current levels of computing power, it would take far too long to make it worthwhile
for the hacker.
So let's say that to calculate the hash going forward, it takes a millisecond, but to go backward
it takes two years, then that hacker probably has better things to do with his time.
So when a user tries to register on our website, then we ask them for the registration password, which
we turn into a hash using our hash function, and then we store that hash on our database.
Now, at a later point when the user tries to log in and they type in their password, then we again
hash that password that they typed in to produce a hash and then we compare it against the hash that
we have stored in our database.
And if those two hashes match, then that must mean that the login password is the same as the registration
password as well.
And at no point in this process do we have to store their password in plain text or are we able to reverse
the process to figure out their original password?
The only person who knows their password is the user themselves.
Now, previously we saw that by using the Enigma machine, as long as we knew what the settings were
for the Enigma machine, which is basically the encryption key,
right?
As long as we knew what that was, then I can decode it by setting it to the same encryption key.
And we end up being able to retrieve the original text. Now, however, if I was to go and change this
to a hash function instead, then you can see that when we try to decode this using the same hash function,
MD5, we get the error
that decoding step is not defined for hash function because you can't really go back.
That's the whole point of the hash function and this is what will make our authentication more secure.
All right, guys.
So now that we've covered creating user passwords, encrypting our database, as well as hashing passwords,
we've kind of reached a level of security that most websites are at.
Now, there's a lot more security that we're going to learn about a little bit later on.
But you're actually at a point where you already know quite a lot about authentication and keeping user
passwords secure, and definitely a lot more than a lot of people who actually run websites.
And I know that some of you guys are keen to get a job.
And if that is you, then I want you to go onto a website called plaintextoffenders.com. I'll
link to it in the course resources.
But here what you'll find is emails that come from various companies where the users requested to reset
their password and they're sending the user a plain text version of their password.
Now, at this point, we know to be able to even get the user's password in plain text, it means that
they're doing some horrible things with securing the passwords.
Either it's encrypted and there's an encryption key somewhere that they're storing or it's simply just
stored on their database as plain text, which is the worst possible type of security.
So given that you already know a lot better than the people who run getlinuxjobs.com or world
sim.com or Telecom Egypt, then you could actually just email these people and tell them that I'm
a web developer and I know about authentication and securing users passwords.
You obviously seem like you might need some help.
Would you like me to work for you?
I recommend giving that a go too
if you're keen on getting a job. If you're not looking for a job, then have a look at these websites.
And if you're signed up to any of them, be sure to delete your account because it's definitely not
secure.
And this is why a lot of companies and a lot of websites get hacked because they don't continue beyond
this point.
So that means it's a really good time to talk to you about how passwords are hacked,
so a sort of hacking Passwords 101 class if you will.
Now, most of the time, I use my programming powers for good.
But in this case, I want to talk to you about how passwords might be hacked so that once we understand
how the other side approaches this problem, then we can learn more about security and make our website
safer for users.
And by the way, I have no idea why hackers are always portrayed in a balaclava.
It's not like they're going to burgle anybody.
I mean, especially this guy, he must be incredibly warm sitting next to all these computers, wearing
so much clothing on his face.
But I digress.
So as a company, this is probably one of the things that you least look forward to. The day when you
wake up and you get a call and you've been hacked.
And this has happened really recently to a lot of big companies like Adobe Creative Cloud got hacked
in 2013, LinkedIn got hacked in 2012.
And there's loads of accounts where their passwords get leaked.
Lots of unhappy users who reuse their passwords and are feeling extremely vulnerable.
And you can see that even to this day, people can purchase these hacked accounts where people might
not have realized that their LinkedIn email and their passwords are linked and people are potentially
buying that data up and using it to hack into their PayPal accounts or other similar payment portals.
So even if you don't learn anything from this lesson, I recommend just going to this website. I'll link
to it in the course resources just for educational purposes.
But put in your email address and make sure that if you do have any passwords that show up, change
all the places where you use that password.
But why is it that all of these big companies are getting hacked and leaking their users passwords?
Are they not at least encrypting or hashing their passwords?
Well, they are.
But consider this.
So you're a hacker and you've managed to get into the LinkedIn user database.
And just for simplicity's sake, let's say it looks like this.
You've got a username and you've got a hash.
And thankfully, they didn't store their users' passwords in plain text, so you can't access their passwords
straight away.
However, if you look at this table a little bit more closely, you will realize that three of the hashes
are completely identical.
Now, why might that be?
Well, remember that the same password always turns into the same hash no matter how often you try it.
And that's a core part of the hash function that we rely on in order to validate our users as well.
That means a hacker would look at this table and realize that Angela, Tony, and Emily all have the same
password, and what they can do is they can start to construct what we call a hash table.
So you would take some of the most commonly used passwords and you would use the same hash function
to create the hash value for each of those.
And these are some of the most common passwords that people love to use.
123456, qwerty, password, 111111.
And so you generate this hash table and then all you have to do is just look up the hash of the user
and compare it against the hash you have in your table.
So you search by the hash value and you land upon the password, which is qwerty.
So now you've figured out that three out of four users in this table all have the same password and it's
qwerty.
So what if they didn't use one of the most common passwords and instead they use something else, say
their date of birth or their pet's name?
Well, let's see how we would make a hash table if we were a hacker.
You would probably start with all the words from a dictionary,
and this is where the term dictionary attack comes from.
You create hashes from all the possible words in a dictionary, and that will only be about 150,000 hashes
that you would need to create.
And then you add to that hash table all the numbers from a telephone book and all the combination of
characters up to six places.
And then you add all of these together and you end up with something close to 19.8 billion
combinations, which admittedly sounds like a large number,
right?
How long would it take your computer to calculate that
many hashes?
So what do we do?
Well, let's go shopping.
Let's go and buy some of the latest GPUs or graphics cards which are capable of parallel processing and
therefore are particularly suited to not only Bitcoin mining, but also generating hashes.
With one of the latest GPS, you can calculate about 20 billion MD5 hashes per second.
So that means with our hash table of 19.8 billion combinations, it'll only take one
of these GPUs 0.9 seconds, which is nothing.
It's not a lot of time to invest in order to hash so many people's passwords.
And to make it even worse, large hash tables have been built for the most common passwords.
So because we've had so much data from previous hacks such as the Adobe one or the LinkedIn one or TalkTalk
or Equifax, we know what the most common passwords are that people use.
And every year companies like Splash Data will compile what are the most common passwords, say the
top 25.
And this is where all of those values that went into our table came from.
But you can actually go one step further.
There are pre-built hash tables that people have created for the top 10,000 most common passwords.
And you can see that MD5 is one of the quickest hashes to calculate.
And this is why it's very, very common to find MD5 hash tables.
And you can even use Google as a basic hash table.
You can paste in the hash that you found from the hacked database.
You perform a simple Google search and you come up with the original password.
Now, if at this point you're extremely scared and you're wondering, well, what exactly can you do
about this?
Well, consider that in our user table, there was one hash that was extremely difficult to find and
it didn't match up with any of the hashes in this little simple hash table we built.
So what if we put that into Google to search on a larger scale and see if it matches any of the hashes
in the hash tables that people have generated?
And it doesn't. It doesn't match anything.
And the reason is because when John created his password, he had a very, very strong password with
uppercase letters, lowercase letters, numbers, symbols, but most importantly, a long password.
When you think about hashing as a mathematical formula, you'll realize that as the number of characters
of your password increases, the computation time that it takes to crack it increases exponentially.
So it doesn't matter if your account on LinkedIn or Adobe  Creative Cloud or Ashley Madison was cracked,
as long as you had a
strong password, they wouldn't be able to work it out from a hash table. So as an example, there's
a website called Password Checker and you can put in your password and it'll tell you not only the strength,
but also how long it will take various types of machines to be able to crack that password.
So let's say that I create a six-character password composed of a random set of characters,
right? 123456.
And you can see that even for a standard desktop PC, it only takes about three seconds to perform a
brute force attack to crack that password.
But let's see what happens if I add another six more characters.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
Now, it takes 31 years for a standard desktop PC to be able to crack it and even a fast GPU takes two
years to crack my password.
So even though all of the websites encourage you to add a capital letter, lowercase letter, some numbers
and some random characters, if you only have six characters in your password, so a short password,
it still doesn't take very long to crack.
So the most important thing of creating a strong password that is almost uncrackable is just to increase
the number of characters. And also to prevent yourself from being a victim of a dictionary attack,
just make sure that you don't use a dictionary word or a place name or something that is in a directory
somewhere like a telephone number.
All right.
So at least after this lesson, you'll know how to keep yourself more secure.
But in the next lesson, we're going to address these vulnerabilities that occur because of weak hashing
algorithms,
and we're going to learn how we can combat hackers who try to attack our database using a dictionary
attack or by creating a hash table.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
But as a quick bonus, if you ever want to trick your friends into thinking that you're some sort of
a hacker, at least according to Hollywood, I recommend checking out a website called hackertyper
.net where you can just mash the keyboard and you end up with something that looks extremely realistic.
But a word of warning: try not to do this on an airplane or in a government building unless you want to
actually get investigated.
All right, so now that we've seen what some of the vulnerabilities might be for hashed passwords,
it's time to level up and learn about a way that we can prevent these types of dictionary attacks or
hash table cracks.
And in order to do that, we have to learn about salting.
Now, what exactly is salting?
Well, we already know what hashing is. It's
when we take a password, we run it through a hash function and we end up with a hash that we store
on our database.
And as we saw in the last lesson, passwords that are generated by humans are extremely insecure.
They tend to be very short and they tend to be dictionary words that are extremely easy to look up and
create a hash table
for. Now, salting takes hashing a little bit further.
In addition to the password, we also generate a random set of characters, and those characters along
with the user's password gets combined and then put through the hash function.
So the resulting hash is created from both the password as well as that random unique salt.
So that means no matter how simple the password of the user is, adding that salt increases its complexity,
increases the number of characters, and we make our user database a lot more secure.
So consider the previous problem that we saw in the last lesson when
we covered hacking 101.
Now we know that three of our users have the same password and we figured that out because they all
had the same hash.
Now, on the other hand, if we had generated a random set of characters, which is the salt, and combined
the password with the salt in order to generate the hash, then they won't have the same hash in our
user database.
So let's try and generate Emily's hash from her password. So we know that her password is qwerty and
we generate a random salt.
So then let's go ahead and put in her password,
qwerty, and then we append at the end that random salt that we generated and we end up with a hash.
Now this hash, however, is not the same as Tony's hash or Angela's hash because the salt is different
each time.
Now the salt is something that the user doesn't have to remember and instead, it's stored in the database
along with the hash.
So that means when the user types in their password, when they try to log in, you combine their password
with the salt and if you generate the same hash, then they must have had the same password.
It's kind of clever, isn't it?
And on our database, of course, we wouldn't be storing their passwords, but only the salt and the
hash.
Now consider our previous statistics.
You can generate about 20 billion MD5 hashes per second.
So even if we added a salt and we made it harder to generate a hash table, with some of the latest GPUs
you can still probably generate a hash table with all salt combinations relatively quickly.
So what else can we do to increase the security?
Well, we can use something other than MD5, right?
Another hashing algorithm that's valued because it's incredibly slow.
And this is where bscript comes in.
This is one of the industry-standard hashing algorithms that developers use to keep their users' passwords
safe, because while you can calculate 20 billion MD5 hashes per second, even the latest and
the greatest GPUs in 2019 can still calculate only about 17000 bcrypt hashes per second, which makes
it dramatically harder for a hacker to generate those pre-compiled hash tables. And a salted hash table
instead of taking something like three seconds
If it was hashed with MD5,
if it was hash using bcrypt, it would take you something like eight months, which is not really worth
the hacker's while.
They'll probably go and search out a company that has less security enabled. And to make our passwords
even more secure
when we're using bcrypt, it has a concept of what's called salt rounds, how many rounds you're going
to salt your password with.
And obviously the more rounds you do, the saltier your password and also the more secure it is from
hackers.
So, what exactly are salt rounds?
Well, let's say that our original user password was qwerty, and we generate a random set of characters
as the salt.
So now we have qwerty and a random set of salt.
We pass it through our hash function, bcrypt, and we end up with a
hash. Now that one round of salting, if we wanted to have two rounds of salting, then we take the hash
that was generated in round one and we add the same salt from before.
And now we run it through, bcrypt, the hash function again, and we end up with a different hash.
And the number of times you do this is the number of salt rounds.
Now, the reason why this is genius is because as computers get faster...
remember that Moore's Law says that every year the number of transistors in a computer chip almost doubles
and the cost of that faster computer halves.
So every year you can get more computing power for less money.
And this is where salt rounds comes in.
When you're hashing your passwords using bcrypt, you can set the number of rounds you want to salt
your password.
So that means maybe this year in 2019, you salted ten rounds, but maybe next year you can increase that
number to 12.
And for every increase in that number, the amount of time that it takes to hash your password doubles.
And so that means you don't have to change your hashing algorithm or update your code other than simply
changing one number to keep up with the times.
So just to review, coming back to that user database, we'll have each user's username stored, we'll have
their randomly generated salt stored, and then we'll store their hash after a set number of salting
rounds.
And when it comes to checking their password when they login, we'ill take the password that they put
in, combine it with the salt that's stored in the database, and run it through the same number of salting
rounds until we end up with the final hash and we compare the hash against the one that's stored in
the database to see if they've entered the correct password.
So let's give that a go in real life and implement salting rounds into our website's authentication.
Hey guys, welcome to day 70 of 100 Days of Code.
Now, today is a crucial time point in our journey of learning to build websites because we're finally
going to be publishing our Flask website onto the Internet.
And in order to do this, we're going to be using the help of a number of tools, including Git and
GitHub, Heroku and also something called gunicorn. And with their powers combined, we'll end up with
our website being hosted live on the Internet with
URL that we can share to anybody in the world
and they'll be able to go and access and use our blog website that we've spent so long building and
perfecting.
And you'll even be able to load it up on your phone and see it in its full glory.
And along the way, we're going to learn about version control using a technology called git.
And also we're going to be upgrading our database from something that is more suited to development
which is SQLite,
and we're going to be taking that to the next step, making it production ready using PostgreSQL.
So that's all yet to come.
So if you head over to the next lesson, let's get started by learning about Git and version control.
Now, before we can start deploying our website, the first thing we have to do and we have to understand
is something called version control. And we're going to be using the most popular technology for version
control, which is Git and GitHub.
So let's talk about version control
in its simplest form.
Let's say that I create a new code file and I write a few lines in it.
Now I decide to put it under version control using Git,
and let's say that I call this save point as number one.
Now this is my first version.
So later on, as I progress, I write maybe a few more lines of code.
And at this point I decide to make another save point and I call this my second version.
So further down the line, I accidentally screw up my entire code file and it's irrepairable.
And I get to the point where I would rather burn my entire code file rather than having to try and fix
it.
You do get into these situations because very often your code is interlinked and each class depends
on another.
And sometimes you can screw up in a way where, you know, all hope is lost.
And I simply just want to roll back to the last save point.
I can do that using Git.
I can do that using other tools as well
but the most popular tool and the one that we're going to be talking about is git.
So you can either compare your current code file,
so the current mess that you've made against a previous version
so at any of the save points before. Alternatively, you can simply just roll back to a previous version
and it doesn't have to be the one that was immediately previous.
You can go as far back or as far forwards as you like as long as you know which version you want.
So that's the theory.
And in order to put it into practice, let's see how we can create some files locally on our computer
and put it under version control.
Now, if you're Mac, Git is already preinstalled with every Mac operating system. But if you are on
Windows, I want you to head over to gitforwindows.org and click download to download it to your system.
Now, once you go through The Wizard, you should end up with a folder called Git installed to your
C: drive under program files. So I can see it right here.
Now, inside this folder, you're going to open up a application called git-bash, and this is where
we're going to be executing all our commands.
So notice how previously we talked about the terminal and how to use command line control of your computer.
If you forgot about this, head back to day 54 where we covered this in detail.
But in order to get started and to be on the same page as the video, I want you to go ahead and cd
over to your home directory.
So that's the tilde symbol.
And once you're there, you should see this as your location.
Now, here, you're basically at the same level as being inside your C drive, inside users and then
under your current logged in users directory.
So this folder and all the things that it contains, you can see, are the same as all the things are
printed out when I hit ls at this location.
So you're now ready to follow along with the video and start working with Git.
Now, the first thing we're going to do is open up terminal, and inside terminal we're going to navigate
to our desktop.
So if you're not familiar with the command line and you haven't watched the module on the command line,
then I recommend you to take a look at it now because we're going to be using a lot of the commands
to create directories and navigate around.
So if you're not yet familiar, then it's a good time to take a look at that.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to cd into my desktop, and here I'm going to create
a new directory called Story.
Then I'm going to cd into this Story directory.
And if I show you with ls, you can see that it's completely empty.
And similarly, inside Finder, I can show you the same thing.
So let's go ahead and create some text files.
So I'm going to use touch to create a file called chapter1.txt, and then I'm going to open
chapter1.txt.
Now, on Windows, instead of using open as the command, it's start. So you can write the start chapter
1.txt and that will open it inside notepad. And you can continue following along with the video.
And it'll open it inside the default application which is Text Edit on a Mac.
Alternatively, you can use a text editor within the terminal, for example, vim.
Now, this is only for people who are really familiar with this.
So it's totally up to you what you decide to use.
But if you are not familiar with using terminal-based editors, then it's probably a good idea to just
stick with the open command and use Text Edit.
So let's go ahead and open Chapter one and let's write something inside, shall we?
OK, so there's my masterpiece done, I'm going to go ahead and hit save and I'm going to quit Text
Edit.
So that was our first chapter done.
So now let's create a git local repository and start tracking some of these file changes.
So to initialize git, we simply write git init.
And as you can see, it's initialized an empty git repository inside the story directory.
Now, if you have a look inside Finder, you actually can't see this .git at all.
But as we learned before, if you use ls -a, you can see all the hidden files and you can see that
.git is right there
and it's going to be used to track all your changes, to commit your changes, and to perform version
control.
So we're currently inside the story directory and you can also call this the working directory.
So as I mentioned before, using git and learning about version control, it comes with some of its own
terminology and language.
So I'm going to try and debunk and simplify a lot of these terms that you'll come across just so that
we can all be on the same page and we all understand what's going on.
So currently we are inside the working directory, which is the story directory.
And here, in order to start tracking the changes of my files, for example, chapter1.txt,
then I need to add this file to what's called a staging area.
And that is basically an intermediate place where you can pick and choose which files inside your working
directory that you want to commit.
So to see what's currently inside your staging area, you can use the git Status command and it shows
you that there are untracked files which will be shown in red.
And this is something that's simply inside your working directory,
so inside here, but it's not yet in the staging area.
So in order to add it to the staging area and to start tracking changes in it, then we have to use
the command git
add. So we're going to type git add and we're going to type the file name.
So in this case, it's chapter1.txt.
So go ahead and hit enter.
And then if we try using git status again, you can see that that file has been added as a new file
and it is now green.
So this is now in the staging area and it's ready to be committed.
So let's go ahead and commit this under version control.
So the command is git commit and I'm going to use the -m flag to add a commit message.
So the commit message is really, really important.
It's something that helps you keep track of what changes you have made in each commit.
So when you create a new save point, you want to be as explicit as possible about what changes were
made between the last save point and this current save point.
So for our initial commit, we can use something very simple like initial commit, and this shows that
this is our starting point.
Alternatively, if you want to be slightly more specific because in our case, we've actually completed
Chapter one, so you can write complete chapter 1.
Now, the thing that you'll realize is that usually with commit messages, they are written in the present
tense and this is the best practice.
So where as it
would probably make more sense, I guess, at least in my head
anyways to write completed chapter one as this save point, it's actually by convention that you should
always use the present tense
so it's like you are doing it now.
You're submitting your changes now.
So let's go ahead and hit enter to make our first commit.
And you can see what commits you have made by using the git log command.
So you can see that this commit was made at this time by this person and it also has a hash and this
hash uniquely identifies this particular commit.
And then right at the end, you see this commit message of what this save point was all about.
So now I'm going to go ahead and create two more chapters. So let's just create chapter2.txt
and chapter3.txt and now we have three chapters.
And I'm going to go in and change some of these text files.
So let's say.
OK, so that's chapter two done.
And finally, let's go ahead and just open Chapter three and edit that as well.
All right, so all three files have been changed, and over here in Finder you can actually get a
quick peek at what the contents are, which is going to be really useful for me to be able to demonstrate
to you what Git is doing behind the background.
So now let's go ahead and add these two new files to our staging area.
So, again, if we use git status, you can see that there's two files that are untracked which are
only in the working directory and not yet inside the staging area.
So we can put it into the staging area by simply adding each of them, as we did before, git add and
writing something like chapter2.txt and then doing git
add chapter3.txt.
But as you can imagine, if you have quite a few files, then it can get incredibly tedious having to
do this one by one.
So of course there is a better way.
So instead of adding these files one by one, we can actually simply just say git add and then use
the DOT to specify everything inside this current directory,
so everything inside the story directory.
So now if I go ahead and hit enter and then let's go to git status again, you can see that there's
two new files that have been added to the staging area. And now we're going to commit those two files
to a new commit, to a new save point.
And you know what to do. If you're following along with me,
go ahead and give it a go.
All right, so how was that? If you remember, the command is git commit and we're going to use the
-m flag to specify a commit message, and we're going to write a message that is in the present tense.
So let's say complete chapter 2 and 3.
So that's everything I've done between the initial commit and this commit.
The only difference is the fact that I've completed now chapter 2 and chapter 3.
So let's go ahead and hit enter.
So again, let's check it out
using git log. We can see that we now have two commits both with different hashes because they are unique
and they are different.
So the initial one was complete chapter one, and it was done at this time.
And then later on, about five minutes later, I completed chapter two and three, and that was the
second commit.
And this is where we are at right now.
So you can see by the head, by this word HEAD, this is the position or the current state that we
are in.
So I just want to quickly recap what we've just done.
So we created a file in our working directory inside our story directory.
So the working directory is the folder or the directory where you initialize your git repository.
When we said git init, we did that inside the story directory.
So that becomes our working directory.
And from now on, git is going to try and track the changes that it sees between the working directory
and the local repository.
So in the beginning, we created a file inside our working directory, inside Story, and then we used
git add to push it to the staging area.
Now, the reason why there is this intermediate staging area, because you might wonder why not just
go from the working directory straight to the repository.
Why do we need this extra step?
Well, sometimes you might not want to add all of your files to be tracked or all of your files to be
committed.
So the staging area is a good place to try and figure out what are the things that you want git to ignore
and what are the things that you want to be tracked.
So once we've used git add, we've put our file into the staging area and we're happy with the changes
that we are going to commit, then the next step is to go ahead and commit it using the git commit command.
So now our file is inside our local repository,
so that .git. And that version is given a name through the commit message.
So that means that even if we've messed up our file, we can still use the last version that's under
version control and we can use a special command called git checkout to revert back or roll back to
the last position in our local repository.
So let me show you what that looks like in the command line and how we would do that in practice.
So at the moment, I've got three nicely written chapters and I have a feeling my book is going to be
a big seller.
So now let's say that I have, you know, been working on Chapter 3 and I have completely messed
everything up.
I just, you know, fell asleep on my keyboard and I happened to have saved my file.
And now if you have a look at it, it's now just mumbo-jumbo.
And I've ruined my masterpiece.
But fear not because we have a version control and we have git enabled, so we have nothing to worry about.
I can actually revert the changes that I've made locally in my working directory.
So at this point you can use git status to see that we have modifications in our chapter3.txt
file that have not yet been committed or added to the staging area.
So if we wanted to, we can actually revert this back to its previous glory.
But before we do that, we can use a git command to check out what are the differences between the current
version of Chapter three and the last save point in our git repository?
So to do that, you can use the command git diff, so the difference, and we'll give it the Chapter three
file name.
And if you hit enter, you can see that this is the part that was deleted, so the part in red.
And then this was the part that was added, which is our gobbledygook.
So now if I've looked at these differences, it might just be that, you know, there's only a few mistakes
in my new version of Chapter three
and I just want to maybe copy some things over
or have a look at how I did certain things previously and change my current file, but other times it
might be that, you know, it's just you want to torch the new file.
You just don't want anything to do with it.
And you would much rather roll back to the previous version.
So if you want to do that, then there is a command called git checkout that is going to be really,
really useful for you.
So git checkout and then we're going to specify the name of the file that we want to checkout which
is chapter3.txt.
And if you just watch over here which is the preview of the current version of chapter3.txt,
once I hit enter on this command that basically asks to roll back this Chapter three to the last version
that was committed in our local repository.
So if I hit enter, you can see that almost immediately
my chapter three has been restored to its previous glorious state and this is the version of chapter
three at the last checkpoint at which I committed it.
So that was this one, which is completed chapter 2 and 3.
So whereas in this lesson we've looked mostly at local implementations of git, so saving these versions
on our computer locally,
in the next lesson, I'm going to talk about GitHub and creating remote repositories.
So I'll see you there.
All right, so whereas in the last lesson we were looking at local implementations of using Git and version
control, in this lesson we're going to talk about how you can create a remote repository, so a repository
that's hosted on somebody else's server or somebody else's computer by using GitHub.
Now, most people would have heard of GitHub.
So if you haven't yet set up an account on GitHub, then this is the time to do it.
So head over to github.com and simply fill out this quick form to create an account on GitHub.
So it's completely free,
and all you need to do is just confirm your email so that you can access it.
Once you've done that, go ahead and sign in.
So once you've signed it, you should be looking at this page.
And what we're going to do is we're going to create a repository inside the browser-based GitHub.
So if you navigate to this top-right corner and click that plus arrow, then you can select new repository.
And I'm going to call my repository same name, I guess we'll call it story.
And let's give it a description.
Let's say my masterpiece.
Now, by default, all repositories that you create on GitHub are public, that means that anyone can
see all of the files inside your saved repository.
So everything that you commit to your remote repository or to your GitHub repository will be public.
So if you don't want that, then you can select private, which requires a subscription on GitHub.
But in most cases, if you're not doing anything that's top-secret or if you're not developing technology
that is completely brand new, then having a public repository is not such a big problem.
And on the other hand, as well, you can see loads of other people's public repositories and you can
see, for example, how they structure their code, what is their style, and you can see how people
do things.
So this is the beauty of open source code.
And as you develop in your journey of becoming a developer, then you might find that you want to contribute
to other open-source projects, help them out a bit, and work in a virtual team to try and contribute
your knowledge and your programming skills.
OK, so now once I've selected public, the next thing is that I'm going to leave this part empty.
I'm not going to initialize a README for my repository just yet.
So the next thing is that I'm going to go ahead and click the big green button and create my repository.
So now you can see that there are two ways that they tell you
you can set up your repository. You can either set it up in GitHub on desktop, their desktop client,
which I am not a big fan of.
But instead, what we're going to do is we're going to use the command-line instructions to set up our
repository.
So we are going to push an existing repository that we've got locally onto this remote repository.
And to do that, we need to copy the address of our Github repository.
And we're going to use these two lines of code in order to transfer or push our existing local repository
from the command line.
All right.
So I'm currently inside my story directory, which also happens to be the working directory for this
particular project.
And here, I am going to again take a look at git log to see what previous commits we've got.
And you can see that we've got two previous commits.
And I would like to push both of these committees onto GitHub.
So to do that, the first thing is creating a remote.
So it's telling my local git repository that I've created a remote repository somewhere on the Internet
and I want to transfer all of my commits over there.
So the command that we're going to use is git remote add origin.
Now, origin is simply the name of your remote and you can theoretically call it anything you want.
You can call it bacon if you want, but by convention and it's highly recommended that you simply keep
the name origin.
And the reason is because most programmers are used to the conventional naming, and that means it'll
be much easier for them to understand what's going on in your project when they have a look at it,
instead of you doing something completely different which will be very surprising and will be a lot
harder for people to understand what's going on.
So git remote add origin, and then we're going to paste the URL of our remote repository on GitHub
and then we're going to go ahead and hit enter.
And now that remote is created so we can push our local repository onto our remote repository, which
is called origin.
So we're going to say git push -u origin master.
And what this line of code does is that it pushes your local repository to the remote repository using
the -u flag or the u option which basically links up your remote and your local repositories.
And then we're going to push it towards the remote that's called origin, and we're going to push it
to the branch that's called master.
So the master branch is simply the default branch or the main branch of all of your commits.
So let's go ahead and hit enter, and there's going to be a little bit of work being done in the background
because it's actually going to have to upload your local repository to the remote repository on GitHub
servers.
And depending on the size of your local repository, this can take various amounts of time.
So now once we see our prompt, so the flashing cursor or the dollar sign, that means our push is
successful and as you can see, it says branch master set up to track remote branch master from origin,
sounds really confusing, but if you head back over to GitHub and if you're on the same page, all you
have to do is hit command+r to refresh or just press the refresh button.
And you can see that all of our files are now hosted on GitHub and it's complete with all of our commit messages.
So if you go into insights, graphs, and go into network, you can actually see our master branch, which
currently only has two save points or two commits.
And if you hover over them, you can actually see the messages of each of these.
So as you build out your project, as you add more commits either locally or pushing it remotely
or probably doing both, then you can see the progress of your files in your GitHub repository.
So now you can see all of the code
if it's a code file or in our case, it's just a text file hosted on GitHub.
And you can point anybody towards this.
And there are actually cases where people do a lot of story writing using GitHub just because it's
so good at tracking your save points and being able to revert to previous versions in the past.
So, for example, if you head over back to the main page and you go to your commits, you can see both
of those commits, when they were committed,
and also, if you click on it, you can see the changes that were made at those time points.
So if we have a look at chapter one, you can see this is all we had at the point when we made our first
commit.
So previously we said that we have a working directory, which is the directory where we initialized
Git.
Then we can push our files to a staging area where we can pick and choose which files we want to commit.
Then once we're ready, then we can commit our files or our save point to our local repository.
So once you've done a few commits, then you actually have this timeline of various commits and this
is called your master branch.
So the Master Branch is your main branch of commits or save points and it is sequential.
And this is usually where your main progress is saved or committed.
Now, later on, we then introduced this idea of the remote repository.
The important thing to note is that you can have a local repository completely in parallel with a remote
repository,
check the differences between them, but you can also sync them or push things from your local repository
to your remote repository.
So in our case, the local repository is the Git file that we've got inside our story directory.
And the remote repository is GitHub which hosts our code and also hosts all of the changes that were
made in between the different committees.
So we have this master branch of various commits, first commit, second commit, third commit, in our
local Git repository.
And when we performed the command git push, then that effectively pushed all of those commits, all
of those various versions and changes and code pieces to our remote repository on GitHub.
So that's what git pushed us.
Hey, guys, well done for achieving a big milestone.
Now here's a quick tip about the upcoming projects and lessons.
Now you might look ahead and you might see, oh, what's going on?
There's no step by step guidance.
There's no solution code.
What's happening here?
Now, what I want you to be able to do after you complete this course is to have achieved all of the
skills that you need to be able to get a job as a python developer.
And one of the most important things you need to be able to demonstrate is that you can write your own
code, not code from a tutorial, not code that I've guided you through, but code that you actually
thought about, that you wrote.
So we're going to help you to build your portfolio in the upcoming section.
I've created some project ideas that are usually quite good when it comes to interviews.
And your job is to use everything that you've learned, plus research plus Googling plus reviewing
some lessons to create those projects and write entirely your code.
But what this means is that you can copyright your code, you can build it out into a real business,
you can put it into your portfolio or put it onto GitHub and demonstrate at your next interview that
you can create your own projects without the help of somebody else.
So I've taught courses on Web development, on iOS development, and I've often seen students come to
job interviews with a project that I'm like, "Oh, I think I know that I wrote the code for that."
Or you see online where people have the same project over and over again with exactly the same code.
This is what you're going to avoid by going that extra step.
Now, I'm not saying it's easy.
It's going to be really hard, but this is how you learn and this is how you progress as a developer.
In this course, I want it to be a safe space for you.
I want it to be a place where you can play, you can explore, you can fail without any repercussions,
because we're all here to support you on your journey.
So don't worry if you can't do something, don't worry
if you get it wrong,
don't worry if it doesn't look great, just share your code and we'll give you feedback and we're going
to get you to that place where you want to be. But you have to be willing to try as well.
So I hope you're going to succeed in the coming lessons and I definitely hope you're going to give it
a go because it is so important for your development.
So here's good luck to you.
And remember, as always, I believe in you.