Hey, guys.
Welcome to day one of your 100 day journey.
And today, we're going to learn about printing, commenting, debugging, string manipulation and variables.
So it's chockablock full of really fun stuff.
And by the end of today, you will have created a band name generator program.
So this is the final project of today.
And the idea is that let's say that your friend was starting a new band, a rock band or a classical
band, and they're struggling to come up with a good name.
So you come in to the rescue and send them your band name generator program.
So it asks you for the name of the city that you grew up in.
So mine was Bristol in the southwest of the UK.
And then it'll ask you, what's the name of your pet?
I had a pet rabbit when I was younger, and I am probably the least imaginative person.
Classic programmer personality.
So I called my rabbit.
"Rabbit".
So now when I hit "Enter", it's going to give me my band name.
And it could be Bristol Rabbit.
So that sounds pretty cool.
That could be like a a rock band.
So this is what you're going to make.
And in the process, in order to create this, you're going to learn about printing, inputting, commenting,
debugging, name errors, syntax errors, string manipulation variables, and a whole lot more.
So if you feel like you can already achieve this and you can prove it by making this program yourself,
then feel free to skip to the next day's lessons.
But for most of you, even if you've started learning Python programming, there's probably still a
lot of new things that you'll find in today's lessons.
Now, as with all the projects that we're making in this course, you get to try it out before you make
it so you can either go to the URL.
Alternatively, if you don't want to type out the full URL, you can head over to the course content
here and then click on the resources and click this link to head straight over there.
And then once you're there, all you have to do is to click run and you'll be able to preview how the
final product is going to work.
So you can type in your own city and follow the instructions until you get to the end result.
So once you're ready, head over to the next lesson and let's get started and get coding straight away.
To begin open up your browser and head over to this URL.
Now, if you didn't want to type all of that out and make some typos and errors and not get to the right
place, then simply just head over to the course resources and click on the link there.
It'll take you directly to this page.
Now, once you've clicked on the link that takes you to the starting replit, you should see something
that looks like this.
And the first thing I want you to do is to go ahead and click on the "Fork" button.
What this is going to do is it's going to create a version of that same replit that you'll see me
working through in the videos, but in this case you'll be able to edit it.
So if you want to save the work that you're doing, I recommend signing up to replit.
It's completely free.
You don't need any credit cards or anything.
Once you've created your account on replit, it will take you to the previous page where you can now
actually click the fork repl button.
And what that will do is it will create a copy of what I've created and put it into your account, and
then you'll be able to see a record of all of the code that you've written throughout the course.
In this course you'll be coding along with me on replit and completing a whole bunch of interactive
coding exercises in our replit classroom.
So go ahead, pause the video, sign up to replit and make sure you've forked the starting copy of
Day one printing start and you should be on a screen that looks like this.
And once you're signed in, then you can actually go ahead and edit the name of the replit or add a
brief description and you'll be able to access it later on through the My Repls folder.
Now, once you've done that, then let's go ahead and walk through some of the different parts of replit
that you'll be using.
First, on the left-hand side pane here, you've got some files and you can see the current file that's
open is this Python file here, and you can create new files or you can create new folders and later
on will be using these features to organize our code.
Now the other part of the left hand side pane that's really useful is the Settings tab here, and I
recommend everybody to switch their font size up to large.
This just makes it so much easier to identify mistakes and any typos you make.
Now we're going to leave everything else as it is, and you can click on the settings button to collapse
that pane so that you end up with more space for writing code.
And this area here is where you're going to be doing that.
All of your code is going to go inside here.
And once we're done with writing our code, we'll click run and it will execute.
And the results of our code will come up over on the console in the right here.
And I generally prefer to code using a darker background.
It's slightly easier on my eyes, especially when you're working at night.
So these are some of the most important parts of replit, but the important thing is it allows us to
just get started.
Now remember that the whole reason why we're learning to program is to be able to tell the computer
what it needs to do and for it to follow our commands.
So let's go ahead and tell the computer to do something, and we're going to do that by writing our
first line of code.
So in this case, I'm creating something called a print function, which is just the word "print", all
in lowercase, and then followed by a set of parentheses.
Now inside these parentheses, I'm going to tell it what I want it to print, and hopefully it's going
to output that inside our console.
So I'm going to start off by writing the classic "Hello World" inside here.
And then once you're ready, then go ahead and click Run.
After a few seconds, you should see the computer follow your command, namely printing the words that
you told it to print inside the console or the output area over here.
And once it's done, it indicates that with the little orange arrow and the way that this command works
is super simple.
You have the keyword "print" followed by a set of parentheses, and then inside the parentheses you tell
it what you want it to print.
And once you've inserted that, then when this line of code gets executed by the computer, it'll know
to simply print or output the thing that you've placed in between the parentheses.
But notice here that it's not just the word hello world exclamation mark that I've put inside my parentheses.
I've also added some quotation marks or double quotes around the word.
And the reason why I've done this is so that I can tell the computer that this bit here in between the
double quotes is not code.
It's not like print where it's supposed to do something.
This is just some text that I've made up that I want it to print out.
And these pieces of text in programming lingo is known as strings.
And you can imagine it as almost like a pearl necklace, right?
It's a string of characters.
And what the double quotes do is they basically show the beginning and the end of that string of characters.
So that means you have to be really careful when you're typing.
For example, if I go ahead and I miss out the closing double quote.
Well, now you can see that there's some changes that have happened to our code already, namely that
the last parentheses, instead of being coloured in white like the opening parentheses or how it used
to be, it's now coloured in orange.
And this is a subtle hint to us.
You're going to get really attuned to these subtle hints because they are the clues that will tell you
what might have gone wrong in your code.
If I run this code as it is right now, it's going to break.
It's going to give me a syntax error and it says something that seems like it's completely non English.
So how can we figure out what this means?
Now the thing I want you to know is that all programmers make mistakes.
We all make lots of errors, like forgetting to add the double quotes at the end of the string or forgetting
to add a closing parentheses.
These things are just common errors because we're human.
But the thing that differentiates great programmers is we're really good at figuring out what the problem
is and how to fix it.
So you can imagine that coding is just a whole bunch of problems that you have to solve.
And in this case, when we get some sort of red text on the right and our code is not doing what we
expect it to do, then all we have to do is take this entire error message where it says something,
something error, and this is some sort of message that we're supposed to understand and we're simply
going to drop it into Google.
And usually the first link you come across will be from a website called StackOverflow.com.
And this is basically the Q&A website that all developers will go to whenever something is wrong with
their code or when they can't figure out how to do something.
So if we click on this link, you can see that somebody else has also had this error.
And some kind souls have told us that the solution might be the fact that you're missing a double quote
before the end of the line.
So if we take a look back at our code, the code that generated this error looks like this.
And indeed, we are missing a double quote at the end of our string.
As you're learning to code, as you're going through your 100 days, I want you to become more and more
attuned to the color of your code.
Because one of the most helpful things that code editors such as this do for us is something called
syntax highlighting.
For example, when I was missing that double quote, it highlighted this entire thing in this orange
color.
And that is basically it telling us it seems like this whole thing is some text.
It thinks that all of this is a string and that we're missing a closing parenthesis.
So if you notice this and you're like, Wait, actually that's not right.
This part should be orange because this is what I want to be printed.
But this part should match the color of the open brace, which is white.
So there must be something wrong here.
And indeed, if you have a look at the error message, it actually has a little carat sign right here
showing you that there's something that's probably not right here and it might jog your memory that,
oh, yeah, I've forgotten a closing double quote.
And now when we run our code, you'll see that it's good as new.
So now it's your turn to try it out in a code challenge.
Head over to the next lesson.
Sign up to our classroom and then I'll guide you through getting started on your first coding challenge.
So all of that and more.
I'll see you on the next lesson.
Throughout this course, we'll be getting you involved in a lot of these interactive coding exercises.
And the idea is that you're not just sitting here watching me talk, that you're actually putting everything
you're learning into practice.
That way it actually becomes your own.
It's a great because we can give you instructions and show you what should happen if you write the correct
code, what it needs to do, and you'll be able to write your code as well as see it run in the console.
Once you're done with your code, you'll be able to submit it and see the tests run.
And if you've written the code correctly, then all of the tests will pass.
If your code isn't doing what it's supposed to.
Then when you click submit, you'll get feedback and you'll see what it's meant to do and what your
code is actually doing.
So you'll be able to use that to figure out what's wrong and fix your code.
And it's through a lot of these exercises that you're going to level up and you're going to become a
better coder.
Now, in order for you to get set up on our coding rooms, we're going to have to get you signed up
and registered with our course.
So in order to do this, I want you to first head over to codingrooms.com and then sign up for
a student account.
Now this is completely free and all you have to do is just do click, sign up, putting your email and
password, and then you can choose student for this question Who are you?
And then putting your first name and last name and click "Finish". Next,
in order to get hold of the Joining Link, I want you to go to the course resources for the current
lesson on Udemy.
So the lesson is "[Interactive Coding Exercise] Printing", and then I want you to click on the dropdown
list and you should see step one sign up to coding rooms, which you should have already done.
And then step two is join our coding room.
So I want you to click on that link.
And once you've clicked on that link, then it should automatically enroll you into our 100 days of
code, the Complete Python Pro Bootcamp, and you should now be able to see every day's corresponding
interactive coding exercises.
So for example, on day one there are four exercises and they are named exactly the same as what you
see in Udemy.
So this is interactive coding exercise one which is printing, debugging, practice, input, function
and variables and you see all the same ones over here that you'll be able to attempt.
Now the next time when you log in, all you have to do is just go into your courses and you should see
the interactive coding exercises for the 100 days of code, and you will be able to continue where you
left off.
Now let's get started with the first exercise.
That's the objective of this lesson.
So we're going to go into day one and it might be collapsed.
If so, just go ahead and expand it and then click on Exercise 1 - Printing.
And here you see the instructions for what you need to do in order to complete this coding exercise.
Now, I want you to go ahead and click on Open Assignment Workspace, and here you'll be able to see
the instructions on one side of the pane.
You'll be able to have your main.py, which is where you write your code.
So all the lines below here, you can just type your code out.
And then once you're done writing your code, I want you to test it by running your code.
So hitting this run button and you'll see the result of your code being run in the console down here.
Now once you think you've completed the coding exercise according to all the instructions over here,
I want you to go ahead and test your code and you can test your code by simply hitting submit.
Now, don't worry about all of this where it says this submission will count towards your grade for
the assignment.
There are no grades, there's no time limits.
Nobody is going to check what you've done.
It's all for the benefit of your learning so you can submit your code as many times as you like.
So once you hit submit, it's going to run the automated test that we've set up behind the scenes,
and it's going to check to make sure that your code is doing what it's supposed to do.
So, for example, in this case, my tests have not passed because there's a cross here and note that
sometimes there'll be more than one test, so you can scroll down and see the other ones.
And the reason why I didn't pass, as they've shown here, is this is my actual output.
This is what my code did and this is what the expected output is supposed to be.
And there's a whole bunch of differences.
This does not look like this, so then we have to go and fix it.
And I've left some feedback in some of the lessons to help you in case you get stuck.
But also there are hints in some of the instructions.
So just make sure that you read everything now if you want to, or if you get really, really stuck,
you can take a look at the solution.
Now, I don't recommend looking at the solution code unless you're actually just checking to make sure
that.
Something hasn't gone majorly wrong or you're not completely stuck, or just for whatever reason, I
really, really want you to persevere and try your best to actually write the code yourself and to solve
the issues and figure out how to make all the tests pass.
But if you need to look at the solution, they are available on replit.
So just click on this link and it'll take you to the solution page in order to see the files.
You can either fork the repl as you have done before.
You'll get a copy of this solution file or what I think is much simpler is simply click on show files
and then click on this main.py file and then you will see the solution code on this page without
having to fork a copy of this repl.
But you can do it any number of ways.
Whichever way suits you best is fine.
Now, once you have written your code correctly, you should be able to see all the tests pass and by
passing it means that there's a little tick along each of these.
And usually in this one there's only one test and this is passed.
So you get a score of 100%.
And the actual output that your code has created in the console now looks exactly the same as expected.
So you are now done and you can go back to your other assignments and you can continue.
So this is a really simple interface and we've switched to this from replit because replit had actually
disabled their classroom technology, which looks basically exactly the same as this.
And we wanted to provide you the best learning experience possible.
So we've switched over to coding rooms and you should be able to sign up and get started without any
issue.
Now remember at the end of the lesson, I will go through the solution with you step by step explaining
the solution as well.
So if you get stuck, don't worry, I'm here for you every step of the way.
But now it's time for you to pause the video and make sure that you've signed up for coding rooms,
already registered for a student account, and then click on the link in step two in the course resources
and sign up for our course and then go over to the first exercise printing and give it a go.
All right, pause the video now.
All right.
How did you get on?
I really hope you gave this a good go because it's in these moments where you're going to be learning
the code.
Unfortunately, no amount of listening to me talk is actually going to give you these skills.
It's only when you actually try it out and get the computer to do the thing that you wanted to do.
That's when you become the master of the computer, also known as a programmer.
So in this case, the instructions are pretty simple.
We have to use what we learn about the print statement to output these three lines and notice how in
this gif the lines are printing out in separate lines.
This one gets printed, then this one, then this one.
But because it happens so fast, it seems like it as if they're getting printed as a single block.
So we're told to write our code below this line.
And we know that in order to print something, we use the print function with a set of parentheses,
and inside the parentheses is where we tell it what we want it to print.
So in the first instance, it's day one space, then it's now it's really easy to make spelling mistakes.
But I really encourage you to actually type out anything that you put into your code rather than just
simply copying and pasting it.
Now, of course, it works exactly the same way.
I could just copy and paste the code in here, but it's often in these cases where you make mistakes,
like for example, forgetting to add the double quotes around the text that you want to print, I really
recommend just typing out the code for practice whenever you're doing these code challenges.
Now, the last line that we want to print is a little bit complicated.
It's almost like print inception, because what we want to print is this function.
This is how we write our function, and that has to go inside here, inside a set of double quotes.
So let's open up a double quotes and then write our print statement.
And in this case, I'm actually using a single quote.
And I'll tell you just in a little moment why that is.
So let's add that single quote.
And finally, the closing parentheses.
This now is the entire code that you would need to be able to print something out.
And when I go ahead and click Run, you can see that the output looks exactly the same as what we've
got here in the gif.
This is what we want.
And when I click submit you'll see that my tests all pass and I can now submit my assignment and I've
now completed the coding challenge.
Now coming back to this single quote, why is it that I've got a single quote here rather than a double
quote, which is what we've been using all this time?
Well, because in.
Python.
It doesn't actually care whether if you enclose the strings.
So these pieces of text are not to be interpreted as code inside single quotes or inside double quotes.
It is identical to the computer.
This honey badger literally doesn't care.
But if you had a set of double quotes and then you wanted another set of double quotes inside the double
quotes.
So, for example, if I replace this with double quotes, you'll see that already the syntax highlighting
is already screaming out to us.
There's something that's not quite right here because the colors are not the same as here, where the
print function is in a particular color, the parentheses are in a particular color, and the text that
is to be printed in, it's in a yet another different color.
In this case, it looks all jumbled up and we're getting some errors here.
So now if I hit run, you'll get syntax errors.
And the problem here is, of course, this is of course, our code things at the end of this string
is here.
And so it doesn't know what on earth is going on afterwards.
And instead it's seeing this as a string, this as a string, and this is being interpreted as code.
So when we want to use some double quotes inside another set of double quotes, commonly you'll see
people switch to single quotes instead.
So you could, for example, write the print statement like so and use double quotes if you want to
print those out.
Or you can do it the other way, which is what I had before, where we use our double quotes on the
outside and single quotes on the inside.
So have a play around with that, if that's at all confusing.
But once you've tried it a few times and switched it around a few times, it should become clear what
it's actually doing.
How did you get on with this challenge?
If you ever need to see the solution, it's always down here as a link.
So I hope you enjoy this challenge.
In the next lesson, we're going to get back to learning about Python and we're going to learn about
strings and string manipulation for all of that and more.
I'll see you there.
All right guys.
Let's get back to learning about a few more things that we can do with strings.
You saw in the last lesson that if we wanted to print things on individual
lines, then we actually had to write them a few times, right?
We had to write print, um,
on three lines if we wanted it to be printed one, two, three,
like so. Now in this lesson I want to show you a method where we can do the same
thing, but by using a single print method.
So saving ourselves a few characters.
So the way that we would create a new line is by writing a backslash and the N
character.
And now if I go ahead and write hello world again afterward and I hit run,
or you can always use the shortcut, which is command + enter on Mac or control +
enter on Windows.
And you can see that once that line of code has been executed,
I've got hello world printed on two separate lines,
separated by this pink \n and character,
which gets replaced by a new line.
So go ahead and give that a go and see if you can create another one.
Remember though,
it's a backslash and not a forward slash but the syntax highlighting should help
you. All right,
we can simply just add another \n and remember that unless you want a
space to appear right before where your hello world appears,
you actually don't want any gaps between each of these lines.
There we go. We've got the same result as before,
but now using only a single print statement and creating some new lines with the
\n.
Now one of the other things that we can do with strings is we can concatenate
them.
What this means is we combine different strings so that they will be added to
the end of another string. Here's an example.
Let's say that we had the word hello and I wanted to add my name to the end of
this word to make it a single string. Well,
I can combine two strings by simply using a plus sign. So I can write "Hello"
+ "Angela". Now here's a question. When this runs,
what do you think it will look like? Do you think it'll write Hello
Angela or hello Angela, all in one word? Let's see what happens.
You can see that these two strings have now been combined into one and there's
no space in between because we don't have a space character anywhere in here.
Pause the video and see if you can add a space in between.
Alright,
so there are two ways that you can do this or maybe three actually. You could add a
space to the end of hello, you could add a space to
the beginning of Angela or you can actually continue using string concatenation
by simply adding another string in between these two
and this one is just a space. So now when I run my code,
you can see the space gets inserted and this long thing gets combined into a
single string that looks like this
once this bit of the code gets executed.
If we think of strings as a string of connected characters,
then string concatenation is simply taking those separate strings of characters
and merging them into one. Now,
this is a good point to mention that in Python programming spaces are really,
really important.
And what I mean by this is not so much the spaces that are inside strings like
this one, but the spaces that you add in your code.
So here, my print statement, if I hit the backspace,
you can see that nothing happens. I can't go any further back.
But if I added a space or if I added a tab using the TAB key,
then you'll see that when I try to run my code, I actually get an error.
And the type of error this time is not a syntax error anymore.
It's now an indentation error.
And it says that there's an unexpected indent at this position right at the
beginning of the print statement. So when you're coding in Python,
it's really important that you start off all of your code at the beginning of
the line and that you don't accidentally have any spaces or any tabs that you've
inserted in front of the line of code.
And the next time you get an indentation error,
then you'll be able to look at where that error is and hopefully you'll be able to
either use Stack Overflow or just remember what this error message means and
you'll be able to fix your code.
Now this is the second error that we've come across.
The last error was a syntax error for example,
when we forgot to add the end double quotes.
And this one is called a syntax error and this one is called an indentation error.
And as I mentioned before, while you're coding,
you are going to make lots and lots of these errors and other ones.
This is the only sure thing that we know.
So it's great that you're already learning about them and recognizing them.
But how can we prevent this from happening in the first place? Well,
paying attention while you're typing helps, but we all get tired and sometimes,
especially when I'm coding at night, sometimes even when I look at my own name,
it looks like it's spelled wrong and I can't figure out left and right.
So in most cases, text editors have a lot of helpful features.
If you go into the settings bar here and you scroll all the way to the bottom,
you can see that there's something called Code Intelligence. And code
intelligence is something that is going to help you auto-complete some of the
functions like our print function here and give you some helpful information or
hints as you type.
So let's go ahead and change it to enabled and close down our settings pane.
And you can see now if I, for example, forget to add my double quotes,
then I already start to get a little red squiggly line here and a little red bit
in the right hand side of the scroll bar.
And if I hover over the red squiggly line,
you can see that it gives me the error that I would get if I ran my code right
now. And so it reminds me that, Oh yeah,
there's maybe something about my string that's not quite right.
And you can also just Google these error messages and see it in Stack Overflow
to remind yourself of what the error might be relating to.
And I can fix it without having to run my code and having it break.
Because remember that when you're writing large programs,
it's not just going to be one line of code.
You can have multiple lines of code each with their own errors.
For example, this one might be missing a double quote,
this one might be missing a plus sign,
this one might have the print function misspelled.
The next one might have a indentation that's not meant to be there,
and when you run your code like this, it'll only give you the first issue.
Once you fix that issue,
it'll continue to the next issue until you've fixed everything,
and this is really painful. But with code intelligence enabled,
every time we make an error such as an indentation error like this,
then we'll be able to hover over it and you'll see unexpected indent.
So we'll be able to fix that. If we forget to close off our print statement,
then we'll get a little squiggly line next to it.
And if we say misspelled our print statement,
we'll also get errors telling us that undefined name or it doesn't know what
this 'prnt' is and the syntax highlighting also changes and everything should
all help you to avoid mistakes and write good solid code.
So now it's time for another code challenge.
And in this code challenge,
I've got a whole bunch of broken code for you and your job is to debug or remove
the bugs from the code and make the code run without any errors.
This word debugging actually comes from a story where back in the 1980s a
moth actually flew into one of the early computers and it got electrocuted
unfortunately for the moth and for the programmer,
it meant that his code wasn't performing as he would expect it to.
So he actually had to go into the computer, pick out the moth,
and fix the wires so that it would work again.
Now we don't have any moths flying around in our code, thankfully,
but what we do have to do is we have to pick out the errors so that our code will
run in the way that we expect it to without any errors.
So head over to the next lesson and try out your first debugging exercise.
To begin,
I want you to locate the day 1.2 debugging exercise.
And now, as you did before, go ahead and read through the instructions.
Be mindful that the output must match the example output precisely.
And when you hit run, this is the outcome you're looking for.
So there's quite a few things broken here,
but I want you to have a go at fixing each line individually and pulling out the
bugs from the code. So pause the video now and give that a go.
All right.
So how did that go? If you haven't got your computer in front of you,
if you're traveling, if somehow you can't access the exercise, just pause
and when you've got time,
then complete the challenge and then come back to the course.
It is so important that you actually do some hands-on stuff.
And I stress that this is the only way that you are going to become the rock
star coder that I know you can be. Let's take a look at the code below.
You can see that when we run our code as it is right now,
we get a new error.
And this is going to point to the first of many errors in this file.
And in this case, it tells us that on line three,
so this one right here, at around this position
or somewhere around here, um, as denoted by the little caret sign,
there is a syntax error. If we study this closely,
you can see that the code highlighting seems to be suggesting that all of this
is code, but this is somehow text. So what's going on here?
Well, notice that we've only got one double quote.
So it thinks that what comes after this is the text,
but what comes before it, it thought it was just a continuation of code.
So to fix this one,
all we have to do is add a double quote right here. That changes the text to the
color that we're used to and this fixes this line.
So if we run our code now, we should get a different error. And indeed we do.
The next one tells us that on line five,
so this one right here, there is an indentation error.
There's an unexpected indent somewhere around here on line five.
So let's take a look at line five and there you go.
There's a little bit of extra space between the print and the beginning of the
line.
So now that we've fixed that one, let's click run. And it will point to
another line of code that's broken. And in this case,
it says on line seven,
which is here where there's actually no code,
there's the unexpected EOF while parsing. What does this mean?
Well, if you're not sure,
then go ahead and paste it into Google and let's take a look at what people say
on Stack Overflow. So as this person,
very kind, Felix, um, has explained, this index error
unexpected EOF
while parsing means that the end of your source code was reached before all
code blocks were completed. What is a code block? Well,
this is a code block because it's a print function,
it has a beginning and it has an end. But what does this line not have?
Well, it's got two open parentheses,
but only one closing parentheses.
So the computer thinks that you are going to continue writing something and then
close it off at the end, which is not the case. In fact,
what has happened is we simply have an extra misplaced open parenthesis.
And now if we delete that and hit run,
you'll see that we have everything printed.
But at this point, notice how on line four
which is the line that we haven't fixed yet,
it prints string concatenation is done with the 'blank' sign.
Whereas in fact, it should say plus sign.
And even though we don't see any errors being printed in our console,
you'll see that we have an output mismatch because I'm expecting to see this
line, the String Concatenation is done with the "+" sign,
but here,
the output doesn't have that part. It's missing this part.
So there's one last thing that you need to debug. And that is of course,
on line four.
And what's happening here is we have this part being interpreted as a string,
this part being interpreted a string,
and it thinks that this plus sign is just us concatenating
these two parts together,
which is why it printed out like this. But in fact,
we wanted to print out is this as text down here.
So what we have to do is to change this outer apart from double quotes
into single quotes.
And now you can see when it highlights this part,
it's all the same color including the plus sign.
Now it sees this as a complete string,
and it's not looking at this as if it's code. So now if we run our program,
you can see the entire sentence being printed out.
So if you've completed the challenge and you've gotten everything right,
then you're now done with this exercise.
If you got stuck and you want to have a look at the solution, as always it's down
here,
and it might be useful to have a look at this page to see where you might've
missed something or where you might've gotten something wrong.
So I hope you enjoyed this code exercise. In the next lesson,
we're going to learn about a new type of Python function,
which is the input function. So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Coming back to our Repl.it,
the Day 1 printing repl that you should have from previously,
I want to talk about a different function.
So we've seen the print function and all the things that we can do to strings
and use the print function and debug it.
But what if we wanted to be able to enter some data?
So if we wanted to say,
ask the user 'what is your name?' And we run this code,
you can see that being printed,
but there's no way for the user on this side to be able to give our code some
data to work with. In order to do that,
instead of using the print function,
we're going to use a different function and it's called the input function.
And notice how as I'm typing,
code intelligence is already giving me some suggestions because it thinks it
knows what I might want and it's right.
So this is what the input function looks like. This is the name of the function.
And again, it's followed by some parentheses. Inside the parentheses
is the prompt that I'm going to give the user.
So when I run this code, it will say, what is your name?
And then the cursor will stay at the end of this line because it's expecting
some sort of input. If I give it my name, Angela and I hit enter,
then this piece of data has now been passed back into my code and it now
replaces this part of the code.
So I'm passing data from over here,
back to over here where I can use it in my code.
Now notice the difference here. It looks quite similar.
When we run print, you can see it says what is your name?
and then the code execution ends and we know it ends because it's showing us
this little orange arrow.
But notice when I run input instead,
I don't see the orange arrow.
My program is actually paused right now in order for the user to provide an
input and it's only when I've given the input and hit enter
does the program end.
The input function looks pretty much identical to the print function,
but instead of the word print,
it's just got the word input. And inside the parentheses,
instead of adding what text will be printed,
we're adding the prompt for the user to give them a hint as to what kind of data
we want. And then when you run this code, it will print out the prompt,
but then there will be a cursor. In some places you'll see it like a flashing
cursor, other places,
it'll just be a solid cursor ready for the user to type in some piece of data.
So what can we do with this data? Well,
we can use it inside our code.
Remember how I said once this line of code executes and I've entered Angela as
the response to this input,
then this part of the code gets replaced by whatever it is that the user typed
in. So in this case it becomes Angela.
And what I can do with it is let's say I wanted to print something like,
hello Angela. Well,
then I can simply write Hello + input and then I'm going to close it off
with another set of brackets.
So I'm going to change my layout instead of side by side,
I'm going to change it to stacked.
And this means that I've got my code at the top and my console at the bottom.
This way my line can go a little bit longer without it rapping.
Notice what's happening here.
This is the input function that I showed you earlier on and this is a print
statement.
So we've got this nested inside the other. And now when I run my code,
what happens is it asked me what is your name?
So I'll write my name and then when I hit enter,
this part is replaced by Angela and it gets concatenated to the word hello and
the entire thing gets printed out down here.
If you find this line of code difficult to understand and to wrap your head
around,
then I recommend heading over to a website called thonny.org and downloading an
application called Thonny. It's completely free and it's available for Windows,
Mac, and Linux. And once you've installed this application,
you can go ahead and paste your line of code here and click on this little debug
symbol. And then we can click on this button,
which is called the step into button to step into the execution of this line of
code
to see how the computer is evaluating this code here step by step.
So you'll see the first thing it tries to do is it will try to run this print
statement. It looks inside, these parentheses to see what it needs to print.
So the first thing is this, Hello,
and it turns that into a string and then it looks at the next thing after the
plus sign to see what it should turn this into.
And this of course is the input function. So as I continue stepping into it,
it's actually going to execute it.
So it's going to run this input function and show the prompt, what is your name?
So that's what shows up down here.
And now if I enter a value in here and hit enter,
then that value that I put right there replaces that previous input function
and is now held inside the print statement.
So if I continue stepping through this code then you'll see it concatenates all of
the pieces together, and finally it just ends up with a simple print
Hello Angela! And if I continue stepping into it,
you'll see that line of code executed until there are no more instructions left.
So if you prefer seeing your code, um,
run like this step by step so that you can see what's going on,
then I recommend giving this a go.
But because of how easy it is to share these Repl.it code bases so that we're
working from the same place, I recommend to do most of your coding here
and only if you get stuck to take a single line of code and paste it into Thonny
to see how it's executed step-by-step. As you're learning to code,
there's going to be new concepts covered.
There's going to be things that take a little bit of thinking before you can
understand it.
So what a lot of programmers love to do is they like to comment in their code.
Now,
you might've seen this already throughout the coding exercises and the solutions
I provided. But in Python,
if you wanted a line of text to not be considered by the computer at all,
all you have to do is add the hashtag or pound sign in front of your text and
this turns it into a comment,
so something that the computer will completely ignore.
So in here you can write code as much as you like, um,
but it won't be executed and when you click run,
you'll see that this is completely ignored.
What I recommend is whenever you come across a new concept in the course to make
a comment above it so that you can explain to yourself what's actually going on
in the line of code below. This way
the next time you come across this line of code and you're not quite sure what's
actually happening here,
you can have a look at the notes that you've written for yourself in your own
words and hopefully it'll re-jog your memory and make it much easier to
comprehend what's going on.
In addition to adding a pound sign manually,
you can also highlight a line of code or simply have your cursor on a line of
code and hold down command and forward slash if you're on Mac or control and
forward slash if you're on Windows.
And if you want to go back or undo your changes,
it's simply command +z or control + z. All right,
so in this lesson we learned about input function,
we learned about putting functions inside other functions and being able to get
user input from the console by using the input function.
So now I've got a coding exercise for you in the next lesson,
and if you've commented this line of code thoroughly and you fully understood
how it works, then you'll be able to breeze through the next exercise.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
All right. So again,
it's time to put theory into practice and get some hands-on action.
You should be able to find the day 1.3 assignment which is inputs.
Click on it and you will see the instructions for this particular challenge.
And the idea is that you're going to write a program
that's going to print the number of characters in a user's name. For example,
if I input my name, which is Angela,
it should output the number six because there are six characters in the word,
Angela. But remember you can't just print out the number six,
because when I'm checking for this code,
I'm going to try a whole bunch of different names as the input.
And you're going to have to use a little bit of thinking,
a little bit of Googling and also a little bit of messing around with the code
in order to get it to work. If you need any help,
there's a few hints down here for you. And if you really get stuck,
then you can take a look at the solution,
but not until you've really given it a go. And I really,
really want to know that you've tried hard.
And the whole point of these exercises is you sit there and scratch your head a
little bit and actually give it a good go.
So I'm going to stop talking now and I'm going to let you pause the video and
try to complete this challenge. All right, good luck.
Okay. So how did that go? If you get stuck, I want to tell you
the programmers secret to getting unstuck
which is go and grab yourself a cup of tea, have a quick break,
look at something else for a little moment,
think about something else and then come back to it. Well,
the tea part is optional. Well, at least if you're outside of England,
it's optional. So let's get started solving this challenge.
So the idea is that we're going to create a program that counts the number of
characters in any user's name.
And that name is obviously going to come through an input function,
and then we're going to use a function that calculates the length of a string
and we're going to send that out as the output.
The first thing we'll probably need is some form of input function right?
And the prompt that we're going to give the user is what is your name or
something similar that asks them for their name.
And I like to add a space at the end of the prompt. This way, when you run it,
you don't actually have that cursor straight next to the, um, the question mark
which looks a bit weird. But either way, once we've entered an input,
then this part gets replaced by that input
and we're going to do something with it.
We're going to calculate the length of that string.
Now using our eyes, we can obviously see that it's six characters long.
But what if you have a really a long name?
So let's go ahead and take a look at how we might figure out,
um, how to you get a function that calculates the length of a string.
I've actually included the Google search that you might need to use.
And so let's just paste that URL in here,
and you can see that we're searching for how to get the length of the string in
Python and we're trying to get results from Stack Overflow.
The first result is a question that seems to pretty match match exactly what we
want. And the answer from user 225312
tells us that you need to use the Len function. And the way that you use it
is by passing the string inside the parentheses.
Now this part might look a little bit different from what you're used to with the
equal sign and everything.
But I have confidence that if you mess around with this code,
you'll be able to figure it out.
Just like what we did with print or input,
the Len function also has a set of parentheses and it will work its magic on
whatever it is that we put inside the parentheses. If I just put my name,
Angela here,
let's just comment out the previous line, and I go ahead and print the result of
this and then I hit run, you can see that it prints 6. Now,
if I change that to Jack, then you'll see it prints 4.
So it will print whatever it is
the length of the string that I've put inside the Len function.
So we're getting close now, right?
Because instead of printing out a string that I've hard coded here,
what I want is to take the input that the user has given me.
So something like this. Now, if you want to,
you can actually add some spaces inside here just to make it a little bit
clearer to yourself as to what's actually going on because there's three
functions here. They are all nested inside each other.
So this is the first one,
this is the one that is going to get the input from the user and replace this
part with whatever it is that they type down here.
Then that string gets calculated using the Len function to get the length of
that string. And then that number will get printed by the print function.
Now let's go ahead and hit run and let's give it a go.
So let's try Jack, hit enter.
And it tells us that it's 4.
But using the same line of code,
if we try a different name Angela, then it prints out six.
How did you get on with this? If you got stuck,
then have a look at the solution Repl.it um,
where you will be able to find the code that I've written here and a little bit
of explanation as well.
The important thing is that you really play around with this code.
Try things and make it break and make it work and just get it to do what you
want it to do.
And remember that if you ever want to visualize these things and the order of
execution, then you can always use Thonny to see that.
So let's go ahead and step in.
You'll see that it goes through Len, input, and then it's going to carry out this
functionality input. I gave it my name, hit enter.
Then it puts that inside the Len function like so,
so now the next step is this part.
We're going to calculate the length of this string.
And as I continue stepping into it, you can see that become six.
And finally we're gonna carry out the final instruction,
which is just to print six down here. Again,
this can be quite useful just to visualize all the steps that are happening
if you want to.
Once you're done, head over to the next lesson and I'm going to talk to you
all about Python variables and how we'll be able to identify pieces of data in
our code. So for all of that, and more, I'll see you there.
Now in this lesson, I want to talk to you about Python variables and it's a
really, really useful concept. But before we get started,
first I want you to head over to the course resources and get hold of the Day
1 variables start Repl.it sandbox or you can simply type the URL into the
browser.
I want you to first go ahead and fork this starting code so that you can work on
your own version of it. Now once you've done that,
then the first thing I want to do is to take a look at this line of code that
you should have already. And when we run this,
we should be pretty familiar with what happens, right?
It will ask us for our name and when we hit enter, nothing happens.
But behind the scenes,
this name or this input has now been received by this function.
But once that's done, it kind of just disappears, right?
And there's no way for us to be able to refer to it in the future. Or is there?
Well, this is where variables come in really handy.
If I give the results of this action a name,
well then I'll be able to refer to it later on.
So at the beginning of the line,
I'm going to call it name and then I'm going to add an equal sign
and what this does is it assigns whatever it is that the user typed in as the
input to this prompt to a variable called name.
So now if I go ahead and run my code again and I enter a name,
now once I hit enter,
normally there's no way for me to get hold of this anymore, right?
But now I can actually go ahead and write print.
I'm going to print the value of this variable name.
So now if I run my code and I write a name,
hit enter,
you'll see that this gets printed and I can use this at any point in my code
just by referring to the name that's attached to this value.
So it's almost like we've saved the data from this action to a name.
And if you think about it, if you had a phone book, let's say,
and you just jotted down the numbers of people,
the next time you look at this,
there's no way for you to know who's number that is, right?
In a sense it's the same thing with the computer.
Even though we've inputted this piece of data,
there's no way for us to be able to refer to this data unless we give it a name.
So in our phone book, we might say that this particular number is associated with
the name James. And in programming we would call this name James a variable.
So we could write something like James equals and then his phone number.
And this means that in the future, if we ever need this piece of data,
we can just refer to it by its name,
the variable name of James. Now,
as the name variable suggests,
it's something that can be changed or can be varied.
So for example,
just because this name is set to something up here doesn't mean that I can't
change it later on. So to make things simple,
let's go ahead and delete the input function and let's just say name is equal to
Jack. Print name.
When I run that Jack is what gets printed inside the console because I'm now
referring to that piece of data by the variable name.
But if later on I decide to give this variable a different piece of data to hold
on to,
let's say Angela and I print name at this time point after I've changed it,
what do you think these two lines will print?
What do you think will first be printed?
What do you think will be printed second? Let's hit command + enter or control +
enter and see for ourselves.
So even though they're both printing the same variable, at this point when we first
call print, it's holding on to the value of Jack,.
But by line 5 I've now changed it so that it's holding onto the value of
Angela.
This makes it a lot easier when we want to write code like what we did before.
For example,
this is the line of code that we had before and we knew that we were going to
get a piece of data from this input function and then we would calculate a new
piece of data using the Len function
and finally we're going to print everything out.
Instead of having such a long line of code, which can be quite confusing,
we can, if we wanted to, use variables to store each of these steps.
So for example,
we could say that the name was equal to whatever the user inserted as the
input
and then when we wanted to calculate the length,
then we could set that variable to equal the Len function.
And then inside the parentheses, we'll pass in the name, the value, that's stored
in the name variable right here. And finally,
all that we need to do is to print the length,
like so. So in this case,
this data is stored under this name and then that data is what's going to be
used in order to carry out this function
and then the result will get stored in yet another variable
and finally that variable will be printed out.
So let's go ahead and run this code and type in my name.
So Angela and hit enter and it does exactly the same thing,
but now we've got all of these pieces of data all associated with a name that we
can refer to at any later point in our code. Now it's time,
you guessed it, for a code challenge.
And I'm going to get you to apply what you've learned.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right guys, it's time for your final coding exercise.
So click on day 1.4 variables.
Now the aim of the game is to switch the values of these two variables around.
So if we go ahead and run our code as it is,
it's going to ask us for a value of a. Let's call it five.
And then it's going to ask us a value for b. Let's call that a hundred.
And then when I hit enter,
what you want the code to do is to go ahead and print a equals 100 and b equals
five.
So, basically switch those values around. And you're going to have to write your
code in here. And it's really,
really important that you don't change any of the code here or the code here.
Now it's easy enough to simply just write print a equals b and b equals a.
But this doesn't test you on anything. This is not the solution.
This is wrong. Don't change the code here, don't change the code here.
Instead, all
you have are these lines where you can write as much code or as little code as
you need to achieve this end. And when you achieve it,
it should look something like this.
You type a value for a, you type a value for b. And when you hit enter,
they get printed out,
but switched around. Have a think about how variables work,
how they store data. And if you get really stuck,
imagine that you have two cups; one holds a cup of milk, one
holds a cup of coffee,
and you wanna switch the contents of the cup around. How would you do that in
real life? And then try and see if you can apply that logic to the code.
Pause the video now and give this a go.
All right. So I hope you didn't cheat
and instead you actually had a think about this problem. If you got stuck,
remember how I said
if you have a cup of coffee and you have a cup of milk and you wanna switch the
contents of the cups around, how would you do this in real life? Well,
you would probably get a third cup, right?
And then you'd be able to shift the contents around.
So that's exactly what we're going to do with our code as well.
We can create a new variable called c and we can set that to equal the value that's
stored inside a. And then later on,
we can get the variable a to store the value that's currently inside b.
And finally,
we're now ready to get b to store the value that was previously inside a,
which is now contained inside the variable c. These three lines achieve this
little switch rule that we've got here.
And this is one of the most common Programming interview questions that you will
come across. And the code is super simple,
but what you have to apply here is some logic.
And I usually think about real life examples
like the cups and I hope that helped you as well.
If this was at all confusing,
then have a go at trying this out in Thonny.
But if you got it right, then congratulations.
This was actually quite a hard challenge.
You had to think about a lot of things and think outside the box as well.
So give yourself a pat on the back if you've got it right.
If you didn't get it right,
then I really recommend to put this code inside Thonny and see how it's being
moved around so that you really,
really understand what's going on behind the scenes.
And then you can move on to the next lesson where we're going to talk about some
of the rules around naming variables. For all of that
and more, I'll see you there.
Now when it comes to naming your variables,
you can pretty much call it whatever it is you want.
So instead of calling this name,
I could have just called it n and I could have called this l and as long as I'm
consistent.
So if I wanted to get the length of N then I would have to change this as well.
And if I wanted to print out L then I have to change this as well.
But there's a couple of rules that you should probably follow.
And the most important one is to make your code readable. Because if you come
back to this in six months, 12 months,
N and L is not going to have a lot of meaning for you.
So try to make sure that it actually makes sense to you.
And if you want to,
you can actually have multiple words in the name of your variable.
So for example, if you wanted to call this username,
then you would write the word user and then you would separate each of the words
with an underscore. But you can't have a space in between.
This is not valid code and if you try to run it, you'll get a syntax error.
So the name of the variable has to be one single unit and in order to separate
words in Python, we use the underscore.
Now if you want to use numbers in the name of your variable,
you can. So for example, length1,
length2. But they can't be at the beginning of the name of the variables.
You can't say 1length or 3length.
That will generate a syntax error as well. Finally,
there's certain privileged words that we use, for example,
the names of our functions like print and input.
And it's usually good practice to not use them as the names of your variables
because you can see that syntax highlighting gets messed up because it thinks
that is actually input function you're trying to create.
And even though often when you run your app, it might not have any issues,
this is really bad practice because it's very confusing.
So try to make sure that all the names of your variables get highlighted,
like the other variables in the same color. Now,
the final thing to remember is that if you decide to call your variable this
particular name, n-a-m-e, and at a later point you make a typo and you spell it
wrong, so maybe instead of name you said nama,
this is not going to work and when you run your code you'll get what's called a
name error because it says this name is not defined. And the idea is that you
would look at where the error is, line 2, print nama and you'll see,
Oh that's not right. It's meant to be spelled n-a-
m-e. So you'll have to go and fix it in order for your code to work.
Now remember that this is not because Python is doing any sort of spell-checking
for you. It's like, Oh, that's not how you spell name. No. In fact,
if you decided to call this nama and you, later on, used it as name,
there's no problems, there's no issues, no errors,.
As long as it's consistent,
this is the name that's associated with this piece of data. Later on,
when you want to use this piece of data, you use this name to refer to it.
And as long as these two spellings are identical,
then the computer doesn't care at all.
So when you get a name error in your code,
you now know it's probably because you've misspelled or mistyped one of the
variable names somewhere in your code. Now in the next lesson,
I prepared a quiz for you where you'll get to select which variable names are
valid and which ones are not good practice.
Have a go at that over on the next lesson.
All right, guys, it's time for the final project of today. So the program that you're going to be
building looks a little bit like this. And you can check it out if you head over to this link, either
by typing it in or heading to the resources page and clicking on the corresponding link.
But essentially, it's a band name generator. And it asks you for a city that you grew up in and the name of your
pet.
And then it combines those together and gives you the name of your band.
There's a couple of things to note here.
Firstly is notice when this input got triggered, the cursor actually showed up on a new line.
So if I run this again, you can see it says "What's the name of city you grew up in?"
And then the cursor is on the next line.
And what I want you to do is to go ahead and head over to this starting project.
So this is the URL
and it's also, of course, in the course resources.
And once you head over here, you can fork this code and complete your own version.
So there's a couple of steps in here as hints.
If you don't want to see these and you just want to go by the end project, you can also just delete
all of these.
But the important thing is once you've completed this project, it should work exactly the same as the
one that you see here.
And in order to do this, you're going to have to apply everything that you learned today, including
printing inputs, variables, new lines, string manipulation, debugging and a whole lot more.
So this is a time to grab yourself a cup of tea  or coffee , pause the video and tackle this final project.
All right, guys, I hope you gave that a go and you were able to complete it. If you want to see how
I've implemented it or if you want to just check to see if you have any errors or if there's something
that you're unsure about, then continue watching and I'll go through the solution with you.
The first step is to create a greeting for your program, in our case, it says "Welcome to the band
name generator."
So that's exactly what I'm going to create.
And we print these messages using the print function.
So I'm going to say "Welcome to the band name generator."
And this when I run, it will just print that message.
Now, the next step is to ask the user for the city that they grew up in. So in order to get some input
from the user will need, of course, the input function.
And we're going to ask them using the prompt, which goes inside the parentheses: "Which city did you
grow up in?"
So now when I hit run, it's going to ask me for the city that I grew up in and I'm able to add a reply
like so.
Now, that data is just going to be lost to thin air unless I capture it and I give it a name, so I'm
going to have to create a variable to hold onto the data that the user inputted.
So we'll just call that "city" and then add the equal sign (=) to assign whatever it is that the user typed
in to this variable name.
And now I have access to the city variable and I can print it or use it later on if I want to, like so.
Now, the next step is to ask the user for the name of a pet.
So we'll call that variable "pet" and we'll assign it the value that the user inputs for:
"What is the name of a pet?"
Now, step 4 is to combine the name of the city and the pet and show them their band name.
Now, there's quite a few ways of doing this, especially if you look around on the Internet.
But the way that you learn in today's lessons is using string concatenation.
So we're going to do that.
So we're going to use a print statement and tell them "Your band name could be..."
And then we're going to add the name of the city and then add a space and then add the name of their
pet.
So now when we run our code
it will ask us for the name of their city and then the name of a pet, and then it should combine those
together and show us the name of our band.
Now, the final step is that the input cursor should show on a new line like this.
So here's the cursor.
But here's the input.
Just so that you get a bit of space and you're not typing it in directly after the prompt here like
what we have.
So how do we do that?
Well, you learned about modifying strings by creating a new line using the \n.
And we can add that both to the end of the city input and the pet input.
And now when we run our code, you'll see that the cursor now shows up on the next line and our program
looks a lot better.
So there you have it.
This is how you solve this boss challenge and this is how you create the band name generator project.
So I hope you had fun with me today, learning Python and a lot of the fundamentals of Python.
And tomorrow I've got another jam packed module of really awesome tutorials and challenges and projects
for you to sink your teeth into!
I'm looking forward to seeing you tomorrow, so I have a rest now and let your brain  work on the things
that you learned while you sleep.
And I'll see you here bright and early.
Good night and see you tomorrow.