Hey there! Welcome to Day 10 of a 100 Days of Code
and today we're gonna learn about functions with
outputs. Previously
we've already seen the other two flavors of functions; a plain function and
also functions with inputs. But in today's lessons,
we're going to be using the skills that we've learned
and we're going to be extending our knowledge of functions to build a
calculator app. I think at some point in every program has lives
they will have built a calculator app.
So if that hasn't already happened to you, then today is your lucky day,
because that's exactly what we're going to be making.
So it's a simple text base calculator,
and we can start off by writing a number and then picking one of the operations:
plus, minus, multiply or divide. So I'm going to divide this by two,
and then it shows us the full calculation, 5 / 2 = 2.5.
And now we can continue calculating with the answer from the previous step,
or we can type 'n' to start a new calculation. Let me type a 'y'
and maybe I'll do 2.5 + 6
and now I get 8.5. By the end of the lessons today,
you'll have understood how functions really work,
how you can use them to reduce redundant code and how you can provide inputs to
functions as well as providing outputs. Once you're ready, head over to the next
lesson and let's get started.
To begin
the first thing I want to talk about is more on functions.
So we've already seen a couple of things that we can do with functions.
The first thing I showed you was how to create a very simple bog-standard
function using the def, the name, the empty parentheses,
and then the colon. And then within the body of the function,
you can do a bunch of things which will be carried out every single time you
trigger or call the function like this.
And the first type of function basically just helps you reduce the amount of
code you have to write
when you have instructions that you want to execute repeatedly. Now,
the next type of function we saw actually had something inside the parentheses
and this something is an input which can be passed over when we call the
function. So in this case, 123
is the argument which gets passed into this parameter called something
and then it gets used within the body of the function.
The second type of function, the functions
which allow for inputs, gives us the ability to modify the code in the function
and to get it to do something different each time
depending on what input was passed in.
We're now onto the final sort of flavor functions
and these are functions
which allow you to have an output
once the function is completed.
We start off with a simple function, and in this case
you'll notice that even though I could, I'm actually not giving it any inputs.
The inputs and the outputs are completely separate from each other.
So this is a normal function that you've seen many times now. And within the
body of the function, I'm going to do some piece of calculation. Let's say
I'm going to calculate what is three times two,
and then save it to a variable called result. Now, once that's done,
I can use the output keyword, which is return.
And then after that keyword, I can put whatever it is
I want to be the output of this function. So in this case,
the output is the result.
And what that means is when I call this function later on and it runs,
then it will go ahead and output this result
and it replaces this line of code where this function was called.
Now that result is held in the code where the function was called and I could
save it to another variable. Result, of course, equals
3 * 2 and that means this output now equal 6.
So this is what the code might look like. Somewhere I would define my function
which has an output, which you can tell by the return keyword. Now,
at some other point in my code, I decide to call that function
and once that function executes, that return or whatever is outputted replaces
the function call. And at the very end,
it means this variable output will store whatever the output is.
So in this case, output would be equal to 6.
The way that I like to think about functions with outputs is almost kind of like
a machine, right?
If you had a machine where in goes some empty bottles and after some processing
or some inputs, outcomes a bottle filled with milk.
So in this case, this function has an input, the empty glass bottle.
It has an output, the glass bottle filled with milk and in the middle,
there's some processes or some code that's being executed to create this change.
This ties together all the things that we've learned about functions.
So now head over to the Day 10 starting replit,
and go ahead and fork your own copy of it. Now,
once you have your own copy of it,
we're going to create some functions with outputs of our own.
Let's start off by creating a new function
which I'm going to call format_name
and the reason is because this function is going to take a first name and a last
name, and it's going to change those inputs,
even if it was lowercase or if it was all caps,
it's going to change it into title case, something like this
where the first letter is capitalized in each word. To begin,
I want you to create this function and then go ahead and add two inputs to it.
One could f_name, so first name and another code l_name,
which is the last name. Pause the video and give that a go.
All right.
So all we have to do to add inputs to our function is just to put the names of
these parameters inside the parentheses.
So now our function is able to take these parameters as inputs
whenever this function gets called.
The next step is we're going to convert these strings that gets passed in,
so it could be something like this, all lower case.
It could be all capitalized, or it could be kind of random, right?
Like some are capitalized, some are not.
But we're going to make it all uniform,
so all of these are going to end up like this. And to do this,
we can search around in Google and you might come across a similar question in
Stack Overflow: How do you convert a string to title case in Python?
They have an example and it's trying to do exactly what we're trying to do.
If we take a look at the answers,
you can see that somebody is helpfully pointing to this title function.
So you take a string and then you write .title and then afterwards,
the string gets transformed and every word now starts off with a capital letter.
And if you want to know more about how this title case works,
then you can click on that link in title and then have a read through the Python
documentation. Once you've read through that,
go ahead and modify this Fname and Lname so that they end up being both in
title case. Pause the video and give that a go.
Right?
All right.
So we want to go ahead and take this Fname and then write a dot and then write
title to convert it to title case.
Once we've done that, then we're going to do the same with the l_name.
And if we go ahead and actually print these out,
and of course, in order for the function to actually execute,
we'll have to call the function. So I'm going to put two inputs in here,
one which is going to be, um, just angela, all in lowercase
and then the second one is going to be ANGELA all in up a case.
And now when I run this code,
you'll see that the result is they both get converted to title case.
In essence,
this part of the code becomes whatever the previous value of f_name is converted
to title case. You might have spotted already that this title function actually
has an output.
It returns a version of the string where each word is title cased.
Instead of simply just printing this,
we can also capture it inside a variable.
Let's create a new variable called formatted_f_name and also
formatted_l_name.
Now what's happening here is we are transforming this input f_name,
turning it into title case.
And then once this function executes,
it has an output and that output replaces this part of the code
and then it gets stored inside this variable.
Now we can go ahead and print the final version of our function
which is going to use an fstring to take the formatted Fname and then add a
space and then print out the formatted Lname, like this.
Now, if I start out with my first name
but all in strange sort of casing,
and then my last name in all caps,
let's go ahead and hit run and see what happens.
You can see that my first name gets converted to title the case,
my last name gets converted to title case
and then that result is stored in formatted Fname
and this result becomes stored in this Lname,
and then they get printed and formatted, like so. Now
instead of printing this result out,
we could also return it as well. In the same way that this title function
returns the output, replaces this part of the code,
we can also do the same with our format_name function.
So let's delete the print function and go ahead and use return
instead.
Now this formatted string becomes the output
and as we mentioned before,
what happens with functions with outputs is this output replaces the part of the
code where the function was called. Now,
if this is the string that we want to print,
then all we have to do is just to save the output
which replaces this part of the code inside a variable like this.
And then all we have to do is just go ahead and print that formatted string.
As you can see, when I run the code, the same thing happens. Now you can,
and you might've alternatively,
just taken this function call and put it straight inside the print statement.
That works exactly the same way.
And we can visualize this using Thonny.
If I go ahead and paste everything we have inside the editor and go ahead and
run debug,
then we can step into and see what are the steps that happen.
So the first thing
when this line 6 gets executed is it tries to call this function, format_name.
So it passes in these two inputs.
And we're now within the function where we have access to these two inputs,
Fname and Lname.
Now the formated_f_name becomes the title-cased
version of the first name and the same thing happens with the last name.
So we now have a formatted_f_name and a formatted_l_name
and that is what's going to be returned as the output.
Now, once that's completed, that output replaces
whatever was in between the print statement,
which is where we called this format name function
and this is what gets printed into the console. As I mentioned before,
we've actually already been using functions that we didn't create that have all
of these functionalities, right? For example,
the Len function takes an input and has an output.
The input is going to be a string,
my name again, seemed to be really obsessed with my own name.
So now this line of code is going to run this built in len function,
calculating the number of letters inside this input that we've given it.
And then it's going to return the result as an output,
which we can now capture inside a variable.
This is the inputs, this is the function
and once this is completed,
the return or whatever it is after the return statement is going to replace this
part of the code.
Then that result or output then gets stored inside of this variable.
So this return keyword is really the most important thing in order to create a
function that has an output,
because everything that comes after it is going to replace where the function
was called. In the next lesson
we'll take a quick look at the return keyword in more detail. Specifically,
let's see what happens
when we have more than one return statement in the same function. All right.
For all of that and more, I'll see you there.
In the last lesson, we looked at functions that return some sort of value.
We created a function called format_name that returned a string. In this
lesson
let's see what happens when a function has more than one return statement.
When the computer encounters a line that has the word return on it,
then it knows that this line is the end of the function.
If I add a line of code after the return keyword, notice what happens when I run
this code. It doesn't ever get executed.
And this has because the return tells the computer that this is the end of the
function and you should now exit the function.
You can actually have multiple return keywords within the same function,
and you can even have a empty return keyword.
So just the return keyword without anything afterwards.
So for example,
we could check whether if the fname is equal to an empty string or the lname
is equal to an empty string. So this case,
it means that when we called it format name, maybe we didn't give it any inputs.
For example, let's say that instead of just calling the function as it is,
we actually used the input function.
So what is your first name and what is your last name?
Now
what happens is it'll ask us for a input and it will take these two inputs
and then call that function and return the formatted version to be printed.
So now in this case, it's possible that we might have just not given it
a first name or not given it a last name and it probably shouldn't go through
these lines of code. But at the moment, it's still running this function
trying to get the title case from the empty string and then printing it.
And I can prove this to you by just adding an extra word in here.
So again, empty first name, empty, last name,
and then it's print result and then of course nothing.
How can we get it to bypass the rest of the code if the user typed in an empty
first name or last name? Well,
we could use what I mentioned before, an early return.
So we could just write return without anything afterwards
and this is going to escape the function.
So it's basically going to terminate the function early.
Now this time, if I leave an empty first name and last name,
you'll see it prints none because there is no output from this to print.
Now, of course,
it's probably safer to actually return something that tells the developer what's
actually going on so we can give a meaningful message,
like return, something like this.
So this way we can catch the cases when something is not quite right and then
exit our function instead of wasting time for it to continue working on
something that we don't want it to do.
We've covered a number of things in today's lesson
and I want you to combine this with your existing knowledge to tackle the
challenge in the next lesson
to get to grips with this concept of functions with inputs and with outputs.
Head over to the Repl.it day 10.1 Days in Month
coding exercise. Here,
you'll notice that I've copied over the is_leap year function that we created
a while back in another coding exercise. Now,
the first thing I want you to do is to modify this function so that instead of
printing leap year or not leap year,
we're actually just going to return true if it is a leap year and false
if it is not a leap year,
because we're going to be using that function in the next function that you're
going to modify,
which is a function that's going to tell you how many days there are in the
month that you specify. So for example,
if I was to call days_in_month and passing in the year as
2022 in the month as 2,
then I should get an output of 28,
as in there's 28 days in February, 2022.
This is the reason why we need to know about leap years
'cause in a leap year, there's actually 29 days in February.
You're going to combine the output from this function
as well as this list of days_in_month
in order to modify this function to output the number of days in a month
when this line of code is called.
It's really important that you don't change any of the code below,
but you are going to modify this function and add more lines of code in it.
Take a look at the hints if you get stuck,
but otherwise, pause the video and give it a go.
All right.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to change each of these print
statements so that it returns a Boolean instead.
So this one should return true, and this one should return true. Now,
when it's not a leap year, I'm going to return false
instead. This way,
basically, when we call this function, is_leap, passing in a year,
then we'll get the output as either true or false.
So we can now use that inside our function days_in_month.
But before we do that, we need to get some inputs.
We need to know what is the year and what is the month the user is interested
in. So that is going to be passed in using these positional arguments.
We're going to ask the user to input a year and input a month,
and then each of these pieces of data gets passed into here and here,
which will end up inside our function ready for use.
The first thing I'm going to check is if the year is a leap year.
How are we going to do that? Well,
we're going to use our function here, is_leap, passing in that year,
and then the output will be checked using the if statement.
Remember that the way that if statements work is that if something is evaluated to true,
then it's gonna carry out the line of code below.
But if it was evaluated and it turned out to be false,
then it's going to skip this line of code.
So instead of using true or false, or if a three is bigger than two,
we're going to use the function, is_leap, and pass in the year that we got as an
input. So this way,
when a year is tested in this function,
then it's going to output either true or false
which is going to replace this part of the code because it's the output from
this function. So now if that output is true,
namely it is a leap year,
then we're going to check if the month they were interested in was the month of
February. So if the is_leap year
is true and the month is equal to 2, well,
in that case,
then we're going to return 29 because there's 29 days in February in a leap year.
If this is the case,
then this function is going to end right here when it returns 29.
But if this is not the case,
then it's going to bypass this line of code and we can output the number of days
in a month for any other condition, so when it's not a leap year.
We can go ahead and simply just use the return statement to tap into that list
called month_days
and we're gonna pull out the value at the current month
that's being requested.
But remember that because lists start counting from zero and the month that the
user's going to be interested in doesn't start from zero,
so if they're interested in January then this month,
instead of being 1, should actually be 0 to pull out this 31.
So then we actually have to subtract one from it.
So now if we test the code and we enter the year
2022 and the month of February,
then we'll get the correct output, which is 28.
That solves the challenge. Now, some of you, I know,
might have gone even further because we talked about using the return statement to
catch out any situations where there might be invalid inputs.
So you could,
if you wanted to, also add an if statement that checks
whether if the month is greater than 12 or if the month is less than one. In
these cases,
then it's actually an invalid input and you could just return invalid month. And
you could of course do the same thing for the year.
And this way it ensures that our function doesn't progress unless we have clean
data.
But this, of course, is not necessary to complete the challenge because we're now able
to figure out the days in the month using this leap year function's output,
and the output from our days_in_month function. In the next lesson,
I'm going to address something that a lot of students are thinking at this
point. And the question is why return at all?
Why not just simply print the outputs instead,
because this way it seems to end up doing the same thing, right?
It's still going to print this down here.
And if we just added a print to this return and a print here and got rid of this
one, then it would still behave exactly the same.
This is exactly what I want to talk about in the next lessons.
So, see you there.
Hey guys,
I want to quickly spend a few minutes talking about a concept in Python known as
Docstrings.
Docstrings are basically a way for us to create little bits of documentation as
we're coding along in our functions or in our other blocks of code.
Now, previously, we've seen that when we use other functions
like the ones that were ready to find by Python, like the length function,
you can see that as soon as I open up my parentheses,
I can see this little piece of documentation that tells me what this function is
actually going to do, namely return the number of items in a container.
So how can we create the same kind of documentation for the functions that we
write? Well, we would do that using docstrings.
The docstring has to go as the first line after the declaration.
So here we've defined the name of our function, the inputs,
and then after the colon, the first indented line will be the docstring.
But that's not it.
You also have to use three of these quotation marks and it's in between these
three quotation marks that you can write your documentation.
We could write something like, well, what is this format_
name function going to do?
What would we want our future selves or another user who's using this function
to know about it? Well,
it's going to take a first and last name and format,
it.
Notice how with docstrings
you can actually write strings that are multi-line. Normally,
if I was to create a normal string, let's say, I dunno,
a = "A String".
If I hit the enter key,
I'm going to get a warning because it's going to interpret this as the end of
this line.
And it won't see this closing quotation mark as being a part of this string.
But when we use a docstring, we can write as many lines as we want
and it will be interpreted all as the same thing altogether,
as if it was fitted onto the same line like this.
Now that we've added our docstring, it's time to see what it looks like. Now,
if I call this function format_name, and I open up the parentheses,
you can see that the text we wrote here now gets populated in the documentation.
It takes the first and last name and formats it to return the title
case version of the name.
So this is a way for you to be able to start documenting your functions and
giving each function a little bit of an explainer.
Now you can also use this as a multiline comment.
So notice how when we write a comment and we go to the next line
it becomes code again.
Now you can in fact use something like this
where you just comment as many lines as you like
and this will be interpreted as a comment
as long as it's not assigned to anything. So for example,
if I create a variable
then this is now a piece of code. Because it's a little bit confusing
the official Python guidance is actually to avoid multiline comments like this.
What is actually much easier is to just write your multiline comment and then to
highlight all of it and then to hit command + forward slash or control + forward
slash on Windows.
That's a much better way of differentiating the comment from actual pieces of
code.
Have a go at adding docstrings to the other functions that you've created and
see it show up when you call your functions.
So we're now ready to tackle our final project of the day
and that's building up a calculator program.
If you head over to calculator-final.appbrewery.repl.run,
you'll see how the final project works.
We get to enter a number and then pick an operation and then pick the next
number and it will calculate the result. Now,
at this point,
we can either continue to calculate with the result from the previous step.
So let's multiply it by two, alternatively,
I can type N and that clears the screen and lets me start out a new
calculation,
like so. Now,
because a lot of the concepts that are covered in this project are actually
quite difficult,
I want to go through this project together and while we're building it up,
there's also a lot of small challenges along the way that I want you to tackle.
Once you're ready, head over to the calculator starting file and fork
your own copy to get started.
Right?
This calculator is going to have some different functions that it can do.
So for example, it will start out with a add function,
which takes two inputs and n1 and n2,
and then it's simply just returns n1 + n2.
This is pretty simple. This is all that there is to
the functionality of adding, takes one number and adds it to the other one.
And I want you to go ahead to create the functions in the same format for these
other mathematical operations. So subtract,
multiply, and divide. Pause the video and complete this challenge.
Right?
All right. So subtract is as simple as add.
So we'll just call it subtract. We pass in again
two numbers, n1 and n2,
and we'll return the outcome as n1 - n2.
And for time sake, I'm just going to copy and paste these for the last two
and I'm going to rename them multiply and divide.
And then when numbers are multiplied,
we use the asterisk sign and the number of divided we use the forward slash.
So now we have four functions; add, subtract, multiply, and divide.
And what we want to do is we want to somehow store these functions inside a
dictionary. Here's another challenge for you.
Can you create a dictionary where the keys are
each of these symbols that we've used to add or subtract or multiply,
and the values are just the names of the functions.
So pause the video and try that now.
Alright, let's go ahead and create this dictionary. Now we start out of course,
with a set of curly braces and as I mentioned,
each of the keys are going to be the symbols for the operations and the values
are going to be the names of the functions. So we've got plus,
and then we've got subtract, multiply,
and divide. So now we have this dictionary,
let's go ahead and save it inside a variable called operations.
Now this dictionary is going to act as the means in which we're going to call
these functions. At some point down here,
we want to be able to tap into the operations and then pass in the key that we
want, so for example multiply,
and then store this as the function that we want.
That means we can then call this function and then pass in one number and a
second number
and this function is currently going to act as the multiply function. Now,
if we change this to plus,
then this function is now going to act as the add function.
So now the next thing we're going to do is we're going to create a variable
called num1
where we ask the user for an input to say
what's the first number.
And there's number of course has to be converted into an integer.
Now, the next thing to do is to ask them for the second number,
so this is going to be pretty much the same as this line of code,
other than the word second. Now,
the next thing is we want to ask them which of these operations they want to do.
Firstly,
we want to be able to loop through this dictionary and print out each of these
keys.
And then we're going to ask the user to type out one of them so that we can
figure out which operation they actually want to do.
Go ahead and try to use a for loop
to loop through this dictionary of operations and print out each of these
symbols. All right,
now we're going to use a for loop
and we know that when we use a four loop with a dictionary,
it will loop through all the keys rather than the values or the actual entries.
We can say for each symbol in the dictionary operations,
go ahead and print out the symbol. And of the moment
if I run this code, you'll see that it'll ask us for the first number,
the second number,
and then it's gonna loop through that list and then print out all the
operations.
So now we're ready to go ahead and ask them for a operation symbol. Pick and
operation from the line above.
So they're going to see all of these keys and then they get to pick an operation
like so. And that symbol is now going to be saved within this variable.
So now we can go ahead and take that operation symbol to pick out the value
that's associated with it. For example, if in this case
the user chose the plus symbol,
then we're gonna pick out the add function.
And then just as I shown you before,
we want to use that add function to add these two numbers together.
But of course,
if they picked a different symbol then we want to be able to carry out the
different operation. See if you can get this calculator to work so we can print out
the num1 and then the operation symbol,
and then num2, and finally the equal sign
and then the answer. See if you can make this line of code work and make sure that
it works whenever you choose any of these operations,
and it will calculate it using these numbers that you input.
Pause the video now.
All right.
The first thing we need to do is to get hold of the calculation function
and this is going to be done using the operation symbol.
So we're going to tap into our dictionary of operations here,
and then we're going to use the square brackets to pass in
the operation symbol.
Now we can use this calculation function as if it were any of these functions.
And that's of course, based on the choice the user made here.
So we can now say calculation function and we can pass in the num1 as the
first input, num2 as the second input.
And of course our function all have a return value.
And so this part is going to be replaced when the code runs with the actual
answer. So we can now save that inside a variable called answer,
and then that will get sent over here and we can now test it out.
So let's try adding three plus five.
So I'm going to use the add symbol and we end up with three plus five equals
eight. Now what about something a little bit more complicated?
Uhm, 45, 78 and we'll choose multiply.
Now, I think in reality that it actually makes more sense to put num2
after the user's enter the operation symbol so that you actually end up with a
better user experience like this. You can pick the first number,
pick the operation, and then pick the second number.
We've managed to get our calculator to work. But in this lesson, I want to talk about something else.
I want to talk about the difference between printing something to the console over here versus returning
something as an output from a function, because a lot of students get very confused at this stage and
they think, well, why don't I just print this results instead of returning it?
What's the actual difference and why would I use return?
That's what I want to address in this lesson.
At the moment, we've got these four functions, and when we call it, we pass over some inputs and
then once we get a hold of the output, we go ahead and print it out into the console.
Now, in the current state of the calculator, it's hard to see the difference between the print and
the return.
But here's a question.
What if we wanted to take the output that comes from calling this function and instead of just storing
it inside a variable and then printing it out, what if we want to pass it as an input to another function?
Let's say that at this point we decided, you know what, we're going to ask them to pick another operation.
And then let's ask them to pick another number.
And finally, let's go ahead and get the calculation function again based on this new operation symbol
that they picked. And then we're going to calculate the new answer
but this time, instead of passing over the calculation function, we're going to pass over the answer
that we got back from this step.
So num1 is now the previous answer
and the second number that's going to be the input is going to be num3.
At this point, when we're calling this calculation function, we're passing over the results or outputs
of this calculation function, and that is going in right here,
and then the third number goes in as the second input.
What basically has happened here is I've taken the output from this function,
so in fact, I could replace this answer with this output,
and I've taken that as the first input into the calculation function and then num3 as the second
input
and then using all of this in order to get the answer.
Let's call this first_answer,
and let's call this second_answer just to differentiate the two answers.
And now I'm going to write a slightly different print statement. In this case, the calculation is done
using the first_answer and then the operation symbol and then the num3 that was inserted at
this point in order to obtain the second_answer.
So now if we give this a run.
Let's do 3 + 2. Now, in this first step of the calculation, we get 5 as the result.
So now if I want to pick another operation, let's I want to multiply 5 by 3.
Then I'm going to take this 5, which is the previous answer,
I'm going to say multiply, and then I'm going to provide the next number, which we'll call 3.
And now it takes the previous answer from the last step and puts that in as the first number in the
calculation, multiplies it by 3 in order to get the final answer.
In this case, what I'm able to do because I have an output from my calculation function up here because
each of these all return their answer, I'm able to take the result from that calculation and plug it
right back into another calculation function using the result of that function call as the input to
another function call.
And I'm only able to do this because I'm using the return statement and because I have outputs from
my functions.
This would not be possible if I was using a print statement.
In the next lesson, we're going to reorganize our code and introduce a while loop so that we can continue
making as many calculations as we want to.
In the last lesson we made it possible to reuse the result of the first
calculation.
The answer for the first calculation became our input for the next calculation,
allowing us to chain the calculations together. However,
this created quite a bit of repetition in our code
and it limits our user to just two calculations.
Let's allow the user to chain as many calculations as they want to.
And I want to throw this over to you as a challenge,
so can you use a while loop and the input function to achieve this?
Ask the user
this question, type 'y' to continue calculating with the previous result or type 'n'
to exit.
If the user types y then your calculator should allow them to continue chaining
together calculations with the previous answer.
If they type anything else the program should exit for now.
I'll give you a few seconds to pause the video before I show you the result.
All right. So the easiest way to solve this is through the use of a while loop.
So let's say that after we've asked for the first number and we've shown them
all of the different symbols that they could possibly pick from,
lets set a flag called should_continue.
And we'll set that to start out as true.
Then we can create a while loop and while it should continue as true,
then we're going to perform these things.
Now we want to change some of this text so that it's a little bit more reusable.
Let's say pick an operation,
and what's the next number instead of the second number.
So now we have a first number, we have a operation,
we have a second number and then we pick out the function from that dictionary
of operations and we get our answer.
So I'm going to change this back to answer and we're passing in num1
and num2 into the calculation function. Now,
once this line has been printed,
everything that occurs afterwards is pretty much repetition.
And instead we're going to ask the user to type y-- type y to continue calculating
with the answer from the previous step.
Let's make that an fstring and let's check what this is actually equal to.
So remember that the input function is also a function that has an output,
which is a little bit then zen,
but the output of this function is whatever the user typed in.
So if they typed in y then this part is going to become y. That's where we're
going to check.
So we're going to check if the result of the input from the user is equal to y,
then in that case that means we should continue and it should repeat back.
But when it loops back,
we want to make sure that num1 is equal to the answer from the previous step.
So we can say if this is true,
then num1 is going to be set to equal the answer.
But on the other hand, else, if they typed anything else,
so we could say maybe type y to continue calculating with answer or type n to
exit.
So now if they type y then the answer is going to be set as the num1 back at
the start of this while loop
so that this num1 becomes the answer from the previous step.
But if they typed n then we want this while loop to the end.
So we're going to change the flag should_continue to false.
So now let's give that a run.
Right?
Let's say the first number is five.
Then we're going to add three to five and then we're going to type y to
continue. So now we get to pick another operation,
so let's multiply, um,
eight by two and we get the result from the next step and we can actually keep
going until we're basically done, right?
So we can take the 16 and we can divide it by four.
But if we type 'n' on the other hand,
then our program ends and we see the prompt once more.
And that's the solution to the challenge,
but it's a little bit sad to just exit, right?
Because with a calculator more often than not,
what you want to do is to start a fresh calculation where you get to determine
the first number and the second number once more.
If the user didn't want to exit
but if they wanted to start a new calculation,
then how can we get them to go back all the way up here so that they provide the
num1 as a fresh input? This is a little bit tricky
and in programming, this concept is known as recursion.
It's basically the idea that you could have a function that calls itself.
So let's define a new function called calculator and this function takes no
inputs and has no outputs.
But all of this code that we've got here so far is inside the calculator
function. To begin when we start,
we have to call the calculator function in order for it to find the place where
this function was defined and to actually carry out all of these instructions.
Now,
the next thing we get to do is a little bit interesting because when the user
types no,
and says that they don't want to continue calculating with the previous answer
but instead they want to start a new calculation,
what we want to do instead of just exiting the while loop,
we want to call the calculator function because what this is going to do is it's
basically going to take us all the way back up to the beginning where we get to
enter a new input again.
And remember that once you reach the end of a function,
everything gets reset to the beginning. So should_continue becomes true again
and this while loop will continue working.
So let's try running this new version.
We've performed a calculation and now we want to start a new calculation,
so I'm going to type n. And now I get to again define the first number again.
This recursion basically happens because we're calling this calculator function
within the calculator function.
Essentially the code runs and runs and runs until it reaches here
and if these conditions are met and this calculator function is called,
then it goes and finds the calculator function in order to call it once more.
But now you have to be quite careful with while loops and with these recursive
functions
because let's say that instead of having all of this code and some checking code
to determine when I should call calculator,
if I actually just called calculator within calculator,
then this is going to be a infinite loop.
It's just going to keep going back and forth.
The calculator function calls the calculator function,
which goes back up and calls and it goes around and round around until forever.
Again,
be careful and make sure that there is some sort of condition that needs to be
met in order for this function to call itself. In the next lesson,
we're gonna add the finishing touches to our program and also fix a bug that you
may have already spotted at this point.
Now that we've pretty much completed all of the logic and functionality of this
calculator, it's time to add in the bells and the whistles,
including adding in the calculator logo and also checking for any bugs.
Adding the calculator logo is pretty simple.
You've done this loads of times before.
All we have to do is import it from the art module,
and then we're going to print it at the beginning of our calculator function.
So this way
when we get to the end and the user wants to start a fresh calculation,
we'll also show them a logo again. Now the next thing to notice,
this is a bit of a bug that you might've seen or not.
But what happens if we try to enter a number with a decimal point?
Let's say we want to calculate 4.5 multiplied by 2.
Our program has already crashed
as soon as I've entered 4.5 and hit enter. As a challenge,
can you diagnose what went wrong and fix this bug? I'll give you a few seconds
to pause the video before I give you the
solution.
Alright. Here's the solution.
The bug goes back to our lesson on datatypes.Notice how it's giving us an error
and it's pointing to this line
number 26. Line number 26 takes this input
which is a string and converts it into an integer. But of course,
a number with the decimal place shouldn't be converted into an integer.
We should actually hold it as a floating point number instead. This way
we're able to perform more accurate calculations.
So instead of just 4 times 5,
we can do 4.5 times 5.5, for example.
So instead of using int here, I'm going to change that to float
and I'm going to do the same here for num2. Now, when we hit run,
I can actually perform calculations using numbers with decimal places,
but I can also use numbers which are whole.
So let's multiply 2.5 by 2, the answer is 5,
and you can see that all the numbers are being reported to a greater level of
accuracy, meaning we have numbers after the decimal point.
And this is all because we converted that int to a float.
Now that there's a lot more features that you could add to your calculator.
You could add a square root capability, you could add exponent capability,
but the important thing here was really for you to see how functions that
provide outputs are really useful
when you come to a more complex program where you can take the output from one
function call and pass it into the next function
call as an input.
So this output can be reused in different parts of the code.
And this not only allows us to reduce repetition and also make our more reusable
and more modular,
but also it gives us the flexibility of performing more actions after a function
has completed. Now,
we're going to be using a lot of the concepts that we've learned here today in
tomorrow's capstone project. A lot of things I've explained,
including things like the recursion
where we're calling a function within its own definition or things like setting a
flag using a wall loop to continue
some piece of code execution is all going to come in really,
really handy tomorrow.
So make sure that if there's anything that you don't understand here
that you review it and you're comfortable with what the code is doing before you
proceed. That's all for today and I'll see you tomorrow.