Hey, it's Angela here. Congratulations on making it through the
first 10 days. Today, I've got something very special lined up for you,
our first capstone project. Today
we'll challenge you to apply everything you've learned so far into one big
project.
You're going to need to dig deep and apply all your Python skills for this
capstone project. But by the end of the day,
you'll have built an awesome blackjack game to enjoy.
This is probably going to be one of the hardest things you'll build yet,
but at the same time, the end result is also going to be the most fun.
The final project you're going to be building is blackjack.
And if you had over to
247blackjack.com or search for any other free online blackjack game,
you can hit play and you can click deal for the dealer to give you some cards.
The game is really simple. Essentially
you're trying to get as close to 21 as possible and all of the cards which have
a Jack, a Queen, or a King count as 10.
So you're adding these two cards up 5 + 10 equals 15.
And you're trying to figure out if you can risk getting another card.
So I'm going to click hit, and I'm going to get one other card
but that takes me over 21 and so the dealer wins.
So this is the game that we're trying to create.
This is what your version of Blackjack is going to look like.
Now the user interface is a little bit simpler,
but it's just as fun to play with.
So our first two cards are a 9 and a 10,
and it also shows us one of the computers cards.
Now I'm already on 19,10 + 9.
I'm close to going over 21.
So I'm going to type 'n' and end the game right there.
I end on 19,
the computer ends on 18 and because 19 is greater than 18,
that means I win.
Have a go at playing the final game by going to black-jack-final.appbrewery.repl.run.
But once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson so that we can actually build this game ourselves.
For all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson. Have fun.
All right.
Let's talk about the mechanics and the program requirements for the Blackjack
game that you'll create. For those of you who are not familiar with the game of
Blackjack  also known as 21,
I'm just going to spend a few minutes to go through the rules with you.
Blackjack is a game that's played using cards.
And the goal of the game is to add up your cards to the largest number without
going over 21. If the cards in your hand
add up two more than 21, then it's called a bust
and it means that you lose immediately.
And it doesn't matter how much you've gone over 21, as long as it's over 21,
then you lose. Now the way that the cause are counted
is that all the cards from 2 to 10 count as their face value.
So a six is a six and a nine is a nine, et cetera.
But the Jack, Queen and King each count as 10 and the other special card is the
Ace.
Now the Ace can either count as a one towards your total,
or it can count as an 11. And depending on whether,
if you've gone over 21 or whether if you're under 21,
you can decide which value you want your Ace to represent.
Let's play a sample game. Let's say that the dealer over here got
a 10 to begin with and you got a queen which also counts as a 10 to begin with.
So these
are the first cars that are dealt and both of these cards are revealed.
And then the dealer deals another card to each of you. Now the dealer's
second hand is concealed so you can't work out what their total is,
but you can see your own card.
So the moment we don't know what the dealer has,
it might be 10 plus anything,
but we know that our score is 13, 10 + 3.
At this point you might ask the dealer for another card.
So now you have three cards and luckily it adds up to 20 without going over 21.
But there is also a possibility that you might've gotten a card that would have
pushed your total over 21 at which point you now lose.
And it doesn't matter what the dealer has in their hand,
you've already lost because you've gone over 21.
Now let's say that we got lucky and our total adds up to 20.
Now at this point we say we don't want any more cards
and the dealer reveals their hand. If. like in this case,
they end up with 20 and we have 20,
then we end up in a draw.
So whenever your score equals the dealer score,
then you will draw rather than win or lose. Now,
if on the other hand, the dealer ended up with an Ace,
which we know can count as an 11 and they actually scored higher than us.
They have 21 and we have 20, well, in this case, we would lose.
Now the rules also state that if the dealer ends up with a hand that's smaller
than 17, so 16 or under,
then they must take another card.
Those are the basic rules of blackjack,
but I'd recommend that before you get started head over to the link that's in
the Blackjack starting file and have a few games of Blackjack
just so that you can see for yourself how it actually works and how you win and
how you lose.
And then head over to the final version of the completed project and play our
simplified version of Blackjack. This way
you'll see what the end result is that you're trying to create
and it will be easier when you're creating the code yourself. Now,
as I mentioned,
we're going to try and keep our version of Blackjack a little bit simpler,
and we're going to assume a couple of things.
The first thing is that the card's that we're starting with comes from this
list. You'll notice that I've got 2 through to 10,
all represented in the list.
And then I've got Jack, Queen and King represented as tens as well.
So this means that the 10 has four times the probability of occurring compared
to the other cards.
Now the Ace is going to start off being represented as 11,
and it's going to count as 11 until the user goes over 21.
Now finally, we're going to assume that we have an infinite deck.
So it means that when a card is drawn from the deck,
it's not removed from the deck. Whereas in a real casino,
they have maybe six or eight decks of cards. When a card is drawn,
then there's less probability of that same card occurring again.
And this is how professional card counters,
the people that the casinos hate the most,
actually go about trying to optimize and improve their chances.
But in order to keep things simple in our game,
we're not going to deal with things regarding probability or removing cards from
the deck.
We're going to assume that each of these cards in the list have equal chance of
occurring. If you head over to the App Brewery Blackjack
starting project,
you'll see each of these rules written out in more detail.
Take a look at it so that you're aware what our house rules dictate.
Now, if you scroll to the very top of the Blackjack project,
I've given you four tracks. So just as when you start a video game
you have the choice of normal, hard, extra hard or expert,
it's the same in this project. You can limit yourself to using only one
hint if you are at expert level in Python.
You can only use hint 1 and 2
if you want an extra hard challenge and maybe a little bit of a cry at the end,
there's also hard and normal. So I'll leave the choice up to you.
And if you scroll down, you'll find all the hints listed in here.
Now I recommend everybody, no matter your experience,
everybody should try out the Blackjack game and also look at how the final
project is supposed to work.
But then I've got other things such as a list where I've broken down the program
requirements. You know how we always say, when you have a big problem,
always try to break it down into smaller pieces.
Now you can of course create this list yourself by exploring the game,
exploring the final project,
and then writing your own to do list of things that need to be coded up.
Or alternatively,
you can look at the one that I've created inside hint 2. Inside hint 3
I've created a flowchart for you
which takes the to-do list and breaks it down into a flowchart where you can
look at the logic in more detail. Now, of course, as always,
it's a good idea to create your own flowchart
using a tool like draw.io or using a piece of pen and paper.
But if you need help,
it's there for you and you can download the PDF and read through it.
Now the rest of the hints
will go through how to solve this project in even smaller
bite-size chunks. Depending on your own level of Python at the moment,
choose your own difficulty level.
But I just want to say before you get started that this project is difficult and
I wanted to give you a bit of a challenge and to push yourself so that you get
stronger.
But it will inevitably be moments where you will have doubt and you will be
wondering, what am I doing? I don't understand anything. And in this moment,
I want you to look yourself in the mirror and tell yourself that you got this.
You can do it. And that remember that I'm here rooting for you.
I believe you can do it.
You've got everything that you've learned so far will enable you to do it.
There's nothing new in this challenge.
You just have to put all the pieces together.
You have to push through the difficult parts and maybe sleep on a problem and
think about it and then come back to it. But I believe you can do it. Once
you're ready, pause the video,
head over to the starting project and give it a go.
And once you're satisfied,
then head over to the next lesson and I'll walk through the solution with you.
Right. So how did that go?
I hope it went really well and you've managed to complete it all by yourself.
If you got stuck, I really recommend just having a sandwich, have a cup of tea,
take a break, and then come back to it.
You'd be surprised what your brain can do when it just has a little bit of rest.
But I want you to make sure that you've really given it a proper go before you
come here and watch the solution.
Cause I'm going to walk you through the solution step by step in case there are
little bits or something that you didn't understand or something that you want
to check. But I really,
really hope that you've managed to tackle most of this yourself. All right.
So without further ado, let's get started coding up our Blackjack project.
Hopefully you've already used hints 1, 2 or 3,
and I'm going to get started with hint 4 and build up our Blackjack project
step-by-step. Now the idea of the hints 1, 2,
and 3 is to get you to create these small to-dos of your own so that you
can have practice breaking down the problem into a list and then breaking it
down into a flowchart and then breaking it down into smaller bite-size to-dos.
So let's start out with the first one,
we have to create a deal_card function that uses the list below to return a
random card and 11 is going to be the Ace in this deck.
So let's get started by forking a copy of this repl and we're going to go and
create our deal_card function.
Now this function is going to contain these cards,
so I'm going to go ahead and paste it in, make sure it's indented
so it's inside the function. And now I'm going to use these cards to randomly
pick one out of this list. So to do that,
we can of course import our random module.
And then I'm going to use random.choice to pick a random card from my list
of cards. And then this of course has an output,
this random.choice
so I'm gonna save that output, namely the random card, inside a variable called
card.
And then finally we're going to return this chosen card as the output.
So that's step 4 done.
Now let's move on to step 5.
So we're going to deal the user and computer two cards each using the deal card
function, and very helpfully
the hint tells us that we can start out with a blank
user_card and a blank computer_card list.
So we basically just have to add two cards to
each of these lists. To do this,
I'm going to use a for loop and I'm going to use the range operator to run this
for-loop twice.
So you've seen this syntax before when we talked about for loops and I've got an
underscore here because we don't actually need this particular variable.
All we need is for this loop to run twice
and this code is going to achieve that. Every single time this loop runs
we're going to get a new card by calling deal_card.
Now remember that deal_card has an output,
it outputs a random card. So if you want,
it's actually quite helpful to add some documentation to this.
So we could say returns a random card from the deck.
And now when I write deal_card
you can see that the doc tells me that this function is going to return a random
card from the deck. So that random card is going to replace this function call
so we can capture that data by storing it inside of a variable.
So we'll call that new_card and set it equal to the output from the function
deal_card. Now,
the next thing we're going to do is we're going to add this new_card to the
user's cards.
So at the moment, it's an empty list and all we have to do is say user_cards
.append
and then the object that we want to add to that list is going to be the new_
card.
Now some of you might be tempted to instead use the plus equals.
You might want to write something like this; user_cards += new_card.
And I want to show you what actually happens when yourun this.
cause this is a really common error.
We get a trace back and we get a type error.
It tells us that the int object is not iterable and it highlights this line 49
as the reason for the error. So what's going on here?
Well,
this += is actually shorthand for writing the extend function.
Now you can see that the extend function is something that extends a list
by appending elements from the iterable. So what does this mean? Well,
it means that whatever you put inside this parentheses,
it has to be a list itself. For example,
if this new_card was a list of cards,
so maybe just the first dealt card and another card
or even just it by itself inside a set of square brackets
which turns it into a list, well then if we run this code right now
we no longer have any errors and if I convert this back to what you saw before,
which is using the plus equals, we also have no errors.
But when you only want to add a single item, not a list, to an existing list
then you have to use append. So hopefully you didn't have this issue,
but if you did,
this is the reason. Now that we've created these two lines,
you can see that it's a little bit redundant because we're creating this new
card variable just to hold the output from this function.
And then we're immediately putting it into this list using the append.
So instead we can actually just get rid of the middleman and put deal_card
directly inside the append.
And this does exactly the same thing in a single line of code.
Once we've done this for user_cards,
we'd probably want to do the same thing for the computers cards.
So it computer_cards.append, and then we call deal_card again,
remembering the parentheses.
So we've got a total of three parentheses at the end and this way we deal a new
card and that new card gets appended to the end of this
list.
All right. So now let's tackle hint number 6.
We're going to create a function called calculate_score
that's going to take a list of cards as an input,
and then it returns the score after calculation.
And it tells us that if we get stuck,
we can look up the sum function to help us.
So let's create a function called calculate_score
and this calculate_score is going to take some cards as an input,
and then inside the body
it's going to calculate the total of all the cards in this list.
So if we take a look at the sum function in Python,
the way that it works is you can put a iterable,
so like a list inside the parentheses as an input
and then it's going to add up all of the items in the list
and it's going to return the total. Back in our code
we can simply write sum, and then inside these parentheses
we can pass over the cards and we can return this value as the output.
Basically
if we had cards equal to a list with 1, 5,
3,
4, then the sum function is going to end up being equal to 1 + 5 +
3 + 4, which is going to be equal to 13.
And then that will become the output of this function.
So now let's move on to hint 7.
A Blackjack only happens when
we have a hand with only two cards and those cards have to be an Ace and a 10
value card. In our deck
we know that an Ace is represented by 11 and we have a number of 10 value cards.
So there's a number of ways that we can check for this Blackjack.
One of the ways is by checking to see if the 11 is in our deck of cards,
and then we can combine that with an and to check if the 10 is also in our deck
of cards. And finally,
we can check to make sure that we've got a hand size of two.
So we can check that the length of our cards is equal to two,
and this would represent this logic: a hand with only two cards, an Ace
which is represented by 11 and a 10. Now, on the other hand
we could actually also simplify this because a hand with only two cards that
must contain an 11 and a 10, we can
instead of checking for both 11 and 10, we can check to
see if the total,
so that if we summed the cards and if this was equal to 21,
then it would be exactly the same thing, right? 10 + 11 is 21
and we've still only got a deck of two. In this case
what we want to happen is we want to return zero instead of the actual score.
So this way we can indicate that the user or the computer has got a score of
Blackjack. That's hint number 7 sorted,
let's move onto a hint number 8. It tells us that inside calculate_score,
we should check also for an 11, which is an Ace.
If the score is already over 21,
then we should remove the 11 from the cards and we could replace it with a one,
because remember that an Ace can count as an 11 or 1.
So in the beginning, when the user's score is very small,
then we probably want to count it as an 11.
But once the user goes over 21,
then we probably want to change it and count it as a 1 instead
so they don't go over and they don't lose. Let's first write
the if statement.
So if there is the 11 inside our deck of cards and the
sum of the cards, so the total_score, is already over 21,
then we want to do something about it.
And the hint tells us to look up the append and remove functions.
So we've already seen the append function many times,
and we know that it just adds a single element to the end of the list.
Now the one that we haven't used a lot of is the remove function
and this we'll search for the first instance of the given element and removes it
out of the list. This is kind of what we need to do.
We need to go ahead and remove the 11 from the list of cards. So we can write
cards.remove, and inside the parentheses,
we use the 11 and then we do cards.append,
so that we end up adding a 1 instead of the 11.
This way we remove the 11 and replace it with a 1.
And hopefully our cards will now take the user to below 21.
Now let's move on to a hint 9. So we want to call
calculate_score at some point in our code
and if the computer or the user has a Blackjack
or if the user's score is over 21, then the game is going to end.
This might be a good time to start tidying up our code a little bit,
because we've got our function over here,
the calculate score function.
And remember that you can only call a function after it's been declared.
So for example, if I wanted to call this function over here,
then I actually can't.
I can't say calculate_score because it hasn't yet been declared.
So instead,
what I'm going to do is I'm going to take this function and I'm going to move it
to where we dealt our cards and I'm going to collapse some of these functions so
I can see my hints and my code a little bit easier.
So now that I've moved my function to above the line where I want to call it,
it's now become valid code.
And this is the place where I want to call it because it's only after I've dealt
the user and the computer some cards can I actually calculate their scores.
Firstly, I want to calculate the score using the user's cards.
So this list of cards from the user gets passed into this function and uses
all of the logic to output some sort of score.
And then I'm going to store that score in a variable
which I'll call user_score.
And I'm going to do the same thing for the computer,
so computer_score equals calculate_score. And remember,
it's always helpful to add a little bit of a docstring to tell ourselves and
other programmers what this function does. Let's quickly summarize it.
So this function is going to take a list of cards and return the score
calculated from the cards.
So now when I open that parentheses,
I know that I probably have to pass in my list of cards in order to get back the
score.
So let's put in the computer_cards in as the inputs,
and now we've got the user_score and the computer_score.
So this score could equal zero
if they got a Blackjack or it could just simply be the value of the cards that
they hold all added up together.
Now that we've called calculate_score
we also want to make sure that if the computer or the user has a Blackjack
or if the user's score is over 21, then we have to end the game.
Let's write our if statements. If the user_score is equal to zero,
or the computer_score is equal to zero,
or the user_score is greater than 21, then in this case
we're going to tell the game to end.
So we could create a new variable called is_game_over
and we start out with false, of course. But then when this happens,
we're going to change that variable to true instead.
Our is_game_over variable is just a simple boolean.
It starts out as false and when certain conditions are met,
then we change it to true. Now at the moment, our program is not finished.
So it was not really obvious how we're going to be using this is_game_over
variable. But we're setting ourselves up for the next steps.
Now that we're tracking if the game should end,
we can look at this value to determine what to do next.
So that's hint 9 completed. Let's test our code and see how everything works so
far.
I'm going to add some print statements here so that I can see what the user's
cards are and what the user's score is. Using an fstring
I'm going to show your cards, so the user's cards, and the current score.
And I'm also going to print the computers first card.
Remember when I first explained the rules of Blackjack,
the dealer will reveal their first card
so you get a little bit of a clue as to what kind of hand they might have.
So in here, we're going to insert the computer's cards
and we're only gonna pick out the first item, so that the one at index zero,
and we do that using a square bracket after the name of the list.
Now let's give our program a run and see if it actually works.
The first thing that prints is a list of our cards.
So in our hand,
we have a 2 and we have a 6 and 2 + 6 added together
of course makes the score of 8.
And then it reveals to us the computer's first card, which is a 10.
Now we can be reasonably assured that our code is working.
And it's a good idea to regularly test your code so that you don't wait until
the end when they're a lot of problems
and you don't know which part of the code is responsible.
Now let's move on to hint number 10.
It says that if the game has not ended ask the user
if they want to draw another card. If yes
then use the deal card function to add another card to the user's card list.
If no, then the game has again
ended. Over here in the if statement
we can add an else because if the game hasn't ended, as in
they haven't gone over 21 or nobody's got a Blackjack,
then we're going to ask the user if they want to get another card.
I'm going to use a input
and I'm going to ask the user to type 'y' to get another card,
otherwise type 'n' to pass.
And I'm going to save this input inside a variable, which I'll
call user_should_deal.
Now we can check to see if this variable is equal to 'y'. Well in that case,
we're going to add another card to
the user's card list by doing the same thing that we did in the beginning
where we dealt two cards to each player by saying
user_cards.append and inside the parentheses
the thing that we want to append is the output from deal_card.
So just a quick check to make sure you've got all the parentheses there and then
we're ready to address the else. If they didn't type 'y',
then that means they don't want another card. Well, then in this case,
the game has again ended.
So we can say is_game_over equals true.
Let's test this out as well.
We got 7 and 11 with the current score of 18.
If we type 'y' hopefully we'll get another card.
And we did see that prompt and we saw something happen,
but our program then promptly ended. Let's take a look at the next step.
How can we get our game to repeat itself?
So hint number 11 tells us that the score will need to be rechecked with
every new card drawn
and the checks in hint 9 needs to be repeated until the game ends.
Notice how we've got this flag, is_game_over, which is set to true
whenever the game ends. It starts off being false
and what this means is we can actually create a while loop
which basically keeps on calculating the user_score
and the computer_score, makes all of these checks
which are in hint 9,
and then repeats itself until the game ends.
Let's go ahead and do that. After all the initial setup,
we're going to create a while loop and the while loop is going to be active
until the game is over. So we can say
while not is_game_over,
then go ahead and carry out all of these instructions.
So calculate the user_score, calculate the computer_score,
check that nobody's gone over 21 and nobody's gotten a Blackjack.
And if the user wants more cards than they should, if they don't then the
the game is over. So let's run this and try it again.
Our cards are 10 and 10 which probably means we shouldn't get another card
cause we're already so close to 21, but I'm going to be daring and press
'y' anyways. And it tells us that our cords are now 10,
10 plus two.
So we got an extra card and that takes up our score to 22.
That worked perfectly.
So now let's go back and tackle the next part. Hint
number 12 says once the user is done, it's time to let the computer play.
The computer should keep drawing cards as long as it has a score less than 17.
So the while loop is responsible for dealing with when the user wants to keep
drawing cards. But once that's done,
then we can tackle hint number 12,
which is how does the computer actually play? What is its strategy?
Well, we know that the computer has to keep drawing cards
as long as it has a score of less than 17. But, of course,
0 which represents a Blackjack is also less than 17,
but we don't want it to draw a card if it has a Blackjack.
We can represent this logic using a while loop; while the computer_score is not
equal to zero and the computer_score is less than 17,
then in this case we want to keep drawing cards.
We're going to take the computers cards
and we're going to use the append to add a card by dealing another card to the
computer.
And then we're going to recalculate the computer_score so that it updates
and this while loop is evaluated on the latest score.
So the computer_score is going to equal calculate_score using the computer's
cards.
And that means that the updated computer_score is equal to the return value from
calculate_score. So that's hint 12 complete. In the next step
we're going to start comparing our player's hand with the dealer's hand.
See you in the next lesson.
At this point, we've created two while loops.
The first while loop is for the user so that they can continue taking cards
and the second while loop is for the computer so that the dealer can follow
their strategy. Now it's time to tackle hint 13
where we create a function called compare.
We pass in the final user_score and computer_score,
and then we compare the scores to see who has won, who has lost,
or if they have a draw.
So remember that in order to call a function,
it has to be declared before the line we want to use it.
So let's go back up and after hint number six
where we had the last function,
let's add this hint here and create our compare function here.
This compare function is going to take the user_score and also the computer_
score and it's going to compare these two scores.
If the user_score is equal to the computer_score,
then we said this should mean that it's a draw.
So we'll return some sort of message that represents this.
But elif or else if the computer has a Blackjack,
so the computer_score is equal to zero, well in this case
we should return that the user has lost and the opponent has a Blackjack.
And then we go through this list and we add in all of these other conditions.
So I'm gonna speed it up a bit.
Now for the final condition,
it says that the player with the highest score should win.
So we can write an elif that compares the user_score against the computer score
and we're basically saying if the user_score is greater than the computer score,
well, then that means that the user wins.
But if that's not true and because we've covered everything else,
we now have the final return, which is you lose.
Now,
remember that if, elif, else statements are evaluated from top to bottom.
Even though if the computer score is a zero which is a Blackjack
which is obviously much less than whatever score the user might have,
because it's going to return at this point and it's going to exit the function,
it will never get to this comparison if this is already true.
If you get confused about how if elif and else works
especially the order in which you add the conditions,
have a look back at the lesson where we talked about this in more detail.
This might be a good time to revise that concept.
But now that we've completed our compare function,
we're going to use it at the end of our code here
because this is a time that the user is done drawing cards,
the computer's done drawing cards
and now we can call that compare function
and pass in the user_score and also the computer_score.
So this should hopefully give us the final result
as a piece of text. Let's run the code as it is and see what happens.
We started out with a 3 and a 6 making a 9.
Now we know the computer at least got a 10, so let's add another card.
So now we have a score of 11 with 3, 6, and 2,
so we can still keep going. And luckily we've managed to get a total of 21.
Now we're pretty much invincible I think. So if I go ahead and hit no
cause I don't want to take any more cards, then let's see what the result is.
So it tells us we win and a big smiley face.
So we can probably give the user a little bit more information,
like revealing the final deck; what the computer got, and what we got.
I'm going to go ahead and create some other print statements above this one.
Maybe I'll tell the user that your final hand is this,
and the final score was...
And then let's reveal to them the computer_score,
and then finally we can print the user_score and the computer_score to
tell them who won, who lost, or whether if its a draw.
In this deck, we've got 14, so let's add another card to it.
Unfortunately we went over because we've got another 10.
So our final hand is 10, 4, 10
and the final score was 24. The computer's final hand was 21,
lucky them.
So we went over and we lost. If we wanted to play another game because we are
Blackjack addicts,
then we want to give the user some sort of means of doing this right?
And that's what the last hint addresses.
So we're going to ask the user if they want to restart the game.
If the answer is yes,
then we're going to clear the console and start a new game of Blackjack and also
show the logo from art.py while we're at it.
Let's go ahead and add a input and we can ask them,
do you wanna play a game of Blackjack? Type yes or no.
So remember that this entire function is going to be evaluated and the result or
the output is going to replace this part of the code.
So we can say that while the input is equal to y
then we're going to keep playing the game.
The game is all the code between hint 5 and the end where we compare.
So if we actually put this inside a function by
indenting it over and then creating a function here called play_game,
well then we can actually call this function,
play_game, every time the user types 'y'.
Now we don't want to clutter up our screen with all the previous games.
So before we call play_game,
we also want to clear the console. And to do that
we obviously have to import the clear function from the replit module.
So from replit
import clear, and now we can call this clear function to clear the console in
here after each game.
And then we can call play_game so that the code in this function gets repeated.
And we also said that at the beginning when we play game
we're going to show the user the logo from art.py.
So let's go back and import that as well.
So from art import logo,
and then at the beginning of every game, we're going to print our logo.
That's all there is to this project
and now let's run it one final time and see the whole thing in action.
Do you wanna play a game of Blackjack? Yes.
And it reveals our beautiful Blackjack logo.
It tells us the cards that we have, so current score of 11.
I'm going to take another card. I'm on 21, which is perfect.
So I'm going to pass now. And it tells me that my final hand was 21,
the computer's final hand was 17 and I win. And now I can play another game just
by typing 'y' again.
And I can keep going on and on playing my game of Blackjack.
So I hope you had fun at building this game with me.
I know this was a really difficult project and I know that some of you would
have probably had some issues,
but I really hope that you persevered and you got through it in the end. And
through the process
you've managed to apply a lot of the things that we've learned in the last 10
days.
This is a good time to review the concepts you've learned and have a think about
what you might need to revise or revisit so that you're really,
really strong on all the concepts
and you're comfortable to continue on to the next 10 days. Now,
if you want to take a look at the final code that I've got here,
then just head over to repl.it/@appbrewery/blackjack-final
and you'll see all the code that I went through with you just now.