The first thing I want to talk about is a concept known in programming as Scope.
And this scope is something that we've actually come across already in our
programming, but I wanted to leave it until we've seen functions,
we've seen if and while loops, different types and blocks of code,
before we start talking about this really important concept. Now,
if you want to visualize this concept,
imagine you have a house with a fence around it and you plant an apple tree
inside your garden. Think about who can access those apples.
Just you and your family right? But what if instead,
you had an apple tree in the neighborhood by the sidewalk, for example.
Well, this is kind of free for all. Anybody can go and access those apples.
This is a starting point for how to understand scope.
Head over to the App Brewery Day 12 start Repl.it and go ahead and fork your own
copy of it.
Take a look at the code that's in the starting file in the main.py and try to
understand what it's doing. First
I create a variable called enemies and I set it to equal 1.
Then I create a function called increase_enemies,
and I try to set that variable to 2. Finally,
I call my function triggering all the lines of code inside,
and now I want you to predict what will this print statement print in the
console and what will this print statement print?
And it might not be what you expect it to be.
So I would expect that here I've got a variable which is equal to one.
When this function is called,
this variable enemies should now be equal to two.
So when it's printed down here from outside my function,
this should be equal to two, and this should also be equal to two.
But look at what happens instead.
I get enemies from inside the function equal to 2,
but from outside the function, it's equal to 1.
So what's going on here? To really understand this
we have to understand the concept of scope. And scope is a really,
really important thing in programing.
You see it in every programming language and although its a little bit different
between the programming languages,
it all goes back to that concept of the apple tree being within a fence or
outside a fence.
So let's take a look at some other examples before we come back to solve this
problem.
The first thing to think about is a concept called local scope.
Local scope exists within functions. So for example,
if I was creating a game and I had a function called drink_potion
which is somehow going to strengthen my player,
well, maybe it would have a variable that's created inside the function.
So it could be something like potion_strength
and I could set that to start off where the value of two.
Now in this case
if I was to go and print this variable potion strength from within the function,
notice I'm indented here,
and of course I need to call this function for that to happen.
Notice what happens when I run the code. It's equal to two.
That's what we would expect, right?
But notice what happens if I try to print the potion_strength from outside the
function here. This firstly gives me an error
right when I'm writing it inside the editor. And when I tried to run it,
it gives me an error inside the console. And the error is a name error
and it tells me that the name potion strength is not defined. Clearly I've
defined it here, but why can't I access it outside the function?
Well, this goes back to the concept of local scope.
When you create a new variable or indeed a new function inside another function,
it's only accessible,
you can only use it when you're inside that function because it has local scope.
It's only valid within the walls of this drink_
potion function.
What if we wanted it to be accessible outside the function? Well,
now we need to think about something called global scope.
The only difference between global scope and local scope is where you define or
where you create your variables or your functions.
So let's say we have a different variable.
Let's say that I created a variable called a player_health and it starts off
being equal to 10. Now let's say later on I have the same drink_
potion function, and this potion has strength of 2.
So now inside my function drink_potion,
if I wanted to print my player_health
even though it wasn't defined within the function, this is perfectly possible.
And if I call my function
drink_potion and then run the code as it is,
you will see 10 being printed.
So this has a global scope. It's available anywhere within our file because it
was defined at the top level of the file. Now, when I say top-level,
I don't mean physically at the very top of the file.
I mean that it's not within another function, like potion strength here because
this is defined indented inside a function.
So this is a local variable
whereas this is a global variable. And global variables are available within
functions, no matter how deep it gets nested
and it's also available outside of functions.
This concept of global and local scope doesn't just apply to variables.
As I alluded to before, it also applies to functions and basically anything else
you name. This is a concept called the Namespace.
So we defined this variable player_health, we define this function
drink_potion.
Anything that you give a name to has a namespace and that namespace is valid in
certain scopes.
This concept of scope applies to basically anything you name.
If I was to nest this function drink_potion inside another function,
let's call it game. Well,
this drink_potion now has local scope within the function game.
So this is why this line is now erroring out because it can't actually see inside
this function. So now in order to call this drink_potion,
I have to be within the four walls of the game function.
So whenever you give name to anything, a function or a variable,
you have to be aware of where you created it.
Now it's easy to notice where you've created functions, we have the def keyword,
right? But when you create a variable
that's the first time that you give it a name and you set it equal to something.
And where you write that line of code defines the scope of that particular
variable. Here it's outside of every other function,
whereas here it's inside a function actually nested two levels deep.
So it has a local scope to this function.
Now, unlike some other programming languages,
if you've come from say C++ or Java,
there is no such thing as block scope in Python.
What this means is that if you were to create an if statement,
say if 3 > 2,
and if you were to create a new variable inside an if block or a while loop or a
for loop, basically any sort of block of code that's indented,
this does not count as offence.
It still has the same scope as its enclosing function,
or if there is no enclosing function then it has global scope.
So let me show you a full example. Let's say we had a list of enemies,
so the enemies could be skeletons, zombies, or aliens. So now,
if I was to define a game level, right?
Like the level that the user is currently playing at,
let's say they're on level 3.
And I create an if statement and I check if the game_level is less than level
5, well, in that case, I want to create a new enemy,
but I don't want the enemy to be too difficult to beat.
So I'm going to pick from the list of enemies and I'm going to pick the first
one. Notice how,
even though this new enemy is a variable that's created within this
if block, if I go outside the if block
so I'm not indented at all anymore, and I try to print this new enemy,
this is perfectly valid code. And if I run the code,
you'll see skeleton being printed.
But notice how as soon as I embed this within a function,
so let's define a new function.
And now this line error is out because within the function there is local scope.
So now this new enemy is available anywhere within this function,
because blocks like if, while, for, all of these blocks of code with colons and
indentation, they don't count as creating a local scope.
So in order to print this new enemy,
I actually have to be within the boundary of this function,
which means my code has to be here.
The most important thing to remember from this is if you create a variable
within a function, then it's only available within that function.
But if you create a variable within an if block or a while loop or a for loop or
anything that has the indentation and the colon,
then that does not count as creating a separate local scope.
Coming back to our original example.
I want to talk more about the global scope and the concept of modifying
something within the global scope. Here we have enemies,
which is a variable that has global scope,
and here we have a function which creates a local scope.
Now we think that we're tapping into this variable and setting it to two.
But in fact, we're actually creating a completely new variable
that's entirely separate from this one.
And this is why when we printed it here,
it showed it was equal to 2. But when we printed it here, it showed
it was actually equal to 1. If you want to make this a little more obvious,
I can call this a skeleton and I can set this to be a zombie.
And when I hit run, you can see again, this prints zombie,
this prints skeleton,
because these two variables are actually entirely different things.
And we're not changing this right here at all,
we're just creating a new variable that has a local scope.
Now it's usually a terrible idea to call your local variables and your global
variables the same name. But in this case,
what we actually wanted to do was we wanted to modify this variable,
we wanted to do something like maybe += 1. And notice how
as soon as I write += 1,
that my editor starts going crazy and tells me that this local variable enemies
is defined in an enclosing scope is referenced before assignment.
What does that mean?
It means that the editor thinks you're trying to tap into a local variable that
you defined somewhere around here.
And then you tried to modify it by adding one to the previous value,
but you actually haven't defined it. What we wanted to do though,
is we wanted to tap into this variable and change it here.
In order to do this,
we actually have to explicitly say that we have a global variable
which is called enemies that's defined somewhere outside of this function.
And that is the enemies that we want to use inside this function.
So it basically takes that global enemies into the function and allows you to
modify it. Without this line of code
we cannot modify something that is global within a local scope.
Now there's a reason why it's so difficult to modify something that has global
scope.
You probably don't actually want to do this very often, because it's confusing and
it's prone to creating bugs and errors. Because this variable with global scope
could have been created anywhere in your code, right?
And you would be modifying it completely independent of when you created it.
So it might've been days between when you wrote this code and when you wrote
this code and it just makes everything more fallible,
more easy to fail.
This is why very often people will tell you when they're teaching you Python to
avoid modifying global scope. You can read it,
that's not a problem. You can use it within your code, like we are here.
But don't try to modify it within a function that has local scope.
But what can you do instead?
What if you wanted to have this functionality like a function that changes the
number of enemies?
How can you achieve this without modifying the global scope within the function?
Well, you could use what we learned about return statements instead,
right? What if instead of modifying the enemies,
you actually just simply returned it as the output.
So return the current value of enemies + 1.
Now once you call this function,
you'll get hold of the output and you can save it to the global variable enemies.
So this now means that this function can be taken away and placed anywhere in
your code and you don't actually need to know how it works.
As long as you know that this is how you increase enemies,
then all you have to do is just call it.
Remember, you should be careful with variables that have global scope,
but don't believe the people who tell you that you should never use global
scope. Global scope can be incredibly useful
especially when you're defining constants. Global constants
are variables which you define
and you're never planning on changing it ever again. It's just something like,
for example, the value of pi, right?
You want to look it up once and you want to put it into your code and you never
want to look it up ever again.
And every other time you want to use it, say inside of a function, then all you
want to do is just tap into that value of pi.
So usually, in order to differentiate these constants
which you're pretty much never going to change from the variables
which you are likely to change,
the naming convention in Python is to turn it into all uppercase.
For example,
if you had PI or you had a URL that you needed to use,
or you have some sort of Twitter handle,
then these are all going to be uppercased, separated with underscores.
What this means is that later on in your function and you want to use one of
these global constants, as soon as you type it,
you can see it's the uppercase and you know
to remind yourself to not modify this inside your code.
Now that we've talked a little bit about scope,
it's time to put your knowledge into action. Head over to the next lesson
and I've got a quiz that will test your understanding.
So, for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Now that you've completed some of the scoping problems, it's time to tackle
the final project.
This final project is a little bit special because now I think you've got enough
experience and enough skills under your belt to actually create this project
entirely from scratch by yourself. So you're flying solo now.
Now the first thing I want you to do is head over to guess-the-number-
final.appbrewery.repl.run
and I want you to play this game quite a few times actually,
just so that you get a good idea of how it works. Now,
the first thing it tells us is Welcome.
And then it tells us it's thinking of a number between 1 and 100,
and then we get to choose a difficulty. So I'm going to choose hard.
Now it tells me that I have five attempts to guess the number,
and I'm going to make a guess.
Now it tells me that 50 is too high, it's not the number that it was thinking,
and I have to guess again. And notice how I started out with five attempts,
I'm now down to four attempts. So let's try 25.
So 25 is too low, but 50 is too high.
So that means the number is somewhere in between them.
Let's try 30. Again, too low. Let's try
4o. Too high. Maybe it's 45.
But I only have one attempt left
cause I went for the hard level. And as expected,
I didn't manage to get the right number and I've now run out of guesses.
So I've lost. If we run again,
we can try playing this on an easy level.
On an easy level, we get 10 attempts instead of 5.
That gives us a little bit of extra opportunity.
So let's try 50. 50 is too high. 25 is too high. 10,
10 is too low. So it's between 10 and 25. So let's try 15.
Now, if 15 is too high, but 10 is too low,
then we're pretty close to the answer.
It's now between 12 and 15, let's try 13, 14.
There we go. The actual answer that it had in mind was 14.
And I had four attempts remaining to get the final answer and I managed to get
it at the end. Play through this game at least three,
four times on the different levels
and remember that the easy level has 10 gos,
the hard level, the user gets 5 gos
at guessing the number. And look at how the code works and how it's functioning.
And then I want you to break down this problem. Write a to-do list,
create your own list of tasks that you need to solve and start with the simplest
one. And once you've tackled that, start putting in some comments into your code.
Write down the functionality your program needs,
and then write the code and then test out your code and keep going until you've
tested it and made sure that it works in all situations.
So this final project has no starting code.
I'm not going to give you any comments or to-dos to start off with.
I want you to try and tackle this entire project by yourself.
And the only thing I'm going to give you is this link so that you can try out the
final project. And I know that there's a lot of ways that you can cheat,
but don't do it. Have faith in yourself. If you tackle this for an hour,
I'm pretty sure you're going to get there in the end.
You have free reign on the styling or the wording,
whatever it is you want it to say.
But it has the have the same functionality. Now
this also means that if you want to get some ASCII art of your own,
then you can head over to this website
which I'll link to in the course resources and just type the name of your game.
So maybe it will be Guess
The Number.
And you can change the font that you want for it.
Maybe something a little bit isometric or maybe ogre,
or maybe train, whatever it is you want.
And then once you're happy with the font,
you can select and copy everything that's on there,
and then inside your project
you can create a new file called art.py and then create a new variable and set
it equal to the design that you've got in mind. Now,
in order for it to look right, you actually have to create this as a docstring,
so three quotation marks to begin with and then three quotation marks to end.
And then just make sure you have enough horizontal space to display the whole
thing in one go instead of it being truncated
when you have a little bit of space and you should be able to see the actual
design.
Pause the video now and create this number guessing game by yourself
as the final project.
How did you get on?
Hopefully you managed to complete the project and you're just here
to check through the solution. Now,
if you haven't given it a proper go and I mean,
at least an hour at tackling this, then go back, keep going.
It's only when you struggle that you actually get better.
You can watch me type code all day long,
and it's not going to make you a better programmer.
So I know you're going to try really hard and I want you to try really,
really extra hard and make sure that you can complete each of these projects by
yourself. I mentioned that this one doesn't have a starting repl,
so we're gonna start out with our own and you can call it anything you want,
but I'm going to call it guess-the-number game.
Now, when you're creating a new project from scratch
like we're doing right now,
it can seem a little bit intimidating staring at a blank screen.
The first thing to do is to just divide the project into the individual
components. So while you're playing this game,
you can see that there are different bits of it that we need to complete right?
The first one is printing all the starting parts of the game,
the next one is trying to figure out how to set this difficulty level,
getting the user to type in a word easy or hard,
and then changing the number of attempts based on that. We can already start
thinking about maybe we need to make a function to set difficulty,
and then we need to let the user make a guess, right?
So they're gonna guess a number. So let's say I'm going to type in 50,
and then we have to somehow check that guess against the number that was
originally selected and then check to see if it's too low or too high.
So now we have some additional parts of our program, right?
We need some sort of way of choosing a random number between 1 and 100.
So that's the first thing that's probably going to happen in our code.
We need to have a function to set difficulty,
we probably need some sort of functionality to, um,
let the user guess a number.
And we'll also want to check that number that they've guessed against the number
that we originally had to see if it's too high or too low.
So probably a function to check user's
guess against the actual answer.
Now notice how every single time I make a guess,
my number of attempts go down.
So we also need to track that right? Track the number of turns and reduce by one
if they get it wrong.
Now it's looping back again to this stage where we're making another guess.
So if 50 was too high, then maybe we'll guess 25.
We have to have some sort of way of repeating this part of the code, right?
We're going to repeat it as long as they have attempts left and they are wrong.
Now, if however they get it right,
so I think I have a good chance of getting it right. So if 25 is still too high,
let's try 12. And there we go. When I get the answer right,
it tells me, you got it. The answer was 12.
So now we've got some of the basic parts of our code down in comments,
and we can start thinking about how to write it out, right?
Let's start by tackling the easiest one,
which is choosing a random number between one and a hundred.
All you have to do for this one is just to import the random module, or even
better yet from the random module, import the randint function.
Now inside our code,
we can simply just use randint. We can say the answer is equal to a randint
that is between 1 and 100. And of course remember that rand
int includes a and b,
so both 1 and 100 can show up.
In addition to this, we probably have to give the user some of these messages.
So I'm just going to copy some of these messages.
So I'm going to print 'Welcome to the guessing game.'
And also I'm going to print that
I'm thinking of a number between 1 and 100, like that.
So now we've got an answer that they need to guess,
and we've got a little bit of starting text for them.
The next easiest thing in this is to figure out a way of letting the user
guess a number. So we know that we'll need an input to
ask them to make a guess, so we can copy this part.
And we can use that as the prompt,
and then we're going to have to save their guess and convert it to an integer.
So they're going to be typing a number here, right? And we'll call this guess.
Now the user is able to guess a number and we now have to figure out some sort of
way of checking the user's guess against the actual answer.
This is probably a good time to create a function.
So why don't we go up to the very top and create our function here.
We'll call this check_answer,
and we're gonna pass in the user's guess and the actual answer in order to
achieve this checking functionality. So in this case,
we're going to check to see if the guess is greater than the answer,
well, in this case, it's too high, right? So we'll just print too high.
Now, what if the guess was actually less than the answer,
still not equal to the answer, but in this case it's too low.
So now the final condition is they actually got it right.
So you could write elif guess is equal to answer,
but you could also just use else because there's no other possibilities.
This else statement catches the moment when they actually get it right.
So in this case, we're going to print what we have here,
and then we'll get to print out the answer. Of course,
we're going to replace that with whatever the actual answer is and turn this
into an fstring. So now that's that step done.
And let's think about what else is easy that we can knock off the list.
Let's think of function to set the difficulty. So up here,
in addition to our check_answer function,
I'm going to create this other function, some way of setting the difficulty.
So let's call this set_difficulty,
and it's probably not going to take any inputs.
It's just going to do some sort of action. So when we first start off the game,
it already asks us to choose a difficulty.
So I'm going to copy this text and I'm going to put that into an input,
choose a difficulty easy or hard.
And then we're going to save this probably into a variable,
which I'll call level, so the level of difficulty that they want. Now,
if this level that they chose was equal to easy,
well, in this case,
we want to set the number of attempts that they have to 10.
So they have 10 attempts. But on the other hand,
if they chose hard, then they only have 5 attempts.
So this is probably a really good time for creating a global constant.
So we already saw this in the previous lesson on scope,
but this is a really nice thing because it means if we create this global
constant at the very top, then if we want to switch around how our game works,
we can really easily access these constant by just scrolling through the top of
the page. Let's call the first one, um,
EASY_LEVEL_TURNS, so the number of terms you get on easy,
which is going to be 10.
And then we'll have HARD_LEVEL_TURNS
and this is going to be equal to 5.
Now I've got these two constants which is global
and I can use it inside any of my functions or basically anywhere on this
page. If the level is easy,
I'm going to set the number of turns to equal the EASY_LEVEL_TURNS.
So this is going to be a number right? Else,
so if they chose hard instead,
then turns should probably be the HARD_LEVEL_TURNS. Now,
setting it here is no use. I actually need it inside my game.
So now going back in my game,
I need to let the user know how many number of attempts,
how many turns they actually get. To start off
I'm going to use a print statement that just prints the number attempts they
have remaining. And it's not always going to be 5.
Sometimes it's going to be 5, sometimes it's going to be 10.
So what I'll need is some sort of way of tracking this number of turns,
right? But how do we know how many turns they get? Well,
it depends on what they chose here, right? If they had chosen hard,
then turns should be equal to the HARD_LEVEL_TURNS. If they chose easy,
it should be equal to the EASY_LEVEL_TURNS.
So instead of using this as some sort of global variable
which I have to change inside here, which would require me saying global,
and then turns so that
I can access this particular variable and change it inside
these steps, it'd would be much,
much better if I just returned these values as an output from this function.
If this is set as return,
then I can simply call this function set_difficulty,
which is going to trigger this input. And then once the user has set it,
then the output is going to be the actual number of turns they have.
And I can now use it inside this print statement to show them how many turns
they have. Now.
I've already written quite a bit of code actually,
and it's probably a good time to run the code. While I'm testing my code,
it's probably a good idea to actually see what the answer is.
So we can add a bit of testing code that just prints out what the actual answer
was selected as. And if we run the code
now you can see we've got the starting part pretty much down.
Welcome to the Number Guessing Game.
I'm thinking have a number between 1 and 100,
and then we've got our little hint here. The actual answer is 63.
So we have to make a guess.
And I've really noticed that that input needs a space here so that I'm not
writing right next to the colon. So let's say I guessed 50.
Now it's asking us to choose a difficulty.
So I've already got a little bit of a problem here.
I should actually have this before the other part.
So I should choose the difficulty and then make a guess.
So now let's stop and run and see if we fix that bug. And you can see
yep, indeed it asks us for a difficulty first.
So I'm going to choose easy
and it tells me that I've got 10 attempts remaining and then to make a guess.
And if I choose hard instead, then it tells me I've got 5 attempts.
Now, if while you are play testing this game
and you realize that actually 5 is not enough, then all you have to do is
scroll to the very top of the game,
change this one global variable here,
and all your changes, you know, will be reflected in the code below.
Now let's get back to our game. Let's say I make a guess and our code ends,
right? Even though I've got my check_answer,
it's not actually being called anywhere.
So it lets go ahead and call that function, check_answer
and then we can pass in the user's guess that they made at this step,
and we can also pass in the correct answer which comes from here.
So let's run our code again.
So I'm going to choose the easy mode and I'm going to make a guess.
Now 50 is too high because I can actually see the answer,
it's meant to be 32. So that works. But I can't guess again.
It's not letting me. It's actually ended the program.
So we probably have to tackle this particular todo
if we actually want to get the right functionality.
How do we get the guessing functionality to repeat if they get it wrong? So that
as you might've guessed is probably gonna require some sort of while loop. While
they've gotten it wrong, we probably should go and let them make a guess
again. These parts will definitely need to be repeated.
So let's create a while loop.
What are we going to check in our while loop to make sure that it keeps on going?
Well,
the thing that we're trying to aim for is to get the user to guess the actual
answer.
If we set the while condition as while guess is not equal to answer,
then that pretty much guarantees that these lines of code will keep going until
the user actually gets the right answer. Now however,
when we do this, we get an error, undefined name guess.
Well because guess hasn't been declared yet.
So why don't we declare it outside of the while loop and simply just create it as
a variable? So we'll set that to equal zero. Now at the moment,
this is a global variable. This is a global variable. This is a global variable.
So it's probably a good idea to put our game functionality inside its own
function. So we can create a new function here, which I'll call game,
and now we'll need to call and trigger this game inside the global scope
if we actually want this to be carried out.
Now that we've done all of this hard work,
let's run our code and let's try it out.
Lets go for easy.
And I'm going to start off by guessing 50 as always. 50 is too low and I can see
the answer is actually 90. So I'm going to go for the next number.
Lets try a number that is a bit too high. 95, too high.
Now, what if I actually get it right? What if I actually guessed 90? Well,
it tells me you got it. The answer was 90.
So the only thing that we're not really doing is tracking the number of turns so
that we tell them you have 10 attempts, you have 9 attempts,
you have zero attempts. And if they get zero,
then they're going to lose right? Here
we have this print statement that runs only once because it's not inside the
while loop. So let's tackle our final to-do
to track the number of turns and reduce it by one
if they get it wrong. Now, where do we know that the user got it wrong?
Well inside the check answer function. If it's too high or if it's too low,
then we have to deduct the number of turns they have. But if they got it,
then we don't. One way of tackling
this is again creating a global variable called turns,
set it to start off at zero,
and then inside this function,
we simply just say turns -= 1 and also turns -= 1 when
it's too low or too high. Now because this is a global variable
we again would need to say global turns in order to use it inside our function.
But as I mentioned,
this is not a good idea because it means that you're modifying the global
function within a local scope.
How can we achieve the same functionality without having to use a global
variable? Well,
we could instead just pass in the number of turns that we currently have and
then inside our function,
we can return the number of turns minus one. And we can do the same down here.
So now when we call this function check_answer,
we can pass in the current number of turns
which remember it got set by the set_difficulty function,
and we can pass that in into here.
Because it's not immediately obvious that this function actually has an output,
it's probably a good idea to add a docstring to this function.
Remember the three quotes,
and then in between we're going to say checks
answer against guess. Returns
the number of turns remaining.
Now when we actually call check_answer
you can see that this is what actually happens and that we have a return that we
can be aware of.
If this is going to be the number of turns remaining,
then we can save that to this variable turns so that we update this local
variable every time we check the answer.
Now this part is a little bit mind blowing,
so you might actually want to put this through Python
Tutor and step through it
step by step to see what's actually going on and how this turns variable is
being updated by the output from this function.
If you're totally happy with what's going on, then feel free to keep going.
So now let's check out our code.
50 is too high and 20 is too low, and 38 is just right. Now
what if I actually ran my number of turns down to zero?
So let's try hard because this is only going to give us five attempts.
So let's say I guess 50 and then 70,
and I'm just going to put in some random numbers so that I end up with no
remaining guesses. You can see it's actually not stopping me right?
And also for some reason we have a bug where the number of attempts we have
remaining is not actually being printed. So let's address that issue.
Well, if we want it to happen every time and repeat,
it's going to need to go into the while loop. Instead of printing our number of
turns here, why don't we print it here inside the while loop instead?
So let's make sure the indentation is correct and now let's try it again.
So I have 5 attempts remaining. Let's make a guess.
I have 4 attempts remaining. And notice how it's counting it down;
3, 2, 1. This should be my last guest,
but notice how it actually keeps on going. It doesn't stop the game.
I can keep going and it's going into negatives now.
How can we fix this? We need some sort of way of tracking
when this number of turns goes down to zero. When that happens,
we have to stop the game and tell them that they've lost.
Why don't we create an if statement, check
if the number of tons is equal to zero and print something.
Let's check the actual final version. Let's see what happens in this case.
When I run out of gos,
I make a guess, it's two low and it tells me you've run out of guesses.
You lose. We can print that here as well.
But notice how if we run the code as it is,
so let's just keep guessing the same number until I run it down to 1.
So now I make a guess, it tells me you run out of guesses. You lose.
But it's still letting me keep going even though I've lost.
How can we make our game end? Well,
luckily we've got our game inside a function
which is being called at the very beginning.
Now remember that with functions you have the return keyword.
You can return with an output or you can just write return for it to exit and end
the function. So now with that return keyword in place,
once I run out of turns, see what happens.
It stops and it doesn't let me guess any more.
Perfect. We've managed to get that
right. The thing that we're still missing is this prompt for the user to guess
again. Now this is kind of optional.
It depends on your own feel for the user experience.
I think it makes sense to say, 'It's too low. Guess again.' because it's kind of
telling them to do something. Although there's make a guess,
also prompts them to make a guess. So you can have, you don't have to.
If you wanted to have that,
then you probably actually have to check that they still have turns remaining.
And if they do, then make sure that the guess is not equal to the answer,
so they haven't got it right within this turn, and then to print that 'Guess
again'. So now every time they get it wrong,
but they still have remaining guesses
it should say 'Too low. Guess again.' or 'Too high. Guess again.'
But if they actually get it right,
so the answer should be 83, then it says 'You got it.
The answer was 83' without asking them to guess again.
Now we've pretty much completed this code.
Of course you could have added additional art.
So you could have created an art.py and then used the text to in the ASCII
generator to create a ASCII art.
Yeah.
And then back in here we could have imported it.
And we could put that at the very beginning of the game.
But the rest of the customization is basically your own, right?
You're free to do whatever it is that you want to and to change the wording, to
change the text.
The really important part was that you were able to play this game,
understand how it worked and then break down the problem into smaller pieces
that you could tackle one by one.
And if you had trouble actually completing this program by yourself,
then you should have noticed when we were walking through it
when I just broke down that big a problem into smaller chunks
how much easier it became tackling each of the smaller things, right?
Letting the user guess a number or choosing a random number between 1 and 100,
you can definitely do parts of this.
And as you built up the game, towards the end you realized, ah,
this was missing or that might be nice.
Then you could start adding more and more bits to it.
So if you wanted to review the final code that you see here,
you can, of course, head over to the guess-the-number-final Repl.it at this
particular link in the course resources.
But hopefully, you've actually managed to build out your own version and it's
even better than what I've done. And if you're particularly proud of it,
be sure to share it so that the rest of us can take a look and have a play with
it as well.
So I hope you enjoyed the project today and I'll see you tomorrow.