Hey guys! Welcome back to a 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to look at debugging,
the process of removing bugs from your code.
If you manage to get to this point,
you've probably written quite a bit of code already,
and I will bet that you've probably made some mistakes, some typos,
some errors and some bugs. So in this lesson,
I want to talk about some techniques and tips for how to find bugs and how to
get rid of them from your code. Now,
the first documented bug was actually found by this lady, Grace Hopper.
She was probably one of the first programmers and one of the pioneers of the job
that we're undertaking right now. Now in her notes,
you'll find a moth that's been taped to the notebook,
and this was found in a relay that was preventing her code from running
properly. And this was pretty much the first
actual case of a bug that's been found in a computer.
Even though we're not dealing with moths these days anymore,
we're still going to end up finding bits of things in our code that prevent the
code from doing the things that we want it to.
The important thing to remember is don't feel down when you've created a bug
because everyone gets bugs. And when I say gets bugs,
I mean, we create them, right? So once you've gotten over this, next,
I want to talk about some of the tips and techniques that you should follow on
how to quickly be able to identify and remove these bugs.
So the first step is to describe the problem.
If the problem is messy and it's not well understood in your head,
then it's almost impossible to debug it.
So untangled the problem and try to make sense of what's going on. To begin,
go ahead and fork the starting repl for today's code.
Now, the first thing to notice here is that I've written a bunch of code in the
starting repl
and we're going to be uncommenting these blocks one by one and eventually
solving all of the debugging problems.
So the first thing you're going to do is to uncomment the first block of code.
Now in this block of code,
we're going to practice describing the problem to help us solve this debugging
problem. Now if you take a look at this function
you can see that at some point in the function,
we're supposed to print this line out into the console.
But if we go ahead and hit run, you can see that nothing gets printed.
So what's going on here?
I want you to take a look at this function and describe the actual problem.
What is the for-loop doing? When is the function meant to print "You got it"?
What assumptions are you making about the value of i? So pause the video,
read the function and have a go at describing the problem.
All right.
So what we've got here is we've got a function that loops through all the
numbers between 1 and 20,
and then once that number reaches 20, it's supposed to print "You got it".
But the problem is that when i reaches 20,
it doesn't print this line into the console.
So now that we've described the problem and we understand what's going on,
let's see if we can solve it. If we think about this problem,
when i reaches 20, it doesn't print out this line.
There's an assumption in there, right?
The assumption is that i will definitely reach 20.
But if you think back to how the range function works,
the stop or the upper bound is actually omitted.
So when you write range(4),
it actually produces a number from 0 up to 3.
And in our case, when we write (1, 20),
it actually goes from 1 all the way up to 19
but not including 20.
The problem here is that i actually never reaches 20.
So this assumption is completely false. Pause the video
and see if you can fix the code so that this line actually gets printed.
All right. So all we need to do is change this to 21 instead of 20
and now when we hit run, you can see it actually works
and we managed to debug this problem. Always when you come across a problem
in your code,
try to describe it so that you really understand what the issue is,
and then test your assumptions and see which of those assumptions is actually
false.
Now the next step is to think about reproducing the bug that you've encountered,
because when you encounter it once but you don't encounter it the next time
that becomes a really difficult bug to fix. Go ahead
and uncomment the next block of code.
And we're going to comment out the previous section because we're done with it
now. So this is the only part that should be active in your main.py.
In this section, we're going to try and reproduce the bug.
So when we run the code,
sometimes it will work and it will print out one of the dice images from this
list, but occasionally you will get an error.
These types of bugs are really difficult because you might test your code only
once or twice, and it looks all fine. It works.
But then occasionally you get an error.
And the important thing is to reproduce that error.
When does that error actually happen?
And based on that knowledge, we can fix our code.
Try to reproduce the bug yourself and try to notice when it happens and see if
you can change the code so that it always produces this error.
[inaudible],
We've got a list of dice images, which are just emojis.
And we've also got this random number, dice number between 1 and 6.
Now, when we try to pick out of our list,
occasionally we get an error.
Now we have to notice when the error occurs, and to reproduce the bug
we have to figure out which of these numbers is actually causing the problem.
So we know that this is a random number between 1 and 6
and if we check the documentation, it tells us that randint
works a little bit differently from range.
It will return a random integer in the range of a and b,
including both end points. So in our case,
both 1 and 6 could be generated and it could be any number.
So if that was equal to 1, well, does it generate an error?
No, it just picks out this particular item.
But what if it was 2 or 3 or 4?
Or what if we tested 6? Well,
now every time we hit run, you can see we get an error.
And now that we've got our error to show up consistently,
it's a lot easier to debug because we know that the index error list index out of
range happens when this dice number is 6.
So when we go back to our previous code, well,
we can't use 6 in this list because lists start counting from 0.
So to get this dice 1, we need dice_num to be 0.
And then this is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
and 6 is somewhere out here and it doesn't exist. Now,
go ahead and fix this code so that all the dice images are represented and we
never see this error again. Alright.
So that is as simple as shifting down these numbers.
So instead of making a random number between 1 and 6,
we actually want a random number between 0 and 5. And now,
no matter how many times we run our code,
we're never going to get that error show up again.
Very often I've asked you in the quizzes
especially to play computer.
And the reason is because this skill of pretending to be a computer reading
through your code and imagining what you going to do each time is really,
really useful, especially when you're debugging.
So let's comment out the previous block and try the next block.
Take a look at this code.
It takes an input
in the form of an integer and it ask the user for their year of birth.
And then it uses an if statement to check if they were born between 1980 and
1994, in which case they're classified as a millennial.
But if there were born later than 1994, then they're classified as a Gen Z.
So depending on which country you're from,
there's different classifications for your particular generation.
This is just the typical words that you hear on the internet.
You're a millennial, you're a Gen Z, you're a baby boomer,
and this comes from a lot of the history of the US. But nonetheless,
I want you to run the code and I want you to see what happens when I put in
1994. Absolutely nothing,
so we have our bug right there. Run through the code line-by-line and evaluate
each statement. For example, if year is equal to 1990,
will line 77 evaluate to true or to false?
What if year is equal to 1994?
Look at each line of code and follow the logic and check what it will evaluate
to.
So I want you to play computer and figure out what is the problem,
and then go ahead and fix the bug. Pause the video now.
All right. So
let's pretend that we got 1994 as the input.
So now I'm the computer
and I know that this year is equal to 1994.
Now with this year being equal to 1994,
I go into this if statement so is 1994,
greater than 1980? Yes it is.
So this actually becomes true.
Now I have to check the second condition and it also has to be true for this if
block to be triggered. So is 1994,
less than 1994? No, it's not.
It's actually less than equal to 1994,
or it's equal to 1994. So in this case,
this condition becomes false.
And we know that if we try to combine a true and a false then it actually just
becomes a false.
So this gets skipped.
Now, next, we look at the next statement, right?
If 1994 is greater than 1994,
well, that's also not true. It be greater or equal to,
or it could just be equal to.
So this condition is also false.
So that means it's also going to skip this next line and there's no more lines
of code left, which is why the computer doesn't print anything.
So let's restore our code to before we started playing computer
and we can identify that this problem occurs because there is no bucket that
actually catches the 1994.
We could simply fix this code by changing one of these conditions to be greater
than or equal to either here or here.
And that means that the year 1994 is not skipped over in our conditions.
And when we hit run, it will actually tell us that we are in fact,
a Gen Z.
Now the next step
and the next tip is pretty obvious. When the editor's giving you an error or when
the console is giving you an error, fix the errors before you continue.
Now, this is a little bit easier when you're dealing with errors in the editor,
because it will actually highlight to you the line that's broken.
So here we've got a print statement and when we hover over it,
it tells us that it expected an indented block. So that should be a good enough
clue to tell us what's actually wrong.
So if we go ahead and indent this block, then that error goes away.
But that's not the only error, no. When you run this code,
you still get another error. So let's say that I am a 12-year-old girl,
we get another error.
And this error does not show up when we write the code,
but it only shows up depending on what input we gave to this age variable.
So now we have a different type of error. We have an error that's in the console.
How do we solve this error? Well,
the easiest way is just to select the parts of the error
that's not specific to your code like this age greater than 18 or line 84,
but the part that is pretty much common to whenever anybody gets this error.
And now if we copy it and we paste it into Google,
then you can see there's a lot of other people who've had this issue.
And if we read what the problem is,
it tells us that you're getting the input from the console as a string
and you must cast that input as an int
before you try to do these numerical operations like comparisons. Back over here,
that's exactly what we're trying to do on line 84 right here.
This age comes out of this input function and it returns a string.
And so in order to turn this into a number,
we of course have to cast it or type convert it into an integer.
And now when we run our code and we give it our age,
it no longer errors out.
And if I tell it that I am in fact 21,
which is still not my real age,
then we actually get the print statement working.
But remember that the errors don't always solve all of your bugs, like this.
In this case there are no errors with my code whatsoever,
it's just not doing what I want it to do.
And these are the most frustrating bugs to debug because nobody is helping you
here. There is no errors that you can Google,
there's no underlines that you can check.
You actually have to rely on your skills as a programmer to fix this.
Now we, of course, know that this needs to be an fstring in order to insert that
variable into this position in the curly braces.
But if you didn't, then this would be a lot harder to debug.
Experience comes in really handy with debugging and the more bugs that you
solve, the better you get at it. So go onto the internet,
try to help people in Stack Overflow. Go on to the discord channel for the course,
try to solve other people's bugs and you will find yourself getting stronger
and better day by day.
Now the next tip has been the thing that you've probably been screaming out for.
Why don't we use print? And indeed you are correct.
Print is basically your best friend. Now as developers
I know we don't have a lot of friends,
but at least we can rely on print to be our trusty friend.
Do you have heartbreak? Use print. Now print probably can't help you with your
relationship issues or family issues,
but it can help you debug your code,
which is a pretty decent thing for it to do.
So let's go ahead and comment out the previous block and let's uncomment this
one. And now I'm sure you're pretty much dying to use print to solve these
debugging issues. Why Angela? Why haven't you been using it before? Well,
I've been saving it for this perfect moment.
Take a look at the code and see if you can use print as your friend to help you
solve the issue. Pause the video now and give that a go.
So here, we've got
a very simple program that figures out the number of words in a book. Pages
starts out zero, words starts out at zero,
and we have to input the number of pages in our book and the number of words in
our book.
And then we multiply the pages by the words to calculate the total number of
words in the book and then we print it out. But if we have a go,
you can see that let's say we have, um,
45 pages making a booklet and we have 250 words per page and we get 0.
So the output that's supposed to tell us the total number of words in the book
ends up being 0. So what's going on here?
How can we debug this? Let's go ahead and use print.
What are our assumptions? Well,
we're actually getting the number of pages and the number of words correct
so that we can calculate this.
Why don't we add some print statements before the final one? Let's print
what's the actual value of some of our variables that we're getting from the
user. For example, I could say, um,
the pages equals and then insert the pages variable in here in an fstring.
And I can also print my other variable in an fstring,
which is the word per page variable.
And this is equal to let's insert that variable as well.
And now when I run my code,
I've got my print statements going and I can test it out.
So we still got 45 pages and then 250 words per page.
Now you can see that my variables are logged. So this one,
this pages variable does equal 45. So it captured my data correctly.
But the word per page equals 0,
which is not what I entered at all. I entered 250
so I was expecting this to be 250.
So now using print, my best friend,
I've managed to narrow down the problem.
It's something to do with this variable.
So let's take a look at what's going on here. Well,
I've spotted the problem,
have you? Pause the video and see if you can fix this code
so the final total number of words actually gets printed when you run the code.
Pause the video now. All right,
we've narrowed down to this one line of code that's probably broken.
And if you look closely, you'll see that instead of a single equal sign
which means assignment,
this variable should be equal to this value.
We had two equal signs.
This means does this variable equal this value?
And this actually gets evaluated and becomes either true or false.
Now, in this case, it's actually false. Words per page starts out being equal to
zero, and then it becomes equal to 250.
So if this line of code is false, then that's just left as it is,
it doesn't actually affect anything.
And this total word is still using zero, which is why it's printing out zero.
So now that we've identified the issue, all we have to do to fix it is that.
And if we run our code again,
you can see it works exactly as it should do.
Now before you start getting really committed to print and start making
friendship bracelets for this print statements,
there's another tool that I really want to talk about
and it's a tool that's bigger, it's fancier, it's more complex.
So what is it?
It's a debugger and we've already seen debuggers a little bit.
So I've already shown you pythontutor.com
and you've also seen us use the debugger in the Thonny editor right here.
Now, in this example, I'm going to stick with the web version of Python Tutor
just so that you don't have to install anything extra.
But if we go ahead and comment out the previous block and uncomment
the last one, you can see that we have yet another problem to solve
and yet another piece of code, that's not doing what it's supposed to do.
So in this case,
we've got a function that's supposed to mutate a list so that it takes a list as
an input
and then it's supposed to multiply each of the items in the list
so the final output should be something like 2, 4,
6, 10, and so on and so forth.
Basically taking each of these numbers and multiplying them by 2,
which happens on this line of code. But unfortunately when we run it,
we just get a list with a single value, 26. So what's going on?
Let's try and debug it.
So I want you to copy these lines of code and then paste it into Python Tutor
and then go ahead and click Visualize Execution.
Now that it's inside the debugger, we can do a lot of things with it.
We can step through the code to see it line by line. So for example,
the first thing that happens is we create a function called mutate and this
mutate gets past a input called a_list.
So now inside this function, mutate,
we've got a variable called a_list and it's this list with these values.
Now, as we keep going, we can see we create a b_list, which is an empty list
and then we use the for-loop to loop through each of the items in the list.
So the first time this item is equal to the first item in the list,
which is 1,
and then we multiply it by 2 to create this new_item variable,
which is now equal to 2.
And now the loop goes back to the beginning and we keep doing this with each of
the numbers in the list. We multiply 2 to each of the numbers.
Now, once we're done with that loop, the next line that happens is this one.
This b_list gets appended with the new item and finally,
we print out the b_list. Now this is where the problem occurs.
Notice how b_list is just a list with one value.
And that is in fact what gets printed. So with this debugger,
we've managed to see line line what the computer is doing,
which is really helpful in itself.
But we can actually make this process even simpler. Inside
most debuggers, you can put a breakpoint
which tells the computer to stop what you're doing at this particular line.
And then at that moment in time,
I want to examine what all the variables and all the functions are doing.
So in our line, the key problem happens right here.
If I click on this line, you can see it becomes red
and this is where it happens, this is the break point basically.
So now I can scroll over to that point in time I can examine the values of all of
my variables. a_list is still what I expect it to be,
but b_list is completely empty. And this item happens to be on the last item
number 13 and the new item is doing what it needs to do,
multiplying it by 2,
but none of them are being added to my list because if I click next,
you can see this b_list is equal to just one value.
And it happens to be the last value that new_item was equal to.
So by using this debugger,
you should now have a good idea of what the problem is.
Pause the video and try to fix this code so that the mutated list with all of
its six values gets printed. Pause the video now.
All right.
So the simple problem is that when we are adding the new item to this b_list,
we're doing it outside the loop.
It's when this loop has completed and at the very end
do we actually call this line.
So what we needed to do to fix this code is just to indent that line over.
And now when we run the code,
you can see that the proper output gets printed
and if we change this code in there, the debugger, if we edited it right here,
then when we visualize it, you can see if I put a breakpoint here
that right line of code gets executed six times
and if we go to that line of code and we hit next,
you can see that the b_list is now getting new values added each time as we
would expect it to. And when we examine all of our variables
especially this b_list variable,
it's exactly what we expect it to equal each step of the code.
So a debugger can be really useful.
It's almost like you've put a print statement on all the variables in your
code,
and you can isolate a particular time point to see what each of the values are.
And as we become even more experienced,
we're going to be using the debugger more and more.
Now, I've got some final tips for debugging,
and these are not so much techniques, but there are just really,
really important tips from somebody who's done quite a lot of coding and created
a massive amount of bugs in my lifetime.
So tip number 7 is take a break. It's really,
really important when you're just staring at the code and you keep looking at
it, it's not going to tell you the solution.
Just have a cup of tea or have a nap,
or just go to sleep and try to tackle it tomorrow.
You will be surprised just how much easier things are when your brains had some
downtime and then you come back to it. Everything seems so much more obvious.
And if you really, really get stuck and you just can't see it, ask a friend,
not your friend print, but your actual friend,
a real human. Preferably a developer, but they don't have to be.
It could be somebody who's taking the course with you.
You could go onto discord and find other students to help you because after all,
you're all just leveling up your own programming skills
right? The really good thing about asking a friend to look through your code is
they won't make the same assumptions that you've made.
So they have some fresh eyes that they can look at the code with,
and it might be incredibly obvious what's actually happening.
And it's really not embarrassing at all.
If somebody managed to help you with your code,
you can offer to help them the next time when they get stuck. And for the person
who's helping you,
they're also just working out their programming muscles, right? Now
the next tip is to run often. No,
you don't have to go exercising to be a good programmer.
But what I mean is run your code often.
Don't wait until you've written loads and loads of code to hit run
and then find out you've got loads of snags and loads of bugs.
But run it after every little execution.
Once you feel like you've changed the program ever so slightly, run it. Confirm
that it's actually doing what you want it to do,
because if you leave it all to the end,
then you end up with a pile of bugs and you don't know where to start. Now,
if you do end up in that situation and you can see multiple bugs at the same
time, try to tackle them one at a time
instead of trying to do bits and bobs of each. It will really, really help.
And the final tip is, of course, Stack Overflow. I've saved this the last
because you really don't want to take every single small bug of yours to Stack
Overflow, that's not what it's designed for. Instead,
it's really designed as a way of asking other developers
when you think that you've come across a bug or an issue that should be unique.
Now, if you think that you issue isn't unique and other people should have
encountered this, then just search Stack Overflow.
If you really think that nobody in the world has had this issue that you are
having right now, then that's the moment to ask the oracle, I mean Stack
Overflow.
I've worked in a lot of companies where everybody just goes to the part when
Stack Overflow is down, because there's just no point. As programmers
we use it and we search it so much and it's become a really vital tool in the tool
belt.
But you only wanna ask a question when you've pretty sure that you've exhausted
all other avenues of debugging and you've searched all of Stack Overflow and you
finally end up with something very strange and very weird that you want others
to help you figure out. So don't worry about creating bugs.
And hopefully at this point, you're creating friendly bugs,
like this little Caterpillar right now.
And as you scale up and become even more advanced,
you're going to be creating bigger and more scary bugs.
So at some point in the future, when you're creating bugs like these,
then you really know that you've become a professional.
You will wish to come back to today when you can tackle bugs like these
instead. So don't worry about
about creating them. It doesn't mean that you are bad programmer. In fact,
it's an important part of every programmer's journey. Just as a sort of personal
note,
there was a point in time where I've really thought that I was not a programmer of
code, that I was just a programmer of bugs.
It seemed like every line of code I wrote was a bug.
So these are my 10 top tips for debugging.
And I hope that any time when your code is not doing what you expect it to do to
come back to this lesson, review these 10 steps, go through them one by one
and I bet 99% of the time, once you've gone through all of these stages,
you will have solved your bug and you will have made your code a lot better.
And remember that every bug that you catch in your code and that you fix is like
lifting a dumbbell in the gym. It's just one rep.
And the more reps you do the better you'll get at programing. In the next
lesson, I've got some coding challenges for you to debug.
Are you ready to flex your programming muscles?
I hope so. Head over to the next lesson and get started.
To begin, go ahead and select the Debug Odd or Even exercise.
All right. So now that you
have learned all about the tips and tricks and the steps to go through
to debug your code,
it's time to put some of that into action. In the upcoming three lessons,
I've got a bunch of code that you've already written before.
The first one, for example,
is the Odd or Even code challenge that you did a long time ago.
Now, the important thing is for you to not just go back to the old code,
copy it, paste it in, submit, done. That isn't going to teach you anything.
There's no point doing this if you're not going to learn. But instead,
what I want you to do is to look at the code, see what it meant to do.
So for example, in this case,
we're trying to input a number and then we're trying to get our code to check
to see if it's an odd number or an even number, and then print it out. Now,
in most of these upcoming code exercises, they're going to be broken,
but it's your job to try and fix it
to make sure that it does what it's supposed to. In this case,
you should be able to type in a number and it should print,
"This is an even number." if it's even, "This is an odd number." if it's odd.
Once you've spotted the problem and debugged and fixed your code,
then I'll go through the solution with you. So pause the video now.
All right. So,
as always, let's first hit run to see if it actually works or not.
And in this case, it doesn't even run. It gives us a syntax error straightaway,
and it tells us that on line three, we've got some invalid syntax. Now,
on line three, that's actually not all that specific.
But notice how sometimes when you get errors,
it's actually nice enough to have a little arrow pointing towards the bit of the
code in that line that it thinks is problematic.
So let's try and fix this error before we proceed.
So why does it have an issue with this equal sign? Well,
remember that two equal signs is checking and one equal sign is assignment.
So in this case,
we're actually saying number % 2 should be equal to zero,
which is nonsense. It doesn't actually make any sense. Instead,
what we wanted was two equal signs so that we can check that the left-hand side
is equal to the right-hand side.
And now if we hit run and we enter a number, it should now work.
Did you manage to get it right?
If not, be sure to review some of the lessons on debugging and try to apply it in
the next exercise. So once you're ready, head over to the next lesson.
All right. So in this lesson, we're going to be debugging our leap year
coding exercise. You've done this coding exercise before, you wrote this code
which checks to see if a year is a leap year.
It prints leap year if it's true, and not leap year
if it's not a leap year.
All you have to do is to fix this code.
So use what you learned about debugging and try to fix this coding exercise.
So pause the video now.
Okay.
All right. So first off,
let's go ahead and just run our code and see if it works.
And then we're going to enter a known leap year.
So a quick Google away lets see when is a leap year.
Well, 2020 seems to be a leap year. So let's try that.
Let's check 2020. And we get an error.
So errors are good. They're much easier to fix than the Programming problems
which have no errors.
And it tells us that there's a problem on line three and it's a type error,
not all arguments converted during string formatting.
What does that mean? Well, what's a type error anyways?
A type error is when you're trying to do something with the wrong data type. In
our case, it's pointing at line three. So if we take a look at line three,
what's happening here?
Well, currently we're trying to take the year that the user inputted, so 2020, and
divide it by four to see if the remainder is equal to zero.
Now, this is a little bit harder to solve than the previous one.
But what you should realize is that it's pointing towards a type error,
so what data types have we got going on? Well,
if we go ahead and print the type of our year,
then you can see that it's of class string.
But if we print the type of this 4 that
we're trying to divide it by, that is of class int.
So this is the problem. These two types are not matched.
So when you try to divide a string by an integer,
this is what ends up giving you this problem.
So why is this a string when we entered a number?
Well it's because the input function, remember, gives the user a prompt and then
takes whatever they type in the console and turns it into a string.
So in order to turn this into an int which is what we want,
we have to wrap it around a set of parentheses and then type
convert it into an integer. And now when we run it again,
we can see that it actually works. And we're happy that we fixed our code.
Once you're done with this challenge,
head over to the next one and complete the final debugging exercise.
So we're onto our final debugging exercise.
This is debugging Fizzbuzz. Fizzbuzz, if you remember,
is a program that will print Fzzbuzz
if a number is divisible by both three and five.
It will print fizz
if it's only divisible by three, and it will print buzz
if it's only divisible by five.
If it's not divisible by three or five,
then it's just going to print the number.
And our code is going to do this all the way from 1 to 100.
So what should happen by the end of this is in our console when we hit run,
it should start typing one and then it should type two and then three,
it will type fizz. And four, it will type four. Five,
it will type buzz and so on and so forth.
You should remember this from the previous exercise where you actually had to
write all this code. Now, as always,
don't just paste the solution code in. That won't do anything.
You need to work for it to gain knowledge.
So now that you know what the program is supposed to do,
what you are going to do is try to figure out all of the bugs in here and try to
fix all the bugs so that the program runs as it should do.
Pause the video, think about the 10 steps and try to apply it here.
Now, just as a quick note, unlike the previous debugging exercises,
there's more than one bug in this code. So, good luck
and I'll see you on the other side.
All right.
So, as I mentioned,
there's quite a few bugs in here and we're going to fix them one by one.
As always,
the first thing we're gonna do is we're just gonna run the code and see what
happens.
So the first thing you'll notice that's a little bit odd is it's printing
instead of just one, two, three, four,
it's printing it as if it's a list with the square bracket around it.
So let's see if we can identify why. Well in our code,
if none of these if statements are true, then it prints the number.
But in this case it's not just the number.
There seems to be some square brackets around the number,
in which case it's printing a list with that number as the single item inside.
So let's get rid of that and let's run our code again.
That looks a little bit better, a bit cleaner. Now let's take a look at the code.
So we know that when the number is only divisible by three then it should print
fizz,
but three, in this case, is actually printing Fizzbuzz, and five is printing Fizzbuzz
and then three and four, it seems a bit of a mumbo-jumbo.
So, what's actually happening here?
It seems like instead of just printing fizz,
it's printing Fizzbuzz and the number.
So there must be a problem in our checking code.
So let's think about what our code needs to do. When the number is divisible by
both three and five, then instead of the number, it should print Fizzbuzz.
So Fizzbuzz should only be printed
if the number that we're currently checking is divisible by both three and five.
Let's use the print statement to help us.
If we use an f-string and we say that we are currently on number and then we
put the number in here. This way
we'll actually print out the current number we're looping through
and then we can see what's being printed each time. So let's run the code.
And if we scroll to the top, currently on number one it prints one,
currently on number two it prints two, currently on number three
it prints Fizzbuzz, Fizz and three. So that is very,
very strange behavior indeed.
It seems like lots of things are true in our if statement. What's happening? Well,
if number is equal to three,
then it seems to be printing Fizzbuzz,
which means if we walk backwards, this if statement must have been true.
Now three divided by three should have zero as the remainder,
so this should be true. But this can't be true,
so this must be false. And it should only print Fizzbuzz if it's divisible by
both three and five. So instead of an or,
this really needs to be an 'and'.
So let's hit run again and see what happens this time. Currently on number three,
it prints Fizz and three. So that's again,
a bit of a problem. So we fixed the Fizzbuzz parts.
It is now printing Fizzbuzz correctly. Namely,
when it's on number 15. But why is it still printing the number?
The number should only be printed if none of the others are true.
But instead, it seems to be printing Fizz and then also printing the number.
What's the reason here? Well,
notice how we've got an else statement here that triggers the printing of the
number. Now, an else is paired with an if. So in this case,
what's happening is it's checking if the number is not divisible by five,
then print the number. That's not what we want. And in fact,
if you look at the print statements,
you can see that only when the number is divisible by five
does it not print the number. When it's divisible by three,
it's still printing the number. This is not what we want.
What we want is for this to be checked, and if that's not true,
then check the next thing. And if that is not true, then the next thing.
And finally, if all three of these are not true, then print the number.
So what we actually need instead of a whole bunch of ifs is actually some else
ifs.
So let's replace those two ifs with some elifs and now let's run our code.
So currently on number one, two, three,
so three now prints Fizz, five prints Buzz, nine prints
Fizz, 10 prints Buzz and 15 prints Fizzbuzz.
So I think we've actually managed to fix all of our code.
So I think we should be able to remove our print statement now.
And indeed we've managed to successfully solve all of the debugging problems
here. Now did you manage to get all that right? Don't worry
if you have to struggle a little bit. In the future,
you're going to be making a lot more bugs and you're going to be repeating this
process of using the 10 steps
to try and identify the problems and fix the code and make it free of bugs.
So hope you had a fun and jam packed day.
Now this might be a good time to revisit some code that you've given up on a
long time ago or projects that you've started
but you've stopped because you ran into bugs. And then review them,
use what you learned today and try to fix the bugs and get your code working.
Now tomorrow, I've got a big day for you coming up.
We're going to spend the whole day creating a big project and we're going to be
making the Higher-Lower game. So I'm looking forward to it,
I hope you are too. So get a good night's rest and I'll see you tomorrow.