Hey! Welcome to Day 16 of 100 Days of Code. Now
today,
we're going to be pulling out the big guns, we're going to be learning about
Object Oriented Programming otherwise known as OOP.
Why are we learning about it? Well, if you think back to yesterday's project,
some of you I'm sure at some point during the project, would have had this
feeling of what on earth is going on with my code?
And the reason is because our code is getting more complex,
it's trying to do a lot of things,
and it's trying to manage a whole bunch of relationships.
So one function is changing a variable,
and then that same function is doing something else to another variable.
And at some point, the logic of our code starts looking very, very spaghetti-
like.
And it's at this point where it's really hard to track and remember what's
actually going on in our code.
So this style of programming is called Procedural
Programming where we set up procedures or functions that do particular things.
And then one procedure leads to another procedure, and all in all, the computer's
mostly working from top to bottom and then jumping out into a function as
needed.
Procedural programming is one of the earliest paradigms of Programming.
In fact, back in the days when we had older languages like Fortran and COBOL,
they rely pretty much exclusively on procedural
programming like what we've been doing.
But the increase in complexity,
the increase in the number of relationships that we need to remember and manage
starts making it look a bit like the dating history of the Kardashians.
And it gets very,
very confusing because everybody has been in touch with somebody else. Now,
the kind of relationships I prefer are one to one, me and my couch.
So how can we maintain a simple relationship in our code while being able to
write more and more complex projects? Well,
this is where the Object-Oriented paradigm comes in really handy.
Now let's imagine that you're tasked with creating the program for a self-
driving car. Now, as you can imagine,
this is a pretty complex project and it's many,
many notches above the coffee machine that we've been struggling with so far.
But what if you broke it down? What is a self-driving car?
What are the different components that make up a self-driving car? Well,
it probably needs some sort of camera module to keep track of what's on the road
and to recognize what's on the road,
it will probably need a form of lane detection to know if we're actually within
the lane or if we need to turn off or if we need to park, and it will need some
way of navigating so that when the user says, I want to go to the bank,
they identify the branch they want to go to,
and then the navigation gets set up and the car knows how to get there.
And finally, you'll probably need some form of fuel management, right?
What should happen when the fuel gets low?
Should it go and automatically recharge at a specified point?
Now I'm obviously simplifying this task. There's a lot,
a lot more that goes into making an automated car.
But we've already managed to break it down into several modules that we can
think about tackling, right?
But imagine if you have a whole team who are all working on this project and
within that team,
there's sub-teams who are working on each of these different modules.
Well then by splitting up this big complex task into separate modules,
then we can all work on this car simultaneously,
massively improving our productivity,
making it much quicker to eventually build all the software for this car.
Plus on top of that, a lot of these modules are reusable.
So if it just so happens that the next year we're tasked with building a drone,
well, a lot of those programming modules that we built, like the camera module,
the fuel management, the navigation,
that's all going to be incredibly useful in our drone delivery software as well.
And because we've taken out these individual chunks of code and modularized them
using Object Oriented Programming,
we won't have to code them up again in the same way that we might need to
if we were using procedural programming.
So what exactly is all Object Oriented Programming? We've seen that we can split
a larger task into that smaller pieces.
And each of those pieces can be worked on by separate teams, separate people,
and also each of those pieces become reusable if we need the same
functionality in the future. But Object Oriented
Programming actually takes that concept even further.
And I think the best way to explain it
is to imagine that you are tasked with running a restaurant.
So you take over this restaurant from your long lost uncle
and you realize that it's actually really hard running a restaurant.
So, first off, you have to be the receptionist and you reserve seats for your
restaurant visitor's and then when they order something,
you have to be the waitress and bring them their order.
And then of course the order needs to be cooked up, right?
So you're also gonna run into the kitchen and be the chef, create the thing that
they ordered and finally,
you're also going to be the cleaner tidying up after everybody
once they've left. As you can imagine,
if you were one person having to do all of these tasks,
that's going to be a pretty rough day. There are in fact one-man restaurants,
and I've seen some work really in well Japan,
where you have one person who's taking the order,
who's making the food, who's tidying up after you.
But the limitation here though, is that look at how many seats he has.
You can't have a large restaurant running everything by yourself. In the same
way we can't create a very complex and really large software project
if we are using a procedural style of programming where we're sort of running a
one man band. It gets very,
very complex and very hard to manage very quickly.
So lets consider the alternative.
What if we had just hired a bunch of people where they each have their own
individual roles. They're trained for it, they know what to do.
The waiter knows how to wait and the chef knows how to cook. Well,
in this case,
you could just be the manager and you can manage all of your staff and tell them
what it is that they need to do.
But then you won't have to worry about the nitty-gritty details of exactly how
they need to go about doing their jobs. So for example,
you don't need to tell the waiter
how to wait on customers and you don't need to tell the chef how to cook an egg
because they already know how to do that.
And we can use the same concept to simplify the relationships in our code and
make it scalable for a larger and more complex project.
We've seen a little bit of why Object Oriented Programming is really useful,
but now let's take a look at how you would actually go about implementing Object
Oriented Programming.
So in the last lesson we talked of this example of the restaurant,
where we hired three types of staff,
and we had a manager who would then manage all of these three different types of
staff. Now,
the reason why Object Oriented Programming is called that is because it's trying
to model a real world object.
So let's say that we are creating a virtual restaurant. Well, in this case,
we probably have to model a virtual chef, waiter,
cleaner, and manager.
So let's say that we were going to model a waiter. In order to model our waiter,
there's probably two things we need to think about: what it has and what it does.
In terms of what it has, well, it might have variables like,
is it holding a plate, true or false?
Or which tables is it responsible for? Maybe table 4, 5 and 6.
Now it also has things that it does.
Maybe they're able to take an order to the chef and maybe they also need to take
payments and add money to the restaurant. So these two different things,
what the waiter has and what the waiter does are
the two most important things that make up an object: its attributes and its
methods. By looking at the code,
you can pretty much see that the attributes is basically a variable.
An attribute is just a fancy word for a variable that's associated with a
modeled object like our waiter here.
Because it's not just a free floating bit of a variable, right?
It's not just somewhere in our main.py.
It's actually a variable that's attached to a particular object.
It's the waiter's tables responsible.
Now the method goes along the same vein. These,
as you can clearly see, are just functions
but we call it a method because it's a function that a particular modeled
object can do.
We need a waiter object to take the order and we need a waiter object to take
payment. Again, these are not just free-floating functions.
Now, there's a lot of new words that are part of Object Oriented Programming and
programming in general, we're going to see them again and again,
and eventually it's going to become a word that's going to be in your
dictionary. But for now, just remember that in Object Oriented
Programming,
we're trying to model real-life objects and those objects have things
and they also can do things.
The things that they have are their attributes
and these are usually modeled with variables, and the things that they can do
are called methods and they are modeled by functions.
So essentially, an object is just a way of combining some piece of data and some
functionality altogether in the same thing.
But we can actually have multiple objects generated from the same type.
So when we've modeled a particular job in our virtual restaurant
like the waiter's job,
and we figured out what are the things that the waiter have and what are the
things that it can do, well,
we can actually generate multiple versions of the same object. So we could have
Henry who's a waiter and we can also have Betty who's a waiter,
and we can generate as many of these as we want from the same blueprint.
And in OOP we call this blueprint, or this type, a class.
And we call these individual objects that are generated from the blueprint
an object.
So now let's take a look at how you use these class blueprints to create an actual
object.
[inaudible]
So here's a blueprint for a car.
And that blueprint that specifies what the color of the car is,
how many wheels it should have, what its mileage is, how much fuel it has,
all of those bits of data combined with all of its functionality
like the ability to drive, the ability to stop and break.
And that blueprint which models a real-life car is known as the class.
And it's from this blueprint,
this class, that we can generate as many objects as we want. Now,
the object is the actual thing that we're going to be using in our code.
The code equivalent of what just happened,
creating a new object from a blueprint,
looks like this in Python. You have the class
which is normally written with the first letter of each word capitalized,
which is known as Pascal case.
This is to differentiate it from all the variable and function names that we
give in Python, where each word is separated by underscores.
So in this case,
the car is the object and it gets created from this car blueprint.
All we have to do to create the object from the class is to give the object a
name, it can be anything you want, set it equal to the name of the class,
and then the parentheses, which in the same way as it activates the function,
it activates the construction of this object from the blueprint.
Now, in order for us to practice this and to see it in action,
we're going to using a library of code that somebody else has created.
And what it allows us to do is to finally start putting graphics onto the
screen. The premise is really simple.
Let's say that somebody somewhere has created a blueprint for a turtle.
Now this turtle has a paintbrush on its back,
and you can tell the turtle to dip the paintbrush in different colors,
pick a different of size paint brushes and most importantly,
you can tell it to draw onto the screen.
This library is called turtle graphics and it's preloaded with every download of
Python so we can get started with it straight away.
So go ahead and open up PyCharm and create a new project.
Now I'm going to call mine, buy the old convention day 16 start
and making sure that I'm on the latest version of Python in my base interpreter,
I'm going to click create. Now, once you've created the new project,
go ahead and create the main.py as we have always done.
In our case,
we're going to be creating an object from a blueprint that somebody else has
already created,
and the blueprint lives in another module called turtle.
So we'll have to import that module.
And we know that from previously,
we can import other modules and use the things that are declared inside the
module by importing it, and then tapping into various things in there.
So for example, if I was to go and create another new file
which I'll call another_module.
Now inside another_module, let's say I create another variable.
And now I can go back to my main.py,
I can import my another_module I just created
and I can tap into that variable
that's inside another module by saying another module dot another variable.
Now let's go ahead and run this code as it is.
And you can see the value of that variable from the other module being used
inside our main.py.
Now I want to do the same thing using turtle, but in this case,
I want to tap into the class called turtle
that's declared inside this turtle module. The wording's a little bit confusing,
but let me show you what I mean.
So I'm going to tap into the turtle module and I'm going to get hold of a
turtle class. So notice how it's got the C here
denoting that this is a blueprint for creating a new turtle
object. Now, remember that to actually construct the object
we need to add the parentheses at the end,
and now we can save all of this into an actual object, which we get to name.
So I'm going to call my turtle timmy
and now I've got a new turtle object. Essentially,
we've done the same thing as we have done up here.
We've imported a module called turtle,
we've tapped into that turtle module here,
and then we've fetched something from that module. In this case,
it's a variable. And in this case,
it's a class which is denoted by the capital T, the Pascal case here.
And then we've used the parentheses to initialize
or basically construct an object from that blueprint
and we've saved it into an object called Timmy.
Now I can simplify this code to make it look more like what we had in the slides
by saying, instead of import turtle, I can say from,
from the turtle module import the turtle class.
So now, instead of writing all of this,
I can simply just write Timmy
equals a new object created from the turtle class and it's constructed.
This is how we would construct our new object.
So now I have this brand new object called Timmy
and if I go ahead and print timmy
you can see that when I run this code what gets printed is a new turtle object
from the turtle module
and it's saved at this location in the computer's memory.
So this is very different from say
if we just printed a string or a number.
It works completely differently. In this case,
it's actually a object that's being printed. Now,
what can we do with this object?
[inaudible]
Now, as we saw before with our car
object it has certain attributes, right?
Like speed and fuel, data that it could keep track of that are really important
to the modeling of an actual car object. Now,
when it comes to accessing these attributes,
the syntax or the code looks like this. Car in this case is the object
and then we use a dot or a full stop to separate the object from the actual
attribute that we want to get hold of, which in this case is speed.
What this code does is it essentially identifies the object
and then it says, from this object get the speed attribute.
This is actually gonna represent the speed of this particular car
object. Coming back to our turtle.
One of the other classes that is inside this turtle module is something called
screen.
And the screen represents the window in which this turtle is going to show up.
So let's go ahead and create this screen
object. I'm going to call my object my_screen
and then I'm going to create it from this blueprint of a screen that we
imported. Now we can tap into one of the screens properties
which is called the canvas height and canvas width.
So let's see what the height is, and notice how we're using that dot notation.
So this is the object and then separated by a dot we've got the attributes that
we want to access from this object.
So I'm going to print that into the console. Now,
when I go ahead and run this code,
you'll see a window pop up very briefly
and that was the screen on which our turtle is going to show up.
Now, if you take a look in the console,
you can see that not only have we printed the turtle object,
but we've also printed the height of the canvas for this particular screen that
we've created.
So the screen here is the object and that canvas height is an attribute that's
associated with that screen.
Now, in addition to the things that an object has,
so data that it holds like the speed or the fuel
which we've already seen, it also has things that it can do, right?
So functions that are associated with that particular object. And these functions
when it's tied to an object is known as a method.
But essentially we would use it the same way as we have done with any other
function that we've created so far.
The only difference is the syntax. Firstly,
we would tap into the car object and then using that same dot notation that
we saw with the attributes, we're saying car.stop.
So essentially what we're doing is we're getting hold of the object and then
we're calling this function that's associated with that object,
which is known as a method. So coming back to our code here,
one of the things that we can do with this screen object that we've created here
called my_screen is we can tap into one of its functions.
And because it's a function that's tied to an object,
it's actually called a method.
So the method name is called exitonclick.
And what this will allow us to do is instead of having our screen show up and
then quickly disappear when our code ends,
this exitonclick will allow our program to continue running until we click on
the screen and then it exits our code.
So let's try this again and notice how we've now got our screen show up
and this canvas has a height of 300 and a width of 300,
but now we can see our turtle in the form of the arrow. So this is our
a little Timmy shown up in the middle.
And our code is only going to exit when the screen detects a click
because we've called this function that's associated with the screen object.
So now if I click on the screen,
you can see process finished with exit code zero, our code is ended and the screen
has disappeared. Now there are other functions as well.
So if we take our little timmy object and we say, well, timmy,
why don't we change the shape of you on the screen
and we'll change you into an actual turtle?
So now when I run the code,
you can see that object in the center is now in the shape of a turtle.
Now,
if you want to know how I know about all these things I can do with the turtle
graphics library, then of course,
I'm getting all of this information from the documentation.
So in the course resources,
you'll see a link to this Turtle graphics documentation,
and it tells you all the things that you can do with your turtle.
So for example,
you can call all of these methods that are associated with your turtle object to
get your turtle to move and draw,
and you can also use it to change its position or change its coordinates,
as well as doing things like changing the color or resetting.
And you can browse through this list to see how you would use each of these
things. So for example,
if I wanted to change the color of my turtle,
I can do that by simply just calling this method, color,
and then inside the parentheses
I pass in the argument of the actual color string.
Now you can choose from a whole range of colors just by putting in the name as a
string into that method which is called color.
So go ahead and see if you can change our turtle timmy's color from the default
which is just black to one of the colors that you see in this link here,
and the link, of course, is in the course resources.
So let's say I want to change it to a coral color like this one.
All I have to do is tap into my object which is called timmy,
and then call the method which is called color onto it.
And you can see all the methods are
denoted by a little M here in the circle.
Now this color, of course, expects some sort of input.
So the input that it expects is a actual string of a color.
And my string is going to be coral, which I picked up from here.
So now let's run our code and see what it looks like now.
Once the screen refreshes,
you can see that our turtle is now a nice coral color,
and we've managed to do all of this to change the shape,
change the color, all because we were able to call these functions
which belong to this
object. Now see if you can use the documentation here and figure out how to get the
turtle to move forward by a hundred paces.
Pause the video and try to complete this challenge.
All right.
So we saw earlier that it has a whole bunch of move and draw methods.
So we can simply use this forward method to get it to move forward.
And in terms of the parameters that it takes,
it takes a number which is going to determine the distance that it's going to
move forward by.
So we said that we wanted our turtle to move forward by a hundred paces.
All I have to do is specify the object that I want to move which is timmy,
and then call that method forward and pass in the distance.
So I said a hundred paces. So now let's run our code again,
and you can see that little turtle just move forward by a hundred paces.
So now we've seen how to create a new Object from a blueprint,
we've seen how we can tap into its attributes by using the object name dot and
then the name of the attribute.
So this is the same as having a variable that's associated with that object.
And finally,
we've seen how we can call methods that are associated with the object.
For example, here
when we changed the shape or when we changed the color or when we told it to go
forwards. Now in the next lesson,
I'm going to show you how you can get hold of more external libraries
not just turtle, but a whole world of packages that you can tap into.
And you can start using these packages of code that other programmers have
already developed,
and simply by creating objects from the existing blueprints and reading the
documentation to get it to do various things that you want it to.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now I've mentioned a lot about using code that other developers have written and
the most common way to do this is through using packages of code.
In this lesson,
I'll show you how to integrate an existing package of code into our project so
that we can practice creating objects and working with attributes and methods.
Now we've seen modules of code where each file that we create in our project is
essentially a module in itself.
But a package differs from a module in the sense that it's actually a whole
bunch of code that other people have written, lots and lots of files all packaged
together to achieve some sort of goal or purpose. Now,
let's say that we wanted to create a table of Pokemon and their type.
So we wanted some way of documenting that Pikachu is an electric type and maybe
Squirtle is a water type. Now,
if we wanted to do that in ASCII so that we could print it in the console, well
then we would have to go about formatting it and it'll be quite painful.
So we might have to print some sort of pipe and then maybe we would have the
name of the field, so Pokemon name,
and then maybe another pipe. And then we would have the name of the next column,
which is their type.
And then finally we would close that off and then we would have to print some
sort of a horizontal line
maybe like this and so on and so forth just to create this table.
And it's quite difficult if you're not used to manipulating ASCII and
visualizing it. I certainly am not up to this task.
So what could we do instead? Well,
we could search for a package that other developers have created to achieve this
goal. And the place that we would do that is somewhere called PyPi,
which is the Python package index.
And this is a bunch of software for the Python programming language that is
developed and shared by the Python community. So we can see their source code,
but more importantly,
we can see how to implement the code and how to put it into our project.
In here, I'm going to search for something called prettytable.
And this is a very simple library that is going to help us to display tables in
a ASCII format.
We can click on the project links to find out more about it.
And this will take us to the Google code archive,
where the documentation is hosted.
If you go to Wikis and go to tutorial,
you'll see some documentation on how to use it.
Now, this particular package is not as extensive as the turtle graphics package.
So there's actually not a lot of things you can do with it,
but its got more than we need for our use case.
The first thing we have to do is to install this package into our project.
Now, unlike the turtle package
which is already preloaded with every copy of Python, in order to use the
packages that you find in the Python package index,
you actually have to install it.
So here's how we do it in PyCharm. First, go to the preferences,
so in Windows, I think it's under file and then preferences. On Mac is under
PyCharm and then preferences.
And then here you'll see a whole bunch of things you can change
including the editor or appearance which we've already messed around with.
But I want you to click on your project.
So my project is called day-16-start and then we're going to go into the project
interpreter. And here we can click on the plus button to install any package that
you find in the Python package index. Make a note of what it's called.
So ours is called PrettyTable and then we're going to search for it inside the
available packages. And once we found it,
we're going to select it and then click install.
If you are working with Repl.it,
you can also install packages just by going to the packages tab
and then again, searching for PrettyTable. Once you click on the package
that you want, click on the plus button to add it to your project.
Now Repl.it is a little bit weird because it says installing
but it never actually confirms the success. But once you click run,
everything will go through and it will work perfectly
as long as you see it in your list of packages here. Now,
if you want to remove the package, you can simply click on the minus button,
but now we're going to work with it.
So now it's installed successfully,
we can go ahead and close this down and click okay.
And we can now access this package called PrettyTable in our code.
Again,
I'm going to import it so I can say import prettytable.
And now I can use everything that's inside this package. Now,
if you want to see the source code,
you can actually right-click on it and select, go to, implementation.
And this will take you to the Python file where this entire prettytable is
implemented, so all of the code that they've written.
It's a little bit daunting and it's got a lot of code in it,
but we don't have to worry about how the code is created and how it works.
All we need to do is look at the documentation for this package and see how we
can implement it into our project. Now in the next lesson,
we're going to get some practice
constructing a prettytable object and using the documentation to explore this
object's attributes and methods. For all of that and more, I'll see you there.
In the last lesson, we added an external library to our project.
Now it's time to construct a prettytable object and practice using its methods
and attributes. Our starting point as always
is the documentation. Here
you can see how to construct an actual prettytable object.
So let's use what we've learned previously about constructing objects to go
ahead and create this object from the class. Now, firstly,
we're going to do the same thing as we did previously with turtle.
We're going to tap into the package prettytable,
and then we're going to import the prettytable class noted by the c here.
Now that we have access to this class inside our code,
I want you to go ahead and create an object from this pretty table class and the
object should be named table. So pause the video and give that a go.
All right. So we said I'll object is going to be called table,
and then we're going to construct it from this class called a prettytable.
So we're going to put it in with its casing.
So this is the Pascal case that we spoke about earlier on,
and then in order to actually give it the go-ahead and construct,
we have to add the parentheses at the end.
So now you've created a new object called table from this prettytable and we
can actually go ahead and print this table. And even at this stage,
it's ready going to start printing out a bare bones version all the table.
But of course this table has no datas
So it's actually kind of hard to visualize what all of these ASCII characters
are doing in an empty table.
But no matter, the next thing we can see in our documentation is how to go about
adding columns. So it's got this method, remember methods
are functions that are associated with an object and this method will add columns to
whatever table we specify. Now the method takes two inputs.
One is the name of the field,
so our field names are Pokemon name and type.
And then we've got a list of strings
which is going to be the data that's going to go into that column. Essentially,
every time we call that method, add column,
it's going to allow us to give a field name as a string,
and then a list of data in order that they're going to go into the table.
So we're going to add our table one column at a time. Using that documentation
see if you can add both of these columns to our table object and then once
you've done that, we're going to print the table object again
and we should be to see an ASCII table. This is what you're aiming for
when you run your code.
It should print out your table and nicely format it in this ASCII style.
Pause the video and complete the challenge.
Right?
All right.
So we've got our table object and remember that methods are functions that are
associated with the object. So we say table object dot,
and then we get to call that method,
add_column. And notice how it takes two inputs,
the field name and the data that's going to go into the column.
So the field name is going to be a string,
and this is going to be the name at the top of our column. So in our case,
it was called Pokemon name. And then after a comma,
we get to put in a list of all the data that's going to go into our column.
So just as a quick reminder, our first column contains Pikachu,
Squirtle and Charmander.
Now, we should have added a column to our table and you can safely ignore all
of these typos because of course, Pokemon names are not real words.
But if you wanted to check against the poke dex
you can actually go to this link in the course resources,
and you can see how each of these Pokemon are spelt. Now,
the next thing we want to add is the associated type with each of these
Pokemons. So for example, Charmander is a fire type of Pokemon,
Squirtle is a water type Pokemon,
but essentially we're going to add the data that's in the second column.
So the field name is called type, and then we've got three pieces of data
that's going to need to go into the list in the same order as the previous
Pokemon. That way we'll actually match them up properly.
So if you haven't already, go ahead and add the second column.
Right?
So again,
I'm going to call the same method on my table and this time I'm going to add the
field type and the data is going to go in the order of the data that I had from
the previous column. So the first one is the type of Pikachu which is electric.
And the second one is the type for Squirtle, which is Water. And finally,
we've got fire for Charmander.
So now this will be matched to this,
this will be matched this and so on and so forth.
If we go ahead and print our table now, so
if we run our code and take a look in here,
you can see how we've now got a nicely formatted table by creating an object
from this pre-made prettytable class and we've now called this method
add_column to add two columns. And when we print our table,
it's now nicely formatted in ASCII. Now,
remember that we can also change the object's attributes.
For example, if we wanted to change the appearance of our table,
that's probably controlled by an attribute. If you scroll down,
you can see that we can change the table style by tapping into each of these attributes.
For example, if I wanted to change the alignment of my data in the table,
I can change this align attribute to L for left-align, C for the center-align or
R for right-aligned.
Do you remember how to tap into an object's attribute? If you do,
go ahead and see if you can change our table from center-aligned by default to
left-aligned. Pause the video and try to complete that challenge.
Right?
So again,
we're going to tap into our table object and we're going to use the dot
notation, but this time
instead of accessing a method associated with the object
which is of course denoted by the M, we're going to access an attribute or in
this case, they've titled F which is a field.
And the one that we want is this align. So let's go ahead and type align,
and now we have access to this attribute. Let's see what happens
if I go ahead and print this align attribute.
You can see that for both of my columns, Pokemon name and type,
the align attribute is set to C, which is centered.
What I want to do is change the whole table to be left-aligned. Just as we would
with any other variable we can of course print it,
but we can also change it.
And we would change a variable by just using the equal sign, right?
So let's change the alignment to left-aligned,
and now let's run the code again.
And you can see now both of my columns are now aligning with the left hand
margin.
So we've seen how we can use attributes
like the ones here to change the styling of our table.
We've seen how we can use methods
like add_column or add_row to work with this table object and get it to
perform some sort of functionality, like adding pieces of data to it.
And we've seen how we can create new objects by simply constructing it from the
blueprint class. Feel free to mess around with prettytable
as much as you like change, other things about it,
or add different pieces of data.
But once you're happy with creating the object changing the attributes and
calling the methods,
then head over to the next lesson where I've got a quiz for you.
Now as we start using objects and their attributes and methods more and more,
we're going to start to see why it is that they are so useful and so loved by
programmers. Now,
I think one of the non-programmers that explained OOP the best is actually the late
Steve Jobs.
And he has this brilliant example that makes it really clear why objects are so
great. In his story
he talks about this concept where let's say you were traveling to Japan and
after a long flight,
you finally land and you go outside and there's beautiful cherry blossoms, Mt.
Fuji is looking wonderful. But unfortunately on the flight,
you had soiled your T-shirt.
You were overly eager with the tomato juice and you spilled everything upon
yourself. So what do we do? Well,
you're in this unfamiliar city and you have no idea
even whether the hell you are let alone where to find the nearest
dry cleaners or launderette. And plus on top of that,
you don't have the local currency. They take yen,
but you only have pounds and you don't even speak Japanese. So what do you do?
It's going to be a real struggle trying to solve this problem. Well,
you staying at a hotel, right? And the hotel staff probably speak English.
So you go the receptionist and you tell it the hotel that, Hey,
my t-shirt is soiled and they say, Hey, no problems. We'll take that from you.
And we'll go and handle all of that messy stuff.
We know how to find the dry cleaners,
we can pay them in the local currency and we speak the local language.
And what you get back is just a nice clean t-shirt.
So this is similar to the process of working with objects. Essentially,
if you have this hotel object
which has a blueprint for how to handle dry cleaning
some sort of clothing, then all you have to do is just get the object hotel and
then call its associated method dry clean,
and then it will do all of the messy stuff for you.
And you don't have to worry about the implementation of this function at all.
So now you can work with multiple objects
getting them to do different things and trust that they know how to manage their
data and how to perform the necessary functionality.
Coming back to a problem that we've already solved
creating that coffee machine with all of the program requirements. Well,
it's time to put our Object Oriented Programming knowledge to the test because
we're going to be making a OOP version of our coffee machine.
Now the program still has the same requirements
as before. You have to print reports for
all the resources, you have to check if the resources are sufficient,
process coins, check transaction is successful, and finally make coffee.
But in this case, you're going to be working with objects.
In the course resources,
you'll find a link to the starting project for the OOP coffee machine.
So if you head over to this link,
you can see that there's a whole bunch of code that we've already written for
you. Now,
the idea here is you're not going to touch any of these other files,
the money machine, the menu, or the coffee maker. All that code has already
been written for you
and it's almost like you're working with an external library.
You're just going to trust that they do what they say they do.
And you'll find a link to this coffee machine documentation that I've created
which describes in detail what each of these classes or blueprints allow you to
do. So once you construct an object from the menu item class,
then you have access to the name attribute, the cost attribute,
ingredient attributes, and there's also descriptions of what it should do
and what an example might be.
You have access to all of these classes and you can build objects from each of
these classes to solve this project.
In order to work with PyCharm, all you need to do is to download the zip
file it with all the starting code from our course resource website.
Alternatively,
if you are already logged in on Repl.it, simply fork the project and then click
on these three dots to download the zip file here. Now,
once you found that in your downloads folder,
all you have to do is uncompressed or unzip it.
And then you can go into PyCharm and open it here.
So click on the open button and then navigate to where you had that folder
downloaded. Remember it needs to be unzipped.
If you're on windows, right-click the zip file and choose extract all.
Then click extract.
You should see an unzipped folder popup next to your zip file.
If you're on Mac then all you need to do is just double-click on the .zip file.
Now, if we click open on that folder,
then it will open up this project. And when you open up the project folder,
you'll see all of the same files.
Now you're only going to be working from the main.py. In fact,
I don't even want you to care that much about the code that's in the other
files.
It has class definitions and a whole bunch of other things that we're going to
learn about in the next lesson.
But for now, I want you to treat it as if it is an external library
which you're just going to use. At the very beginning of the main.py file,
I've already imported all four classes that you are going to be using; menu,
menu item, coffee maker, and money machine.
Now all of these classes are documented in the coffee machine documentation
website.
All you have to do is head over to this website and read through what each of
the classes do. Some of them have attributes and methods,
others just have methods.
So each of these classes have already pre-written code that do a lot of the
heavy lifting and all of the code that we had to write when we wrote the coffee
machine code from scratch.
But this time you're only going to be using these four classes and the objects
created from them in order to achieve exactly the same goals as before.
So while the goals are fresh in your mind from the previous day,
you should review the code from the previous day and then have a read of the
documentation and see how you would implement exactly the same project
but this time using only the objects created from these classes.
You'll need to spend some time on this because you'll need to think through how
to create objects from these blueprint classes and then how to use the objects,
how to call the methods and the logic that's required to put everything
together. Pause the video
now, have a think about this problem, and try to make the coffee machine do
exactly the same and have all the same functionality as the coffee machine that
you created in yesterday's project.
If you got stuck or if you had any problems completing this project, the first port of call is to review
the lessons you learned today.
It might just be that you need to see some of the theory a few more times and listen to it a few more
times and practice it a few more times before you're ready to tackle this final challenge.
But if you have completed it and you just want to see the solution, then I'm going to go through it
with you right now.
Again, we're going to complete all of the program requirements step by step.
So the first thing is to print a report for all of the current resources in the coffee machine. Back
in PyCharm,
I'm actually going to collapse this entire project folder because I'm not going to be writing any code
other than inside main.py.
Now you can see up here, we've got access to four classes. And if we take a look inside the documentation,
you can see that both the coffeemaker class and the money machine class have a method called report.
And this is going to print a report of all of the resources like water, milk, coffee,
and this is going to print a report of the current profit.
So our final report is going to be both a report from the money machine as well as the coffee maker.
Let's go ahead and start off by creating some objects from these classes.
For example, the money machine is going to be just called money_machine
or you could call it my_money_machine.
You can actually name your objects anything you like.
But I'm just going to use the default Python snake case to create a new variable money_machine, which
is going to hold my object. And my object is going to be created, of course, from the money machine
class.
And the construction happens when I add the parentheses.
So now I have a object created and stored inside this variable money_machine.
Now, if I want this money machine to create a report, then all I have to do is tap into the object
and then write a dot and then call the method that I need, which is report.
So now if I go ahead and run my code,
you can see it prints out the current amount of money in the machine.
Now let's do the same thing for our coffee maker.
Again, I'm going to call it coffee_maker, and you see this frequently.
The object naming tends to be the lower case and snake case, so separated by underscores, version of the
name of the class.
So the name of the class is CoffeeMaker, and usually you'll see people name the object exactly the
same, but in lowercase.
And now that I have my coffee _maker, then I can go ahead and call the report method on that object
as well.
And now, if I run my code once more, you can see that I've got everything now being reported and printed
out.
So in this case, we don't actually have to care how report is implementing all of this functionality.
All we have to do is read the documentation, find the method that does the thing that we want, and
then trust that it will carry out the functionality as described.
Now that we've completed step 1, the next one is to check that resources are sufficient.
My first port of call is going to be going over to the documentation.
And you can see that the coffeemaker class actually has a method called is _resource_efficient.
And all we have to do is pass in the drink, which is a menu item, and then it's going to check and
give us true, if that drink order can be made, and false if the ingredients are insufficient.
So how do we get hold of this drink menu item to pass over to this method?
Well, if we take a look at the menu class, you can see it has a method called get_items and this is
where you really see reading the documentation properly,
actually absorbing everything that's in here becomes really, really helpful.
This menu class has two methods that are really useful.
One, It's able to get a hold of the names of all the items that are available on the menu.
And it returns it as a string separated by forward slashes.
It's also able to find a drink based on the order name.
So if we passed in one of these names to this function find_drink, then it's going to return a menu
item object if it actually exists.
Otherwise, it's going to return none.
We're going to need both of these in order to ask the user what they want.
Let's go ahead and set up our while loop. As we had previously
I'm going to create a new variable called is_on and it's going to start off being true.
And then while coffee machine is on, well then we're going to get hold of all the options that we
can offer the user. And we get that by calling that method get_items.
But of course, because this is a method, it's associated with an object.
So we have to create an object from this menu blueprint.
So let's do that next to all the other objects being created.
So let's create a menu object and it's going to be created from the menu class,
and then we add the parentheses.
And now we have access to that object by the name menu.
The options are going to be equal to the menu object and then we're going to call the get_items method.
And then when this method returns, it's going to save the string and all the options into this variable
called options.
Now we can get the user's choice by asking them for what would you like?
And then inside a set of parenthesis we'll offer them all the options. And then, of course, I need
to turn this into an fstring.
And the code highlighting immediately tells me that this is actually now working.
So once I've got the user's choice, then I can incorporate the reporting behaviour into this choice.
Remember, previously we said if the choice was equal to off, then that means the is_on is going
to be equal to false, and elif
the choice is equal to report,
well, in this case, we're going to get the coffeemaker and the money machine to make their reports
into the console.
Finally, we're ready to tackle the next problem, which is how do we check that we have enough resources?
And this is going to require us to find the drink given the order name that the user chose from the
choice and then get hold of the menu item which comes as the output from this method call.
So else, we're going to save our drink as a variable called drink, and then we're going to tap into
the menu.find_drink. And find_drink, you'll notice, takes a order name as the input.
So this is a string and this is going to be equal to whatever the user chose inside this choice.
So let's put the choice in here as the input.
And now, once we've got hold of this drink, let's go ahead and print it.
Remember, we're expecting a menu item object at this stage.
So let's click run, and let's make sure that we can hit report to get the report,
we can say off to switch off the machine and exit the code, and we can also get hold of a latte by
passing in latte as the drink that we want.
And we now get printed a menu item object at this particular location in the computer's memory.
Perfect.
Everything is working as expected.
Now, instead of printing the drink, I'm going to tackle this step 2, which is to check that the
resources are sufficient.
Again, that's going to require us to look through our documentation. And you'll see that the coffee
maker class has
that method is_resource _sufficient, and it expects a menu item object as the input.
And then it's going to return true when it can be made and false if it can't.
So let's get hold of our coffee maker object and then get it to check if the resources are sufficient
to make the current drink that we're interested in.
And let's go ahead and print the results here
and run our code.
Let's say that we wanted to make a latte. That's going to be resource sufficient, so true. Espresso,
also true, and a Cappuccino is also true.
So we can make all three drinks, basically.
Now, instead of printing this, what we want to do is we want to check if this is true and then proceed
to the next step if there are enough resources.
Now the next step is to take payment from the user and to process the coins and check the transaction
is successful.
Notice how in our coffee machine documentation for the money machine, we don't actually have a way
of processing the coins. But it what it does have is it allows us to make payments passing in the cost
of the drink and then it will return true when the payment is accepted or false, if insufficient.
So let's see what happens if we actually try to make payment.
Let's tap into our money machine object and then call the make_payment method and we have to pass in
the cost of the drink that the user ordered.
So we've got the drink object here, which remember is a menu item, and each of the menu items have
three attributes that we care about: the name of the drink, the cost of the drink and the ingredient
list.
So this is what we're interested in at the moment. So we can pass in the drink.cost which is the
attribute that's associated with the drink object,
and that cost is going to be processed by this make_payment method from the money machine.
And then finally, it's going to tell us whether if this was successful or not.
So let's see what happens when we run this code as it is.
Let's say I wanted a latte,
notice how it's asking me to insert coins:
how many quarters, how many dimes, how many nickels and how many pennies. A the coffee machine,
I don't actually need to care about how the money and the coins are processed.
All I had to do is call make_payment and it deals with all of this automatically.
Finally, it gives me the change and it returns true, telling me that this make_payment was indeed
successful.
If you actually look inside the money_machine code, then you can see that it has a method called process_
coins, but it's called when make payment is triggered.
This class is going to process coins, and then it's going to decide whether if it was successful
or not. And if it was successful, it's going to add the cost to the profit,
and if not, it's going to tell you that that was not enough money and your money is refunded.
Coming back over here, if this is successful, then that means the user has managed to pay and we fulfilled
step 3 and 4 just using one method.
The final thing we have to do is to actually make the coffee.
And that, of course, happens right at the end here.
And all we have to do to make the coffee is get hold of the coffee maker object and then call the make_
coffee method and we can pass in the order, which is our drink.
Because remember that the make_coffee method expects a menu item as the input parameter.
We can actually simplify this code even more by saying, well, if the coffee maker is_resource_sufficient
and the money machine was able to take payment, well then we can get the coffee_maker to make coffee.
So now let's go ahead and run our code.
And let's report to begin with, to see how much resources we have to begin with.
And then let's order a coffee.
Insert lots of money and we've got our coffee back.
So now let's go ahead and order a different coffee, latte, and let's go ahead and insert lots of money.
And you can see, here's my latte.
But now, if I hit report, you can see that the objects, the coffee maker has been managing our resources
and the money_machine has been managing our profit.
Now, if I decided to order another latte, then it should actually tell me, sorry, there's not enough
water and there's not enough milk. So it can't make me that drink.
And we've managed to achieve all of this functionality by writing very few lines of code, and the code
itself is actually very, very easy to understand.
Even if you came to this completely fresh, you've never seen how each of the methods are implemented,
you don't know how the coffee maker works,
you don't know how the money machine works,
you can see quite easily what it's trying to do.
And so if you only have to write this kind of code, then it would make it so much easier to create
even more complex functionality in your coffee machine, right?
So have a play around with these classes:
the coffeeMaker, the moneyMachine, the menu, the menu item, etc. And see what else it is that
you can do with this code
while not touching any of the blueprints for each of these classes.
Now, in the next lesson, I'm going to be showing you how to create your own classes so that you can
actually start structuring your code using full object-oriented programming.
And we're going to learn about these things like the initialization and how classes are declared and
why there's all this self all over the place.
That's all yet to come on tomorrow's lessons.