Hey guys,
welcome to Day 19 of 100 Days of Code. Today
we're going to be learning more about turtle graphics,
but we're also going to look at event listeners, higher order functions, state,
and multiple instances of an object.
And we're going to be using this knowledge to build a whole bunch of games. We're
going to be making Etch-a-Sketch, one of my favorite childhood toys.
And this game is going to allow us to use the up and down arrows to move our
turtle forwards and back
and then we can turn our turtle clockwise and anticlockwise to continue
drawing.
So we can use this to create circles or to create lines.
And we can basically create drawings using our turtle program.
In addition,
we're also going to be making a turtle racing game where we will get to bet on
the color of a turtle who will win the race.
And then once we click okay to the popup,
then all of our turtles go to the starting line and they start moving at a
random pace.
And then once the first turtle hits the right edge of the screen,
it will be declared the winner and we will get to see if our turtle won or not.
So at the moment, the red turtle is not looking like it's going to make it.
I think the orange is probably-- Oh, the yellow's overtaking it.
And there we go. We lose. The purple turtle
was the winner of the race. So I hope you're
as excited as I am to build these projects together. Once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and let's learn about how we can listen to key
strokes on the keyboard.
Now in order to be able to create a lot of the games that we've spoken about,
we need a way of being able to listen to things the user does,
like when the user taps a specific key on the keyboard. And the code that allows
us to do this are called event listeners.
So if we look at the turtle documentation,
you can see that there's a whole section on screen events,
including listening to key presses or listening to a click or other things that
you can listen to. So the important thing is this listen method.
This allows the turtle screen to start listening and waiting for events that the
user might trigger, like tapping on a key.
I've gone ahead and created a new PyCharm project which I've called day-19
and I've created my main.py file inside the project. Now,
the first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to import the turtle class and the
screen class from the turtle module.
And then I'm going to use them to create my Tim the turtle,
and also create a screen object.
This is basically going to control the window when we run our code.
So you saw it just flash just now.
Now in order to start listening for events,
we have to get hold of the screen object and then tell it to start listening.
And once it starts listening,
we have to bind a function that will be triggered when a particular key is
pressed on the keyboard. Now,
in order to bind a key stroke to an event in our code,
we have to use an event listener.
So the one that we're going to be using is this onkey method.
And you can see it expects a function with no arguments and also a key,
like the
'a' key on your keyboard or a key symbol, so the space or up or down.
So I'm going to say screen.onkey
and then I have to bind some sort of function to this method.
So let's create a function and we'll call it move_
forwards.
And all that this function is going to do is it's going to get Tim to go forward
by 10 paces. And let's not forget our colon here.
Now, coming back to my onkey method,
I'm going to say that when the space key, so the space bar, is pressed,
then trigger the function move_forwards.
Now here's a really important point; when we use a function as a argument,
so something that is going to be passed into another function,
we don't actually add the parentheses at the end.
The parentheses triggers the function to happen there and then.
But what we want is we want this method, onkey, to listen for when the space bar
is pressed and only when that happens to trigger this move_forwards function.
Now, the final thing I need to do is to add the exitonclick so that my screen
doesn't disappear when I run it.
And now what I'm going to try is when I hit the spacebar,
you should see my turtle move forwards by 10 paces each time.
So we're now controlling our turtle using a keystroke.
What we've essentially got here is a function that's being used as an input.
Let's say we have a function called function_a
that takes some sort of input.
And then we have a function called function_b, we can actually pass function_b
into function_a like this.
So notice that when we pass a function as an input,
we only pass the name without the parentheses at the end.
But how exactly does this function onkey work?
Because it's kind of crazy to use a function as the input to another function,
right?
So want to show you a quick example of passing a function into another function,
and I'm going to use the calculator example that we did many,
many moons ago. Um, when we created a calculator that could take two numbers,
add, subtract, multiply, or divide those numbers.
So we've got our four functions here. Now,
you don't actually have to write any of this out, cause it's quite tedious.
I just want you to watch and listen.
So let's say I create a final function, which I'll call calculator.
And this function is going to take a n1 and n2, two numbers,
but it's also going to take a function as an input.
Now, inside this calculator function,
I'm going to take the function name that was passed in
and then call that function by adding the parentheses and then passing in n1
and n2. So now I have my calculator function
which can take any function as an input.
And once that function has been passed in here,
then that function will get triggered passing in n1 and n2. Let's return
this result as the output,
and then let's call our calculator function,
let's pass in some numbers and let's pass in the name of a function.
So now let's go ahead and save this into a variable and then print that variable
result. So now when I run the code,
you can see I get five printed and that's because I've got add as the third
input here. But what happens if I change this to multiply? Well,
I get six instead of five.
And what happens if I put divide? Well, I get zero because,
because it's rounding up to a whole number.
But essentially what I'm trying to demonstrate to you is this concept
which is known in Python as Higher Order Functions.
And the idea of a higher order function is a function that can work with other
functions. So in this case,
our calculator is a higher order function because it's actually taking another
function as an input, and then working with it inside the body of the function.
Now there are certain programming languages where you can't do this at all.
But in Python, this is pretty commonly used.
And it's really useful when we need to listen for events and then trigger a
particular function. Now, while we're on the topic of functions,
I recommend that when you're using methods that you haven't created yourself
like for example onkey, to use keyword arguments
instead of positional arguments especially if like in this case,
the position doesn't actually have any meaning.
So now that you've seen how event listeners work,
we're going to be using event listeners to build out our Etch-A-Sketch program
in the next lesson. So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Now that you've seen how event listeners work, here's a challenge for you.
I want you to build a Etch-A-Sketch app.
This is what you're aiming for.
You should be able to create a turtle that will allow you to press the W key to
go forwards, the S key to go backwards,
the A key to go counterclockwise or leftwards and the D key to go right or
clockwise. And then be able to draw things like this,
or you could do up and right to draw curves like this.
We're kind of creating that childhood game which is Etch-A-Sketch.
When you press the C key,
it should clear all your drawings and put your turtle back in the center.
So think about what you've learned so far about how event listeners work,
and then use the turtle documentation,
read through the different methods that you have access to,
and then try to figure out how you can get this Etch-A-Sketch program to work in
the way that it's shown here. So pause the video and give this challenge a go.
This is the demo code from previously
and this is a really simplified version of how the event handlers work.
So for example, we've got our move_forwards function
which is going to be triggered when the space key is detected by the screen.
And the screen is able to detect it because it's listening for those keyboard
strokes and clicks. Now,
because the onkey function can only receive a function with no arguments,
at least this is what we see in the documentation,
then that means we have to create four separate functions, moveforwards,
move back, turn left, and turn right.
So now all I need is three more of these functions,
move backwards, turn left, and turn right. Now,
I'm going to change this binding from space to w which is going to be move
forwards.
And then I'm going to copy this and make three more of these so that I've got my
w as move_forwards,
and then I've got my S as move_backwards,
my a as turn_left and my d as turn_
right.
So now all we need to do is to actually create these functions.
So let's create our move_backwards
which is going to take Tim backwards by 10 paces.
And then the next function we're going to create is to turn_left.
And this is going to get the current heading of our turtle and add 10 degrees to
it.
So if you imagine that the turtle starts out pointing towards East
and this heading is going to be zero. And we know that to point North,
it becomes 90. So if we want this to turn leftwards,
then we have to add to the current heading value like this.
So this could be our new_heading,
and then we can get Tim to set
it's heading to that new heading so that we turn left by 10 degrees each time.
Now you could have also used simply just the left function.
So you could have said tim.left by 10 degrees. Both methods work
and it's totally up to you which one you choose. Now in order to turn right
it's basically the opposite. So instead of adding 10 degrees,
all we have to do is subtract 10 degrees or alternatively calling
tim.right, passing in 10 degrees.
Now we have all four functions defined and tied to a keystroke
let's go ahead and test it out.
So w should take us forwards, s should take us backwards,
a should turn left and D should turn right.
So perfect.
Now the last thing we wanted to code in was some sort of way of clearing the
screen. And we said we would bind that to the C key.
So I'm going to create a function called clear which I'll define here.
And this function is going to clear the screen wipe out all the drawing
and then take our turtle back to the beginning,
which was at the middle of the screen.
This is going to require a little bit of reading in the turtle documentation.
If you scroll through this list, you'll actually find two clear methods.
One is a method that is for the turtle
and another is a clear method for the screen,
which is the window basically. Now this clear is going to clear everything.
It's going to delete our turtle and everything else that's onscreen.
Whereas this clear,
which is tied to the turtle, is just going to delete this particular turtle's
drawings. So this is what we need to do.
We need to get hold of Tim and then call clear on him to get rid of all the
drawings he's made so far. Now,
the next thing we're going to do is we're going to bring our turtle back to the
center, to the starting point.
And this is going to be aided by one of the methods called home.
So I found this in the documentation and it says that it moves the turtle to the
origin, which is in the middle of the screen. Now,
all we need to do is to call home and notice what happens if I run this as it is.
So I can draw and basically make a mess.
And then when I hit C
you can see it goes back to the home,
but it's actually drawing its whole path back there as well. To prevent this from
happening we have to pull the pen up, which we've used before.
And then once Tim has reached home, then we're going to put the pen down
ready for the next drawing.
So now we can make a drawing, hit C, and then it goes back to the center.
Did you manage to complete this challenge? Don't beat yourself up
if you didn't manage to find some of the methods like home or clear.
It's a matter of getting practice with reading the documentation and having the
patience to go through it and look for the relevant methods.
And on top of that, it's just a matter of messing around with the code.
Try things out, see what happens. And each time you add something, run the code,
see if it does what you want it to do. And if not, fix it.
And that is the endless cycle of software development.
So don't get frustrated if you got stuck.
As long as you managed to make it work in the end
and you've learned some lessons from this process,
then you can congratulate yourself on completing the job.
And I find that I always learn more when I make more mistakes
and when I struggle more. Once you're done playing around with the code,
head over to the next lesson, and we're going to be learning about object
state and creating multiple instances of the same object.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
The objective is we want to be able to build a turtle race,
where we have multiple turtles to run along a line and then see who actually
reaches the finish line first. Now here's a question though.
We know how to build one turtle from the turtle blueprint,
but what if we need more turtles? How do we get hold of them?
Well,
we know that we can use a class or a blueprint to define what a turtle should
appear like and how it should behave.
So what it has and what it can do. Now,
we can then take this class and construct an actual turtle object from it
which is then doing all the drawing and walking around on the screen.
So this is what the code has looked like so far. We have Timmy
which is our turtle object, and turtle coming from the turtle module is the
class which is used to construct this object.
But that's not the end of the story because the whole reason why we can have
these blueprints is so we can make more objects.
So, we're not limited to just one turtle object.
We can create as many as we need in the same way that we have created Timmy.
We create Tommy, Johnny, Jenny, and Benny.
Even though both Timmy and Tommy are turtle objects,
they actually function completely independent of each other.
So in programming, we would say that they are each a separate instance.
So what does that mean? Well,
that means that they're each an example of the turtle object.
So just as you and I are both examples of human objects,
Timmy and Tommy are both examples of turtle objects.
And that means that at any moment in time,
they could have different attributes and they could be doing different things.
So that means, for example,
Timmy could have his color set to green while Tommy could have its color set to
something completely different, like purple.
Now the fact that each of these objects can have different attributes and can be
performing different methods at any one time in programming is known as their
state.
So the state of Timmy's color attribute is green and Tommy's color attribute is
purple. So in this case,
they have different state in terms of their attribute or their appearance.
But they can also have different state in terms of whether
if they are doing something. For example,
Timmy could be asked to move forwards while Tommy is staying completely
stationary. So Timmy is in the middle of a method call
whereas Tommy is not doing anything at all. Now in the next lesson,
we're going to be building out our turtle racing game
and we're going to see this in action.
The idea that you could have separate versions of the same object each with a
different state and acting completely independently from each other in order to
race against each other. So don't worry if this doesn't make sense
a hundred percent just yet. Head over to the next lesson
and we're going to start writing some real code to better understand this
concept.
All right guys. In this lesson, we're going to be building out our turtle race.
And through building this race,
we're going to get more familiar with these concepts of state and instances.
And that's because we need to create multiple turtles to join our race.
This is what we're aiming for. In the beginning,
there's going to be a little popup that will ask us to bet who will win the
race. And it asked me to choose a color.
Now the turtles are in the color of the rainbow,
so I'm just going to pick the red one. Once I hit okay,
we have all of our turtles lined up in the starting position and they will start
making random steps towards the right edge of the screen. Now,
the first hurdle that reaches past the right edge of the screen is going to be
the winner.
And at the moment it looks like the green turtle is probably going to get there
first. There we go. So as soon as a turtle crosses the finish line,
then it will print out a line telling us whether if we won or whether
if we lost our bets and which turtle won the game.
So this is the goal.
Now I'm going to get started by deleting all of the code inside our previous
Etch-A-Sketch project other than these few lines.
So I've got Tim my turtle, screen
which is a screen object that is going to hold the screen until I click on it so
that I can see what's going on. Now, because in this game
the dimensions of the screen or of the window is really crucial,
I'm not just going to get the default screen size show up. Instead
I'm actually going to use one of the methods that is in the screen object
which is called setup. And setup, as you can see,
allows me to set up the width and the height of this window
that's going to show up.
So I'm going to set the width of my screen to 500 and the height to 400.
So I should end up with a 500 pixel wide, 400 pixel high screen.
And once I hit run, you can see this is what it gets resized to.
Now, if you came across this code and it was somebody else's code,
then these numbers and their positions don't actually make a lot of sense,
which one's the height, which one's the width. So in these situations,
I recommend using keyword arguments rather than positional arguments. Oh,
let's write out the parameters explicitly. Our width
to be 500 and our height to be 400. This way
when somebody else comes along and reads your code,
it's a lot easier to understand rather than just 500 and 400,
cause it could be both ways.
So now that we've got our screen set up,
the next thing I want to do is to bring up that popup and ask the user to make a
bet. Now, if we take a look at the Python documentation,
um, where we've been spending a lot of time recently,
you can see that there is a method on the screen
which is called textinput.
And this is going to show up a popup window and it allow the user to look at the
prompt and the title and to enter a piece of text.
And if you want the user to enter a number, then you would use numinput.
So let's go ahead and add that here. So it will be a method from screen
which is called textinput and then it's got two parameters.
One is the title which in my case
I'm just going to say 'Make your bet'.
And then the second parameter is going to be the prompt. And in my case,
I will probably say, um,
which turtle win the race and tell them to enter a color.
Now, this works really similarly to our input
which we've been really used to because it will return the string and we can
catch that string inside a variable.
So we'll call it user_bet and we'll set it to equal the output from this
method.
Now let's give this a shot.
Let's run the code and then let's enter a color, hit okay.
And if we take a look in our console,
you can see that that bet string is printed in here.
So now the next thing we're going to do is we need to do something with our
turtle. I'm going to move it down a little bit.
And what I want my turtle to do is I want it to go to the start of the line.
So the very left edge of my screen. Now I could,
of course, just say tim.backward by, um,
however many paces,
but thinking forward and knowing that I'm going to have six or seven of these
turtles,
I can't just tell them all to go backwards because they're going to go to the
same position. Instead, we're going to use a method that the turtle has
which is called goto.
And this allows us to define an X value and a Y value.
But how do we know what X and Y values to give it? Well,
we first have to understand how the Python turtle coordinate system works.
So if you imagine your program window as a graph where the center of it is at
the coordinate (0, 0). Well
then if you have a window that has a height of 400,
then that graph will have a Y-axis that extends from the center at zero all the
way up to the top edge and then from the middle
it goes down to the very bottom edge, which is going to be -200.
So 200 plus 200 makes up 400 and the same happens with the X-axis.
So if the width of the screen is 500, then
the X-axis goes from the center 0 to positive 250,
so half of 500. And then from zero to -250.
So here's a question. Let's say we wanted to move our turtle here.
What do you think would be the X and Y coordinate of that point?
Okay. So let's say
that this is roughly halfway on the X-axis and about halfway on the Y-axis.
Then half of 250 is 125 and half of 200 is 100.
So at this point would have the coordinate of 125 by 100.
If we wanted our turtle to go all the way to the left side of the screen
say maybe starting over here or starting over here, well,
then we would have to use that
goto method and then specify a X-value and a Y-value. Following the logic of the
total coordinate system then in order to move our turtle to the very left edge,
then we should supply an X-value of minus 250
which is half of the width of 500.
Now the Y-value will determine where on the Y-axis our turtle moves to.
So if we had it at zero
then it would basically just go straight backwards and it would not go up or
down. But let's say that we put it at, um,
-100. So now if I run this code,
you can see that it goes in the right direction,
but it's actually gone off the screen.
So what's happened here is that -250 is on the very,
very edge of the window.
And once our turtle moves over there and the arrow is at the back,
then you can't actually see it at all.
So let's try changing that X-value and shifting our turtle a little bit more to
the right. Then you can see it moves to pretty much the start of the window.
So I recommend using this goto method and trying out some different numbers
just to see where it ends up on the screen.
And once you put in some different numbers in here,
you'll start to get the hang of how this coordinate system actually works.
But just remember that the X-axis is along the horizontal.
It goes from zero to positive and zero to negative.
And then the Y-axis is along the vertical,
going from zero to positive and zero to negative.
So we want to get rid of this line and we don't actually want our turtle to draw
at all. So to do that, we're going to do tim.penup,
and we're actually never going to put the pen down because we're going to be
moving the turtle itself.
And the other thing is that it would be really nice if instead of an arrow,
we actually got a turtle.
So we can of course say tim.shape and set it to a turtle shape,
but here's an even easier way. When we create a new turtle,
look at the prompt that it's giving us.
It's actually giving us a way to initialize a new turtle object already with a
shape set up.
Now this shape is set to have a default value
which is basically the arrow.
But we can also specify the shape and give it the turtle shape to begin with.
Now, when I run the code you can see that firstly,
I get a turtle shape and then the pen is up and I'm not drawing
and then it moves to this place on the graph; -230, -100.
So now the next thing we want to do is to be able to create lots of turtles,
right?
What if we had all of the colors in the rainbow and we create a turtle for each
color?
So there's six colors in this list and these of course,
correspond to the colors which turtle will recognize.
So here's a challenge for you.
I want you to create six turtles,
one for each of the colors in this list of colors.
You're aiming for the turtles to all go to the starting line in a distribution
that looks something like this. It doesn't have to be precise,
you don't have to get it perfectly right.
But just make sure that they're sort of evenly spaced out and they are at the
starting line. So this is what you're aiming for; six turtles, six colors,
all starting at the starting point along a different point on the Y axis.
Pause the video and give that a go.
So we know that in order to create lots of turtles,
we're going to need some sort of a loop.
So let's go ahead and use a for loop to say turtle_index
and we're going to create a range to specify how many turtles we need.
Our range function will go from 0 to 6.
And remember that the range function actually doesn't include the number six,
so it'll create a range from 0 to 5. And once we've done that,
then we can indent this block of code so that we create six turtles.
But at the moment, they're all going to the same position.
So how can we change this? Well,
we want the X-position to always be the same for all the turtles,
because the X-position is along the horizontal axis
and we want all the turtles to start at the starting point.
Nobody gets a headstart. But the Y-position is the thing that we want to change.
A really simple way of doing this is to simply create a list of Y-positions
and you can work out some sort of reasonable position that you want to take.
So let's say we start out at -70 and then we just increased by 30 each
time.
So then that becomes -40 and then -10 and then 20,
50 and 80.
So it's roughly distributed somewhere along the middle. Now,
instead of using this Y-position
which is hardcoded -100,
we're going to take the Y-positions and then pass in our turtle_index like
this. So now when we rerun this code,
you can see that for each of the turtles
they're all going to get an individual Y-position
and they're all separated by 30 in distance.
Now we've got our turtles neatly lined up at the starting point.
The next thing is to give them a different color.
So we're going to use the list of colors and then picking out the color using
the turtle_index.
So now we should get some multicolored turtles and it will be much easier to bet
on a turtle. So now that we have our turtle race
all set up and ready to go,
the next step is to actually get the turtles to start moving.
But before we can do that,
I really want you to get a good grasp of how the coordinate system works in
turtle. So in the next lesson,
I've got a quick quiz for you just to make sure that you really understand
what's going on here.
In the last lesson,
we figured out how we can get our turtle race up and running and get our turtles
at the starting positions. Now,
the next job we have is to figure out how we can get these turtles to start
moving. The movement is going to have to be randomized
and each step they take will have to be a random number. That way they don't go
straight to the end
and we end up with a terrible gaming experience.
So what we're going to do is we're going to create a random number,
let's say between 0 and 10,
and then we're going to tell the turtle to go forward by that random amount.
So it could be anywhere between 0 and 10.
And then we're going to get this to repeat itself many, many times.
As you might've guessed,
this is probably going to involve some sort of while loop.
So let's say we start out with a variable called is_race_on and it starts out as
false.
But then once the user has made their bet and we can check to see
user_bet exists, then in that case
we're going to switch that is_race_on to true.
And then we can use our is_race_on inside our while loop.
Now this way we prevent our while loop from starting up while the user is still
deciding on which turtle they're going to bet on.
So it doesn't start prematurely.
Now when the user has made their bet and the race is now on, well
now we're going to need to get hold of a random number.
We're going to use the random module to get hold of a random int between the
range of 0 and 10.
Now randint is actually inclusive,
so the random number could be zero all the way up to 10.
So now we're gonna call this the rand_distance,
and this is going to be the distance that one of our turtles is going to move
forwards by.
So we want some sort of turtle.forward and the distance that it goes forward
is the random distance.
Now we have lots of turtles that we've created,
but we kind of haven't really done anything with them.
What we want to do instead is to have some sort of list of turtle.
So we'll call all_turtles,
and this list starts out as empty.
But every single time we create a new turtle,
then we can append that turtle to this list. So at this stage,
it doesn't really make sense to call all the turtles tim anymore, right?
Because they're all going to be individual instances.
So let's go ahead and refactor and rename this to a new_turtle.
And now what's happening in our for loop is we're creating a new turtle and
each of those new turtles are going to be appended to our all_turtles list.
So now we're going to have a list of multiple turtle instances,
and each of those instances is going to have a different state.
So for example,
they already start out with a different Y-position and a different color.
But later on,
we're also going to get them to move forwards by a different amount.
So we can loop through our list of turtles,
so for turtle in all_turtles,
let's go ahead and create a random distance for each of them and then move that
turtle forward by the random distance.
So now if we run our code
and see it in action,
you can see that once all of the turtles have gone into their starting
positions, they stop creeping along each time by a different amount.
Now, however, our turtles are actually going to keep going until forever.
It's basically a loop that's never going to stop.
So let's think about what the stopping conditions should be. Well,
once any of these turtles have actually reached the end of the screen
which is the X-value of +250,
once they've reached this line, then that's kind of the end of the race,
right?
But a turtle object is a 40 by 40 object.
So if we're only detecting for the 250,
then our turtle would have already overshot.
So instead, we want to detect when the turtle has reached the 230 mark. Back in our
code in our for-loop,
we can check to see if the turtle that we're currently looping through,
if it's X-coordinate is greater than
230. Well, in this case, it's basically won.
Now at this stage,
if we print this current turtle's color,
then you'll actually see something a little bit strange.
You can see that firstly,
it prints multiple values because the while loop is still continuing and the
other turtles continue to go forward.
But the first value is going to be the turtle that won.
And you can see it prints yellow and yellow.
So what's going on here? Well, if we look at this color method,
you can see that you can either use it to set the pen color and fill color,
or it will return the pen color and fill color.
So when it prints out two colors,
the first one is going to be the pen color and the second is going to be the
fill color. So if we only want to know the pen color,
then we can just get hold of the turtle.pencolor.
This is going to be the color of the body of the turtle. So in our code,
we can say that the winning color is equal to the current turtle.pencolor.
And then we can now check to see if the winning color is equal to the user's
bet, because if this is the case, well then the user has won, right?
So we can tell them you've won.
And then we can tell them the color of the winning turtle.
Now, however,
if this is false or rather in the else statement,
well, in that case, we're going to have to print the same thing
but now we're going to tell them that they've lost.
Yeah.
Finally, when the first turtle reaches the X-coordinate,
when this first color gets printed,
we want to stop the while loop. This way
the remaining turtles don't continue to nudge forward
and we get end up with lots of winners like this. So inside this
if statement, when the turtle's X-coordinate has surpassed 230,
we're going to change the is_race_on to false.
Now we're ready to test out our code. And again,
I'm going to bet on the red turtle and I'm going to speed up the playback speed
of this race when I'm editing this video.
And now the game has ended and you can see that the blue turtle is the one that
first got its head across the finish line.
And it tells me just as much. I've lost and the blue turtle is the winner.
So we've now used Python turtle to build a very simple turtle racing game.
And we're starting to use these X and Y positions in the turtle coordinate
system. Now, these coordinates take a little bit of getting used to,
especially thinking about things such as if a turtle is 40 pixels wide,
then in order to get the turtle to the starting line
we have to subtract half of the width of the turtle, which is 20.
So then 250 minus 20 becomes 230.
And it's things like this that takes a little bit of getting used to.
So what I really recommend is to have a play around with these values,
make it smaller, or make it larger, change the size of the screen.
And just until you're really familiar with how the coordinate system works
before you proceed to the next lesson, because as you keep going,
I'm going to presume that you've already had a play around with it and you know
exactly how it works. Now,
the other thing that we saw a lot of in this project is this concept of having
multiple objects created from the same class. So in this case,
we're using the turtle class to construct a turtle object called Timmy,
but we've also got a separate object called Tommy. And Timmy and Tommy are both
Tuttle objects, but they're different instances. So they can act independently,
they can have different appearances, they can have different colors,
different attributes, and also a different speed of movement.
So we've seen in our turtle race that each of these instances can act of their
own accord and have different state.
And that's shown in the different speed of movement and this capability of
creating multiple objects which can act and behave independently
is really the secret to why Object Oriented Programming can be so
powerful.
We can create so many of these objects and get them to do our bidding in various
parts of our program. And in the coming lessons
as we build more and more complex projects,
you'll see this concept of having multiple instances with different state being
shown again and again. And we're going to come to see and enjoy the benefits.