Hey guys, welcome back to Day 2 of 100 Days of code.
In today's lessons, you're going to be learning about datatypes, numbers,
operations, type conversion, f-strings, and a whole lot more.
And by the end of today,
you will have learned enough to build a tip calculator.
So it looks a bit like this. It says, welcome to the tip calculator.
It asks you for the total bill that you need to pay.
So let's say it came to $124.54 we hit enter and then it asks you how many
people do you want to split the bill between?
So let's say this five of us having the meal and it asks you finally,
what percentage tip would you like to give?
So let's say we give a 12% tip.
Now it's going to calculate what each person should pay,
taking into account all of these pieces of information that you've put in.
So I know that I'm pretty bad at math,
especially when it comes to splitting bills.
And I'm normally the person who just says, yeah,
just tell me what I need to pay so I don't have to calculate it.
It's like the bad-at-math tax that I pay.
But in order to build this, you're going to need to learn some new skills,
including working with numbers, converting data types from one type to another,
and a whole lot more. So if you feel like you can tackle this, no problems.
Then feel free to skip today's lessons.
But I bet that there'll be loads of stuff that you'll come across in the
upcoming lessons and coding exercises that's really going to make you a better
developer. So once you're ready to get started,
head over to the next lesson and let's start coding.
Yesterday you saw that we could use the Len function to get the number of
characters in a string. So for example, when I write Len,
hello and I print this out,
we end up with 5. There's 5 characters in the string hello.
Now here's a question.
What happens if instead of counting the number of characters in a string,
what if I put in a number instead and I wanted to know how many digits are in
this number? Now if I go ahead and run this code,
you'll see that it actually crashes.
I get a whole bunch of red text and it tells me that there is a type error and
something about the type int. So what is all of this about?
Well, in order to understand it, we first have to learn about data types.
Now on day 1, we already explored this data type called strings.
Now you're probably not going to be surprised to learn that there's a whole lot
more other data types out there.
And today we're going to explore some of the most important and some of the most
basic data types such as strings, integers, float, and booleans.
And we'll explore each of these in detail.
So go ahead and get hold of the day 2 start coding sandbox and go ahead and
fork your own copy of it. Now once you've done that,
let's take a look at some of the data types.
So we already learned about strings, right?
And we know that this is just a string of characters.
So the word hello is comprised of these five characters strung together.
And we always know that strings, when we create them,
we have to create them with these double quotes around.
Now because this is a string of characters,
we can actually pull out each character individually. So we could, for example,
instead of just writing hello, we can add some square brackets.
So take a look on your keyboard and see where those are.
And inside the square brackets, we can put the index or the position of the
character that we want. So, for example,
if I wanted to have the first character out of this word hello,
I would put zero right here.
And if I go ahead and print what this actually will give me,
you'll see that you get capital H because that is the first character of this
string.
And it's really important to remember that programmers always start counting
from zero because we work with binary, zeros and ones.
So whenever you want to get hold of the first character or the first of
anything, it always is at zero.
So this method of pulling out a particular element from a string is called sub-
scripting. And the number in between the square brackets determines
which character you're going to pull out,
and it just goes up from zero to one to two and so on and so forth.
So whenever you get a result that's just off by one,
then remember to check whether if you've started counting from zero or if you
started counting from one.
Now you can of course extend this and get hold of the last character.
So pause the video and see if you can change the code so that 'o' gets printed
out here. All right,
so this is a simple as simply counting from zero, one, two, three,
four. So if we change this to four and we run our code,
then you'll see that 'o' gets printed instead of the H.
So by using these square brackets and putting a number inside,
we're able to dissect our string and pull out individual characters as and when
we need it.
And this will come in really handy in a lot of the programs that you'll write in
the future.
Now it's important to remember though that just because I can write a number
like "123",
as long as it's kept inside these double quotes,
then this is not treated as a number by the computer.
It's treated just as any other piece of text. You can't, for example, say,
um, what is "123" + "345".
If I try to print this, what do you think will happen?
Do you think it will give me 123 + 345
in the traditional sense,
like calculating it or do you think it'll do something else? All right,
let's hit run and we get 123345.
So it's basically just concatenated these two strings together,
just as we have done with other strings like hello and world, right?
Because it sees the datatype of these two pieces of data as strings.
When we use the plus sign,
it will actually just concatenate these two things instead of doing a
mathematical operation. Now if we want to do that,
then we actually have to declare our number as a number data type.
So one of the most common that you'll see is called an integer.
So this is programming lingo for just whole numbers, numbers
without any decimal places.
And in order to create an integer or declare an integer data type,
all you have to do is just write the number without anything else.
So now if I just write the numbers, 123 + 345
and then I go ahead and print this,
then you'll see that we actually get 468.
So it's actually being calculated because I've got actual numbers instead of
strings.
Just as we have some useful things that we can do with strings.
There's some really handy things that you can do with integers.
Commonly when we write large numbers,
at least in the UK or in the US, we'd like to put commas in between the
thousands.
So when we think of large numbers with these commas in between to split it into
an easier to understand number. In Python,
we can replace those commas simply with underscores and it will be interpreted
by the computer as if you had written this.
So the computer actually removes those underscores and ignores it.
The benefit is just for us humans to be able to visualize it more easily.
So I mentioned that all whole numbers
no matter if they're positive or negative, are called integers in programming.
So what do you call it when you actually have decimal places? Well,
they are called a float and this is short for a floating-point number.
So for example, if you had um, the numbers of PI,
you have 3.14159
and this, because it has a decimal place, is now a float data type.
So if you think of the decimal point as being able to float around the number
because it could occur at any point,
then you've got yourself a floating point number.
Now the final data type is something called a boolean.
And this is very simple. It only has two possible values,
true or false.
Now note how these values always begin with a capital T or capital F and they
don't have any quotation marks around them or anything.
So this is actually a data type which is going to be used a lot in your programs
to test if something is true,
if something is false and for your program to respond accordingly.
So we're going to be using this a lot more in the future.
Now that you've seen a lot of the basic data types, strings, integers, floats,
and boolean,
I want you to head over to the next lesson where I've got a quiz for you to see
if you've made this knowledge your own. So head over to the quiz and give it a go.
Previously we saw how the Len function gives us a type error when we give it a
number instead of a string.
So let's talk a little bit more about data types and functions.
And the way I think about functions is kind of like some sort of fancy machine
that you might see in a factory, right? So in this case,
we've got some sort of machine that's going to take potatoes into chips and we
don't really care how it does it,
but it's probably going to have to peel the potatoes, wash the potatoes,
cut it up, fry it,
and then finally return it to us as an output in the form of fries.
And if this is the first time that you're watching one of my tutorials, um,
this is probably a health warning. I talk about food a lot. Um,
so be prepared if you haven't eaten.
Now let's say that we took the same machine that normally processes potatoes and
we decided to get a rock and we just pass this through the function,
then we're getting an error, right? This is basically what happened here.
This length function doesn't like working with integers.
And by forcing this through,
we end up with an error and our code breaks and it gives us this thing, a type
error.
Now do you remember previously we had this challenge where we asked you to get
the um, get an input from the user, what is your name?
And then we use the length function to get the number of characters of their
name. And let's just save that to a variable. Let's call it, um,
num_char equals this.
And then we print your name has plus num_char, number of characters + characters.
So in this case you would expect it to prompt the user to enter their name.
Let's say I entered my name Angela,
and the length of that string would be 6
so this would be equal to six. And so this would get substituted in here.
And then with string concatenation, we end up printing
"Your name has six characters." But this is not what happens.
And I know that some of you might have tried this for the previous challenge and
you would have gotten a type error.
So it tells you that you can only concatenate strings,
not integers. So in this case,
we were concatenating a string to an integer.
This is what we get. We end up with an error.
So how can we prevent these type errors and how can we see the data type that
we're working with? Well,
we could use a function called type,
which basically will check whatever you put between the parentheses and give you
the type of data that it is. For example,
if I go ahead and just comment out this line of code
which breaks and go ahead and put num_char,
so this particular piece of data inside this type function,
and then I'm going to print the type of num_char.
And now if I hit run, let's enter my name.
And you can see it's telling you that this is an integer.
So adding a string to an integer doesn't make any sense,
which is why you got the type error.
Now every so often when you're writing code and you're not quite sure what the
type of data of something might be,
then you can simply just put it inside a type check function,
right? Like so. And then you'll get an answer.
Now in addition to type checking,
we can also do type conversion or you might hear it called type casting where we
change a piece of data from one particular data type to another.
So it, for example,
we know that this variable num_char has the data type of integer.
If we wanted to turn it into a string so that this line of code wouldn't break
anymore,
then we could convert it into a string by writing str
and then inside the parentheses, we put in the variable that we want to convert,
which is called num_char. And now we save this into a new variable,
we'll call it new_num_char.
And once we've converted this into a string and stored it under this name,
then we can use it inside our print statement, new_num_char,
and now it won't break anymore. And it tells us your name has six characters.
So in this case we've taken a integer data type,
put it inside the parentheses of a str function,
which takes a object in between the parentheses and converts it into a string,
which we then store inside this new_num_char
and we can now use it in our print statement because all the data types of all
the pieces of data that we're adding together have the same data type, string.
Now you're not limited to only converting numbers into strings.
You can convert a whole bunch of different data types.
So let me go ahead and comment out this code and I can show you that
let's say that we had a variable a, which we set two a number,
right? 123.
And if I do a type check on a and print this,
you'll see that as you would expect, it should give you integer, right?
A is an integer.
But now let's say I converted a into a string by wrapping it inside the string
function, then hit enter. You can see it's now of type string.
Now I can do this with other things as well. So for example,
I could turn my whole number here into a float and when I run my code,
now we see that the type of my variable is a float
and that's pretty straightforward, right?
But let me ask you two quick questions before we wrap up.
What will this line of code print? Alright, you guessed it,
this will print 170.5 but what's actually happening behind the scenes is we're
converting this string 100.5 into a floating-point number and then we're adding
70 to 100.5 and finally we're printing the results.
But what about this line? What will print here? Have a guess.
Well, this time we get 70100. So in summary,
you can use the type function to investigate the data type you're working with
and you can use functions like string, int, or float to convert to that data
type. In the next lesson, I've got a coding challenge for you.
So head over there and we'll get started.
All right, now
it's time to put what you've learned into practice by clicking on the data types
day 2.1 code challenge.
In this challenge,
the idea is that you are going to be given a random two-digit number,
so something like 39, and your code that you'll write
will be able to add the first digit to the second digit and end up with a
numerical result. So for example, if the input was 39,
then 3 + 9 would be equal to 12. So the output would be 12.
And if the input was 26,
then your code needs to print 8 to the console.
So you're going to need to think about type checking, type conversion,
as well as everything that you learned before.
And then you're going to write your code below this line without changing any of
these lines. So pause the video now and give this code challenge a go.
All right. So how did that go? Did you manage to do it? If not,
have a cup of tea or give yourself a little bit of a break,
think about something else and then come back to it and try it again.
If you've already
given it a good go and you want to see what the solution might be,
then follow along with me.
So the first thing we know is that we're going to have a variable
that's going to be equal to a two-digit number.
But remember that that could mean anything. That could mean an integer,
that could mean a floating-point number, that could even mean a number as a
string.
So it might be helpful to actually find out the data type of this two-digit
number that we get. And to do that, we of course use the type function, all
lowercase. And then in between the parentheses,
we add the thing that we want to check. So it's this variable.
And then let's go ahead and print the result into the console.
So now let's run our code and let's type a two-digit number,
say 56.
and we get the result that the type of this two-digit number is a string
because, of course, we're getting hold of this through the input function and the
user could be typing anything into this input, a string,
their name or a number.
So now that we know that this variable has the datatype string,
then you can think of a little bit about what we know we can do with strings.
We can subscript strings, right? So if we had a string like hello,
and we want it to get a hold of the first character, we could put zero there.
And when I print this,
we'll get H being selected out of this string.
So if we know that we can subscript strings to get a hold of a particular value
at a particular position just by using subscripting like this,
then we can do the same with our two-digit number.
So we could say two_digit_number, let's get hold of the first digit.
So let's call it
first_digit equals two_digit_number [
0],
and then the second_digit could be two_digit_number [1].
Now,
when I go ahead and print these two items,
first_digit and second_digit,
then you'll see that if I enter a number like 87,
then my first digit is 8 and my second digit is 7.
So now I can probably start thinking about adding those two digits together.
For example,
we can say that result equals first_digit plus second_digit.
But of course, when I run this right now and I print the value of result,
you'll see that for a number like 87
what I will get is just a eight concatenated to seven,
which turns it back into 87, which is not what I want at all.
Especially after all of my hard work separating out the digits.
What I want to do instead is to turn each of these,
which currently has the data type of string,
so I can demonstrate that to you by saying type of first_digit,
you can see it is a string.
So if I could only change first_digit and second_digit from string data types
into an integer data type by using the type conversion that we learned about
in the last lesson, well then once I do that,
then this plus sign has a whole different meaning because now it's going to add
this first_digit to the second_digit instead of concatenating it.
So now if I go ahead and print the results,
then you'll see that for the same number
87, my result is now 15.
I've now managed to achieve what the code exercise wants me to do.
So did you manage to get it right? If not,
go ahead and have a look at the model solution
and I've written some comments for each line of code that walks you through each
of the steps.
Now notice that instead of converting the second_digit here,
you can also do it up here, like what you see right here.
So I have a play around with the code,
especially if you struggled with this and didn't manage to get it right.
And then once you've understood what's going on here line by line,
if you need, have a look at the previous videos,
then go back to the code challenge and attempt it again.
And only once you're happy that you really understand everything that was
covered in this challenge,
then head over to the next lesson where we're going to talk more about
mathematical operators
like the plus sign and others that you can use in your code. So for all of that
and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In the previous lesson we saw how we could use the plus sign either to
concatenate strings together or as a mathematical operation where we add two
integers or two floats, basically two numbers together.
In this lesson I want to show you some of the other mathematical operators that
you have access to
in addition to adding. The next obvious one is subtraction.
So 7 - 3 , you would just use the minus sign,
but then when you get to multiplication it's a little bit weird. Um,
instead of using the x or some sort of time symbol,
you actually use the asterix.
So you would say something like 3 * 2 and that would be 3
times 2.
Now the final one is division and that's done using the forward-slash, so 6
/ 3 and when that prints out,
it'll give you 2.
Now one thing to notice here is that whenever you're dividing things,
you actually always end up with a floating point number.
So you can see even though six divides into three cleanly,
we're still getting 2.0. And in fact if I put a type check around this division,
you'll see that it will print float instead of integer.
And this is just something that happens with division in Python.
But at the end of the day, you get the result that you need and it doesn't really
matter whether if it's a float or if it's a integer.
Now the last one that's really useful is two asterisk signs and this gives you
access to the exponents or when you want to raise the number to a power.
So for example,
if you wanted to get a hold of 2 to the power of 2, then you would write it
like this and 2 to the power of 2 is of course basically just 2 times 2
which is going to be equal to 4.
Now if I change this to 2 to the power of 3,
then that's going to be 2 times 2 times 2. So that should be 8 and so
on and so forth.
Having the exponent being built into the language is one of the reasons why
Python is really loved by a lot of data scientists and mathematicians because
it's really optimized towards manipulating and handling numbers. Now,
one of the things that you have to be careful about when you are doing these
mathematical operations is when you have more than one operation on the same
line of code, then there's a certain level of priority.
So some of these operations like division or multiplication are going to be
first class,
whereas other ones are going to be more economy like the plus and minus.
And the rule that you might've remember from high school is something called
PEMDAS.
It basically states the order of priority is parentheses,
exponents, multiplication, division, addition and subtraction.
So the things that happen first are the things inside brackets, then it's our exponents,
then it's our multiplication and division.
And finally, the lowest priority is our addition and subtraction.
Now it's a little bit deceiving because of this order.
It makes it seem like as if multiplication happens before division,
but actually they are equally important.
And when it actually comes to your calculations,
the calculation that's most to the left is the one that will be prioritized
between multiplication and division.
So let me give you a real-life example to make this more clear.
Let's say we had a line of code where we wanted to multiply 3 * 3 +
3 / 3 - 3.
If I was to execute this entire line of code and print it out into the console,
here's the time where you play computer again and guess using what you've
learned here, um,
what exactly will be printed because you will get a number printed,
it will calculate this entire line of code for you. But the order matters.
Is it going to first add 3 to 3 then multiply the result by 3 or is
it first going to divide through by 3 and then add 3 to it?
What is the order?
And I want you to really pause the video and have a little play with it on pen
and paper before you come back and we'll show you the result.
Using our rule, PEMDAS,
we can see the first thing that happens is what's in the parentheses,
so that doesn't matter. The next thing, our exponents,
we don't actually have an exponent here.
We don't have 2 to the power of 3 or something to the power of anything.
So we can ignore that as well.
So the next level is the multiplication and division.
And as I mentioned, they are all equal importance.
So this 3 * 3 and 3 / 3 are both equally important,
but the calculation goes from left to right.
So the first thing we see is actually the multiplication. So if it helps you,
you might want to add LR to the end of this mnemonic.
So it becomes PEMDASLR, or at least that's the way I would think about it.
So even if this was division and this was multiplication,
this calculation will always get executed first.
Coming back to the question I asked you, what do you think this number would be?
Let's go ahead and comment out all the other code and run this line of code and
it will give us 7.0. Now if math is not your strong point, don't worry,
it's not mine either and you're the sort of person who would prefer to see it
visualize. Then I recommend again putting this line of code in Thonny,
and then go ahead and clicking on the debugging symbol and then just step into,
so press F7 or this button multiple times and you'll see it evaluate
this line of code step-by-step.
So first it looks at the entire thing and then it goes from left to right.
And the first calculation is 3 * 3 and that is the one that's going
to execute first and it becomes 9.
Next it's going to look along this line of code and see that the next most
important thing is this division here, 3 divided by 3.
So it's going to carry out that next and that becomes 1.
So now 9 + 1 is going to be the next thing because it's the most to the
left and then it becomes 10 - 3 and we finally get the result of 7.
So now here's another challenge for you.
How can you change this code so that instead of getting 7,
we get 3?
How can you change this line of code given what you know about PEMDASLR?
See if you can figure it out. Pause the video now.
Alright, so this will involve a little bit of trial and error.
And the most important tool we have access to is the parentheses or the
brackets. This means that we can actually isolate bits of our code,
which normally have very low priority and turn them into higher priority
operations. So in this case,
we know that 3 * 3 is going to happen first,
and then the multiplication, and then the addition on the left,
and then the subtraction.
But if we added a set of parentheses around our 3 + 3,
then out of all of these calculations,
this particular one suddenly becomes the highest priority and it will happen
first.
So if I change what I've got in Thonny to our new version and go ahead and debug
through it,
the very first calculation it's going to perform is this 3 + 3  inside
the brackets and we end up with 6.
So then it's going to go again from left to right,
prioritizing multiplication and division.
So then it's 3 * 6  is 18. 18 / 3 is 6. 6 - 3 is
3. Just by isolating certain calculations,
you can elevate it to right at the top of the priority list and you will be able
to perform the calculation that you need.
Now that you've learned a lot about calculations and performing mathematical
operations using Python, I've got another code challenge for you.
So head up to the next lesson and you'll be able to discover it there.
All right. So in this code challenge,
click on the date 2.2 BMI calculator code exercise.
So the goal of the challenge is to be able to work out somebody's body mass
index based on their weight and height that they input.
So the body mass index is basically a way of measuring somebody's body
composition that's kind of independent of their height, right?
If two people are both 60 kilos
but one of them is tall and the other person's short,
then the shorter guy is probably a little bit more overweight, right?
So if you take a look at this chart here, let's say, um, for me,
my height is around 1.8 meters and about 60 something kilos.
So I'm in this normal weight bracket of BMI 18.5 to 25.
So this is a really helpful tool for, um,
healthcare professionals to figure out whether if somebody is underweight,
normal weight or overweight,
that is based on their height and weight. In our program,
we're going to calculate this. So when we run our code,
you can see it's asking us for an input, height in meters.
So mine is 1.8 and my weight is say 63 kilos.
And when I hit enter,
ideally, I would like to get my BMI printed out as a whole number like this.
So how can we achieve this? Well, firstly,
you have to take a look at the equation that's used to calculate the BMI.
It's somebody's weight in kilograms
divided by their height squared.
Then once you've got the result,
we want it to be printed as a whole number or as an integer.
So you'll have to think a little bit about type conversion,
you'll have to think about the mathematical operations that we learned about in
the last lesson and combine everything you've learned so far in order to solve
this code challenge. So pause the video now and give that a go.
[inaudible]
All right. So now that you've had a go at it,
I'm going to reveal of solution. In our code
we've already got access to the height and the weight as variables,
so we can simply use them straight away. So for example,
I could just print the height and it would be equal to whatever the user typed
in when they were asked for it by the input. So in this case,
my height would get printed out as 1.8.
If we can access the height and weight,
then we can calculate the BMI by simply replicating the mathematical equation
here.
So we know that the BMI is equal to the weight divided by the height squared,
so we can take the weight and then we can use the forward-slash for divide.
And then we can divide it by the height squared.
So we're going to use the exponent operator to the power of two.
So this is how we could work out the BMI,
but you'll see that if we actually run this code right now
we'll actually get an error.
And what it's going to tell us is that on line 8,
so right here where our equation is, there's a type error.
And it saying that you're trying to use the exponent or the power function for a
string and an integer.
So the 2 is the integer,
but this is still a string. And we can confirm this
if we check the type. So type of height,
let's comment that out, and let's print this.
Then you'll see that when we enter some numbers here,
the type of height and weight in fact is string because they came from the input
function,
which we saw in previous lessons. Before we can actually just simply run this
equation and get the values we want,
we have to convert all the strings into other data types,
right? Now the weight is probably okay as an integer or a whole number because
it's already pretty accurate, 80 kilos or 85 kilos.
We don't necessarily need any decimal places.
But the height on the other hand definitely needs to be a floating-point number
because if it was an integer, then there would only be height of one meter,
two meter, three meter, four meter.
And because most people lie between one meter and two meter, then we really,
really need those numbers after the decimal place
in order to get an accurate calculation. So the height
definitely needs to be a float and we can convert it into a float using this
line of code here,
where we're converting the string into a float. And the weight
you can either convert it into an integer or a float. It doesn't really matter.
So now if we run our code again, you'll see we no longer have any errors
and we're now able to print our BMI.
Let me enter my height and weight again.
And you can see I'm getting this BMI with a massive list of numbers afterwards.
So in our result, we said it should be a whole number.
How can we convert this BMI into a whole number? Well,
we can turn it into bmi_as_int and convert this floating-point
number, the BMI with all of its numbers after the decimal place, into an integer
a whole number,
which will just simply cut off everything that's after the decimal place.
And now if we print this bmi_as_int,
run our code,
then you'll see that we get a whole number being printed out,
which is now our BMI. In the next lesson
I'm actually going to show you how we can round these floating point numbers so
that when it's 19.5 or above,
it becomes 20 when it's 19.4, 19.3, and then it gets rounded down.
But for now, this is all that we want.
We wanted you to be able to cut off the end and turn it into a whole number.
If you want to have a play around with the solution code,
then head over to this Repl.it over here and you'll be able to see the solution
code with a lot of comments
explaining the code line by line and showing you some different ways of doing
things. For example,
instead of converting the weight and height in line on the line where we're
actually doing the calculation, you could do it beforehand. Alternatively,
instead of using the exponent operator
because something to the power of two is simply just something multiplied by
itself, right? Then in this case,
you could also just do height_as_float times height_as_float.
Have a play around with this code and make sure that you're comfortable with
everything that's here.
And if you got anything wrong at all in the code challenge,
then go back and fix it. Now in the next lesson,
we're going to be talking about more mathematical operators
such as rounding numbers instead of just cutting off the end.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In the last challenge where we calculated the BMI,
you saw how when we had a number that had a long list of numbers after the
decimal point. For example,
if I had divided 8 by 3 and I print this out,
you'll see that the value is 2.666666 and if we had just turned this 8
divided by 3 into an integer, right now it's a floating point number,
but if I convert it into an integer,
you'll see that all it does is it just chops off everything after the decimal
point. Instead of what we would traditionally do,
which is to round the number.
So if it's 2.5 it would go to 3, if it's 2.4 it would go down to 2.
Now in Python it's super easy to round numbers.
All you have to do is to use the round function like this.
If we write round(8 / 3) then it's going to round it into a
whole number and you'll see that instead of 2 we actually get 3 now
because 2.6 recurring becomes 3.
Now if you wanted to, you can actually go a step further.
You can specify the number of digits of precision you want to round it to.
So if I said I want to round it to two decimal places,
then I could write (8 / 3, 2) and then the number of places
that I want around it to.
So now our 2.666 recurring becomes 2.67 because I said we should round it to 2
decimal places. So if it makes it easier,
it might be easier if I write it like this.
So 2.666666666 and I'm going to round it to two decimal places
and again, I get the same result,
2.67. Now another way of modifying numbers is instead of dividing,
say 8 / 3,
we can also use the floor division,
so where you have two forward lashes instead of just one.
Now we know that whenever we divide any number by any other number,
the result always gets turned into a floating point number.
Now if you didn't want that and you just wanted an integer,
so a whole number chopping off all the numbers after the decimal in place,
you can just use the floor division like this.
And in this case, you would get 2 straight away without having to convert it
into an integer. And in fact,
if I go ahead and check the data type of the result of this calculation,
you'll see that it's actually an integer
whereas if I had just used the single, um, forward slash division,
then I get a floating point number with decimal places.
Even if this is a clean division, say 4 / 2,
this is still going to become a floating point number and the number is going to
be represented like this, 2.0, like so.
Now if we had saved the results of this calculation into a variable instead,
then one of the things that you can actually do is to continue performing
calculations on this variable. So for example,
I could do 4 / 2,
which is going to be equal to 2. But then if I want to divide it by the 2
again,
I could actually say result /= 2. And when I now print results,
I'll actually get 1 because it's 4 / 2 then divided by 2
again. Now very often when you're writing code,
say for example if you're keeping track of the user's score,
so you could have score = 0 to begin with and every single time in
your code say a user scores a point,
then you can get hold of this score variable again
and instead of saying score now equals the previous value of score plus one,
you can simply use this shorthand, +=,
so +=1. And now when we print score,
you'll see that it's actually equal to 1.
So instead of using +=, you can use -=,
which just takes the previous version of score and removes 1 from it.
*=  and /=.
So this is really handy when you have to manipulate a value based on its
previous value, which you'll have to do a lot in programming.
Now the final thing I want to show you is something called F strings and this
makes it really easy to mix strings and different data types.
So far, up to this point,
if we wanted to print, uhm, something like your score is,
and then we wanted to print the score we have to write plus,
but of course because these are different data types,
this is a string and this is an integer, we got a type error.
So we've had to convert this into a string before it will actually successfully
print when both the datatypes match.
Now this is quite painful and understandably a lot of programmers will need some
slightly more convenient way of incorporating things that have different data
types. Let's say um, the score is equal to zero. Um,
let's say the height is equal to 1.8 and isWinning is equal to true.
So here we've got a integer, a float, and a boolean,
and we want to mix it all into a sentence that is a string and get it printed
out.
So instead of having to convert all of these and use a whole bunch of plus
signs and then you have to convert everything into a string,
it's really, really painful, right?
So what we can do instead is use something in Python known as an F string.
And when an F string allows us to do is in front of a string like this one,
we type the character 'f' and it's really important that it goes in front of the
double quotes or a single quotes if you want to write your strings like this.
But I like to use double quotes and a lot of other Python programmers do too.
So essentially you're adding just the character f in front of the string,
and now this is an F string and you can start adding various values into this
string. So for example, if I wanted to write,
your score is equal to this variable score,
then I can put that variable inside a set of curly braces like this.
And now when I print my string, this one right here,
you'll see that it says your score is zero and it does all of the converting and
all of the stuff behind the scenes and you don't have to worry about any of
this. So if I want to continue along,
I could say your score is this,
your height is adding the height and then you are winning is then let's add
that final boolean value
and get it to run.
You can see that our entire string now prints out your score is 0,
your height is 1.8 you are winning is True.
So all of these different data types got combined into a string by using an F in
front of the string and then using these curly braces to place our variables
into this string. By using f strings,
you cut down on a lot of the manual labor of inserting different data types into
a string.
And this is going to come in really handy just about on the next lesson where
I've got a coding challenge for you.
Head over there and complete the challenge.
So you should see day 2.3 Your Life in Weeks, and this is the challenge that we're going to complete
in this lesson.
The idea is that there's a really great article by Tim Urban of Wait but Why on visualizing your
life in weeks.
And I was reading this recently, and it really made an impact on me, especially when you see that
a whole life from age 0 to 90 can be mapped out like this in weeks where every week is represented
by a little checkbox and you can see each of these boxes right?
This is like how many weeks you have in your whole life, and it's not as small as I thought it would
be.
I thought each of these boxes would be like invisible because they're so tiny because
I have so many weeks in my life, but it's actually not true.
There's actually not that many.
So in today's coding challenge, what I want you to do is to create a program using the mathematical
operations that you learned about, as well as the fstrings that you learned about in the last lesson
to tell us how many days, weeks and months we actually have left
if we were lucky enough to live until 90 years old. The code is going to ask you for your current age,
let's say that I'm 12, and then it's going to calculate the number of days, weeks and months you have
left in your life if you lived until 90. And then it's going to print it out to you
like so.
And the important premise of this code challenge for all of the test to pass is that there are 365 days
in the year, 52 weeks in a year and 12 months in a year.
I know that because of leap year, it's actually a little bit more than that,
but for this exercise sake, let's just call it 365, 52 and 12.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge and then head back over here and we'll walk through
the solution together.
All right.
How did that exercise go?
I'm sorry, it's a little bit dark making you think about how many days, weeks and months you have left
in life, but you can think about it as a motivation, right?
If I only have 400 months left, I don't know if I want to spend one of those months just watching Game
of Thrones.
Maybe I want to do something for other people.
Maybe I want to create something.
So how are we going to calculate this?
Well, we've got hold of the age from the input, but you might remember from previous lessons that
the input always creates a string data type.
In order to do your maths, we do still have to do a type conversion, so we have to change our age
into a number.
So let's call it age_as_int, age is never going to be a float, right?
Because not many people are going to tell you that they are 56.4 years old, so we're
going to accept this as a whole number. So we'll convert our age into an int.
Now the next stage is we have to do some calculations.
We have to calculate the number of years left, right?
So let's call it years_remaining and that's going to be equal to 90,
so we're presuming we're going to live to 90, minus age_as_int.
So now that we've got the number of years remaining, we can calculate the number of days, weeks and
months left.
So days remaining is going to be equal to years remaining multiplied by 365 because there
are 365 days in a year, and then we can do the same for weeks.
And months.
So now that I've got hold of the number of days remaining, weeks remaining and months remaining, then
I'm ready to actually use it inside my string.
But before we do that, it's always helpful to check your code as you go along to make sure that it
works exactly as you expect it to.
So let's go ahead and try to print what is the number of months remaining.
So if we go ahead and run our code and let's say that we're 80 years old, right?
Which means that we'll have 10 years remaining and we'll have 120 months remaining.
So all of that looks pretty good to me.
So the next thing we have to do is to somehow output this sentence where it says you have x days, y weeks
and z months left.
So let's copy that and paste that sentence in here.
And then I'm going to turn it into a string by wrapping it inside a set of double-quotes.
Now that I've got a string, I can turn it into an fstring by putting the card to 'f' before the string.
And instead of having x, y and z, I can replace them with some curly braces inside of which I can
put my variable names.
So I'll change this to days_remaining, this to weeks_remaining and this to months_remaining.
So now that I've got my string, I have two options: I can either just wrap this inside a print statement
and print it as it is.
But what I think might actually make it easier to read is to save it inside a separate variable called
message.
And then in the next line, I can simply print my message.
It does exactly the same thing, but I think this is a little bit easier to read.
So now let's go ahead and run our code and see if we get any errors.
It's asking us for our current age, let's say, was 67 years old.
Well, then we only have 8,395 days and 1,196 weeks and 276 months.
So I hope you managed to get this code challenge right
and even though the challenge is a little bit dark,
well, at least remember that when you become a really good programmer, you'll be able to cut down
on a lot of the boring things and repetitive tasks in life.
So at least you'll be claiming back some of those days, weeks and months.
So I hope you had fun with me on this code challenge. In the next lesson,
I've got a quiz for you. So head over there and give it a go.
Hey, guys, welcome to the final project of today, and in this final project, we're going to be building
a tip calculator.
So the final output is going to look like this.
It's going to print
Welcome to the tip calculator.
And it's going to ask you for an input for how much the total bill came to.
Let's say that we and a couple of friends went out for lunch and it came to 124.
56 dollars.
And then it'll ask you, what percentage tip would you like to give?
So let's say we want to give a 12 percent tip.
So we enter 12 and hit enter.
And then finally it asks how many people are splitting this bill?
Let's say there's seven of us and then hit enter.
Finally, it's going to tell us that each person should pay about $19.93.
Notice how the final bill, even though after all of these calculations, it's probably got more numbers
after the decimal point, we only want two decimal places of accuracy, so it should be rounded to two
decimal places.
The second thing to remember is that these are percentages, and in order to calculate a percentage of
something, you can multiply a number by the percentage number divided by 100.
Let me show you this in a little bit more detail.
If you head over to replit/appbrewery/tip-calculator-start, then you've got
these starting file for this project.
And here I just want to quickly show you how the math works, because this project is not about testing
your math.
It's about seeing how well you've understood the programming concepts.
Let's say that we had a bill of $150.
If we were to apply a 12% tip on top of that, then 12% is going to be equal to twelve
divided by a hundred, which is equal to 0.12.
Now the next step is we can multiply 150, the total bill, by 0.12.
And this will give us what 12 percent of 150 is, which is 18.
Now we of course, have to add the tip onto the final bill so it becomes 150 plus 18.
So $150 with a 12 percent tip is equal to $168.
Now, a shorthand way of doing all of this is simply multiplying 150 by 1.12.
So the 1 is 150, and then it's 0.12 on top of that.
So when we do this, it gives us pretty much the same number.
Now, if during your testing and your coding you come across some sort of number that looks a little
bit strange because you think 150 multiplied by 1.12 should actually equal 168
precisely.
So what are all of these extra numbers at the end?
Now, the short answer is you don't have to worry about it.
It's simply related to how Python processes these floating-point numbers.
If you're really interested and you want to read about this, then I'll link to this page in the Python
documentation where they tell you why this is happening.
But be warned, it's pretty dense and it's pretty heavy.
But the final conclusion is it's just the way that Python is approximating this number.
So you don't actually have to worry about this.
Now, once we've gotten to 168, the next step is to split it between five people.
So 168 divided by 5 is equal to 33.6.
Now, what we want to show the user is we want to show them the amount that they have to pay with two
decimal places of accuracy.
We want to say something like 33.60 if this is the case, because that's normally
how we represent numbers when it comes to money.
So what I want you to do is to also be able to round any of these numbers to two decimal places.
If you have successfully created this program, then it should work exactly as this example version
would, which you can find if you go to tip-calculator-end.appbrewery.repl.run, and
you'll be to see the formatting where it actually tells you each person should pay this particular dollar
amount and it's rounded to two decimal places.
And this is the amount after taking into consideration these three different inputs from the user.
Have a play around with the final product and then have a think about how you would create this program
step by step and then give it a go by forking this starting repository to your own account and then
try to achieve this result.
This is going to test everything that you've done so far including fstrings, including complex
mathematical operations,
including PEMDAS and calculating numbers and the order in which mathematical operations are run by
a computer, as well as everything you learn in the previous lesson and the previous days as well. I think
this is going to be a lot of fun and the end result is going to be kind of useful the next time that
you need to split the bill between friends.
So I'm going to let you pause the video and get on with it.
And then once you're done, if you want to, head back over here and I'll walk through the solution with
you. But I really recommend you giving it a good go before you come back.
So pause the video now and I'll see you later.
OK, so we've seen how the program is supposed to work and we're trying to create it from scratch by
reverse-engineering it essentially. The first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to fork the starting
project and create my own version of it which I can edit.
Now, the first thing our program should say is welcome to the tip calculator.
So that's easy enough.
We just have to create a print statement.
Perfect.
And if you're creating a really enthusiastic tip calculator, you can replace the full stop with an
exclamation mark.
OK, so let's run it step by step to make sure that we don't have any errors along the way.
So the first step seems to be working. Now
the next step is to ask the user for some input.
And we want to know what was their total bill, what did it come to?
So let's go ahead and create an input and ask them what was the total bill?
And then we'll add a dollar sign or whatever currency it is that you prefer to work with.
Because when we actually run this, you'll see that the input will go straight after the end of that
string,
so at the dollar sign.
So now we can enter a dollar amount like this, but it's not really saved anywhere.
This data just disappears because we haven't stored it inside a variable.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Let's call this variable bill and we'll set it to equal whatever the user typed in to this input.
Now, remember that this bill is going to have a data type of a string, right?
So if I go ahead and hit run and let's just type some numbers in here, you'll see that the data type
of the bill is, as we said, a string. In order to be able to do math,
you might remember, we have to change this into a number format,
so a float or an int.
Now, in this case, because the bill is likely to have numbers after the decimal place, it's probably
better that we turn it into a float so that we get the most accurate result possible. Now that we're
done with the bill,
the next question the tip calculator should ask is what percentage tip would you like to give? 10, 12
or 15?
Or you can, of course, switch this up depending on how much tip you normally give.
So the next line is going to be another input.
Here, I'm asking the user, how much tip would you like to give and giving them some examples. And
notice how in my examples, I don't actually have the percentage sign here because I don't really
want them to type the percent sign into this input because if they do when they say 12%,
this is going to be really hard for me to turn the 12% into an actual number.
So you could, in your input message, say something like how much tip would you like to give 10,
12, 15?
Please don't add any percentage signs.
Just add the number or something like that.
But again, once we've done this, it's not stored anywhere unless we add it into a variable.
Now we've got a bill that stores the total bill as a float and we've got a tip which is going to be
a whole number, 10, 12 or 15,
right?
So depending on what you think is best, you can either turn this into a float or in my case, I'm probably
going to convert it into an integer.
So now we're onto the final step, which is how many people to split the bill between.
So let's go ahead and create a variable called people.
And I'm going to add an int wrapper around this input so that even in the very beginning, we know that
we have to convert the number of people into a whole number because I've never had a meal with
3.5 before.
So the input is going to be how many people to split the bill.
And at this point, they should enter the number of people which will turn into an integer stored inside
this variable called people. So now that we've got all the data collected from the user, we're finally
ready to do some math.
And we said that the way to work out the tip is by multiplying it by 1. and then the number after
the decimal point is whatever percentage they decided to give.
So it would be 1.1 if it was 10 percent and 1.15 if it was 15 percent.
Let's go ahead and calculate the bill_with_tip.
So remember how we said that before the tip percentage is equal to the whole number, 10, 12 or 15,
divided by 100, which turns it into 0.1, 0.12 or 0.15,
and then once this calculation is done, we can multiply it by the bill. And then finally we add that
to the original bill.
So let's go ahead and print this and just check to see that it looks sensible.
So bill_with_tip is what we're going to print.
And let's put some easy numbers in there.
And let's say that the bill was a hundred dollars and the tip was 10 percent.
So then the 10% of hundred dollars is ten dollars.
So the bill_with_tip,
that's what's going to be printed next, should be 110. So we can type anything in here because
we're not using it.
And you can see that this calculation, bill_with_tip, is 110, which is what we want.
Now, there's a lot of other ways that you can express this.
For example, you could say, bill * (1 + tip/100).
So this would actually give you the same result as well.
But remember what we said previously about how Python is a little bit weird with floating-point numbers.
But essentially this is still giving us the same result, which is 110.
So you can choose whichever way you find most intuitive.
And if you want, you can even split this up into several steps, right?
We could say that tip_as_percent is equal to tip/100.
And then we can multiply the bill by the tip_as_percent to get the total tip amount.
And then finally, we can get the total bill by adding the bill to the total_tip_amount.
Feel free to do this whichever way makes sense to you, but I'm going to leave it with as many steps
as possible so that you can actually work through the logic if you got stuck on this math.
Now, the next thing we need to do is to divide the total bill by the number of people.
So if we had five people, then we would divide it five ways,
right?
So let's call this bill_per_
person, which is going to be equal to the total bill divided by the number of people.
Now, at this stage, this bill_per_person is a floating-point number, so it could have many, many
digits after the decimal point.
If we want to round this to two decimal places, then you might remember from some of the lessons today,
we have access to a function called round.
And here we can add the number that we want around, which is the bill_per_person,
and then after a comma, we can specify how precise, how many numbers or how many decimal places do
we want to round this bill to.
And in our case, it's two decimal places.
So now this is the final amounts, which I'll call final_amount which is the bill_per_person rounded
to two decimal places.
And we can now finally print this to the user and say each person should pay...
And remember, you can either use string concatenation which will require you to convert this number
into a string again, or use the trick that we learned in the previous lessons where we can create an
fstring by adding F in front of the string and then using some curly braces to insert the final amount
right here.
And we can write the final_amount dollars or we can put a dollar sign in front and maybe a colon here.
And now if we clear our console and run our code, then you'll see it work.
So welcome to the tip calculator.
What was the total bill?
Let's make up some random number.
What percentage tip?
Let's say we're going to get 15 and then we're splitting it between five people. And it calculates everything,
doing all of that maths.
And finally, it rounds it to two decimal places, giving us the final amount each person should pay.
But what if we test it out with the initial numbers?
Let's hit, run and let's try to put in 150 dollars as the total bill, and then we're going to give
a 12 percent tip and we're going to split it between five people.
Notice that is telling us that each person should pay $33.6.
But normally, we're used to seeing that rounded to two decimal places.
But we have that round function here already.
So why is it not doing its job?
Well, if you think about it, the result of this calculation is just 33.6. There's
nothing after the six, but we want it to display a zero. And this is a formating problem rather than
a mathematical rounding problem.
So what do we do?
Well, we go to our good friend Google whenever we're stuck and we're going to search for how to round
number to two decimal places in Python.
And if we take a look at the first Stack Overflow question, you can see that this person had pretty much
the same problem that we had.
And if we're scrolling down, you can see that the solution is to use some sort of formatting. And we
can try out each of these examples one by one in code to see how they work,
and we can also take a look at the documentation that they link to.
So the actual way that we do this is by using a colon and then dot and then we specify that after the
dot, we want two decimal points in our float. And we use the format function to do this.
So instead of using round, we can create this final amount variable by creating a string using that
format, :.2f, and then we can use the format function to pass in that bill_per_person.
And now when we run this again, using the same inputs, we now get a .60 at the very end
and this is basically turned this bill_per_person, which is a float into a string.
And that string is abiding by this particular format, which is the two decimal places.
How did you get on with this project?
Did you manage to get it in one go without having to look at the solution? If you got stuck at any point
or if your code didn't work as you expect it to,
this is a time to go back to it, fix it, and make sure that you've understood everything that's been
covered through this exercise.
But if you already created it and it's working perfectly, then you're ready to go out there with your
tip calculator in hand.
Remember that you can save the URL of your tip calculator in your phone as a bookmark.
So the next time you go out and have dinner or lunch with friends, then you can crack open your own
tip calculator and figure out the final bill.
So I hope you had fun building this project and doing all of the coding exercises and learning about mathematical
operations, fstrings, data types, type conversion, and all of the things that we did today. Have a rest
and I'll be back tomorrow teaching you about conditional statements and how we can get the program to
do different things depending on certain conditions or certain parts of our code.
So I bid you good night and I'll see you tomorrow.