Hey guys, welcome to Day 20 of 100
Days of Code. Today
is really exciting because we're going to be using the knowledge that we've
gained about Object Oriented Programming
as well as what we learned about how to use the turtle module to build the
famous snake game. Now,
this is probably one of the most famous mobile games that ever was,
and it's definitely one of my favorite. And my history with it goes back all the
way to my very first mobile phone,
the Nokia 3310. It might be showing my age a little bit here,
but this was my first ever mobile phone.
I remember loving it so much that I actually had it next to my pillow when I
went to sleep. And this was probably one of the first affordable mobile phones.
And it was endlessly customizable with different cases and different keys.
But the most exciting thing about it
was the snake game. I would compare
with my friends and see who got the highest score in snake
and we would spend days and days playing this game. And compared to the iPhone
games of today, of course, this was very, very simple, but nonetheless,
it is still super addictive. Over the next two days
this is the game that we're going to build. A snake game that has,
um, a moving snake, which you control using your keyboard,
and you can go and get food,
and then it grows in length as it eats more food.
And you have to make sure that you don't end up getting tangled or hitting the
wall.
And the goal is to eat as much food as you can while staying alive.
There are some people who are truly masters at this game, um,
which I personally am not,
but they managed to get their snakes to crazy lengths and start having these
strategies for how you can avoid hitting your tail and how you can keep going.
So once you've built your snake game, you'll be able to play with it,
and you'll be able to show off your high scores to the rest of us,
but I'm sure you're going to do a lot better than me.
It's not that hard to beat me at snake. As always,
when we're thinking about a complex problem
the first step is to break down the problem.
And I'm going to break down this problem of building the snake game into seven
separate steps.
And the way we're going to do it is we're going to tackle the first three steps
on Day 1 and the last four steps on Day 2.
So we're going to split up this game into two parts and we're going to tackle it
over two days. The first step is to create a snake body,
and we're going to do that by creating three squares on the screen,
all lined up next to each other.
And then we're going to figure out how to move the snake so that it continuously
moves forward
and all we have to do is tell it to change direction. Afterwards,
we're going to figure out how to control the snake using keyboard controls.
So we're going to be using the up, left, down, and right arrow keys to move our
snake across the screen.
And that is what we're aiming for by the end of today,
Day 20. On Day 21,
we're going to continue and we're going to build out the last four steps of the
snake game.
Then we'll need to start putting some food onto the screen and started to detect
the collision with the food so that once the snake hits the food,
then a new piece of food gets created randomly on the screen at some sort of
random location.
And then it's a matter of keeping track of the score and creating a scoreboard.
So we're going to learn how to write text in our program so that once the snake
hits a piece of food, the score automatically updates.
And then next we're going to figure out when the game should end.
So one of the cases when the game should end is when the snake has collided with
the wall. And at this point we should see game over,
show up on screen and the snake should no longer move.
And then finally,
the other reason why our game could end is when the snake has collided with its
own tail. So the snake basically can't chase his own tail.
And as the snake gets longer, this problem is more likely to occur.
And when their head hits any part of the body of the snake, then it's again,
game over. So these are the seven steps
that it takes to create the snake game.
And once you're ready, we're gonna get started with step one on the next lesson.
So I'll see you there.
So to start off,
go ahead and create a new project called snake_game in PyCharm.
And then inside this project, we're going to create a new main.py file.
And inside our file, we're going to need our normal imports.
So I'm going to say from turtle import the screen class and also the turtle
class. Now,
the first thing we're going to do is we're going to create a new screen,
which is basically going to be the window that shows up.
And then we're going to set up our screen so that it is 600 by 600.
So the width is going to be 600 pixels and the height is also going to be 600
pixels. And notice how I'm using these keyword arguments
so that it's a little bit clearer to the next person looking at this code
what's actually happening here. Now,
the other thing I want to change is the screen's background color.
So there's a method called bgcolor and inside here
we're going to write the text black so that we end up with a black screen.
Now,
another thing that you might not have seen before is how to set the title of
the window that shows up. And we do that through a method called title,
and you can name your program here. So I'm going to call it 'My Snake Game',
but you can of course call it whatever it is you want. Now finally,
at the very bottom of the file, I'm going to say screen.exitonclick.
So this way, when I actually run it, it doesn't just disappear straight away
and it waits for me and I can look at what's actually happened so far.
So I'm going to click run and then select my main file.
And once it pops up,
this is what you should see, a 600 by 600 square window
and then at the top of the window, you'll see the name of your program,
which is My Snake Game. And the background is now black.
Now that we've set up our screen,
we're ready to tackle the first of our seven steps,
which is to create a snake body.
And we're going to create three squares
which are each going to be turtles,
and they're going to be lined up next to each other along the horizontal axis.
So let's think about this. When we create a new turtle,
it has a dimension of 20 pixels wide by 20 pixels tall.
And if we want three of them lined up next to each other,
then we have to think about how we create their coordinates. As a challenge,
I want you to think about how we can create this. Here
we have three separate squares
which are each a turtle object and they're shaped like a square and they have a
white color. Now, they're positioned
so that the first one is (0, 0),
the next one is 20 pixels to the left and the next one is again
20 pixels to the left so that none of the squares overlap with each other,
but there's also no gaps. So it looks like a whole snake.
This is your challenge
and you might have to think about a few of the things that we've done before in
order to achieve this. So browse the documentation,
look back to the previous code that you've written and see if you can solve this
challenge. Pause the video now.
Alright.
So the first thing we're going to need to do is to create some sort of turtle,
right?
So let's call this segment_1 and this is going to be a new turtle.
And remember that when we initialize the turtle,
we can already specify the shape.
So we can either say shape = "square",
or simply just leave it as square. So now at this point,
we should end up with a square turtle, but because it's black,
when we run the code, we won't actually see it on screen.
So let's change this segment color to white.
And all we have to do is write the word for the color
and now when we rerun our code,
you can see a white square at the center,
which is at position (0, 0).
Now the next step is to create our other two white squares.
So let's go ahead and copy these bits of code,
and I'm going to create three of them in total.
So segment_2 and segment_3.
Now here, we're going to create the same thing,
but we obviously have to change the positioning because otherwise we end up with
three squares all on top of each other,
and we can only see one square because this is a 2-D image.
So let's go ahead and make segment_2 go to a different position.
So the first thing we have to specify is the X,
which you remember is the horizontal axis here.
And if we want another square to the left of it,
then we're going to have to go to -20 from zero.
That way it will be shifted to the left by 20 pixels.
Let's say go to -20
and then the Y-axis is going to be zero because it's not going to move up or
down.
Now let's take a look at the result of this and you can see we've now got two
squares lining side by side,
but the third square is still at the center.
So the third segment is going to be shifted a further 20 pixels.
This is centered on (0, 0), this is at (-20, 0),
then this has to be at (-40, 0).
So let's tell our segment_3 to go to (-40, 0).
And this is what we see.
Did you manage to achieve this or did you do it in a different way? Now,
a much easier way of creating this would have been to use a for loop.
For example, we
could have created a list of
starting positions
and this could contain some tuples.
So we know that in order to specify where the segment should go to,
we have to provide a tuple, which is a X and a Y value.
And we know that we can create a tuple just by using a set of parentheses and
then adding values in there, separated by commas.
So if the first segment has to be at the center, then that's going to be
(0, 0), and then the second piece is going to be at (-20, 0),
and the third piece is going to be at (-40, 0).
Now we can create
a for loop. So for
position in starting_positions,
let's loop through this list and create a new segment for each of those
positions. So now we're going to create a new segment
that's a square turtle, that's going to be white,
and we're going to get the segment to go to the position that we're currently
looping on. Now we can delete all of that code
and when we run our code again, you can see we have the same effect.
We have all three pieces. So if you can't remember how tuples work,
be sure to go back to the lessons on tuples in Day 18,
where we talked about how to write them and how they work.
But that completes our first step.
We've managed to create three segments that will comprise our snake
and in the next lesson,
we're going to figure out how to get our snake to start moving by itself on the
screen. So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
In the last lesson, we managed to create our snake's body by creating three
squares that were each turtle objects. Now in this lesson,
we're going to move on to the next step where we actually move our snake
automatically across the screen without having to do anything.
So this way the snake is continuously moving forwards and all we have to do as
the user is just to change its direction. Now,
how would we go about moving the snake? Well,
we've already got these different segments that are created, but at the moment,
there's no way of organizing all the segments.
They're kind of just created and placed on screen.
So let's put them into a list called segments,
and let's start out that list as an empty list. And then later on,
once we've created each new segment,
we go ahead and append it to this list.
If we want something to continuously happen in our program,
the way that we've usually done that is through a while loop.
So let's create a new variable called game_is_on and let's set it to true.
And while game is on,
then we're going to move each of the segments.
The simplest way that I could think of to move this segment is to loop through
each of the segments in our list of segments,
and then to get each of these to go ahead and move forward.
So let's say we move forwards by 20 pixels.
Let's go ahead and run this program and see what we get.
The first thing we notice is that the behavior is very weird.
We've got a line that's being drawn
and that comes from each of the segments
which are individual turtles.
And they're all drawing this line as they're moving.
The first thing we want to fix is that line.
So when we create each new segment,
before we tell it to go to its position,
let's go ahead and tell it to pull the pen up. This way
it won't actually draw
and all that we'll see is the actual turtle pieces.
So now we see our three turtle pieces scurrying along like some sort of weird
Caterpillar, but definitely not in a snake like way.
How can we fix this?
One of the things that you notice about turtle is it will first create the
turtle when it runs this line,
the turtle will get created at the center positions, so coordinate (0, 0).
And then it will be moved to whatever position we tell it to go to.
For example, for the third segment, it starts out life at (0, 0)
and then as soon as it gets told to go to this position, it goes to (-40, 0).
Now we can see that happening on screen.
When we created our snake body,
you could see each individual piece being created and then moved to their
location. Now, if we wanted to turn off that animation,
then we would have to use one of the screen class'
methods called tracer. And tracer takes a number as a input,
and it turns the animation on or off.
And when the tracer is turned off,
then we can use the update method to tell our program when to refresh and redraw
the screen. When we think back to the old TV monitors,
the cathode ray tube monitors or CRT monitors,
the way that they worked is by painting on a strip of color line by line
by line, slowly covering the entire screen.
And then once it's done one screen, it's going to go back to the top
and then it's going to paint the pixels for the next scene. And effectively,
it's kind of like how a GIF animation works.
A gif animation is composed of many images. So for example,
if we wanted to animate,
we would increase this line and then we would start drawing out a leaf until
eventually we end up with an animation like this. Now,
when that's all combined and played back very quickly,
then this is the animation you see. In our game
what we could do is we could describe each of these scenes and tell our program
when it should redraw each picture.
So that way we could start out with one picture and then hit update and then do
something else on screen,
maybe move each of our segments and then tell the screen to update again
to show the user the new result.
And then each time we make the changes we want to happen
and then call that update method to tell the screen
to show a new image each time. Let's first turn off the tracer.
So the tracer is a method in the screen class
and in order to turn it off, we're going to set it to zero.
So now once the tracer is off, if we actually try to run our program,
you can see it's just a black screen and nothing will happen.
Even though we've got our while loop and we've got our for loop and lots of
things are meant to be happening, but until we call update,
the screen is not going to refresh and it's not going to show us what's been
happening in our code.
So let's say that we decide to call update after all of the segments have been
created, so right about here. Let's call screen.
update. And now if I hit run,
you'll notice that pretty much immediately. As soon as you run the program,
our snake body will show up, not piece by piece,
but in its entirety. Now, if on the other hand
I move our screen.update line of code into the while loop so that once each
segment moves, I get the screen to update,
then this is what you're going to see.
You see each of the pieces moving along one by one.
Now it's not really clear what's happening.
So I'm going to slow it down a little bit.
And I'm going to do this by importing the time module.
Now I'm going to add the time.sleep and I'm going to get it to sleep by one
second.
So this basically just add a one-second delay after each segment moves.
So each segment moves, the screen updates,
and then we sleep for a second before the next time this happens.
Notice how in this case,
our snake is moving piece by piece.
So first this first piece, and then the second piece,
the third piece with a one-second delay between each movement.
Now,
what happens if we move this screen.update to outside this for-loop?
So basically we only update the screen
once all of the segments have moved forwards.
Now notice how our snake is moving forwards as an entire piece.
It's going to move all three segments forward before the update gets triggered
and we refresh the graphics.
So it looks like as if the whole snake is moving as one piece. Now,
instead of getting it to delay by one second after each segment has moved,
if I move this up here
then it's only going to be delayed by one second
after all three segments have moved. This way
our snake is moving a little bit faster. And we can make it move faster still
if we cut the amount of time that we're sleeping.
So let's change it to 0.1 second sleep
and you can see our snake is now moving at a reasonable speed.
Now you might think that we've solved the challenge and we've now got our snake
to move automatically forwards, but there's a problem.
How do we turn our snake?
Let's see what would happen if we control the snake head and change direction.
Let's say that at some point, we want to turn the snake so that it turns left.
Well, what happens then?
So this first piece is now facing up,
the second piece is going to continue moving forwards as does the third piece.
Now on the next iteration of that for loop,
that first piece is going to keep moving towards North while the second and
third pieces are going to keep moving forward because they're not going to
change their own heading.
We'll get this strange behavior because our snake segments are not linked. To
illustrate this, let me go ahead and change the first segment,
so the segment at index zero, and get it to turn left by 90 degrees.
And notice when I run the code,
you see how that head is moving in a circle all by itself,
and the body has completely left the head and has continued to go forward.
So how can we solve this? Well,
we have to rethink the way that we move our segments. Again,
we have our three segments, but if instead of moving everything forwards,
what if we get our last segment, so segment_3
in this case, to move to the position of the second to last segment,
and then the second segment to move to the position of the first segment,
and then the first segment itself to go forward by 20 paces?
And if we go back to that situation where we're trying to turn our snake,
then in this method, it will still continue to work.
So we've got our three segments, one, two, and three.
Our third segment goes to where the second segment used to be,
second goes to where the one used to be,
and then the one is going to turn and then move to the left.
Now the next turn is the interesting part
because at this point we saw how
if these two pieces just continue moving forward,
they're going to move away from the head of the snake and it's going to move in
opposite directions. But using this method,
our third segment is going to move to where the second segment used to be,
the second goes to where the first used to be,
and the first continues moving forward. This way,
our snake has pretty much straightened out as you would expect this snake to
behave. Now, it's just the matter of actually implementing this,
which is the hard part.
So I'm going to go ahead and delete the part where I told the snake to turn left
and I'm going to delete this for loop
which just moved each of the segments in our list of segments forward by 20
paces. Now, instead, what I'm going to do is I'm going to create a for loop,
but this time I'm going to loop through each of the segments going from the last
segment to the first segment,
so basically in reverse order. Now to do this,
I'm going to use the range type of for-loop.
So I'm going to say for segment number or seg_num in the range,
and this range is going to have
a start, a stop,
and also a step.
So the start is the number that we're going to start
the range from, the stop is where the range is going to end,
and the step is how we're going to get from the start to the stop. For example,
if we wanted a range of 1, 2, 3, then of course start is going to be 1,
stop is going to be 3 and step is going to be +1. Now,
if we wanted a range of 3, 2, 1, however,
then the start is going to be 3,
the stop is going to be 1 and the step is going to be -1.
In our case,
what we actually want is actually to go from 2,
1, 0.
So the start will be 2, the stop will be 0, and the step will be -1.
Now, unfortunately, even though we have these named parameters,
because the range function in Python is actually something that's not quite pure
Python, it's something that comes from the C language,
it doesn't actually let us use these names.
I'll show you when we run our code, this is actually going to give us an error.
But for the time being,
it's actually much easier to visualize this as we write the code inside this
for-loop. So in this case,
the segment number is going to be equal to 2, and then 1,
and then finally 0.
Now we're going to use that to get hold of the last segment from our list of
segments.
So we can tap into that list and then get hold of the last one
using that seg_num.
And then we're going to set it to go to a particular X and Y position.
Now the X and Y position that we want it to go to is going to be the second to
last segment's position.
So how can we get hold of the second to last segment? Well,
we're going to get hold of the segments and then pass in seg_num but then
-1. So when we first start out, we start out with 2.
So the segment at position two is going to be the last segment.
And then the segment at 2 - 1 is going to be the second to last segment.
Now this one we're going to get hold of it's X coordinate
and we're going to set this to a variable called new_x,
and then we're going to do the same and get hold of the new_y.
So we're going to get hold of the second to last segment's Y coordinate,
and then we're going to use these coordinates, new_x and new_y to tell this last
segment to go to the position of the second to last segment.
Now, as I mentioned before,
this range function comes from the C language.
So if we run it with these keyword arguments
it's actually going to give us an error
and it tells us that this range function takes no keyword arguments.
So while it's really nice to use it to visualize it,
if we actually want it to work, we have to delete these.
But just before I delete it,
I want to this so that we're no longer using these hard-coded numbers.
So instead of going from 2 to 0,
we want to go to the length of the segments.
So in the future, if we had 10 segments or 20 segments,
that our code would still work. Now,
the length of the segment is actually three to begin with.
And we know that lists start counting from zero,
so 0, 1, 2, ... the last position is going to be the length - 1,
and then we're going to stop at the zeroth segment.
So now we can go ahead and delete these named arguments.
And we end up with this. Now we can run our code and we won't get any errors.
Notice how all three of the segments went to the same position,
the position of the first segment. So in addition to moving these segments,
remember that we also have to move the very first segment actually forwards by
say, 20 paces. So at the very end of all of this code
outside of the four loop,
we're going to get hold of the first segment, so segment at position zero,
and then we're going to get it to move forward by 20 paces.
So now when I run this again,
you can see our snake is now moving freely forwards and even if at some point,
the snake needed to turn,
let's say it turned left by 90 degrees,
then our code is still going to work.
Notice how our snake is now turning in a circle and all of the subsequent
pieces are following the head along its path. That's it.
This is the code that will get our snake to automatically move forwards.
Now, there was quite a few concepts mentioned in here,
and you have to think about the segments in terms of how they move in the graph
and also this idea of getting hold of the last segment and then telling it to go
to the position of the second to last segment and then doing this for all of the
segments.
So it's a little bit mind-bending and it might be worth just taking a second
look at this code and going back in the video where I explain how this worked in
the slides, just so that you're really clear with how this works.
Once you are, then you can move forward and head over to the next lesson.
So far,
we've managed to get our starting segments for our snake to appear on screen.
And then we managed to get our snake to automatically move forwards and to
figure out a way for the tail of the snake to follow where the head is going.
Now it's time to tidy up our code a little bit so that all the parts that are
related to the snake's behavior and the snake's appearance go into a separate
class. So that by the end of the whole project,
we should end up with three classes; a snake class, a food class,
and a scoreboard. And all of these classes will be in separate files,
managing only one thing.
And the goal of the refactoring is so that you could create a separate file,
snake.py, import the snake class that you've created in that file.
And then once you initialize this snake,
it will do everything that we have so far and create our three segments snake
onto the screen. And then finally, while the game loop is running,
we're going to get the snake to continuously move forward just by calling snake
.move. This is what you're aiming for.
Have a think about how you can take the existing code that you've got in the
main.py and extract all of the snake related functionality into a separate
snake class and make your main.py end up looking like this.
The program should do the exact same things as before.
The only difference is how the code is organized. Have a think about this.
You might need to revise some of the things you learned about how to create
classes, how to create objects from the previous lessons.
But pause the video,
I want you to give this a good try before you come back when we'll go through
the solution together.
Alright.
So the first thing we need to do is of course,
to create our snake class. And remember that in Python, class names are in Pascal
case, so the first letter needs to be capitalized.
And then inside this class, I'm going to create my init.
Now the code in here is going to determine what should happen when we initialize
a new snake object. So firstly,
I'm going to take the starting positions and take it over to our snake.py.
Now, I'm actually going to put this in as a constant. So right at the top,
and remember that in Python,
the constants are named with all caps like this,
and also with snake case with underscores separating each of the words.
Now we can use these starting positions inside our snake class to create our new
snake. So we're going to need to move our segments over as well.
So let's create a new attribute that's associated with our snake class called
segments. And remember,
we're going to need to use self when we're working within a class.
After that, we're going to create our snake.
So I'm going to create a method called create_snake down here.
And this method is going to do everything that we previously had over here,
but we're going to move that into this method.
Now there's a couple of things we need to change. Firstly,
we change these starting positions into a constant,
so let's make that consistent.
Second thing is that we need to import turtle into this file from the turtle
module in order to use it to create a new segment.
And then finally, in order to refer to our attribute segments,
we have to say self.segments and then append this new segment to our snake
segments. That's this part done.
The next thing we need to do is to get rid of this code and move it inside the
snake. So again,
I'm going to create another method that's associated with the snake class called
move. So when the snake moves,
it's going to look to this code to figure out how it should do that. Again,
because we're inside our class, it's no longer just segments.
It's now self.segments.
So let's go ahead and replace it in all the places where we have our red
underlines and now that's pretty much it for our snake class.
We can create a new snake object and each time we do that,
it creates a three-segment snake using the starting positions
which are declared at the top. So if we want the snake to show up on screen,
then we're going to have to first import the snake class from the snake file,
and then we're going to create a new snake object from that class.
And once this line gets triggered, then we're going to be calling
create_snake and our three-segment snake will show up on screen like this.
Now the next step is while the game is on,
the screen is going to update every 0.1 second.
So that's essentially what this is doing.
It's saying that delay for 0.1 second and then refresh the screen.
And every time the screen refreshes,
we're going to get the snake to move forwards by one step.
Now at the moment, each step is defined here as 20.
So again, I want to extract that into a constant up here,
so we're going to call it the MOVE_DISTANCE
and we can set that to 20 and then change this to use the constant here.
And the reason why we have all these constants is so that if we wanted to tweak
our game,
say if we wanted the snake to start at a different position or for it to move
further each time, then we don't have to dig through the body of our code.
All we have to do is look at the top,
look at all the things that we can change and then change it accordingly.
So now coming back to our code here,
all we now really have here is just these few lines of code and everything that
is snake related,
creating the snake or moving the snake is now abstracted into it's own class.
This way when something goes wrong with our snake,
we know who's responsible and which file to dig through
to figure out the reason. Now, at this point,
if we go ahead and rerun our code,
you can see that our program works exactly the same as before.
Nothing should have changed and nothing should have broken ow because our game
isn't yet able to go into the game over sequence,
there's no way of stopping the snake other than hitting the stop button.
So don't worry if at this stage inside your console
you see a lot of red and it says things like keyboard interrupt,
or trace back errors. All of these are normal.
The thing that you're more concerned about is whether if, when you run the game,
whether if it actually works like it used to,
so namely your snake moving across the screen.
If it does exactly what it used to and your main.py is now much simpler and
all of your snake functionality and behavior and appearance is now inside its
own class, then you have successfully achieved the goal of this lesson.
So we've now managed to create a snake body, move the snake,
and we've even managed to put our snake related code into a separate class.
Now the next step is to figure out how to control the snake.
Now we're going to control the snake by using the up, down, left, and right arrow
keys.
And we're going to be using our key bindings that we learned in yesterday's
lessons to be able to translate this into a change in direction of the snake. In
our code right after we create our snake,
we're going to call the screen.listen method to start listening for
keystrokes.
And the keystrokes that we're going to listen for are the up, down, left, and right
arrow keys. Now those keys are described by a string.
So it's a uppercase 'U' and then a 'p' so this would be up.
And then it's again, uppercase 'Down', 'Left',
and 'Right'.
These are the keys that it will detect, obviously the up,
down, left, and right arrow keys on the keyboard.
The function that you're going to bind it to is going to be a function in the
snake object and it's going to have the same name. So for example,
it'd be snake.up,
and that will be triggered when the up key is pressed.
And then the same thing happens with snake.down when the down key gets
pressed and then again with left and right.
Your job is to have a think about how you can create these methods up,
down, left, and right, in the snake class
so that when the up key or the down key is detected,
you can move the snake and change its heading accordingly.
So remember that up is going to be towards North, down is going to be South, left
is going to be towards the left of the screen and right is going to be towards
the right of the screen.
So have a think about the headings that we spoke about in previous lessons.
And if you need to, it might be worth just setting up a brand new project,
getting a turtle up and running and then setting it's heading from zero all the
way to 360, just to see which direction it's actually facing.
If you managed to complete the challenge,
you should be able to control the snake
and even though it's going to continue moving forward,
you now determine which direction it moves in by using the arrow keys.
Pause the video now and see if you can complete this challenge.
All right. So I've already created all of these lines of code
which is going to get the screen to listen for these key strokes.
And then when it detects it,
it's going to call these methods in the snake class.
So inside our snake class, let's go ahead and create those methods.
So we've got up,
down,
left, and right.
Let's think about how we can turn the snake up. In order to turn the snake,
the segment that we're most interested in is the first segment.
That's basically the head of the snake.
So we could tap into self.segments and then get hold of the zeroth segment,
which is the first one, and then change its heading by calling setheading.
And then we can tell it to, for example, if it's up,
then it should actually be turning to the 90-degree direction,
which is actually towards North.
Now I'm going to go ahead and put a pass on all of these other methods,
just so that we can actually test our code and it doesn't give us any errors
because these functions are currently empty. Now, if you don't have the pass,
it won't like it because Python doesn't like the idea of empty functions.
But now we can at least just test this one thing.
So when we run our code,
we should be able to hit the up key and you can see the snake changed direction.
Let me just do that again.
And this is because we managed to get the first segment,
the head of the snake, to change
it's heading to 90 degrees and then the rest of the body will follow because
it's continuously moving on every tick of the clock.
So using this, we can now set the rest of the methods.
But because we're going to need the head of the snake quite a few times in our
code, it might make sense to actually create a separate attribute.
So after we've created the snake, after we've got some segments inside this list,
we can create an attribute called head,
which is going to be the head of the snake.
And this can be equal to self.segments at index zero. Now,
remember if you have this line of code above the create_snake,
it's probably going to error out because at this point the segments is empty
and if you try to get the first item from it, it's not going to allow you to.
So look at the positioning of the code here. Now, once we've got this set,
we can go down here and change everywhere
where we need to use the head of the snake. So for example,
when we're moving the head forwards and when we're moving it up,
left, down, and right. Now we can set
each of these headings. Up is going to be a heading of 90, down is going to be
270,
left is 180 and right is 0.
These directions are just simply counter-clockwise.
So the turtle starts out pointing towards East and that's a heading of zero,
and then going anticlockwise, up is 90, left is 180, down as 270.
This can be easily verified just by testing out some numbers, right?
You could just put some numbers in there and then just try it out and see which
direction it goes and then you'll be able to figure it out.
But we've also mentioned this in previous lessons
so you could also go back and take a look at when we looked at the heading of
the turtle. So now if I go ahead and run this,
then you should see that I can now freely control the snake by going left or
right or down or up. And if you managed to do this,
then you should consider yourself successful. Now,
while I was testing this code,
I realized that there's something about the snake game that we haven't really
accounted for.
And it's the fact that the snake can't move back on itself.
It can't go forwards and then go the opposite direction because that requires
the head to change directions.
And this is not allowed in the official snake game.
So how can we code this into our game? Well,
we have to figure out when the head is pointing towards down direction,
then we shouldn't allow it to go up. And similarly, when it's pointing up,
we shouldn't let it go down, when it's pointing right
we shouldn't let it go left. So at the top here,
I'm going to create some constants.
I'm going to create a UP direction and it's going to be 90, DOWN direction is going to
be 270, LEFT is going to be equal to 180 and RIGHT is going to be equal to
0. So now that I've got all of these as constants,
I can go in here and set the heading to instead say UP when it needs to go up,
DOWN, LEFT and RIGHT. In addition,
we're going to do an if check.
So we're going to say if the current self.head.heading
is not equal to down, well, in that case,
it's allowed to move up. So this way,
it just means that if the current heading is pointed down,
it can't move up. But for all other directions,
if it's already moving up or left or right,
then it can change the heading to up.
Now be really careful here because it's not just self.head.heading,
it's actually heading as a method because remember that the head of the snake is
the first segment of our list of segments
and each segment is a individual turtle.
The turtle has a heading method
which will give you a direction in terms of these 360-degree numbers,
and then we can use that to check to see if it's equal to down.
And if it is, then it's not allowed to go up.
So using this logic,
see if you can complete the rest of the three methods so that when you run your
code, you can turn in all directions.
But when you're facing one direction,
you can't go backwards, like this.
Okay?
Alright. So it's going to be pretty straightforward.
If it's already going up, then it's not allowed to go down.
If it's already going right,
then it's not allowed to go left. And finally,
if it's already going left, then it's not allowed to go right.
So this way, even though our snake can move freely through the space,
it can't go back on itself. And there we have it.
We've now managed to create our snake, get it to move and control it
using our key presses.
Even though it seems like our game is still not quite there,
we've already come so far.
So this comes up to our hour mark
and it's now time to take a break, refresh your minds,
look at some of the concepts that you might be confused about that we covered
today,
especially this concept of using the update to refresh the screen,
as well as using the timer
to delay the refresh so that we can control how often it happens.
And then using our key bindings as well as separating all classes.
We looked at a lot of things today. Now, tomorrow,
once you're rested and fresh and ready,
we're going to be finishing up the snake game.
And we're going to be learning about inheritance as well as slicing
and we're going to be building out the full functionality of this game.
So I hope you're looking forward to it. I certainly am. I'll see you tomorrow.