Hey guys, welcome to Day 23 of 100 Days of Code. Now,
today we're going to be building towards our second capstone project,
and this is going to be a turtle crossing game.
You might've played Crossy Road. So this is a similar concept.
We have a whole bunch of cars going across a super busy multi-lane highway
and our turtle is the player who has to cross the road.
This is what the gameplay looks like. The player controls the turtle
which can only go forwards, and
there's a whole bunch of randomly generated cars
which are going horizontally across the screen. Now, once a player
reaches the other side of the screen, the cars speed up,
but the player goes back to the starting position,
ready to cross the screen again. Now,
at some point when the player turtle hits a car,
then that is game over. It's a pretty simple game,
but it's going to test you on a lot of things that you've learned so far,
including how to great classes, how to inherit classes,
how do you use the objects created from those classes and also your knowledge of
the turtle coordinate system and the turtle game engine.
Once you are ready, head over to the next lesson where you'll find the starting
code for this project, and also you'll be able to choose your difficulty level.
So head over there and get started now.
Now, hopefully you've already downloaded the starting project,
so you can go ahead and click open in PyCharm,
find the location where you've downloaded your turtle-crossing-start and make
sure that you've unzipped that zip file
and you've got the actual folder, which contains all of the starting files.
So select the folder and then click open and we have to configure a Python
interpreter and make sure that your Python interpreter is at a minimum of Python
3.8. So you can use 3.9 or above,
but if it's lower than 3.8,
you might get some errors and some problems. Refer back to when we first started
out using PyCharm and we installed Python if you get stuck on this.
Now, if you take a look at inside our project folder,
you can see I've already created four files for you.
These files are pretty bare bones,
but if you take a look at the main.py file
which is your starting point for your program,
you can see that I've written a little bit of code that we learned about in
previous lessons.
So we've created a screen object and we've set up the screen to be 600 by 600
pixels.
And then we've turned off the tracer by doing the tracer(0),
and instead, we're getting the screen to update every 0.1 seconds.
So within the while loop, the code is going to run every 0.1 seconds.
So whatever it is that you put inside this while loop,
it's going to be refreshed every 0.1 seconds.
Now, you'll also see that I've imported some classes from these files; player,
car_manager, and scoreboard. Now,
inside these files,
I've created the starting point for each of the classes.
The player class is going to be the turtle which we're controlling to cross
the road,
the car manager is going to generate all of the random cars and move them
across the screen,
and then the scoreboard is just going to write the level that we're currently
on and also the game over a sequence. Now,
inside each of these classes, I've got pass written here
just so that the linter will stop screaming at me. So,
as we mentioned before, Python doesn't like things are empty,
so empty functions, empty classes, and you'll get these errors.
Instead of getting these errors, all I've done is simply written pass
which essentially just makes this an empty class.
So when you're creating these classes,
just delete the pass and you can create it as you would normally. Now,
in addition, we've got all of these constants in here. For example,
the starting position of the player turtle,
how much the turtle should move each time and where the finish line
is on the Y-axis. In the car_manager
we've got the colors of the cars,
we've got the move distance of each of the cars on each refresh,
and we've also got how much the move distance should increase every time the
user levels up. Finally, we've got the scoreboard
which just contains the font that you are going to use to write out the score
board. That's pretty much an introduction to the starting file.
So once you're ready,
feel free to head over to the next lesson and get started with each step of the
game.
All right. So just as previously,
we've split up this large problem of building the game into five smaller
sub-parts. Firstly,
moving the turtle, controlling it with the keypress, creating and moving the
cars automatically across the screen,
detecting a collision with the car and detecting when the turtle reaches the
other side. Finally,
we create a scoreboard that keeps track of which level we're on
and also that shows game over at the end.
So the first step is to move the turtle using a keypress.
The turtle can only go forwards, and every time we hit the Up key
the turtle moves forward by a set amount until it reaches the other side of the
screen. This is the first thing that we're going to tackle. Now,
because this is related to the functionality of the player,
let's go ahead and create this inside the player class.
I'm going to delete that pass
and I'm also going to import the turtle class from the turtle module.
Now, our player is going to inherit from this turtle class.
So inside our init,
we're going to need to add the super.init
or you can add it automatically using the light bulb.
So now this player class can do everything that a turtle class can do and we can
make it do even more.
The first thing we're going to do is we're going to set the shape of our player
and we're gonna set it to a turtle.
The next thing we're going to do is we're going to call penup so that this
turtle just remains a shape and it doesn't draw. Finally,
we need to get it to the starting position and get it to face North.
We can do that by setting self.goto and then we can set it to go to the
starting position,
which you can see is a tuple because it's enclosed inside parentheses and you've
got values separated by a comma. Finally,
we're going to set the heading of our turtle so that it faces North,
which is 90 degrees.
So now all we have to do is go back into our main.py,
after we've set up our screen,
let's go ahead and create a new player from the player class.
Let's go ahead and run this code.
...
And you can see that we've got our little turtle showing up here at the center
of the bottom of the screen and it's facing North.
So now the next thing we need to do is to get that turtle to move upwards
every time we hit the Up key.
That means we're going to need to get our screen to
listen for events. After calling screen.listen,
we're going to get the screen to listen to a keystroke. So we can use onkey to
set the Up key as the key to listen to.
And then when that happens, then we're going to call player.
go_up. And remember that when we're calling methods inside the listener,
we don't want to add the parentheses because this will trigger it at the point
where it evaluates this line of code. Instead,
we want to trigger this function only when this Up key is detected.
So now all that's left to do is to go into our player.py and define that
function go_up.
So how can we move our turtle up? Well,
we can get our turtle so self,
and then we can get it to move forwards by a distance.
And the distance is going to be the move distance that's set in this constant
here. This means that later on when we want to change the move distance
if we want it to go further each time, we can just edit it at the top of the
file instead of digging through the code.
Now let's run our code again and let's just make sure that it works.
So now every time I hit the Up key
my turtle moves up and it keeps on going until it reaches the other side of the
screen. So that's the first step completed. Now,
if you think you can complete the next step by yourself,
then head back to that list of problems broken down and see if you can tackle
the next one by yourself. If you can't or if you need some extra help,
then you can always come back to the videos and I'll walk you through the steps
one by one.
In the last lesson, we managed to figure out how to get the turtle
to move with a keypress and that's with every press of the Up key
the turtle moves further towards North.
Now the next task is to create and move the cars.
The cars need to move from right to left and they need to be randomly generated
along the Y-axis here.
So they need to be generated right to the right edge of the screen and they can
appear anywhere along this line,
and then they're going to move automatically towards the left at a fixed pace.
Each of these cars,
you can see, are going to be turtles and they're going to be 20 by 40
pixels. So we mentioned that by default
every turtle that we create is 20 by 20 pixels.
So we'll need to stretch the turtle to make it into this shape.
Now that we are concerned with the cars let's create our code inside the car
manager.
The first thing we'll need to do is to import the turtle class from the turtle
module and our car manager is going to have a init where we create all of our
cars. So I'm going to create a list called all_cars,
and it's going to start out being an empty list. Now,
at some point,
our main.py is going to call a function from the car_manager called create_
cars.
And this method is going to create a random car somewhere along the Y-axis with
a given dimension. Each of these cars,
so let's call it a new_car, is going to be a turtle object and it's going to be
created in a square shape. Now, in addition,
we're going to have to change the dimensions of this turtle
and we're going to use that method that we used before
which is this one, shapesize.
Now, what shapesize allows us to do, if you remember,
is it allows us to stretch our turtle along the width and along the length.
So we want the width to be double the original size,
so two times 20 pixels is 40 pixels and the length we don't want to be stretched
at all.
So we're going to say it's one times the original length. In addition our new
car is not going to draw, so we're going to get it to penup.
And also our new car is going to have a random color. So we can set the color and
then we can import the random module so that we can use one of these colors in
this list.
And we can say random.choice and then pass in our list of colors from this
COLORS constant. Finally,
we're going to define where it's going to go on the screen. To do that
we need to define a random_y position.
So this again is going to be created from the random module and we're going to
use the randint and then we're going to define somewhere along this Y-axis,
which is the vertical, somewhere for this call to be generated at.
So we know that our screen is 600 by 600, so
that means the Y-axis goes from +300 to -300.
But we don't want the car to be generated all the way to the edge because
remember the turtle needs a bit of starting space and also a bit of ending
space. So you can play around with this number,
but I've ended up going with -250 to +250.
This means that we get a good range in the middle of the screen and that the
turtle has a bit of empty space at the beginning and also at the end when it
needs to move across. So now that we've defined our random_
y, we can tell our new_car to go to the x position
which is going to be the very edge of the right screen,
so that's going to be +300, right to the edge.
And then the y position is going to be the random_y that we just created.
And finally, once we've created our new_car,
we're going to append it to our list of all_cars which of course,
because it's defined in a class, it has to have the self in front of it.
So self.all_cars.append,
and then we're going to append this new car that we've just created.
Now, coming back to our main.py,
let's create our car_manager from the CarManager class,
and then we're going to use it inside our game loop here
so that on every refresh of the screen,
every 0.1 seconds,
we're going to get the car_manager to create a new car.
And strictly this probably shouldn't be plural because each time we call this
method, it only creates one new car.
So let's change that method so that it only creates one car,
but it creates one car every 0.1 seconds.
Now at this point in time if we run our code,
you'll actually see nothing happen because the cars are being created at this
right edge here
and it's not yet visible on the screen. To make it visible
we have to move our cars across the screen.
Let's create another method which we'll call move_cars because this method is
going to go through our list of cars,
so for car in self.all_cars,
and for each of those cars, it's going to move it towards the left
by the move distance that we've defined up here.
So to do that, all we need is to get the car
to move backwards by the starting move distance.
Now it's going to loop through our list of all_cars that were created
and then for each of the cars,
it's going to move it backwards by five paces.
So now in addition to getting the car manager to create a new car on every
refresh of the game loop,
we're also going to get it to move all of the cars by five paces.
Let's hit run
now and you should see that we've got our cars being generated,
but notice how I've made a slight error in the stretch. Instead of stretching it
along the length, I've stretched it along the width
and this is why we've got this random array of shapes moving.
So let's go back to our car manager and change the width to stretch by one and
stretch to the length by two. So now if we rerun our code,
you can see the cars are now the right shape,
a rectangle that looks like it's moving to the left.
Now notice how, in my case,
the cars are being generated far too frequently.
We've got way too many calls and it's impossible for our turtle to cross the
road.
So we need to figure out a way of how we can reduce the number of cars that are being
made. Instead of creating a car
every 0.1 seconds at every refresh of the game,
we need to slow this down a little bit.
And one way we can do this is by using a random number.
Let's say that we create a random_chance
which is going to be a one in six chance,
so it's almost like throwing a dice. If you get a one on the dice,
then we create a car.
We can do this by getting hold of our random module,
creating a random int between one and six
and then we can say that if the random_chance is equal to one,
then, and only then do we actually create a new car.
So this basically ensures that every six times the while loop runs a new car will
be generated.
Now it's not going to be precisely every six times because there's some degree
of chance involved. But notice when we run our program
now, see how the cars are now being created much less frequently.
And we've actually got some space for our turtle to cross.
So that is how we create and move our cars across the screen and make sure that
they don't occur so frequently that our turtle has no chance of crossing the
road. I hope this walkthrough was helpful.
Don't worry if your code doesn't look the same as mine, it doesn't have to.
What matters is if you're able to achieve the desired functionality of the game.
There are a million different ways that you can solve this problem.
And as long as it works, whatever way you choose will be the best way.
Now in the last lesson we created these rectangular cars randomly along the Y-
axis.
And then we managed to get them to move across to the left side of the screen.
The next step is to detect when the turtle collides with the car.
So that way, when the turtle hits one of the cars,
we can stop the game and prevent further cars from moving. Inside our while
loop I'm going to detect the collision with the car here.
So I'm going to get hold of all the cars in the car_manager object and I'm
going to use a for loop to loop through each of the cars in that list of cars.
And then we're going to detect whether if the car has a distance to the player
object that is less than 20.
Remember that our cars are 20 pixels in height by 40 pixels in width.
If the player is less than 20 pixels from the center of the car,
then it probably means that it's collided with the car.
So if this distance is less than 20,
then we're going to stop the game.
And the way that we stopped the game is of course,
by turning this game_is_on from true to false.
Let's run our code again and let's see this in action. So we can move our turtle,
we've got randomly generated cars moving across and let's just park our turtle right
here. When that car hit our turtle
it immediately stopped the game. Now,
if we want to take a look at what's happening
so for the screen to stay open instead of closing
once the process is finished, we can tell it to exitonclick.
So now let's run our code again and notice this time
if we collide with one of the cars
you can see that it stops and it waits for further instruction,
which eventually is going to be just the game over text showing up on screen
and we also the final level showing up on screen. That's it.
That's how we detect collision between the car and our player.
In the last step,
we figured out how to detect when the player turtle hits a car and to stop the
while loop which stops the game at that point.
Now we're going to figure out how we can detect when the turtle reaches the
other side of the screen so that once our turtle makes a successful crossing,
then we can return the turtle to the starting position and speed up all the
cars. So I'm going to do that right here,
and I'm going to detect a successful crossing.
So what is a successful crossing? Well, the player turtle has the reach
the finish line, right?
Which we've defined the Y value for as 280 here in the constant.
Now you could do this in a number of ways.
You could define a method here or simply just get hold of the player's position
and then figure out if it's over 280 inside our main.py.
Now I'm going to create a method here instead
and I'm going to call the method is_at_finish_line.
This method is going to return true
if the turtle is at the finish line and false while it's not.
So how do we detect this? Well,
we can get our self.ycor
and we can see if that is greater than 280,
which is our finished line Y value.
What that means we've pretty much gone over the finish line, right?
So if this is the case, then we're going to return true.
But while that's not the case, any other time when we check this,
we're going to return false.
So now coming back to our main.py,
we can call our player.is_at_finish_line and we can say,
if this is true, well in that case
we're going to get the player to go back to the starting position.
So inside our player class let's create yet another method which I'm going to
call go_to_start.
And this just involves getting our player to go to the starting position
which we've defined here in a constant.
So notice how we've got a little bit of repetition here,
so we can actually delete this line and simply call self.
go_to_start. Back in our main.py
once the player is at the finish line, we're going to get the player to go
to the stat.r And if we go ahead and run our code
as it is right now,
you can see that once the turtle makes it across the road,
[inaudible]
it goes back to the starting position.
Now the very last thing we need to do is to increase the speed of the cars when
the player reaches the other side,
because effectively they've just gone to the next level.
What we can do is when the player reaches the finish line,
we can get the car_manager to increase the speed of the cars.
Let's create a method inside our CarManager class
which we'll call level_up. And in this method,
we're going to get the cars' speed to increase by 10 every time.
So if we have an attribute called car_speed and we initially set it as the
starting move distance,
and then we use this car_speed to determine how far it should move backward
each time. Well then when we level up,
we can say self.car_speed now increases by the increment that we've defined
here, which is the move increment.
So now when our player reaches the other side at the finish line,
then in addition to getting the player to go to the start,
we're going to get the car_manager to level up our cars as well.
So now when my turtle reaches the other side of the screen,
not only does the turtle go back to the original position,
but the cars also increase in speed.
In the last lesson,
we figured out how to detect when our turtle reaches the other side of the
screen. And when this happens,
we return the turtle player to its original position
and we also increase the speed of the cars by the move increment that we
defined as a constant. So in this lesson,
what we're going to do is the final step,
which is to create a scoreboard that keeps track of which level the turtle
player is on, and also when the turtle hits one of the
cars to display
the words game over in the center of the screen. To do that,
we're of course going to go inside our scoreboard class and again
we're going to need the help of the turtle class.
So let's import that from the turtle module and I'm going to make my scoreboard
a subclass of the turtle class.
So it's now inheriting from the turtle class.
And once we've defined our init and managed to get it
to inherit everything from the superclass,
then our scoreboard is now able to do everything a turtle class can do.
What do we want it to do? Well,
we have to initialize it with a couple of things first. For example,
we probably want to start out by hiding the turtle,
we just want to use it as a pen to draw. And in addition,
we don't want it to move and draw. So we're going to pull the pen up.
We're going to be using the write method instead.
And what we want to write is the level, right?
So the current level that the player is on. In order to do that,
we also have to keep track of the level.
So let's go ahead and create a new attribute
which I'll call level and let's start at level 1.
So then we can insert this right here with self.level
and in addition to writing this text,
we can define what we want the alignment to be.
So I want this to be on the left and also what the font to be.
So I'm going to use this font that was declared up here as a constant. Now,
inside our main.py next to where we've defined our player and our car_
manager
I'm going to create this new scoreboard object and that's going to be created
from the scoreboard class. Now notice when I run the code as it is,
you can see that our level is left-aligned,
it's got the font that we defined and it's writing the text that we want,
but it's not in the right position. To define the position
we have to do that right before we tell the scoreboard to write,
so right here, but after where we've got our penup.
So this way we don't draw a path to where we're going to.
So now we're going to define self.goto,
and I'm just going to get it to go to probably the top left corner.
So that's going to be probably -280 and then it's going to be
+280 on the Y. Now, if we just check the positioning,
you can see that it's a little bit too far up on the Y-axis.
So it lets move it down a little bit and you can tweak these things until you
get to the point where you're happy with its positioning.
So I think this looks pretty good. Now,
in addition to writing the level,
we actually have to update it every time the player levels up, right?
And they do that when there's a successful crossing.
So at some point here,
we should be able to call scoreboard and we should be able to get the scoreboard
to increase the level.
So let's go into scoreboard and let's define that function, increase_
level.
And the first thing to do when we're increasing the level is of course getting
hold of this self.level and then adding one to it each time.
In addition, we're going to need the level to be rewritten again.
So let's cut this out of the init and let's instead define a custom method
which we'll call update_scoreboard.
Yeah.
Inside this update_scoreboard, we can write the current level.
So now inside the init
we can call self.update_scoreboard
and also when we increase the level,
we can call self.update_scoreboard.
Now at the moment, as it is,
it's going to overwrite what used to be on the scoreboard.
So at the moment it's on level 1,
but once I make a successful crossing,
you can see that level 2 is going to be overwritten over level 1.
To prevent that when we update the scoreboard,
we have to get the scoreboard to clear itself
so that it deletes all the previous stuff that it wrote. This way
when we actually run our code
you can see that our scoreboard will refresh and clear the previous text and
write the new text each time.
So now the final thing to do is to write the words game over in the middle of
the screen when the game ends. To do that, I'm going to create
another method here
which I'll call game_over. And inside this method,
we're going to get our turtle to go to the center.
So we're going to say self.goto and the center is, of course, at
(0, 0), and then we're going to get it to write,
but this time we're not going to write the level anymore. Instead,
we're going to just write the words GAME OVER in all caps.
And I want the alignment to be centered and I want the font to be the default
font. Now, when we actually detect a collision,
not only is game_is_on going to be false,
but also we're going to get the scoreboard to show the game over sequence.
So now we can run our code and you can see that when my turtle collides with a
car,
then it says game over in the center.
And because when we wrote game over, we didn't clear any of the previous texts,
the user can see at the highest level that they managed to reach.
That's it. That's the entire game.
Hopefully you've managed to build this entire game by yourself and you're just here
to check a few niggling issues. But if you struggled with this code,
then I really recommend to review the previous lessons where we created the
snake game or when we created this turtle crossing game
and try to see if you can create these two games from scratch by yourself
by looking at how the game works. Because if you continue forward,
things are only gonna get more complex.
And I'm assuming that you're going to take the time to review and revise before
you continue.
So have fun playing with the turtle crossing game and be sure to let me know in
the Q/A what your highest level is that you managed to reach and also
remember to attach a picture or it didn't happen.
And this is a great project for you to customize.
So think about what you might want to change
like the colors or the shapes and make the game really your own and then take a
screenshot of it and share it with us in the Q/A so that we can all
appreciate and congratulate you on your work.