Hey guys, welcome to day 31
of 100 Days of Code. And you've been learning quite a lot of things
now. We've been looking at handling exceptions,
using the JSON data format, passing and reading CSVs
using pandas, opening and writing to files and a whole lot more.
So it's time for your capstone project.
And in this capstone project,
we're going to be building a flashcard program to help you study.
And it's especially great with studying for languages. Now,
when I was in school,
I studied French and it was a lot of vocab that we had to learn for tests.
Pomme is Apple, and I would memorize all these words,
all of the grammar tables, and yet after four or five years,
I couldn't really speak much French.
So I decided to go for immersive language learning.
I went to France,
I hung out with friends and I tried to immerse myself in the language and
culture. But that also failed. I had a lot of fun,
but my French didn't seem to improve all that much.
But then I discovered a new way of learning languages and it all started with
looking at Chinese characters. There's a lot of Chinese characters out there.
There's something like 50,000 Chinese characters in total from history to now.
There's a lot of characters that you could learn. They each have a different
meaning and they each have a different pronunciation.
Imagine that. Trying to learn 50,000 characters. That's no easy feat.
But then a friend told me that actually you don't really need 50,000
characters. Your average professor, who is very eloquent,
can write a lot of the characters and use them with ease,
only knows about 10,000 and your average person probably only uses about 8,000
in their day to day lives. And if you basically just want to get by in life,
you can pretty much rely on the 3000 words that an average teenager would know.
And finally, if you actually just want to be able to watch some simple movies,
read some simple books,
then you could use the average kid vocabulary of about that the 1000 characters.
And at this point, I think to myself, 1000. That's quite doable.
I could do 1000. If I learn just 10 characters a day,
that will take me less than a year to learn all of these characters.
But it's not just 1000 random characters either.
There's such a thing as a frequency dictionary.
So a dictionary that's not listed here by A, B, C, D,
but it actually listed by the frequency that a particular word occurs in common
usage. For example,
if you take the first 1000 characters that are most commonly used,
then you can pretty much read most of the Newspapers,
you can watch most of the TV shows because these
are the words that are the bread and butter of the language. It's like in English,
the a, the, of, from, why, yes, no,
these are words that we use every day, again and again.
The crazy words like anti-establishment or glioblastoma.
These are not words that you need to really know for day to day life.
So let me show you the program that you'll build
where you can learn the most frequently used words in any language.
It's a flashcard program,
and it shows you the front and the back of the card. So for example,
French, demande. In English means request. After three seconds,
the card flips and I can check whether if I knew the right answer.
If I got it right I'll press the tick and if I got it wrong
I'll press the cross. So let's try another word.
Parti means left or to leave. Attendez
means to wait
and I think I knew that word. So I'm going to click the check mark.
And what that's going to do is it's going to take the flashcard out of all of
the list of flashcards so it doesn't show me the things I already know.
And instead it only shows me the things I don't know
so I can review it and say, Oh, I'm not sure what loin means
so I'll say cross,
and that will go back into the deck and it might come up again at some point.
So this beautiful piece of software is what we're going to be creating.
But more specifically,
you're going to be creating because after all, this is your capstone project.
But don't worry,
I've divided up into four steps and I've got some step by step instructions for
you in the next lesson. Now, if you're wondering,
how did you get the most frequent words for the flashcard app in the first
place? Well, let me show you.
There's a Wiki for the frequency list of different languages,
and it lists most of the common languages. If we go to French,
you can see that there are loads of different lists that people have compiled
that list the top, most frequently occurring words.
And one of the ones that I thought was really relevant is the words are based on
subtitles.
These subtitles come from all sorts of shows and movies that are relevant to modern
culture. And when you look at one of the subtitles,
this is one of my favorite shows by the way,
you can see that the subtitles are listed by language.
And if we pick out one which is in English and we take a look at it,
then you can see
it's basically just all the words that are spoken in the movie or in the show
and it's been transcribed into subtitles. Now
then if we take all of these words that are from the most commonly watched
movies and shows, we end up with these frequency lists.
So if we take a look here,
it shows the most frequent words from 1 to 5,000.
And at the very beginning,
it's your I, of, is, all of these things that are really common.
And then as you scroll down, you get to some longer words.
And if you scroll to the bottom,
you can see you're getting some more and more niche words.
These frequency lists are compiled by a user called Hermitd
and Hermitdis a Hermit Dave
And he has a GitHub repository where he's compiled all of the frequency words,
and you can see the latest version from 2018.
Now he's got all of the frequency words for many languages
and it's listed by the language code,
so French would be FR for example.
And here you can see the top 50,000 most frequent lists or the full entire list.
We're probably not gonna learn more than 1000,
and I'm certainly not going to get to 50,000.
But this data here lists all the words that he found in these subtitles and the
frequency that they occurred.
And once they've been sorted in order of frequency,
this is what you end up with.
So I've already studied some of the first 200 words.
So if I take a hundred words from this frequency dictionary
and I put it into a Google sheet, then I end up with something like this.
Now,
what I want to be able to do is to create a flashcard where the front of the
flashcard is the word in French,
and then on the back of the flashcard is the answer in English for what
that word means. Instead of having to flip through a dictionary
finding out the meaning of each of these words,
there's actually a really neat trick in Google sheets that I want to show you.
If you hit equals to
start a new formula and you type in Google translate,
you can see it expects some inputs.
First is the piece of text that you want to translate,
so I'm going to click on this cell, and then it's the source language.
So this is the language as a code. So for example,
Spanish is ES and French is FR. And then the final input.
it expects is the language code that you want to translate it to.
So in this case, I want to translate it to English. So I'm going to use en.
And then we can close off the parentheses, hit
enter and after a little while with good internet,
you'll see the English translation for this word. And of course,
because we're an Excel,
we can simply just drag this cross all the way down to all of our words.
And after a little while, bam!
It's translated all of those words into English.
So this is a really neat trick and I'll link to the docs for this particular
formula.
And also you can take a look at the language support that Google's translation
service has and you can see the language code for each of these languages.
So if you want to try learning Macedonian or Malay,
and this is going to be your best bet.
So now that I've created my Excel sheet
essentially of a French and English words,
I've got potentially a hundred flashcards with the front and back data already
saved inside this Google sheet. Now,
all I have to do is simply download it as a CSV
and we'll be able to work with it very easily. Now,
you don't have to worry about downloading this or getting hold of this because
I've already included the final CSV data in the starting project for you to be
able to use.
So head over to the next lesson and get started building your very own study
aid, the flashy flashcard app.
All right.
So hopefully you've headed over to the course resources and downloaded the
starting zip file for today's project. So go ahead and unzip it.
And then let's open up this folder using PyCharm.
Okay.
Here you've already got two folders, data and images.
We're going to be using all of these images inside the images folder to create
our project. So this is the front of the flashcard,
the back of the flashcard, the right button and the wrong button.
And we're going to be writing our code inside main.py. So notice here
we've already got the background color hex code defined.
So we'll be able to use it in our coding as well. This is what we're aiming for.
This is the user interface for this program.
It's going to have a window with a title and inside this window,
we're going to have the card front image here showing up.
And on that card, we're going to have two pieces of text,
a word that says title and a piece of text that just says word.
And these are going to be formatted according to the instructions,
so in terms of font and size, et cetera. Finally, at the bottom,
we've got two buttons, a cross, and a checkmark.
And they're basically buttons that have the images right and wrong inside them.
Let's get started. Inside main.py,
the first thing I'm going to do is to go ahead and import tkinter.
So I'm going to import all the classes from tkinter
and then I'll be able to use it to create my window.
All right.
I'm going to set a title for my window and I'm going to give it the name of our
app
which is going to be called Flashy or whatever it is you want to call it. Next,
I'm going to give this window, um,
a configuration and I'm going to set the padding of the window to 50 pixels in
the X and 50 pixels in the Y.
Now this window is also going to have a background color
which is going to be set to this BACKGROUND_COLOR
constant that we have up here.
So now that I'm done configuring my window,
I can go ahead and get my window to start off in the main loop.
And now I should be able to run this code and just check that it works.
Here's our window with the background color
and there's already some padding in it and making this window a little bit
bigger. Now,
the next thing to do is to somehow put this card front image onto our window.
I'm going to be using a canvas object.
And if you remember, canvas object allows us to layer lots of things on top
of each other. So here is an image and then on top of that,
we've got some text being created.
And as long as we specify the position for each of these items,
it can all be overlapped on top of each other.
So we're creating our canvas from the canvas class
and then I'm going to give my canvas a width and height.
So I'm going to set the width and height to be the same as the width and height
of my card.
So the width is 800 and the height is 526.
You should've seen these numbers in the instructions as well. Next,
we're going to create our image from the photo image class.
So let's call it card_front_img
and this is going to be created from the photo image class
where we have to specify a file name. Now, previously,
all we've done is we've just said the actual name of the file,
which in this case is card_front.png. But in our case,
this particular file is actually inside our images folder.
So we have to specify the full file path for this to work; images/card_
front.png.
And then we can get ahold of our canvas and create our image inside.
So the image is going to be set to our card_front_img
and then we have to specify the X and Y values of that image. Because it needs
to go into the center of the canvas,
we're just going to half the width for the X and half the height for the Y.
So this goes in as a tuple
so half of 526 is 263
and then I'm just going to put our canvas onto the grid and I'm going to set the
row to zero and the column to zero as well.
Now, just be careful when you're writing strings like this,
because it's pretty easy to make a typo like I have here. Instead,
I prefer using PyCharm's autofill.
So when you have a file path,
you can type in the name of the folder forwardslash and then the name of the
file. And we can just hit enter for it to insert it for us automatically.
Now, if I go ahead and hit run,
then I'll see that I've got a background which has the background color,
and then 50 pixels of padding on all four sides, in the middle
I've got my canvas displaying
this card_front.png. The only thing about this card is that it's still got
that white background. How do we get rid of that? Well,
we can change the background into the same color as everything else,
so this background color. Let's go ahead and get our canvas
and then let's config it to have a background color
that's set equal to our constant like this.
Now the background color is the same,
but we now have a line that is all around our canvas.
If you remember from previous lessons,
I told you that you can simply get rid of the highlight thickness and set it to
zero. And that basically just gets rid of that border.
So now we have a window with our flashcard showing up and the image has the
shadows which I created in illustrator
so that you'll be able to see it as a 3D card. Now,
inside the card, not only do we have an image,
but we also want to have some text.
So let's go ahead and create some text. And we can set the text to say Title.
So this is the first piece of text. In addition,
I'm going to set the font to a tuple
which is going to use the Arial font, and then it's going to be 40 size
and finally I'm going to make it italic. Now,
before we can hit run,
we also have to specify a X and Y position for our text.
So our image was created at 400 X, 263
Y, our text is going to be created at 400 X and 150 Y.
Now remember that these positions are relative to the canvas.
So 400 makes it halfway along the width
and then this 150 is going to make it a little bit towards the top
so that's a good position for the title. Next,
we're going to create another piece of text
and this piece of text is going to be the actual word, so that the French word or
the English word.
So we're going to set it at the center of our canvass
so exactly centered on the image,
and then we're going to say that the text is going to be equal to the word for
now anyways. Later on we'll probably change it.
And then the font is again also Arial.
And this time it's going to be a bit bigger and it's also going to be bold. So
there we have it. We've got our flashcard pretty much all laid out.
Now we just have to add our two buttons. Below our canvas
I'm going to create two buttons. First, there's going to be the unknown button.
This is going to be the X which the user presses
because they don't know what's on the back of the flashcard.
And this button is going to have a special attribute though,
the image attribute and that image is going to be a photo image.
So let's put this as the cross_image,
and it's going to be a photo image
which is going to be created from the images folder
and it is the wrong.png.
And that image is what's going to go inside our unknown button.
Let's go ahead and layout our unknown button on the grid so that it'll actually
show up. Row is going to be 1,
so below the canvas, and then column is going to be 0.
So now you can see our X button show up here.
Next, I'm going to create the check_image. This is going to be the checkmark.
And in this case, its again,
a photo image created from a file
which is in our images/right.png.
And of course, you can always just double click on each of these images and view
them and just make sure that they are the ones that you want to use.
So once we've got our image, we can create our known_button.
And this is going to now have a image attribute set to this check image.
And then we can place our known_button onto the grid as well.
So row = 1 and column is going to be equal to 1 as well.
So its on the same row as the unknown button,
but it's just shifted a little bit to the right. Now at this point
if I run the code,
you can see that our check button is all the way on the right while our canvas
and our cross button are in the left most column.
So you know what you need to do. You have to change
this canvas grid to have a column span of 2.
So it starts at column 0 but ends at column 1.
Now when you run it,
you can see it's nicely placed onto the screen in the way that we want it to
look. Now, if you want to get rid of the border around the buttons,
then the easiest way is to again,
change the highlight thickness to 0.
So lets add that here and here.
But both on Mac and Windows,
you'll see this fine line around the button and it's not easy to get rid of it
because it's their so that you can click on the button and you can see this
visible depression.
That way it lets the user know that the button press was actually successful.
But that's fine.
And we're now pretty much done with our user interface. In the next step
we're going to get rid of these placeholders, title and word, and we're going to
start picking out the words from this french_words.csv,
picking out random records like this or this so that we can put the French word
into right here and change the title to say French.
For all of that and more, head over to the next lesson and see the instructions.
Now that we've created the UI,
the next step or step 2 was to try and get the buttons to start working so
that when we press the cross or the tick button,
we get a new French word being shown in the middle here,
and the title switches to the word of French. So how do we do this?
Well, firstly, for both of these buttons
the unknown and the known button,
we're going to add a command. And remember the command links to a particular
function that is going to be called.
So we'll call that next_card and we'll add that to both the known and the
unknown buttons.
Now that we've got next_card added here,
now let's go ahead and create this function next_card.
What exactly is this function going to do? Well,
it's going to take the words from the french_words.csv
and it's going to get hold of some of these words and their translations.
So it basically,
you can imagine these as single rows that we want to get hold of.
Now, what we need to do first though
is we need to use pandas in order to read from that CSV.
So we're going to first import pandas and it should already be installed in
your project. If not, you'll see a red light bulb
and then you can just click on it and then install that module.
Once we've got pandas enabled though,
we're going to use panders to read from a CSV and the CSV is our french_words.csv
from the data folder.
Now we're going to set this as equal to the data.
So this is now going to be a data frame. And in fact,
if I go ahead and print it
now
you can see that pandas will nicely format our table with the column headings
and also record numbers
and each of these rows are basically the pieces of data that we're interested
in. Now that we've got a data frame,
we can convert that data frame into a dictionary.
Let's go ahead and create a dictionary which we'll call out to_learn,
so that's the word that we need to learn,
and this is going to be a dictionary that's created from this data
from this french_words.csv. But notice how at the moment,
if we just use the default method of creating a dictionary,
what our to_learn is going to look like is like this.
We've got French and then inside
we've got all of the French words and then we've got a key later on called
English and all of the corresponding English words.
Now, that's what we want. Instead, we want to change one of the parameters
which is orient,
so how do we want to orient the table to create this dictionary? Now in the hints
for step 2, I already showed you that you could use this
orient set to records and this way it'll give you each column's values as a
list. Let me show you what that looks like.
So let's change this parameter orient,
and we'll set it to equal the string records.
Remember that there's an 's' at the end.
And now we can compare the previous version of the dictionary
that's generated from the data to the new version.
So let me run the code again and you can see now we've basically got a list of
dictionaries and each dictionary has a key, French,
the French word, a key English,
and then the English word and so on and so forth. This is really,
really useful for us because we can basically pick a random entry from this list
and we'll be able to tap into the French value and the English value later on
when we flip our cards. That is our to_learn dictionary done.
So when the next_card function gets called,
then we're going to need to pick out some data from this dictionary and the way
that we're gonna pick it out is randomly.
So we're going to import the random module and we're going to use random.
choice in order to pick out a random item from this list of words to learn.
And once we've got a random choice which we'll call current_card,
then we can get hold of the data from this current_card by saying current_card
[French]. Remember that in this french_words.csv
we've got a capital F and a capital E.
So our keys must match that exactly.
So let's go ahead and print this
and you can see now that when I press on one of these buttons,
either the cross or the tick,
it's going to pick out a random French word from my list of words in this
french_words.csv. So now instead of printing it,
let's go ahead and put it into these pieces of text on our canvas.
In order to do that,
I'm going to create a variable called card_title to hold on to the title and
the card_word to hold on to the word text.
And now I can go ahead and tap into my canvas and say
itemconfig and the item that we want to configure is firstly
our card_title
and the thing we want to configure about it is to change the text to say French.
So that's the title remember, which is the part that's up here.
And then we're going to do the same thing using canvas.itemconfig
but this time we're going to configure the card_word,
and this is going to be set to exactly what we printed before,
which is the random card that was picked out and the value under the key French.
So now when I hit run again,
you can see that when I press either of these buttons,
I'm going to get a random French word showing up right here.
But notice how when I first run the app
you can see that it still has the placeholder title and word showing up.
Instead, we want it to show the next card.
So we have to call this function once we've created all of our UI
but before we get to our main loop.
So we'll call our next card. And this way,
once we've created all of our images and everything else,
then we can generate the next card,
get the data and put it into the card title and card word. So in fact,
if you want to,
you can actually delete these two pieces of text because they won't actually do
anything at the moment. And now as soon as we hit run,
you can see the first thing we see is already a French word
and it will keep going through all of the words that we have in our CSV.
There you have it. We've now managed to read from the CSV,
get a dictionary of all the records in the CSV and to randomly get the French
word showing up in our flashcard. Our flashcard currently,
doesn't actually flash. It doesn't change, right?
We need a way for us to be able to set some sort of a timer,
say a 3-second timer,
and then for our card to show us the opposite side or the backside and to show
us the English translation of the words.
That is what we're going to tackle on the next lesson.
So head over to step 3 and have a read of the instructions.
Now that we've got our words showing up in French,
it's time to see the other side of the card and see the English equivalent so
that we can check our knowledge. To do this
we're going to have to implement some sort of way of changing this card after a
set amount of time. So we're going to flip the card
after three seconds are up. To do that
we're going to use the window.after method.
Right after here where we've created a window,
we're going to say window.after.
And then we can specify the amount of time in milliseconds.
So I'm going to say three seconds or 3000 milliseconds.
And then the function that we're going to call is a function
that's going to be called flip_card. And if we want that to work,
then we're going to have to create it. So I'm going to create right here,
just above.
So I'll call it flip_card and this function is going to take care of changing the
card to show the English word for the current card,
and also going to change the image from the card_front to
the card_back, and also we're going to change the color of the text as well.
In our flip card,
we're going to get hold of the canvas and we're going to first item.config
the card_ title. So we're going to change the card_title to,
instead of saying French, we're going to say, well,
this is now the English translation,
and then we're going to config the card word,
and this is going to be still from the current card,
but we want to get ahold of the value under the key English instead.
Now at the moment, this current card is locked up inside next_card.
So we can't actually get hold of it without creating a new random choice.
So what we can do is we can create our current card
and we can set it to a empty dictionary.
And then we can change this to a global and tap into that current card to modify
it and save this random choice from our list of French and English pairs.
So once we've got that inside there,
then we can tap into it inside flip_card and we can say current card
get hold of the value under the English key.
And that way we update both of our texts. So right now if I hit run,
you can see that immediately after three seconds
we switched to the opposite side and we have our English and the English
equivalent of the same word showing up. So for example,
in French matin, in English means morning.
So that's how we can verify that we actually know the meaning of the card.
In addition to changing the words, I'm also going to change the image.
So notice how we saved the words with a variable.
We can do the same thing for this create image method.
We can say the card_background is equal to canvas create image.
And in addition to creating the card front image,
we can also create the card back image.
Now, you have to be really careful here
because if you create this card back image
which is a photo image created from file,
if you create it inside one of these functions, by the end of the function
call, that reference to that particular image will be gone.
And it won't work if you create this photo image inside flipcard and try to set
it inside this method. So you have to create it outside of any of the functions.
So let's change the file to images/card_back.png
and now we're going to get our canvas to again,
call itemconfig.
And this time we're configuring the card_background.
And the attribute that we want to configure is the image property.
So we're going to change that to the card_back_img
which we created right here.
So now let's just check that again.
Let's wait three seconds and then it's changed to
the back of the card. On the back of the card
we want these two pieces of text to actually have a different color.
We want it to be white, just so that it stands out from the background.
And to do that, we can add it along with our item config.
Not only are we changing the text,
but also changing the fill of the text to white.
Okay.
And now when our card flips over,
you can see its a green card with a white text.
Now,
one of the things we have to do is every time we click on one of these buttons,
it has the flip back to the front of the card, right?
That means changing the text color and changing that background image.
So that happens when we go to next card.
So in addition to configuring the text and the words,
we also again have to itemconfig the card_background so that we can change the
image back to the card front image.
In addition, we have to change these text colors to have a different fill,
so we're going to change it back to black.
Right.
This way, when the card flips, it goes to green,
white on green. And then when we go to the front of the card,
it goes to black on white.
Now notice how once we go to the next card,
that card flipping mechanism has gone because we only ever call this window
after the first time we create the window.
So we actually need this to happen a few times. In fact,
we need it to happen every single time we go to the next card.
So after we've configured all the things on our card,
we're gonna call a window.after, three seconds, flipcard.
So this way, even if we go to the next card and we wait three seconds,
it again goes to the back.
Now one of the bugs you might have encountered is if you clicked this button
many times and you go through lots of different words,
you see immediately, that card actually flipped.
And it's because that window.after three seconds is counting down in the
background, waiting, waiting, waiting until three seconds
at which point it's going to flip the card.
It doesn't care that you've actually just gone onto a new card and you want to
wait again, three seconds. In order to get this to work,
we actually have to give this line of code a variable so that we'll call it the
flip_timer. And this is now a global
which we can tap into and we can add it after a comma over here,
flip_timer. Alternatively,
you can also go onto a new line and say global flip_timer.
It doesn't really make a difference other than the fact that this probably takes
less lines of code. Now, once we've got access to our flip_timer,
we can say that every time we go to a new card,
when we click on one of these buttons, we're going to invalidate this timer.
So we can say window.after_
cancel and then pass in the ID of our flip_timer.
And then after we've set up this card,
we can set up a new flip_timer so that it waits for again three seconds.
And now once I've added that bit of code, it should fix this bug.
So now whenever I keep going or I press the check or the crossmark,
it doesn't really matter.
It's not going to flip until I land on a card and wait for three seconds
before it flips. There you have it. We've got our card
flipping technology added to our code.
Now all that's left is to get rid of the cards that the user says
they know
and to create a new CSV that is going to hold all the cards from this to_learn
dictionary and to remove the cards that the user says they know.
And then that way, the next time we run our app
it will remember which words we've learned and which words we haven't so that we
can load up only the words we have yet to learn.
So for that, head over to the next lesson where we've got the final step of the
flashcard project.
We are now within sight of the finish line. We're onto the last step.
So this is the solution for step 4. And in step 4
we want to be able to improve our program so that the words where the user
clicks the checkmark to means they already know that word.
They know what it means and they don't wanna see it again in this list.
So what we want to be able to do is to remove the words that the user knows from
this dictionary of words to_learn. And to do that,
we have to change this command. When the user clicks on the unknown button,
we're going to simply just give them the next card,
which is a random word from the list of words.
But when they use it clicks on the known button,
instead of clicking on next card, we're going to call a different function
which I'm going to call is_known. Now is_known
is going to be a function
that's going to remove the current card from the cards that are in the list of
words to learn.
So what we're going to do is we're going to get hold of our list to learn,
and then we're going to call the remove method.
And then we're going to remove a particular element from it.
And that happens to be the current card.
So remember, the current card is a dictionary
which we got by randomly choosing from our list to learn.
So now, when the user says is_known,
then the current card is going to be removed from the list of words to learn.
And then after we've done that,
then we're going to call next card from this particular method. At the moment,
if we run this code and I just keep clicking the check mark,
eventually, we're going to have a very small list of words that we're going to
pick from. In fact,
if I go ahead and print the length of my list, to_learn,
you can see that the first time I run this code and I click on the is_known
button, we have a hundred words. But if I keep clicking on this,
then you'll see that every single time,
I'm just reducing that list because I'm saying,
I already know what this word compris means
and that word is now taken out of my list of words to learn.
So now that list is smaller by one entry.
Now this works right now, but if I rerun the app,
then you can see it goes back right to the beginning
and it has a hundred words again.
So in order to keep hold of the words that I still need to learn,
I have to save this list to a new permanent file
each time the user clicks on this is_known button.
So the way that I'm going to do that is by using pandas again.
I'm going to use pandas to create a new data frame.
And that data frame is going to be created from our list to_learn.
Now, I'm going to save this as our data,
and then I can say data.to_csv in order to save it as a CSV file.
So I'll call this words_to_learn.csv.
So now, if I press my check mark
and I take a look within my files,
you can see that words_to_learn.csv is created.
And at the moment it's got 89 entries. But if I keep clicking this a few times,
it's going to reduce each time.
So this is now a permanent storage of all the words that I have yet to learn.
But I don't really want it randomly in the middle of my project.
I want it to be saved alongside my french_words.csv.
So I have to change this to a file path
which is going to be data/words_to_learn.csv.
So let's go ahead and delete this file and do refactor.
And then we're going to run this again.
And next time you'll see that it appears in the right place.
Now, in addition to saving it to CSV,
we also have to read from that CSV because instead of using the words from our
original list which is our french_words.csv,
I actually want to be able to read from my words_to_learn.csv instead,
because that way, every single time I rerun the app,
it's always going to give me all the words that I've yet to learn.
So currently we're on 87. If I run this again,
you can see that the first time I click on this,
it's going to go to 86 instead of going back to 100.
But there is a problem here though
because if I delete this file, words_to_learn.csv, and I go ahead and run this, the first
time this runs it's going to crash and we have that familiar file
not found error. So we know how to deal with that.
We need to catch this exception. The exception occurs right here.
It happens when we try to get hold of this piece of data
which may or may not exist. So if it does not exist,
so we're going to catch this except file not found error. Well,
in that case, we're going to be using the original data
which comes from the french_words.csv. So we'll say pandas.
read_csv
and then we're going to read this file, data/french_words.csv.
So this is always going to be there because it's preloaded with our project.
But if we do manage to find our words_to_learn.csv,
then that means this program has been run before and we've removed some of the
words we already know. So we can catch that with an else statement and we can say,
well, in this case,
we're going to set a global variable called to_learn
which starts out as an empty dictionary.
And we set it to the data that comes from this CSV.
However, if that file was not found,
then this to_learn is going to be set to the original data.to_dict
and we're going to orient according to records as well.
Okay.
Now, when we run our code, you can see we have no errors.
And the first time that it runs,
it's going to pick from our french_words.csv. Now,
once I've started saying I've learned this, I've learned this,
I've learned this, then it's going to generate a words_to_learn.csv.
And the next time I run this code,
it's gonna start using that words_to_learn.csv and start where I left off.
Now, there is one slight weird bug to this.
When you take a look at the words_to_learn.csv,
it adds the record number to the first column
every single time I run the code. So if I run this code again,
you can see now I have three columns of all of the records.
So basically when we read from this particular CSV,
we generate a data frame. And when I read from that data frame,
so let's delete this and run our code again,
you can see that pandas is automatically added in these record numbers.
So that gets then added back into our words_to_learn.csv when it saves it into
the file. If we want to get rid of these record numbers,
all we have to do is when we save it to the CSV,
we can set a property called index to false. This way
it just doesn't add the index numbers to our newly created list
and now if I rerun this code,
you can see that our words_to_learn.csv
doesn't actually include an index. It only includes the actual records or
the actual words and their English translations.
That's
basically it. That's all the solutions to our capstone project.
And you've now built a fully fleshed flashcard that you can use to learn
languages.
So you could have the front with whatever language you want, and the back with
English translations, or you can use it to learn Programming facts.
You could have the front with a Programming word and the back as the meaning of
the Programming word.
You could use it to study History or Geography.
And this program is going to help you manage all the things that you don't
remember and keep showing it to you until you do. Have fun modifying this
flashcard app and I hope it will be helpful in your studies as well.
If you've built something particularly interesting, again,
be sure to share with us in the Q/A so that we can all admire and
congratulate you on your hard work.