Hey guys,
Welcome to Day 33 of 100 Days of Code. It's Angela here
and today we're going to be learning about application programming interfaces,
also known as APIs. What are we going to use it for? Well,
we're going to learn this technology so that we're able to create an ISS
tracker.
So this is the international space station and it floats high above in the sky
and it circles earth many, many times a day.
Here's a video that's taken from the ISS and you can see how glorious earth
looks in the eyes of the ISS.
And what we're going to try to do is we're going to try and track where the ISS
is currently at in the sky. And at the time point
when the ISS is in the night sky, right above where we are,
then we're going to send ourselves an email
telling us to look up and spot the fast-moving ISS.
Once you are ready, head over to the next lesson and we'll get started learning
about APIs.
First, let's take a look at what application programming interfaces
are and then we'll see how we can use them to start pulling in some data from the
internet. So when you're browsing the web,
you might've realized that there's a lot of websites out there that carry a
whole bunch of data. For example,
you could go onto Yahoo weather and see next week's weather predictions for
any city in the world,
you could go onto Coinbase and see what is the current market value of various
cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin and Ethereum.
You can also go onto the MBA website and look at various stats about your
favorite basketball players. Now,
what if we wanted to use the data that they have?
How can we tap into it and use it in our own programs? Well,
that's where application programming interfaces come into play.
They all are a set of commands, functions, protocols, and objects
that programmers can use to create software or interact with an external system.
In the upcoming lessons
what we're going to be focusing on is this interacting with external systems.
Namely,
we're going to try and interact with various websites and pull live data from
those websites. Essentially,
the API is an interface or rather a sort of barrier between your program and an
external system.
And what you're trying to do is you're trying to use the rules that the API has
prescribed to make a request to the external system for some piece of data.
And if you have structured your request
according to all of the requirements that this external system has set out in
their API,
then they will respond to you appropriately and give you the data that you want.
But if you don't follow the rules,
then your request will be invalid and they will tell you to go away.
So if we think about the websites we saw before, Yahoo weather has a Yahoo
weather  API
which you can tap into using your programs or apps and get things like 10-day
forecast, wind, atmosphere, astronomy conditions,
and Coinbase has their own API,
which lets you tap into the current live prices of various cryptocurrencies.
And of course, the MBA also has an API for you to be able to get various
information that you're interested in on leagues, teams, players, games and a whole
bunch more.
So essentially, you can imagine these websites as the sort of restaurant,
right?
And the data that powers these websites as the kitchen behind the scenes.
We can't really go to a restaurant as a member of the public and just go in to
the kitchen and start raiding their cupboards. You can't, you know,
imagine going to your favorite Japanese restaurant and heading straight into the
kitchen for some of your favorite Kewpie mayonnaise.
That's not really appropriate. In a restaurant
we have a menu and this menu is kind of like the interface between you and the
restaurant.
It's the thing that tells you what you can order and what you can't.
So maybe you can get a cake, a sandwich or tea from the restaurant,
but you can't just go into the kitchen and demand whatever it is that you want.
Essentially an API is exactly that. It's the menu.
It's all of the things that you can do to interact with
an external system such as a website
that carries data like Yahoo
weather or the MBA website. In the coming lessons
we're going to be looking at how we can read the documentation for the API and
interact with them to be able to pull pieces of data that
we want in the moment that we want it. So for all of that and more,
I'll see on the next lesson.
Now,
one of the most important aspects of an API is the API endpoint.
And you can imagine that as a location, right?
So we said that if we want to get data from a particular external service,
then we need to know what location that data is stored. So for example,
if you wanted to get money out of a bank,
then you need to know where that bank is and what is its address.
And that, when it comes to API
lingo, is called the API endpoint. And that's usually just a URL.
So for example, if you wanted to get crypto data,
you might use api.coinbase.com.
This is the location where the Coinbase data can be found.
Now, in addition to knowing the API endpoint,
you also have to make a request over the internet.
This API request is kind of similar to going to the bank and trying to get some
money out, so trying to withdraw some data from their vault.
As you can imagine, the world would be completely chaotic
if everybody was allowed to just go into a bank and take out the amount of money
they need without any sort of checks and balances.
So that's why, in the bank, you have a bank teller
so somebody who is there to ask you, "Can I help you? What you want?" and to prevent you
from going to the vault by yourself. And to also call the police
if you try to do that. Now this bank teller is kind of acting like the API.
It's the interface between you and the external system or between you and the
bank vault. And you can make a number of requests to this lady.
You could, of course, ask her to give you some money,
but that obviously is going to involve checking your ID,
making sure that you have your account number and she'll have to do a whole
bunch of checks.
But you can also go into the bank and ask the bank teller for things that
doesn't require any form of authentication. For example, you can say,
well, what are your opening hours?
And this is the equivalent of making a very,
very simple get request where you just try to get a piece of data from a website
using their API. Now,
one of the simplest APIs that I like to introduce students to is the
international space station current location API.
This is the endpoint,
and you can see that it returns the output in the form of a JSON,
which we've already played around with quite a bit.
If you want to make a request to this API,
you can of course use your browser to do it. Just paste the end point,
which is a URL into the address bar.
And once you hit enter, you can see the result
come back in the format of a JSON.
And this describes the current ISS position in terms of its longitude and
latitude. If I refresh this,
then I will make a new request to this end point
and I will get a slightly different piece of data back because the ISS is moving
actually quite fast through the air. So every time you can see that
it's moved by a little bit. Now, if
reading the data like this is a bit difficult,
I recommend installing a free Chrome browser plugin quote, JSON Viewer
Awesome
and what it will do is whenever it sees JSON data being rendered in the
browser,
it will display it in a nice tree structure and it will look something like
this.
So you can collapse each of these parts and you can see that this is a
dictionary effectively with three items, timestamp, message, ISS position.
And then when you tap into the ISS position,
you can get the longitude and latitude.
Now we've already seen the JSON data format,
and we know that it was originally created for JavaScript,
but later became almost the standard way of transferring data across the
internet. And the reason for it is really simple.
If you take something like a Python dictionary, let's say you have a wardrobe,
right? It's kind of like you're going to Ikea. You spotted a wardrobe
you would like, but you don't want to carry this home in its entirety.
It might not even fit in your car. Well, what do you do? Well in Ikea,
at least the way they've solved it, is they sell you a flat pack.
So all the pieces flat against each other and you go home and you build it
yourself. This is the equivalent of a JSON. It's very minimalist,
it doesn't have a lot of spaces and a lot of indents.
It just has a couple of symbols to denote which are the keys,
which are the values, which are the separate key-value pairs.
And this can be transported across the internet very,
very quickly because of how small and flat it is. Now,
once you receive this JSON,
then you can reconstitute it back to your original Python dictionary or a
JavaScript object depending on what programming language you were working with.
And this is the equivalent of taking a screwdriver and putting it together that
Ikea furniture.
But luckily for you, this process is a lot less painful than putting together
Ikea furniture. It's actually super easy.
Let me demonstrate. Here
I've created a brand new project from scratch day-33 and inside my main.py
I'm going to try and make a request to the ISS location API.
So the first thing I need to do is I need to import a library to help me to do
that.
And the one that I'm going to import is called requests and note that there's an
's' at the end.
And this has to be installed because it does not come prebuilt with Python.
So you can click on it, and then once you see the red light bulb,
click on it and get it to install the package called requests.
Once that's done, then you'll be able to use it. Now,
what we're going to do using this requests package is we're going to call one of
its methods called get.
So this is going to help us get the data that we want from the endpoint.
The endpoint goes in in an argument called the URL,
and we have the check the documentation to know what the endpoint is.
So in this case, if we want to get hold of the current location,
then this is the endpoint URL.
So we can simply copy it and paste it in here as a string.
Now, once we've gotten the data from this,
then it's going to be returned and we can capture it inside a new variable
which we'll call response.
So this is going to be equal to the response that we get back from this
particular website's API.
Now let's go ahead and print this response.
So let's run our project and making sure that you are connected to the internet
because this line of code is going to go across the internet and fetch this data
for us. We get back a response.
Now we have successfully made our very first API request from within our Python
code. However, when we print the response,
we don't see the JSON data like we did when we made the request directly inside
our browser. Instead, we see this number 200 printed here.
That is our response code. And in the next lesson,
we'll dive deeper into how to work with these responses and what exactly these
response codes mean.
So what are the response codes that we can get from an API?
Response codes actually have a very specific meaning,
but the most important thing they tell us is if our request succeeded or
if it failed. Now, if you've been using the internet for a while,
you've probably come across the 404 response code. And the 404
response code basically means that the thing that you're looking for doesn't
exist. And you can see various websites having fun with this
404 page.
Basically when you're trying to retrieve something from a website and it doesn't
actually have the thing you're looking for, then this is the code you get.
But there's actually a lot more response codes other than just 404.
And in fact,
you could summarize these status codes just by looking at the first number.
If it is 100 and something, then it's telling you, hold on,
something's happening. This is not final.
If it's 200 something then it is saying, here you go. Everything was successful.
You should be getting the data you expected.
If it's 300 something then it usually means you don't actually have permission
to get this thing, so go away. 400 something, it means that
you screwed up. Either it could be a 404
which means that you screwed up
and the thing you're looking for doesn't even exist,
or it could be 500 something, which means I,
as in the server that you are making the request to, screwed up. And maybe the
server is down, maybe the website is down or maybe there's some other issue.
So that's just a quick,
at a glance, sort of way of remembering what's actually happening
when you are getting these response codes.
Now you can actually dig deeper into this response object and you can get a
whole bunch of things from it. For example,
if you wanted to know the actual status code instead of just a response object,
then you can say response.status_code,
and you actually only get the status code. But notice how
if I change this URL and I make a typo in here,
instead of iss I have is,
then now I get a 404 as my response status code.
OK. So if we get the status code 200 then it means that we were successful.
But what do we do when we get a different status code?
What should our program do when the request fails?
We might be tempted to write code like this. By checking to see if the response
.status_code is not equal to 200,
we can actually figure out well, this means that there probably was an error.
Now it doesn't really make sense to just print out an error because the user who's
using our program might be expecting something to happen.
So in most, cases you might want to raise an exception instead.
You could say bad response from ISS API.
But we learned from our module on errors and exceptions,
this is not very good. Firstly, this is not a very specific exception.
It's going to raise a very general type of exception. And secondly,
all that we're catching is when the status code is not 200.
What if we wanted you to know specifically which status code we got back? Well,
we could, of course check well
if the response status code was equal to say
404, then we'll raise a particular type of exception that says that resource
does not exist. And then we can have,
um, an elif that says, well,
if the response status code was 401,
then that means that you should raise an exception because this particular code
only happens when you are not authorized to access this data.
Now there's a lot of status codes that you could be getting back.
And in the course
resources I'll link to this particular web page where it tells you all of the
possible codes that you could be getting and what it means. As you can imagine,
it's impossible for us to write this many
if statements checking for every single possibility. What do we do instead?
You can actually do away with all of this by getting the request module
to generate the exception instead.
The requests module is the most popular way for Python developers to work with
APIs. And you can see in their statistics just the number of stars,
number of forks,
and from these stats, you can see just how much active development there is and
how popular this particular module is. Now,
if you want to take a look at the documentation,
then you get taken to their website and it tells you all of the things that it
can do, which is quite a lot actually.
Now I won't read through all of this with you,
but if we take a look at one of the sections, Errors and Exceptions,
you can actually call raise for status on the response you get back in order
to raise a HTTP error
if the request returned an unsuccessful status code.
Basically instead of us trying to raise an exception for every single possible
status code and telling the developer what might be the reason, we can simply use
the request module by saying response.raise_for_status.
So now what you'll see is that if we don't get a 200
which is the pass-- Let's say I mess up this end point again,
then you'll see an exception being raised and it's telling us, look,
it's a 404 client error. This URL is not found.
So this request module is actually really powerful and we're going to see how to use
various aspects of it in the upcoming lessons.
But for now, the first thing we need to get hold of is the actual data from this
particular API. To do that,
we tap into our response and we get the JSON data.
So this is the actual data. And when I print it,
you can see that it looks exactly the same as what we got in our browser.
Coming back to our code where we have this JSON,
we can tap into it just like we would for any Python dictionary.
We could use some square brackets and then type in the name of a key that we're
interested in. For example,
if this was a Python dictionary and we wanted to know the iss_position,
then we would add the square brackets and then pass in iss_ position.
And now when we print data,
you can see it's now narrowed down and drilled into the position to give us this
longitude and latitude.
So we can go even further and tag on another set of square brackets and try to
get hold of, say the longitude.
And now we get that actual piece of data. There you have it.
We get access to the longitude by tapping into our data in the format of a JSON
and then getting the iss_position. And inside that dictionary,
we can get hold of the longitude. And we can do the same thing in order to get
hold of the latitude,
right?
But we would change the key of course, to latitude.
So now I'm going to create a tuple with the longitude and the latitude.
And now if I print it out,
you can see how I've managed to nicely format my code and get the pieces of
data that I want in order to be able to work with it in my project. Now,
if you wanna see where that particular latitude and longitude is on the world
map, then we can use a tool called latlong.net.
So if you go to geographic tools and go to latitude and longitude to address,
then you can paste in the longitude and latitude values that we got from
our API. And when we click convert, then you'll see on the map,
it shows where in the world the ISS is right now.
So at the moment, it's somewhere to the East of Japan over the Pacific ocean.
And of course, it's telling you no address found because I don't think anybody
lives right there.
So have a play around with that and make sure that you've fully understood
what's happening in these few lines of code and how we use the API endpoint to
get the data that we're showing up right here. In the next lesson
I've got a challenge for you.
Now that you've seen how you can make the most basic type of request to an API
endpoint, I want you to build a Kanye quote machine.
This is what it's going to look like and these are real Kanye quotes.
So every time you click on this button
which has a Kanye emoji, you can see
he'll say different things.
And some of the things he says are incredibly deep and other things are a little
bit weird. But we've created the starting file for this
so you don't have to spend a lot of time building up the UI.
All I want you to do is to figure out how to use the API
which is at kanye.rest
and this is the API endpoint. So you can test it out of course
in your browser just by putting it into the URL bar.
And you can see you get back a very simple JSON with just one key and one
value. And every time you run it, it'll give you a random quote.
Head over to the course resources and download the Kanye quote
starting file. And once you've unzipped it and opened it up,
you can see that there's the background.png, the kanye.png,
and there's all of the existing code that's required to generate this user
interface in tkinter. The point here is,
I know you can make tkinter apps,
but I want you to use the request module that you learned about just now in
order to get this function to work so that every time the Kanye button,
this one, is pressed, then we trigger this get_quote function.
And this is going to fetch the quote from the Kanye API here and fill it into
this quote_text on the canvas. Using what you've learned before
I think you can do this pretty quickly. So pause the video now and give it a go.
Yeah.
All right. So to begin,
we, of course, need to import our very important requests module,
and you need to install it if you see some red squiggly lines.
But if you see it grayed out like this then it means that we've already installed
it into the starting files. Now,
once we've got hold of that module,
then we can write some code here so that we get our function to work.
Now, what should happen when the user presses on the Kanye button? Well,
we have to fetch a new quote from the API.
This is the API endpoint
and we're going to use the requests module to make a request and get some data
from this API.
So this is the code that we used before to figure out where the ISS was.
And we're going to save this as the response. Now,
once we've got our response,
we're going to call response.raise_for_status.
So if we don't get a 200, which is everything is okay,
then we want to actually raise an exception. Now,
the next thing we're gonna do is I'm going to get my response to show me the
JSON data. And I'm gonna save that as the data.
And then if we take a look at what the response looks like,
then you can see it's just a single key-value pair
and the key is quote and the value is the random quote.
So we can get hold of the actual quote by simply tapping to our data and then
using square brackets to fetch the value under the key quote.
And once we've got that piece of text,
then we want to put it into our quote_text which is on our canvas.
And as you saw before,
the way we do this is we say canvas.itemconfig.
And the item we want to configure is, of course, our quote_text.
And the thing that we want to configure about it is its text.
And we're going to set it to equal this quote that we fetched just now.
So now if I run my code,
you can see my Kanye says app showing up,
and this is where the Kanye quote is going to go.
So if I click on Kanye, you can see how it shows all of his quotes.
So did you manage to get that? If not, be sure to head back to the last lesson and
take a closer look at how we formatted our request and our response.
We've seen how APIs can have endpoints and we said
that's equivalent to the address of the place that you want to get some data
from, or you want to communicate with.
But APIs also have something called parameters.
And this is a way that allows you to give an input when you are making your API
request so that you can get different pieces of data back,
depending on your input in the same way that we've given different inputs into
the same function in order to get a different outcome.
Coming back to our bank analogy, that's kinda similar to going to the bank
and instead of just asking them for what are your opening hours,
a sort of broad stroke question, you can also pass in a parameter.
For example, you could say, well, what time do you close on Monday?
Or what time do you close on Tuesday?
And this allows you to get these specific piece of information that you're
interested in depending on the input that you provided as a parameter.
Now, not all APIs have parameters. Some are incredibly simple,
like the ISS location API.
But other ones allow you to provide parameters.
And this is a sunrise and sunset API that gives you the time when the sun is
gonna rise and set wherever you may be.
So you have to obviously provide a location so that they can tell you when the
sun is going to rise and set at your position.
We can do that through two parameters, the latitude and the longitude.
And you'll notice that in the API documentation,
they will usually tell you how you should structure your parameter.
So for example, here
the latitude can be specified using a lat key,
and the longitude is lng as the longitude.
And they want those pieces of input as floating-point numbers. Now,
you also see that some parameters are required and others are optional. Just as
we can have optional and required parameters when we create functions,
you have the same thing in APIs.
The optional ones all have a default value.
For example, the date you could provide,
say you wanted to know the sunrise and sunset on a particular day in the future
or in the past, but you can also leave it empty
and it will default to the current date.
Now the endpoint in this case is this particular URL,
api.sunrise-sunset.org/json. But don't worry.
I'll also link to this documentation in the course resources as well.
Let's see how we can get this to work.
I'm gonna comment out all of the things that were related to our ISS location,
and I'm going to use this requests module in order to get the sunrise and sunset
times
because this is going to be really important when we're creating our final
project
because it's almost impossible to spot the ISS in the sky unless it's actually
dark.
So we need to know when the sun is going to go down and when the sun's going to
come back up in order for us to know
if the sky is actually dark enough for us to be able to spot the ISS
traveling in the sky. Let's go ahead and set up another response
which is going to be set up to a request.
And this request is going to get some information from this particular endpoint.
So let's copy that over and make sure that you leave out this final
full stop.
That's just a part of the sentence and not a part of the API endpoint.
So it should look something like this.
And then we're going to get our response to raise an exception if there was an
error status code. So anything other than 200, basically. Now, if I run this
as it is, you can see I already get an exception.
And the exception is a 400
which, if you remember, means bad request.
This server cannot or will not process the request because of something that they
think is your fault. In our case,
the thing that we've done badly is we haven't provided the required parameters.
So how is it supposed to tell us the sunrise and sunset times
if we don't tell it our location? Let's fix this.
Let's create a set of parameters and you can do this by simply creating a Python
dictionary.
Now the keys for the parameters must match the ones specified in the API
documentation.
So it's lat for latitude and lng for longitude.
So let's create those keys as strings,
and then we can provide our latitude and longitude.
So how do we know what is our latitude and longitude? Well,
we've got our good old friend latlong.net.
So here I can type a particular place name. So right now I'm in London.
And if I click find, it will find me on the map and it will tell me what is my
latitude and what is my longitude.
So let's copy these over and let's create them as constants.
So I'm going to have a MY_LAT
which is equal to this as a floating point number.
And then my longitude--
Remember to include any negative signs if you see it.
That's actually a part of the latitude longitude encoding.
So now I can set my lat key to the constant
MY_LAT and the longitude key to the constant MY_LONG.
So these are the values that I got from my latlong.net search and
then I formatted all of this into a dictionary using the keys that were
specified in the API documentation here.
Those are the only two required parameters.
So if we now add this in to our get requests under the argument called params,
then we're now able to run this request again
and you'll see that this time we don't get any exceptions.
So we can assume that everything went swimmingly.
The data that we get back is under the response.json.
So let's go ahead and print out that data and see what we managed to get.
We got a JSON as usual and the JSON contains the sunrise time and the sunset
time, in addition to other things like when is the solar noon,
how long is the day, what is the day length and so on and so forth.
So you can see this one is a lot longer than what we had before. Now,
the two pieces of information that we're interested in is just the sunrise and
sunset times.
If we want to view this JSON data in a nicely formatted way,
then we can do that by putting the full request into the browser URL bar. And the
way that you format parameters in a URL string
looks something like this. In the sample requests,
they've shown you that this part is the end point URL.
And then afterwards you can add a question mark to denote that you're going to
add some parameters.
And then you add each parameter with the key equal sign and then the value
and then you can tag on more parameters with the ampersand or the and symbol.
So let's try putting this into our browser bar.
So here's the latitude which we'll paste in here
and here's the longitude which we'll paste in here.
So now let's hit enter and you can see there our JSON Awesome
Viewer which we installed at the beginning of today's lessons is now active
and it's showing us all of this data in a much nicer format.
So we can see that this sunrise time that we're interested in is the value for the
key sunrise which is then inside of another key called results.
So we can use these two keys to pull out these specific pieces of data that
we're interested in. So we can get the sunrise
which is equal to data, and then square brackets
we put in the first key
which is results
with an s and then we can add the next key
which is sunrise.
And we can do the same thing for the sunset time.
And now if we print out our sunrise or our sunset time,
you can see its actually the exact piece of information that we're interested
in. Notice how this data is formatted
and it's giving us the time in a 12-hour format.
So it's going to have AM or PM tagged on at the end.
Now what we want to do is we want to be able to get the current time so we can
use the datetime module. From the datetime module, we'll import the date
time in class.
And then we can get the time now by tapping into that class and then calling the
now method.
But you'll notice that the format of time now is very different from our sunrise
and sunset time. Our sunrise and sunset time
are in the 12 hour format
whereas the time that we're getting back from datetime is in a 24-hour clock
format.
So how can we change this data that we're getting back from the sunrise and
sunset API? Well, back to the API
we go. Notice in one of the parameters, there is a parameter called
formatted which is an optional parameter,
but it can be turned off or on.
On is by default,
which means it's going to format it in a particular way with the 12-hour clock.
But if you switch off the formatting,
then it will give you the Unix time in this particular format and this will be a
24-hour clock. So here's your challenge.
Go ahead and change the parameters that you have and make sure that the data
that we get back is not formatted, so it's set to zero.
Pause the video and complete this challenge. Alright,
all we have to do is to add one more parameter to this dictionary and the
parameter must have a key that matches the one specified in the documentation,
so I'm just going to copy that over, and then we're going to set this to 0
for off. So now if we rerun our code,
you can see the data we're getting back is now in Unix time
which is a 12-hour format time.
So currently where I am in London
the sunrise time is actually quite early, it's at four o'clock in the morning.
So notice how the first part is the date
and then we have a T and then after that we've got the time.
What we want to be able to do is to compare this part from our sunrise
sunset API against this part from our datetime API.
So how can we just isolate the hour number from each of these?
Well, we can use a Python method called split,
and you've seen this before.
Basically you have to provide a separator and it will split a string by that
separator creating a list. So if you click on this, try this yourself,
you can see that this string becomes this list by splitting that string with the
pound sign separator. Now, in our case,
the separator that we want to separate by is firstly,
to split it by this T,
which is going to give us this part as the first item in the list and this part
as the second item in the list.
And then we can take the second part and then split it by the colon and then we can
get this first part of the list. So here's how we would do it.
So we can say sunrise.split
and then the separator we want to use was that capital T.
Now if I hit print,
you can see we've got a list that is now separated with two things on either
side of the T. So let me just comment out the time now
and we've got the sunrise and the sunrise split next to each other.
So that T is removed
and the two things on either side have become two items in our list.
Now we want to split this part further.
We can get this item by tapping into the item at index one,
so 0, 1,
and then we can split this even further by tagging on another split function.
Here, we can split it by the colon. So let's go ahead
and provide that as the input.
And now you can see the result we get back is this. We've split the part that
comes after the T by the colon and we've got 04,
03, 32+00, and then 00.
This is clearly the item we want
so all we have to do is just to add a zero at the end.
And now we've got the actual
hour in the 24-hour clock formatted from our sunrise time.
You could in fact,
just simply take all of this part after the sunrise and tag it onto the end of
this line and also this line so that we actually get the sunrise and sunset
times in terms of the 24-hour clock, like this.
Now we're perfectly poised to start comparing it against the time that we're
getting right now.
So we can take our time now and tap into the actual hour,
and you can see now that we've got our sunrise, which is this first number,
sunset, which is the second number,
and the third number is the current clock time in terms of the 24-hour clock.
So in order to figure out whether if it is day or night,
all we have to do is compare this number against these other two.
Now in the next lesson,
we're going to finish off this project and put everything together in order to
get an email when the ISS is passing overhead and it's currently nighttime.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
All right. Congratulations on reaching the final project for the day.
Head on over to the course resources and download the starting files for the ISS
overhead notifier project.
If you followed along with all the lessons today,
then you've seen how we can get data from a particular API by simply just
providing an endpoint. So this is the simplest type of API calls.
And then you saw how we could pass, along with the API call, a set of parameters
in the form of a Python dictionary in order to get a specific piece of data that
we want based on the parameters that we pass over. So in this case,
it was the sunrise and sunset time of our local area.
Now later on,
I showed you how we can split the string that we get back from the sunrise and
sunset times in order to get the particular numbers that we're interested in,
which is the time of the sunrise and sunset in the 24-hour clock format.
Now it's time to put all of this together.
If the ISS is close to my current position and it's currently dark,
so basically it's nighttime, then send me an email to tell me to look up.
That's the objective of the challenge. However, as a bonus challenge,
see if you can further modify the code so that it runs every 60 seconds
if the ISS is overhead.
These are the three things that we need to achieve. And just as a quick tip
before you get started,
remember that the sunrise and sunset times are both in the format of strings.
So if you want to be able to work with them to compare to time
now, you also have to change this to an integer.
Now, the second tip I've got is that the ISS position,
the longitude and latitude that you get back, will be decimal numbers,
but it is currently in the format of a string.
So you'll need to convert that into a floating-point number
if you want to compare it against your current position. Now,
when we're checking whether if the ISS is overhead,
we want to have a margin of error. It doesn't have to be right above me,
precise to this number of decimal points. It can be plus or minus five.
So if the ISS's latitude with anywhere between say 56 and,
um, 51 minus five, which is 46,
then that's perfectly fine. That means I'll still be able to see it.
Take a look and find your own latitude and your own longitude
and see if you can figure out how to compare that against the ISS's a latitude
and longitude and adding in that degree of error. In fact,
consider creating a function that returns true if your position is within plus five
or minus five degrees of the ISS position and false otherwise.
So you should now have all the capabilities to complete this challenge.
Pause the video,
give that a little bit of a think and see if you can complete the challenge.
Thank you.
All right. What
we want to do up here is we wanna compare the ISS's position against our
position. Now,
what we want to check is to see if our position is within plus or minus five
degrees of the ISS position. So let's take one part of that position,
the ISS's latitude
and we want to check to see if it is close to my latitude.
If my latitude is currently 51,
then 51 minus five would be 46.
So we can check to see if 46 is less than or equal to the ISIS latitude.
And then if the ISS latitude is less than or equal to 51 plus five,
which is 56. Then if this is true,
it means that this value is in between these two values.
So let's replace these numbers with my actual latitude.
So MY_LAT - 5
and then MY_LAT + 5.
And then we have to make sure that it's also true for the longitude.
So we're going to do basically the same thing,
but this time using my longitude.
So in my longitude minus five is less than or equal to the ISS's longitude
and the ISS longitude
should be less than or equal to my longitude plus five.
If both of these things are true,
then my position is pretty much within plus or minus five degrees of the ISS.
At this point, I should probably create some sort of a function for this.
So I could say is_iss_overhead.
And I can indent all of this into that function.
And if this happens to be true, I'm going to return true.
This part deals with checking
whether if the ISS is at a similar position to my position,
the next part deals with figuring out whether if it's nighttime or not.
So again,
let's create a function and I'll call it is_night.
And this function is going to return true when it is actually nighttime. In
order to figure out whether if it is nighttime,
then we're going to get a response - so there's a typo there -
from our request to the sunrise-sunset API
passing in all of these parameters which contain my current location.
And then from the data we get back,
we figure out the sunrise and sunset time by formatting that string
and then turning it into an integer
which is going to represent the current hour in the 24-hour time format.
So then we figure out, well,
what is the current time using the datetime module?
And we can check to see, well,
if the time now is greater than or equal to the sunset time,
or if the time now is less than or equal to the sunrise time,
then it means it's dark.
So now we're getting a warning telling us that this time now is a datetime
object, but the sunset and sunrise are whole numbers or integers.
So what's happened well? Datetime now is, in fact,
the current date and time,
but what we actually want is the current hour and that converts it into an
integer making this comparison valid.
So if it is currently nighttime,
then we're going to return true. And if the ISS is overhead,
then we're also going to return true. So now we've done these two parts,
all that's left to do is once both of these things are true
we can send ourselves an email to tell us to look up.
So if the ISS is overhead and it is currently nighttime,
then we're going to initiate our email sending
which is going to require our smtplib.
And I'm also going to add my email and password as constants up here.
And now we can create our connection
and I'm using again a Gmail server.
So it's going to be smtp.gmail.com.
So we went through all of this when we talked about email in detail.
So I won't waste time talking about it again,
right?
I'm going to send this email from my own address and also to my own address
because after all I'm just making a notification for myself. And the message in this
case is going to have the subject line of look up and I can even add an emoji
here.
And then the content is going to say
The ISS is above you in the sky.
That's it. That's all there is to this. Now,
it'd be quite hard to test this code because we have to wait for the perfect
condition before all of these things will actually be true. While this is the end
of the challenge for you,
there's one thing I want to change with this code to make it a little bit
better.
We can actually put this if statement inside a while loop.
So we could say while true,
which means this loop is going to go again and again, and again,
checking if the ISS is overhead and it's at night.
Now this is going to happen quite frequently because its in a while loop,
but we can slow it down by using the time module.
So we could import the time module and then say time.sleep
and we can get
it to sleep for 60 seconds or however much long you want to wait between
running the script. So now if you hit run,
you won't see that final code where it tells you that your program is done
running.
It's actually continuously running in the background and it's going to execute
this code every 60 seconds.
So as long as you have your computer on and this is running,
then you can run this for a whole 24 hours. And I'll bet you
at some point in the night,
you'll get two or three emails telling you that the ISS is overhead.
So all you have to monitor is just to switch your notifications on on your phone
and when that email comes in to look up into the sky.
So I hope you enjoyed building this project with me
and I hope that you're going to be able to spot the ISS tonight.
If you do, take a video and let us know what it looks like.