Hey, guys, it's Angela from the App Brewery.
And in this lesson, we're going to deep dive into how exactly does the Internet work?
So what exactly is the Internet?
A lot of people think it's a cloud, something that's hanging around in the sky.
It's super complex, super difficult to understand, but actually that's not it at all.
The Internet is pretty simple.
All it is, is just a long piece of wire and wire connects different computers to each other.
So you might have one computer that's in London and another one that's in Seattle, and they can talk
to each other and transfer data through this giant wire.
Now, some of these computers attach to the Internet, have a very special job.
They have to be online 24 over seven ready to serve you all the data and files that you are requesting
when you try to access a website.
And these are called servers.
And what they do is they serve you all the data and files you need to be able to access and interact
with certain websites.
So these computers are called servers.
And any computer that a user would use to access the Internet is called a client.
Now you can imagine a web server as a giant library that's open 24 over seven, and you can go in there
at any hour of the day and say, I want to see Google's homepage or I want to see the latest posts on
TechCrunch and would be able to serve you with all the files and data you would need to be able to view
whatever website you want.
Now, as you can imagine, if there's a library that's big enough to house all of these websites, then
it's going to be pretty difficult to quickly locate the thing that you want out of this giant library.
Right?
So how is this problem solved on the Internet?
Well, let's say that you're sitting at home on your computer and you type in Google.com because you
want to head over to the main Google home page.
Well, what happens behind the scenes is that your browser will send that message to your ISP or your
Internet service provider.
So these are the people who you pay to be able to access the internet.
If you live in the US, that will be AT&T or Comcast.
And if you're in the UK, there will be something like BT or TalkTalk.
Now the message that you're sending the ISP is I want to see Google.com and the ISP will then relay
that message to something called a DNS server, which stands for a domain name system server.
And a DNS server is essentially just a souped up phone book.
And what happens when you make that request through your browser is the DNS server will look up in its
database to find the exact IP address of that website that you're trying to access.
And every single computer that's connected to the internet has an IP address.
It's kind of like a postal code for your computer so that when people need to send and receive files
on the Internet, each computer can be located and contacted using their unique IP address.
And once the DNS server finds that IP address, it will send it back to your browser through the ISP
over the Internet.
Then you can make a direct request to that address.
And what lives at that IP address is of course the Google servers and they'll be able to send you back
all the files and data you need to be able to view the Google Home page.
Now you can try this for yourself to look up the IP address of the Google Home page, head over to this
website nslookup.io and type in google.com and they should show you the exact IP address of the Google
servers that you can access.
Now, if you try checking this on a different day, say in a week or in a month's time, you might see
that this address actually changes.
And that's because many websites, including Google, use something called dynamic IP addresses, as
well as a content distribution network or a CDN.
This basically ensures that it gets you to the closest server to where you are located.
And also this address will change depending on whether if it's being used or not.
So don't type in what you see on screen.
Instead, head over to nslookup.io and look up what is the closest IP address to you that is currently
being used.
So if you copy it and paste it into a new tab, then you'll be able to replicate that process and see
the Google Home page show up.
So to summarize, the Internet is just a bunch of wires that connects up different computers, but it's
just on a much bigger scale connecting up all the computers in the world.
But what about the oceans?
I hear you ask.
Well, that's one of the coolest things.
There are these massive undersea cables connecting all the continents on earth.
And if you head over to submarine cable map.com, you can see all of these cables and see the ones that
connect.
You up to the Internet.
And these undersea cables are massive, consisting of hundreds of fiber optic fibers, each of them
using lasers to transmit up to 400GB of data per second.
This is a cross-section of one of the cables that run to New Zealand.
It's an absolute marvel of modern technology.
And it looks really beautiful, don't you think?
And to think that every single time we load up a web page or click on a button on a website, behind
the scenes was sending signals that navigate all of this crazy underwater and above water wires.
And all I need is just an IP address.
And through tiny electric signals, traveling at the speed of light through the oceans and halfway around
the world in a matter of milliseconds, I get to view my favorite websites and that is how awesome the
internet is.
And we're going to be taming it to build our own websites and web apps.
And to be able to do that, we first have to understand how exactly do websites work.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now that we've spoken about how the internet works, in this episode
I want to talk about how exactly do websites work. What exactly does HTML,
CSS and JavaScript do exactly? Now, in order to access a webpage,
we all know that you need a browser, right? And that can be Chrome,
Safari, Firefox, whatever is your favorite one.
These are all pieces of software that allow you to look up the IP address of
your website and be able to receive data that it can render into this beautiful
websites that we see. Now,
the data that you receive from the server usually consists of three types of
files; HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
And it's very likely that you would have come across these types of files or
these words before,
because they're so common and there are so integral to how websites work.
But, what exactly do they do
and why are there so many different types of files?
Why can't we just have one file that's, you know, a website? Well,
they actually have very different jobs.
The HTML code file is responsible for the structure of your website.
So if a website was a house,
then the HTML would be the builder who would come in to build the walls or put
in a toilet. Basically they establish the structure of your house.
And when you write HTML code, you also build up the structure of your website.
So you could use HTML to add an image or button or text box,
whatever it is that you need in your website. Now,
the second type of file are CSS files,
and these files are responsible for styling your website.
If you were building a house, then this would be the painters and decorators.
They would be going around
painting the walls or adding stylistic flourishes to your place,
and generally making the place look the way that you want it to.
And that's exactly what CSS code does as well. When you incorporate CSS,
it allows you to specify how you want your website to look.
So you could say that, yes, I have a button that I got from my HTML,
but that button I want it to be red and I want the text to be white
and I want the font of the text to be an Arial. That is all done using CSS code.
Now the final component is the JavaScript code.
And this is the code that allows your website to actually do things or have
behavior. And if you were building a house,
you would have the electrician come in,
who would be able to connect the wires so that your light bulbs actually switch
on or somebody who comes in and does the plumbing so that your toilet can
actually flush. And the JavaScript code does exactly that.
It allows your website to actually do things and have behavior.
So if we take the Google website as an example again,
once we receive these files from Google server,
when our browser loads up the HTML files, we'll get to see the structure
of the website, namely, there's one image which has their logo,
there's two buttons, and there's a text box where we can enter our search. Now,
when we receive the CSS files,
then that will modify the appearance of all of those components.
We don't have any more buttons or any more images,
but the now look the way that Google wanted it to. And finally,
when we incorporate the JavaScript files,
then our website actually starts having behavior. It has functionality
and it's actually able to do something rather than just display some images and
texts to us. Now, with the knowledge that we've already acquired,
we can already start messing around with websites on the internet.
So open up Chrome and head over to techcrunch.com.
And if you're not familiar with it,
it's basically a technology news website where I get my latest tech news.
Once you're over here,
I want you to right-click on the title here and click on inspect.
Now this brings up the Chrome developer tools,
and we're going to be exploring this in a lot more detail,
but for now we're going to use it to do something really simple.
You can see that when I right-click on that heading and click inspect,
it automatically opens up the entire code file that was used to render this
website. So these are all of the elements that make up this website.
And when you click on inspect,
it will highlight to you the part of the code that corresponds to the thing that
you right clicked, right? In this case, it's this title.
And inside this title, you can see that there is a link,
which means that when you click on it, it'll go to another web page,
but it also got a bit of text. So right inside Chrome developer tools,
if you double click on the bit of text that corresponds to the title,
you can actually edit it.
So let's go ahead and change the front page of TechCrunch.
Let's say something like,
uhm..
So this is a great way of pranking your friends,
especially when they can see that you're on tech crunch.com and the title or any
of the texts on the website is what you want it to say.
And this is a great joke to play on friends who are maybe not quite as
technologically advanced as you,
because they haven't taken the course that you have. Now unfortunately,
when I hit refresh on this website, all of my good work is gone.
And the reason is because when I'm editing it here inside my browser,
I'm actually changing the local copy of this file that I got back from the
server. But when I click refresh,
then that makes a new request to the servers to load up a fresh copy of the
website. So of course, then it updates to the original content.
But in the coming lessons, we're going to be working with HTML, CSS,
and JavaScript so that you can create and host live on the internet,
your very own websites and through learning how to code and how to build
websites
you are going to be able to make websites that say anything that you want it to,
look the way that you want it to, and have the functionality that you need.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you in the next lesson.
Now let's get started by learning a little bit more about what exactly is it and how do we use it to
create websites.
Now, no matter what browser you like to use, Chrome or Safari or Brave, even all of these applications
do the same thing.
They take different files such as HTML, CSS and JavaScript, and they render them into a website.
But even though most modern websites are created using these three different file types combined together,
you can't create a website with just a CSS file or just a JavaScript file.
However, you can have just an HTML file.
And in fact, that's exactly what the first websites were created with HTML.
Now HTML defines the content and structure of the website.
So for example, in this case, all that my HTML file does is it it renders a heading that says my website.
And when this file is opened by the browser, it will display that heading saying my website.
Now what exactly is HTML?
Let's break it down.
So HTML stands for hypertext markup language.
If we look at the first part, hypertext, what does that mean?
Well, it refers to the pieces of text which can link to other documents in the website.
So these pieces of text are hypertext or hyperlinks, and they are the foundation of how an HTML website
works.
Now, if we take a look at the World First website created by Sir Tim Berners-Lee, who also happens
to be the inventor of the Internet, then you can see it's filled with these hyperlinks marked in blue
and exactly as you would expect.
If you click on any of these hyperlinks, it takes you to another document, another HTML file.
So if we go back, you can see that we were on projecting HTML.
And if I click on one of the hyperlinks like how can I help, it will take me to another HTML file and
this is how hypertext works.
And there's even a link on this website explaining exactly what hypertext is.
So now that we know what hypertext is, what about the other part, the markup language?
What is a markup language?
Now, if you look at the English language, we often see little bits that function very similar to markup,
like these double quotes.
The presence of these quotation marks is what tells a reader that this part is a quotation.
And as you'll find, this is going to be really similar to what you see in the editor's review of manuscript.
So used to mark them up and show different things, such as, for example, which parts need to be bold
by adding a squiggly line underneath it and which parts need to be underlined by adding a straight line
through it.
So how do you do markup with HTML?
Well, it's done through what's called HTML tags.
Now, in the early days of the Internet, there were only very few HTML tags.
These days there are loads more, but realistically, you're only going to be using some of the most
important ones such as headings H1 through to H6 or the paragraph tag the P tag.
So here you can see all of the HTML tags, but when we narrow it down to the ones that you actually
need to know, then it makes it a lot more approachable.
And in the rest of the course we're going to be covering some of the most essential tags.
And so don't worry about learning them.
So don't worry about memorizing all of them or learning them.
We're going to cover them as we need them in our projects and in our exercises.
So in the next lesson, we're going to get started by learning about the heading tag, one of the most
OG HTML tags that ever existed.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now, in the previous lesson, we took a look at what is and in this lesson I want to get us started
using HTML as quickly as possible so we can learn how to write our own code and start creating websites
with it.
Now, in this lesson, we're going to be learning about one of the most important elements, the heading
element.
And this is what a heading element looks like.
It starts off with what's called an opening tag here, and it ends with what's called a closing tag.
Now, if you look closely, the opening and the closing tag actually have one thing that's different,
and it's this forward slash right here.
And that is what makes this a closing tag.
And what goes in between these two tags is the content of that particular HTML element.
So in this case, what we're saying we want to do is we want to create a H1 heading and what the heading
is going to contain is these words Hello world.
Now, very often when you hear me talking about HTML, you'll hear me refer to tags and elements and
you'll see this on the Internet and everywhere else as well.
So what exactly is the difference?
Well, the tag refers to these bits.
These are tags.
Anything that's inside an angle bracket we call these angle brackets is a tag.
And they have different names.
So as I mentioned, this one is the opening tag.
And this one at the end is, of course, called the closing tag.
Now, these are the tags.
So what's an element?
Well, the entire thing here, this is an element that includes the content as well as any opening or
closing tags.
This is the HTML element.
And these parts are the tags.
So hopefully that'll make things a little bit clearer the next time you hear about tags and elements.
What is the purpose of these heading elements?
Well, the idea comes from book binding.
If you create a book and you create a table of contents like this one, you'll see that there's a sort
of hierarchy, right?
You've got the top level headings here.
This would probably be a level one heading and these would be a level two heading because they refer
to something that's more or less related to this approval section.
And you can see inside section eight here, there's even another subsection 8.1, which goes into more
detail about some aspect of eight.
This in our case might be an H three heading.
These levels are what we get to define using our HTML headings.
This is what the code would look like for all six level of headings and remember that there is no heading
seven.
There is no such thing as an H seven that does not exist once you've gone to heading six.
That's pretty much the end as defined by the people and anything that's lower in importance, you would
start using a different type of tag, which will go into a little bit later on.
But for everything from one through to six, the structure is pretty much the same.
You've got an open tag, which is H one or H six, and you've got a closing tag that has the corresponding
number.
Now if you create a tag like this with an H one and then you end with a different one like an H six,
then that's not going to work either.
Just remember that when you're writing your own code.
Now, what does this look like?
If we were to run this code, this is what we would get.
We would get different heading levels and by default, they would be styled to have different sizes.
So heading one being the biggest and heading six being the smallest.
We can of course further style this later on, but as soon as we type these headings, it just gives
us an indication of our levels to make sure that we've written all our code as intended.
And this essentially follows that structure we saw earlier on with the table of contents.
The level one headings are the biggest and the level six headings are the smallest.
So now that we've seen a little bit about how all of this works, let's try an exercise where we create
our own heading elements.
To download the starting files, you have to go over to the course resources for this lesson and click
on the 2.1 heading element file in order to download it.
Now, if you don't know where that is, then you might have missed where at the very beginning of the
course there's a lesson called how to download the course resources and in there I show you exactly
how to download each of the course resources for every single lesson.
So if you miss that, be sure to head over there to take a look and see how you can do this.
Now, once you've downloaded this file, it's really important that you extract it or what we call unzipping.
Now, the first thing I want you to do is to create a folder for all of your web development projects,
and you can create that folder anywhere you like on your desktop in your C drive, in your username
section, wherever you want, but just call it web development projects like this.
Now, once you've created that folder, then I want you to go ahead and open up the zip file that you
just downloaded by double clicking on it.
And once you've opened up that zip file, I want you to drag it into your Web development projects folder
like this.
And then you'll be able to access them right here.
Now, the next step is we're going to open it up in VS code.
Inside vs code, go to file and we're going to create a new window.
Now open up the explorer here.
And then when we're here, we're going to open up our web development projects folder that we just created,
and you should be able to see that folder heading element.
Now, if for some reason this is not working for you, especially if you're on Windows, this might
be because you haven't actually extracted this folder properly.
So again, make sure that you double click on the zip file or on Windows.
You can also right click on it and click extract.
And then once you've done that, drag, that folder that's been extracted into your web development
projects folder and open up that folder inside your VS code.
When you're here, you can see that there are three files in this folder called 2.1 heading Element
one is the index.html.
This is where you're going to be writing your code and I've got some starting code for you which we're
going to need to modify in order to complete this challenge.
Now you've also got the solution, which I don't recommend looking at until you've completed the challenge,
just to check your code or see if there's any differences.
Now notice how I've added a little bit here so that you don't accidentally see it unless you wanted
to.
But if you want to see the solution, just scroll down and you'll see it down there.
The goal of this exercise is to make the code here, create a website that looks like this.
Remember previously when we did our setup and download for VS Code, I showed you how to install the
extension live preview.
If you don't see live preview when you click on extensions, that might mean that you've missed out
on some parts of that video.
So please go back to the setup and download videos for VS Code because there's some other things that
I need you to set up as well.
Make sure you don't skip any of these lessons unless you know exactly what you're doing and you're really
familiar with everything.
What that live preview allows us to do is to go into our code file index.html, right click on it and
click show preview.
So it should now open up another pane and you can see it shows us our book chapters, Section one,
Chapter one, chapter two, chapter three sections and Diagrams and Subsections.
Unfortunately, everything seems to be just on one long line, and if you drag it out, you can see
it's just one long line.
There's no formatting at all and there's no indication about hierarchy.
So that's where the challenge comes in.
You're going to use what you learned about heading elements in order to format this code here in the
index.html so that we end up with something that looks like this.
So we want the preview to show us heading one elements heading two elements heading three elements.
And this one this diagram one is actually a heading four element.
So you should have H one through to H four in your code here.
So now is the time to pause me in the video and try to complete this challenge.
And after you're done then you can resume the video and we'll walk through the solution together, pause
the video now and give it a go.
All right.
So we're going to have a single h one element up here, which is going to be for this word book.
So we're going to put an H one element right here, and we're going to drag our book, which is the
content.
Remember, in between these two tags, that's how our heading tags are formatted.
Now, the next one are these Chapter one, chapter two, chapter three sections, and they're all going
to be the next level of hierarchy, which is an H two.
So let's do that for all three of them.
And then we can move on to our H three, which is going to be the sections within the chapters.
And now I'm just going to fast forward through the rest of the code so that you don't get bored.
And then finally, this diagram, which belongs inside section one in chapter two, is going to be the
final and the lowest level of hierarchy, which is an H four.
And once we've completed all of this code, you can check yourself against the solution code and you
should see it's pretty much the same.
Now, one of the things that you'll find is when you hit save using command S or using file save, you'll
see that IT auto formats our code so that we lose any of the indentation.
Don't worry if this happens to you, it's perfectly normal.
And if we check ourselves against the solution, you can see they match.
Exactly.
And we end up with the same result as the goal image, which is what we were aiming for.
How did you manage that?
Don't worry.
If you got things wrong, this is where it's safe to go wrong and try things because we're just learning
there's no tests and there's nobody watching you.
All that matters is you're actually learning stuff.
That's what's important.
Have a play around with the code.
Don't worry, if you do anything wrong, there's always a solution.
And me here to help you.
There's a couple of things to note in terms of do's and don'ts when it comes to heading elements that
I want to talk to you about.
One important rule is notice how in our exercise there was only one H1.
It's not good practice to have more than one H1 because the H1 is the very top level heading.
Imagine the H1 as the book title and the table of contents as including the other parts.
So maybe the H2 would be the first chapter.
Don't have more than one H1.
Instead, if you need another subtitle or another level of heading, then go to the H2 or H3 or all
of the other ones up until H6.
Now the other thing to watch out for is don't skip a level.
When you're creating heading elements, don't go straight from H1 to H3.
If you have an H3, there should also be an H2 somewhere on that web page.
Instead, I recommend to just go in order when you have an H1 that you've created and then you realize
you need another heading, then go to an H2.
And then if you need another level of heading that's even lower in priority, go to an H3.
Don't jump between the different level headings.
These are not things that will break your code.
Your website will still look fine even if you break all of these rules.
But they're just rules for convention.
And because we're going to be professionals, we're going to start off on the right foot and learn all
the rules that we need to know.
Now, if you wanted to read up even more on the heading elements, then I recommend going to the professional
tool, which is our Mozilla developer network web docs, and they have documentation for all of the
HTML elements that exist.
And when you read up on each of these pages, they tell you more details about things that you need
to know, and they show you some interactive examples of how it all works.
Now, I don't recommend reading through all of these for all of the HTML elements, but I do recommend
that if you're going to use a new element that you haven't seen before and you don't know how it works,
you haven't had a lecture on it, then I recommend just taking a quick look at the docs and seeing some
examples about how they're used in a similar way that I've shown you in the lectures.
Now that we've learned about one of the most important HTML elements, the heading elements, in the
next lesson, we're going to move on to another super important element which is the paragraph element.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
So now that you've seen what you can do with the HTML heading element, the next one we're going to
learn about is the paragraph element.
And this is also related to formatting and putting text on our websites.
This is what a paragraph element looks like and similar to the heading element, you've got the opening
tag and the closing tag, and in between you've got the content that is going to be your paragraph.
Now the reason why we need a paragraph tag is because if you just had plain text in your HTML document,
when you run the code and you see it on a website, what you'll see is something like this.
The text, they run into each other onto the same line and you can't actually tell where one paragraph
begins and where the other ends.
On the other hand, if we had created two paragraph elements for these two lines, then when we run
the code you will see them being separated with a line in between to be able to distinguish the different
paragraphs.
And this is also really important for people who are using screen readers, so people who might be blind,
because what the screen reader will do is they'll see the beginning of each paragraph element and it
allows the blind user to be able to skip to the next paragraph easily and be able to see what's going
on each time.
Now let's put those skills into practice by trying an exercise using the paragraph element.
If you head over to the course resources for this lesson, you should be able to download the zip file
for the 2.2 paragraph element.
And once you've extracted and unzipped it, then go ahead and put it into your web development projects
folder and then open it up inside vs code.
I showed you how to do all of this in the previous lesson in HTML heading element as well as the initial
lesson when I showed you how to download course resources, so be sure to check those places if you
don't know how to get hold of this folder.
But once you have it opened up like this, then I want you to go ahead and open up the index.html file,
which as always, is where we're going to write our code.
Notice here we've got three paragraphs, the first paragraph, the second paragraph and the third paragraph.
And then there's some placeholder text in Latin, which doesn't mean anything.
It just is there so that you can see what a paragraph of text would look like.
And when you go ahead and right click and show preview, you should see that all of the paragraphs are
jumbled together into one long line and we can't tell where one paragraph begins and the other one ends.
So now it is your mission to solve this problem using what you've learned about the paragraph element.
So go ahead and format these three paragraphs using the paragraph tag and once you're done, you should
see the preview.
Show something like this where each paragraph is separated into new lines and clearly visually, we're
able to see the difference and we're able to distinguish these three different paragraphs.
Pause the video now, and once you're done, we'll go through the solution together.
All right.
We're going to use our paragraph tag.
So we're going to put the open tag here just in front of our first paragraph, and then we're going
to put the closing tag at the very end of our first paragraph, and then we're going to repeat that
basically for all of the other paragraphs.
Now you can see here I'm just clicking and dragging.
Alternatively, you can cut it and then paste it at the very end of the paragraph.
It really doesn't matter how you do it, as long as you get those tags in the right places.
And now hopefully your preview should have updated and you can see these paragraphs forming as we type.
So this looks pretty much the same as our goal.
And if you check the solution HTML, you should see the tags in the correct places as well.
So hopefully that wasn't too hard and you were able to do it all by yourself and you've seen now what
is the benefit of using a paragraph element to separate text into different paragraphs of content?
Now, what you saw in the exercise are bits of placeholder text, and it's what we would refer to as
Lorem ipsum.
It's something that you'll come across quite a lot, especially in web design.
It's so that we don't end up with something like this where we're trying to simulate content in a paragraph,
but then we're just writing content, content, content, or this is a paragraph, this is a paragraph,
this is a paragraph.
And the reason why we don't want to do this is because these are all the same words.
The sentence has the same length.
It doesn't look like what a natural block of text would look like, and we don't have the time or energy
to actually create the content just for testing and web design.
So that's why we use something called Lorem Ipsum.
And Lorem ipsum apparently comes from Latin classical literature by a famous author called Cicero.
If you've heard of him and it's over 2000 years old and this has been in use in the print industry for
many, many years, ever since the 1500s, even, where people started laying out newspapers and when
they didn't have the content for the layout, they would use this placeholder text.
If you want to get hold of them, you can go over to Simcom and there you'll find Lorem ipsum even in
different languages like Dutch or Polish, and you can use this tool to generate as many paragraphs
or words or bytes or lists as you need by simply using this generate button.
And here I've got five paragraphs ready to go to put into my new web design.
Now, instead of having something that looks like this where everything's all the same length, instead
we have very natural looking paragraphs that mimic pretty much what a regular English article would
look like.
And this is done in a matter of seconds using Lorem ipsum.
Now if Lorem ipsum is a little bit too boring for you, there's actually some novelty versions of this.
One of my favorite is bacon ipsum.com and it will generate similar to Lorem ipsum, but then you'll
get words like bacon and flank and pork loin and pork belly.
Now if you're not a meat eater, then maybe you should try something like bro ipsum.com where you can
have all of the bro terminology in a Lorem ipsum format.
And apparently the things that bros say are things like Taco pow and washboard and rail and heli paopao,
whatever it may be.
And if none of these take your fancy, then I recommend going on to Google and you can actually find
more of these kind of things by just searching for funny Lorem ipsum.
And there's a whole bunch of different ones like vegan ipsum or pirate ipsum and you'll come across
all sorts of different placeholder text generators.
But the important thing is you know how to get hold of them and you can use it in your code.
So as an add on challenge, if you want to, you can generate your own version of Lorem ipsum or Bacon
ipsum or bro ipsum and you can create an article using the paragraph tag and the Lorem ipsum that you've
generated.
Feel free to modify the index.html in the coding exercise that we just completed.
So have a play around with that and be sure to comment in the Q&A sections below.
If you find some Lorem ipsum that you think is ridiculous or really funny or really cool and I'll see
you on the next lesson.
All right.
So in this lesson, we're going to learn all about the void elements such as the horizontal rule and
the break element.
What exactly are void elements?
Well, we've seen what non void elements are, such as the paragraph element or the heading elements,
and they're not void because they have content right here in between.
A void element is an element where you are forbidden from putting any content inside the tag.
And in fact the tag itself even looks very different.
So this is a horizontal rule element and you can see that it starts out with an angle, bracket ends
with an angle bracket.
But then right here, there is this forward slash just before the end of the tag.
You might think this looks a bit like the closing tag of a normal HTML element, but it's actually subtly
different because here in the closing tag, that forward slash is just after the opening angle bracket.
It's right here in front of the letter.
Whereas in the void elements, the forward slash is actually just before the end of the tag.
And normally by convention, you'll see a little space here as well between the tag name and also that
forward slash.
This is just something to be really careful about.
When you're creating these void elements.
Make sure that you've got the forward slash slashing in the right direction so this way and not a backslash
like this.
So when it points to the right, then it's a forward slash and when it points backwards, then it's
a backslash.
So what does this look like when we add it to a HTML document?
Well, here we've got our previous two paragraphs and right in between the two paragraphs I've added
a horizontal rule which will hopefully help us divide the content to show that this part is not related
to this part.
And we've got some sort of separation in between when we run this code or when we view it in a web browser,
this is what you would see.
You would see the first paragraph, the second paragraph, and then you would see this horizontal rule
or basically a horizontal line where the air element would be in that document.
Now the horizontal rule is not the only void element.
Another common one you'll see is the break element.
And it looks like this.
Now, similarly, again, we've got the name of the tag and then we've got that forward slash and then
we basically end the tag.
So there is no opening tag.
There is no closing tag.
There is only a single tag that looks like this.
And the name of the tag goes right before the forward slash.
Now, how does the break element work?
Well, it's really useful when you have things where you need to separate things onto separate lines
in order to have the correct meaning.
For example, if you have poems, they are in fact meant to be in the same paragraph, but they should
really each be on different lines in order to make the rhyming work or in order to make the structure
of the poem correct.
So this is a poem from one of my favorite poets, William Blake.
And in order for it to work, we can't have it all run in one line, even if it's in the same paragraph.
If we had this code right here, even though yes, it is all in the same paragraph, it is all related
to each other and this does make sense.
But you don't look at poetry like this.
It doesn't really work.
We don't know where we're supposed to breathe and how we're supposed to read out the poem.
So instead we can add our break elements that we just learned about.
Our void element doesn't have any content in it, but it just shows where the breaks in this paragraph
has to go in order for this poem to look right.
And when this HTML document is rendered, this is what you'll see.
A perfect layout for a poem.
The World in a grain of sand and heaven in a war flower.
Hold infinity in the palm of your hand and eternity in an hour.
And it's all beautifully formatted thanks to each of our break elements at the end of each line.
So now it's your turn to try an exercise using these void elements.
So go ahead and download the starting files for this exercise from the course resources for this lesson.
And when you've extracted it and open it up, this is what you should see in the index.
We've got the name of our poet William Blake, and this is apparently his real address that he lived
at at some point in life.
And then we've got two paragraphs from Wikipedia which briefly describes the poet.
And I want you to use everything you've learned so far in order to format this document so that it will
look like the goal that I've got right here for you.
As you can see, this top level, the name of our poet is going to be rendered as an H one, because
that is the most important thing about this particular web page.
And then we've got the address of the poet, which is rendered as a paragraph.
But notice that addresses, even though they are a single paragraph, they again need to be broken up
into separate lines using our break element.
And then finally, we've got a horizontal rule that separates the address and the name of the author
from the little bit of description of this author, which should sit in two separate paragraphs.
Now I want you to pause the video and edit the index.html so you end up with this goal PNG.
When you preview this website instead of this jumbled block of text that we have at the moment.
Pause the video now and give this challenge a go.
All right.
So hopefully you've given it a go and everything worked out.
I'm going to run through the solution.
So first we said we were going to have an H one for his name, and then we're going to have a paragraph
tag that encloses the address.
Now, in order to have that address on different lines, we're going to add our break element to the
end of each line.
And remember, our break element is a self-closing tag.
So we're going to create it like like so.
Now I'm going to go ahead and simply copy and paste it to the end of each line and you can see how nicely
our address is now formatted.
And finally, we wanted these two paragraphs at the end to be separated.
So I'm going to go ahead and simply do that.
And now we are pretty much golden.
We've achieved our goal output.
We've got our H1, our address separated, and the only thing we need to do is to add that horizontal
rule between the address and the two paragraphs.
Let's go ahead and add the other void element that we learned about.
And now we've completed the challenge and you can check yourself against the solution to make sure that
everything that you did looks exactly the same.
Now, a neat trick I like to use is to simply copy the solution and go to diff checker.com paste in
the solution code.
And then paste your code and then go ahead and click find difference.
And it should highlight all the places that are different in case you've misspelled something or you've
done something wrong.
So for example, in this case, in our version, there is a space after the word Blake and the closing
tag, which in terms of HTML will not make any difference.
But had I instead maybe written the H1 incorrectly and I didn't write the H for the closing tag, then
you can see our output looks completely different and we're looking through all of this text.
We don't know why it's happened, so we go ahead and copy it and then diff it to the solution.
And it should highlight the fact that that is incorrect and we should now be alerted to check the difference.
That's one tip that I have for you today.
And let me just go back to our index.html fix this bug and we should now be ready to go.
Now in terms of do's and don'ts with void elements, sometimes you see people doing is they add a break
tag to add a new line instead of creating a separate paragraph element.
Now, this is not what you want to do because this is not very good for accessibility, which means
it'll make it harder for blind users with screen readers to understand the content on your website.
So I recommend you always create new paragraph elements when you have new paragraphs and use the break
element only when there is some sort of reason why you would want to separate the different lines in
a single paragraph.
But it still is a single paragraph such as in the case of a poem or in the case of an address that we
covered in this lesson.
Now, the final thing to mention is that sometimes when you look at the horizontal rule element or the
break element, you might see it represented.
Without this final closing tag, you might see people simply write this and this is perfectly valid
HTML.
So you could in fact have a horizontal rule that looks like this.
You could have a break element that looks like this instead of the one with the forward slash at the
end.
And these are both valid options.
You could go for this or you could go for this as of HTML5, the latest version of HTML.
What it's starting to do is it's starting to ignore this forward slash at the end so it doesn't even
look at it.
It sees the first part and already knows that a break is a void element and a horizontal rule is a void
element.
So it doesn't actually need to keep reading.
But I recommend to write your code with this end forward slash.
And the reason is because when you read your code, you as the human, it will be much easier for you
to see that this is a void element and it doesn't need a closing tag so that you don't end up being
confused and you can identify the void elements and the non void elements easily and distinguish them
from each other.
So that's just a quick tip and something to alert you to when you see it written like this on the internet.
Both versions are valid.
You can pick and choose, but I recommend going with this version.
So now that we've gotten a introduction to HTML, I want you to put everything you've learned together
in order to create a new project.
So the project that we're going to be building today is called The Favorite Movie Project.
It's going to be a website to keep track of all of your favorite movies that you've watched When you
go to Roger Ebert.com, he is one of the greatest film critics of all time.
In fact, he's passed away now, but he's got movie reviews and ratings for all the movies that he's
watched.
And you can see that when you go to his website.
I think this is a really great way of keeping track of what you've watched.
Because when friends ask me for recommendations, I can never remember what it is that I've watched
in this year that I really like and what to recommend.
So what we're going to be building today is a very simple website.
It's going to be a website that tracks your favorite movies maybe of all time, maybe of the last year,
whatever you want to do.
And the requirement is you should have at least three movies that you put in here.
So what you're going to need is to create a H1 as the title of the website, and then you're going to
have an H2 as the subtitle, and then you're going to have a horizontal rule as your void element in
there.
And then you're going to have three movies that you're going to list and they're all going to be created
using the H3 element.
And then finally you should have a section which is going to be a paragraph element that's going to
describe why you liked those movies.
And this is basically a very simple format for this website.
Now feel free once you've done all of this to continue to mod this website, to change it up, to add
things, to add break elements, whatever it is you want to do.
But at the minimum, I want to see all of these elements represented on a page.
And of course, feel free to add your own movies.
And I would love to see in the Q and A a picture of your website to see what it is that are your top
movies.
And maybe I'll get some inspiration.
So the next time when I have movie night and I can't figure out what to watch.
So I'm curious to see your recommendations as well.
So go ahead and download the movie ranking project ZIP file from this lesson's course resources.
If you don't know how to do that again, go back to one of the first videos in the course at the very
beginning of Section one where I showed you in a video how to download course resources.
And once you've unzipped it and extracted it, then open it up in vs code and go ahead and code to your
heart's content using everything you've learned.
Pause the video now and give that a go.
Now let's go through the solution.
In my case, I'm going to have an H one at the top, which is going to be the title.
So, um, top movies of all time, according to Angela.
And then afterwards, I'm going to create a subtitle which I will write my best three movies.
And then after that we were going to add a horizontal rule to separate this part from the actual content
of our website.
And I'm going to create an H three to represent each of the movies I'm going to recommend.
So I'm going to recommend A Spirited Away, which is one of my favorite animes.
And I'm going to use a paragraph tag to describe a little bit about why I like it.
So I'm just going to call it favorite anime.
And then the next movie we will be Ex Machina.
And I really liked it because it's a really cool sci fi movie.
And then finally, the third one is going to be the movie Drive with Ryan Gosling because it was really
beautifully shot.
Cool.
This is the basics of what you would need to have done for this project.
It has all of the elements that were required and you can see in the goal PNG that it's got all the
things that we've described, even if the text is a little bit different.
Of course it won't be, according to Angela for you, it will be according to your name.
And now that you've done that, feel free to add different things in here as you would want.
Maybe add a bit more to the paragraph tags, maybe add a poem about your favorite movie, go crazy,
try out things and share in the Q&A your project as a screenshot.
If you don't know how to do a screenshot, be sure to be sure to type that into Google.
How do I create a screenshot?
And then you can add it into the Q&A and we can all look at your favorite movies and be inspired.
So I hope you enjoyed building the project together.
And in the next section we're going to dive a little bit deeper into some more intermediate aspects
of HTML.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.