Now that we've seen how HTML elements and tags work, it's time to explore the bigger picture, what's
called the HTML boilerplate.
And this will allow us to understand the structure of our HTML files, just like how there is structure
to letters that you would write.
For example, there's the section where you have your address and then you probably would include a
dear so and so, and then you have the body of your letter and finally you would write something like
your sincerely and then your name and signature.
Similarly, there is a structure to our HTML files and it looks something like this.
And this is called a boilerplate.
It's what you usually start off with when you create any new HTML file.
And we're going to go through it line by line so that we understand it.
At the top of every HTML file, there should be a doctype declaration.
And that's what this tag does.
It tells the browser which version of the file was written in.
Now the latest version of HTML is HTML5 and the Doctype declaration looks like this with an angle bracket,
an exclamation mark, doctype in all caps and then HTML.
And this line tells any browser that's reading our HTML file that we have written our code in HTML version
five.
The next part that we've got is the actual HTML.
Now, this is going to be the root of the document.
It means that everything else, every other element, no matter if it's an H1 or an image or a link,
it's all going to go inside the opening and closing tags of the HTML element and this attribute where
it says Lang This is the language of the text content in that element.
So for example, if you're writing a website that is going to be targeted at English speakers, then
you're going to set your lang to English.
N.
Now this isn't very important for the users who can see your website.
It's more important for the users who can't because there are various screen readers and assistive technologies
that will look at this language attribute so that when they read out the website, they can pronounce
the words correctly.
Opens profile photo follow at you.
Angela Button.
Now, with the HTML element, we're starting to see the beginnings of a hamburger.
There's a bun at the top and there's a bun at the bottom.
For those of you guys who have been my long term friends, you know how much I love food analogies,
but this is a great one because when we have an HTML element, usually there is the opening and the
closing and everything that belongs in it is sandwiched inside.
Now the next part of the HTML boilerplate is the head element.
And this is an area where important information about our website is placed that is not going to be
displayed to the user.
It includes things that will help the website render in the browser correctly, but it doesn't include
any sort of content like text or images or anything that the user will see.
So one of the things that you should always have in the head section is a meta tag for the character
set encoding of the web page, and in this case it's set as UTF eight.
What this does is it ensures that the characters that you're using on your website gets displayed correctly.
So, for example, in certain character sets, it won't allow emojis to render in other character sets.
They won't have certain symbols like multiplication and division symbols.
And that's what this meta tag takes care of.
Usually by convention in our HTML boilerplate, we will simply just include this tag as is using the
UTF eight character set, which is one of the most common.
So you don't even have to think about it.
Now another thing that you should have in your head section is the title of your website, and that
title is usually what gets displayed up here in the Tab Bar.
And in fact, if you right click on any website in Chrome, you can click to view page source and you
can see we've got our Doctype, we've got our HTML element inside it, we've got our head, our character
set.
And then if we scroll a little bit more, you can see we've got our title here.
And in between the opening and closing tags of the title, it tells you what title should be displayed
up here.
So in our case here, the title was simply say my website.
Now there's a lot more things that can go into the head element, as you've seen when we looked at.
The Google Home page.
But for now, these two are the most important things that will always go into your files.
And it's important to know.
We'll cover other tags as we come across them.
Now, the next sandwich inside the sandwich, if you will, are two slices of tomatoes.
No, just kidding.
It's actually the body element.
Just like a person.
After the head element comes the body element.
Inside the body element is where we're going to be spending the majority of our time creating and writing
our website.
This is where all of the content of the website goes.
So the text, the titles, the images, the links, everything that you can do with HTML.
Creating content and structure goes in between the opening and the closing tags of the body element.
So somewhere inside here.
Now what can go in here?
Well, we've seen already how an H1 works so we can put in a heading, we can add images, we can add
lots of things.
And this is essentially where the meat of our website is going to live.
Once our burger collapses down, you can see that this is what a typical website's HTML code is made
up of.
So no matter what you add into your body, you can vary it up.
But by default, most websites will start off with a boilerplate that looks like this.
When you're starting out, I often recommend students to type this out when they're creating new websites
and in fact you can have a go doing this now by going into VS code, typing out these elements and creating
your website entirely from scratch.
Now we're beginning to see this idea of nesting in an HTML document, and this is going to be a concept
that's going to become super important as we learn more and more programming.
But it's simple to understand if we come back to this analogy of the hamburger.
So we have our HTML element which has the opening and closing tags here, and it is exactly like our
hamburger bun.
So this is our top bun and this is our bottom bun and sandwich.
In between is everything that goes inside the HTML element.
Now, if we take a look at our body element, then you can see here we've got the opening body tag,
which will represent with a slice of tomato and the closing body tag.
And in between those two slices of tomato is the content for our website.
Now you'll notice that some of the HTML tags, even though they have an opening and closing tag, they're
not on different lines.
And that's because if we can fit it on one line and we can see the beginning and the end very easily,
then we don't actually need to create several lines.
But nonetheless, it still got a beginning and an end.
Now the important thing for us when we're writing code and we've got all of this sandwiching going on
that we indent our code properly so that you can see that this clearly lines up with the opening tag
here.
So they are clearly sandwiching something in between.
And then we have two spaces and we've got the next indentation level here.
So this one lines up with the closing tag and through this kind of indentation you can quite easily
visualize that this head section is clearly embedded inside the HTML section.
So just like our lettuce is inside our hamburger, by indenting our code properly, we'll be able to
keep our code tidy and we'll be able to see at a glance exactly what our code looks like.
Now, finally, because we're using vs code, I want to tell you about a shortcut.
That means you don't have to type out this boilerplate every single time.
Once you've typed it out once or twice and you know exactly how this boilerplate looks, you can save
a lot of time by simply typing exclamation mark.
Hitting Enter on the first selection and then it will automatically insert all of that code for you,
saving you a lot of time, especially when you're creating many documents.
Now, the important thing here, though, is this only works if you have created a dot HTML website.
So notice that when you create a new file inside vs code, if you name it and save it as something something
dot html, then this trick will work.
If you save it with another extension, then it won't.
There's a couple of things here that we haven't seen before.
Couple more meta tags and there's a lot of other meta tags.
But here we've got one line here which says HTTP equivalent compatible content, i.e. edge.
This basically just keeps our code compatible with Internet Explorer.
And in fact, I normally don't write this line anymore because Internet Explorer has been deprecated
and is no longer in use.
So if you want to keep your code clean, you can actually delete this from your code or to generated
boilerplate.
Now the next one tells you the viewport and it defines how the website should be displayed relative
to the screen that it's being rendered on.
And this line of code just tells the browser how to display your website when it first opens.
So now that we've learned all about HTML boilerplates, it's time to build your own boilerplate, or
in this case, build your own burger.
As you notice, there are endless numbers of HTML elements and we're going to be creating our own HTML
elements.
But the important thing here I want you to understand is how nesting works in HTML and how you can keep
your code tidy by using good indentation and keeping good programming practices.
If we're building our own imaginary burger, let's imagine the world's best burger.
You can have it vegan, you can have it vegetarian, you can have bacon, you can have whatever it is
your heart desires, but you have to write it in code.
Let's begin by creating a bun.
So I've got a bun element that I've created which has an opening and a closing tag, and I've added
an attribute.
You can add as many of these attributes as you like.
And remember, we add attributes by giving it a name, and then after an equal sign, we give it a value.
Now the next part is for you to invent.
So head over to VS code and build your own burger, adding in whatever elements you want.
Add tomatoes, add ham, but make sure that you're keeping the indentation correct and that you're working
with this idea of opening and closing tags.
But you can be as creative as you like, and be sure to share your code for your burger in the Q&A section.
And if you want some inspiration.
This is one that I made earlier, but I want you to practice making your own and doing it your way.
Have a go at that and once you're done, head over to the next lesson.
Hey guys.
In the previous lesson, you've learned a lot about different types of HTML elements and you already
got started using them to create websites.
Now in this section we're going to take it a little bit further and explore some more intermediate and
advanced concepts in HTML.
We're going to get started in this lesson by learning about list elements, the ordered and unordered
lists.
Now, if you've spent any time around on the Internet recently, you'll notice that it's completely
full of lists.
If you go on to BuzzFeed or any of these sort of clickbaity articles, usually they'll create a list
of something such as great items that must have been invented by geniuses.
But also if you look at something like the FBI's ten Most Wanted Fugitives, this is also created in
this website using a list.
So how do we create these lists ourselves?
Well, let's start off with one of the most common types, the unordered list.
And it's super simple to create simply, you have a starting tag with UL and then have a closing tag.
Now, normally we've had one line elements such as this where we get to add some content in between
the open and closing tags.
Now in this case, however, it's a little bit different.
They actually go on separate lines because in between these two open and closing tags, we need an extra
type of tag in order to complete this unordered list.
And these are called list items.
So here you can see we've got three list items and each of them contain some piece of content.
But all three items are enclosed inside this unordered list.
So for any list to work and display content, then you're going to have to add list items into it.
So what does this look like if we actually run the code?
Well, this is what you would see.
Essentially unordered list items will create these bullet points because such as in the case of a shopping
list here, the order of the items doesn't matter.
So that's why an unordered list would be perfect for this situation.
However, on the other hand, if you needed your list items to be arranged in a particular order, then
you would create an ordered list.
And once you've added the list items inside there, what this will do is it will give you numbers.
So it would start from one and the number next to each list item will depend on the order that you put
into this ordered list element.
If this milk was down here, then it would get the number three and so on and so forth.
That's all pretty simple.
So if we compare the ordered list, the ol element that gives us numbers and versus the UL, the unordered
list item, which just gives us bullet points, simple as that.
And coming back to our FBI ten Most Wanted Fugitives website, you can see they actually created this
website using lists.
So when you right click on any of these images and select inspect, you can see that each of these photos
are actually a list item placed inside an unordered list.
Now there's a whole bunch more to this website which we're going to learn in future lessons.
But the really important thing is for you to see that this is a really important part that you see in
websites all over on the Internet.
So it's really important that we understand how to use them.
So now that we've learned a little bit about ordered and unordered lists, let's try an exercise to
make sure that you've understood everything.
Go ahead and download the list element zip file from this current lesson.
And as always, if you forget how to do that, or if you just started on this lesson, then I recommend
going to one of the earlier lessons where I show you how to download course resources.
Now, once you've downloaded and extracted the folder 3.0 list elements and dragged it into VS code
or your web development projects folder, then you should be able to see it here on the file Explorer
on the left.
If we explore some of the files for this current coding exercise, you can see we've got an index.html
that contains some plain text which you're going to be formatting into lists.
And if we take a look at the goal, feel free to choose whichever heading sizes you want.
But for me, I think it made the most sense to have one H1 and then the ingredients and the instructions
as h2's and then any other headings like this part and this part as h3's.
But the most important thing I care about in this exercise is you manage to create these lists.
So we've got an unordered list for.
Section one of the ingredients to create the dough.
And then we've got another unordered list for the filling ingredients.
And finally, we've got all the rest of the instructions as a ordered list.
Think about how you're going to create this and don't worry about typing all the text out because if
you look inside the index.html, you'll see all the text typed out for you already.
All you need to do is to add the HTML tags and to format the document into an HTML website.
And in the end we should end up with this recipe website for creating delicious cinnamon rolls.
Now, if you watched my recent Instagram takeover of the Udemy account, you'll see me making the same
cinnamon rolls.
And if you want to do the same, then this is the recipe for you.
This is what you're aiming for and using what you've learnt about list elements.
I want you to go ahead and pause the video and complete this challenge.
All right.
So did you manage to do that?
Let's go ahead and walk through the solution together.
So I'm going to show you the preview on the right side so you can see the website update as I type.
First, we're going to start off with our heading tags.
So I'm just going to add a bunch of headings in quite quickly.
All right, so that's all the headings out of the way.
So now we're on to the proper work, which is creating our lists.
As I said, the ingredients don't really need an order, so we're going to create an unordered list.
So in between our start and end UL tags, we're going to have each of these as a list item.
So I'm going to create the list item tag.
And once I've created that, then all I need to do is to drag my first list item in between the list
item.
Now, if clicking and dragging doesn't work for you, if this doesn't show up, then you can also just
right click, copy and paste that also works.
Now I need to do this many times, so for efficiency's sake, I'm just going to paste in another 4 or
5 of these and drag in all of the other ingredients into each of these list items.
Now, when you're actually coding this from scratch, you won't need to do all of this dragging because
you'll be typing your list item and then you'll be writing your item name in here like so.
But because we've written all the text for you, hopefully to save you some time so that you're actually
doing more coding and less sort of busy work, then this is how we do it.
Again for the filling.
We've got another unordered list and then inside there are three list items.
So let me go ahead and paste those three list items in and drag each of them in between the tags like
so.
So now we've got our ingredients and we've got our two unordered lists showing up perfectly.
Now all we have to do is to create the final list, which is going to be an ordered list, because if
you think about it, instructions have an order, right?
You can't first bake the thing if you haven't created it yet.
Inside this order list, we again need these list item elements and we need to create as many of them
as we have steps.
So I'm going to drag each of the lines into the list elements.
And there we have it.
We've got all of our list items and all of our instructions showing up perfectly inside an ordered list.
And if we check against the goal, then you can see we've pretty much completed everything perfectly.
Now, one thing to talk about at this point is notice how some HTML elements are one line and other
HTML elements are on multiple lines.
When you paste long lines of text in between the start and end tags of an element, sometimes vs code
will automatically put the closing tag onto the next line.
Now you can edit this so that it all goes onto the same line, or you can purposely make sure they're
on different lines and you see it being sandwiched between the open and closing tags.
Now this is a personal preference, so it really doesn't matter how you want to do this so you can do
this however you like.
But for me, I like to have list items all on the same line.
This just kind of helps me see visually how many list items I have, and it doesn't clutter up the list
with all of these list items.
So have a think about whether, if you like to see your elements like this all on one line with the
content enclosed or if you prefer to have it like this where things are more indented and you have the
content in between two lines of your list item.
In the next lesson, we're going to talk a little bit more about this type of indentation.
So don't worry if that doesn't make sense just yet.
We're going to talk about nesting and we're going to talk about indentation of HTML elements.
So once you're ready, head over to the next lesson and we'll continue from there.
Now, in the previous lesson, we learned a little bit about ordered and unordered lists.
Now in this lesson, we're going to take that concept a little bit further.
I want to show you how you can nest things inside others.
For example, we saw that we could already nest the list elements inside an unordered list and you would
see it indented like this.
But we can actually go a step further and we can actually nest a list inside another list.
So in this case, what you see is we've got the first unordered list that starts here, and this is
where it ends.
But we've also got another unordered list here.
And this is where the second one begins and where it ends.
When this is rendered in a website, this is what you'll see.
You'll see it's looking like this.
So you've got the first list that is this entire part.
And then inside the first list, we've got a separate list.
Under this particular bullet point.
Now, how does the code look?
Well, it looks quite simple.
All you have to do is inside a list item.
You see how the starting list item is right here.
And the end list item is down here inside this list item.
Instead of simply just having a single line of text such as what we've got up here, instead, we've
actually embedded an entire unordered list.
So first we'll write the text for the list item, and then after the text we embed our unordered list,
just as you would see in any other normal list.
And then we end up with what's called a nested list.
This is the part where indentation your code becomes super important because imagine the code looked
like this and not like this.
When you look at this code at a glance, it's a lot harder to see that you've got a list embedded inside.
Another list.
Right.
Because you have to actually read what each of these tags are instead of using the clues that's offered
by that indentation.
And as you can imagine, we can have even crazier nested lists like what I've got right here.
So there's actually three lists here.
One is up here.
This is the first list.
This is a unordered list.
And then we've got a second list right here, which is again, an unordered list.
And that's embedded under the list item for be.
And then to complicate things, I've added a third ordered list that's listed under this second item
right here.
This amount of craziness starts to really highlight the issues that you're going to have reading this
code.
Imagine somebody else gave you this code and you had to figure out without looking at the right hand
side, what is going on right here.
It's a lot easier if we have it indented, right, Because we can clearly see one unordered list, the
second unordered list and the third ordered list because they're all nicely indented and is a lot easier
visually for when we're reading code.
So when you're writing code, you also are thinking about how other people are going to find reading
your code.
Now let's try an exercise to really drill this home.
I want you to download the nesting and indentation zip file from this current lesson, and I want you
to open up inside vs code as you have done previously.
Now, in this case, if we take a look at our goal is to create a super complex nested list.
In the last lesson you already saw how you can create simple list elements, whether it's unordered
lists or it's ordered lists.
It's pretty simple to create just a list with some list items.
But in this challenge, I want you to create something a lot more complicated.
Let me walk you through it.
So firstly, we've got a unordered list that has just three list items A, B and C, but under item
B, notice here we've got a ordered list.
This ordered list also has three items and under item B to the second item, we've got yet another unordered
list.
And inside the first item we've nested another unordered list.
And inside the third item we've embedded another ordered list.
This is a little bit complicated and in order to really understand it, you need to take a look at this
part of the video because here I've got the code that will create this simpler structure.
And the important thing to notice is that whereas normally you would probably have a list item that
starts like this and then you would have it closed like this.
In the case when we're embedding a list, that closing tag does not go here, but instead it goes all
the way at the end of the nested list.
Once we're done nesting, this unordered list right here, then do we close that list item?
So this is a really important thing to take notice of.
And then I want you to just study this page a little bit to see how I created this list using this code
and then take this and apply it to the challenge in the coding exercise.
Have a good think about it.
Take some time to try and complete this challenge.
I for one, believe that you can do this if you just spend some time thinking and trying it.
And as always, remember you can use the preview feature to see how your code is turning out and shaping
up while you're writing it.
And I think that will help you quite a lot.
Pause the video now and give that coding exercise a go.
All right.
So how did that go?
Now, if you didn't give that a go, I want you to stop the video now.
Make sure that you've tried it.
You're not going to learn coding through just watching me code.
You're only going to learn programming by actually doing it.
Solving challenges, feeling stupid, sometimes feeling like you're not good enough.
But at the end, when you do get it, when you do succeed, it's going to feel amazing.
And I promise you it was the same for everybody who's gone through this journey.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to run through the solution and I'm going to drag my goal up over
here so I can compare it to the preview as I go along.
So the first step is creating the first unordered list with three items A, B and C That should be pretty
easy to do.
And let's go ahead and create that.
All right, so now we've got the top of our nest, which is our A, B and C.
If we take a look at our goal, compare it.
We've got A, B, C inside the bullet.
B, we're going to embed right here, a ordered list.
So it's again going to have three items B1, B2 and B3.
And we know it's an ordered list because it starts off with the numbers one, two and three.
Let's go ahead and embed that inside this second B list item.
Remember what I said when you embed a list in another one, you find the list item you want to embed
it in.
And after the content of the list item, which is of course, this B right here, then we go ahead and
hit enter and that is where we create our list.
We're going to create an ordered list in this case and it's going to have three items.
The first one is going to be B1 and then B2 and B3.
Now let's again compare and contrast.
We've got our B1, B2, B3, but take a look inside this B2 item.
Again, we're going to nest another list and here we've got a unordered list B2, a B2B and B2C.
Let's go ahead and do that.
Right here inside the B2 list item, we're going to create our unordered list, our UL, and we're going
to have B2, a B2B and B2C.
Let's compare.
We've got B2B, B2B, B2C, so we've already got most of the parts done.
The final nest in this big long chain is under B to A, we need to add a unordered list, B to A and
B to a B.
Now, the way that I've named each of these hopefully should help you with the nesting.
If it doesn't, then you just have to compare against the goal and try matching it visually.
In this case instead of under the second item, it's actually nested under the first item.
And again, it's an unordered list with just two list items B to A and B to a B.
Now we've got pretty much all of this part sorted.
All we need to do now is just to add the final ordered list in bed under the B three list item.
Let's find our B three list item.
After the text, let's hit enter to create a new line and then we're going to create an ordered list
like this and we're going to add our two list items B31 and B32.
So now if we compare our goal and what we've got in the preview, you should see it's completely identical.
And through this process, hopefully you've learned a little bit more about nesting.
And one of the nice things about Visual Studio Code is that it will automatically indent things as you
write your code.
It knows, for example, list items, go inside a list.
So whether if it's a UL or an O, L, when you go to file and save or use the shortcut command here,
in my case on a mac, it's command s.
If you're on a windows, it's probably Ctrl s.
When you do that, it automatically re indents everything.
So even if you kind of mess things up in a big way as you type like I've got here and you've made all
of the structure look very weird.
If you save Visual Studio code will re indent everything for you so you don't have to necessarily indent
things, but it's important you understand what the indentation means.
So here you see a line right here and it links the opening UL to the matching closing tag, and then
it has indented these two list items over so that you can see these two items probably belong to this
unordered list.
And very often in HTML you will have matching tags.
If there's an open tag, there's probably a closing tag.
And all of these things on screen such as these lines.
And the indentation is here to help you to understand how your code looks so that if you actually have
an error, such as, for example, if you had forgotten to close this UL and when you see your code
doing weird things like for example, in this case, why is my C in an ordered list when it should be
at the top level with the other unordered list?
What is going on here?
Well, I can then follow these indentations.
I can see that this UL obviously matches along this line down to this closing one.
And then this next one is a list item.
So these two are on one line, they're matched and then this next list item is matched up with this
one.
But then wait a minute, what's going on here?
Why is this ol matched to a list item?
Or maybe there's something missing right here?
Well, it is, of course, the missing closing tag.
So this way I can start to figure out where my errors come from.
So we're going to do a lot more of this kind of error checking and mistake correction, which we call
debugging in future lessons.
But this is just a taster in this lesson for how you can use some of the tools to help you make sure
that your code is working and that you're writing the correct things.
And when you do make a mistake, as we all do, you can use the nesting in indentation in order to diagnose
what's wrong with your code and help you fix it.
So that's all for nesting and indentation.
In the next lesson, we're going to learn about anchor elements and we're going to start creating hyperlinks
in our web pages.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Hey, guys.
In this lesson, we're going to understand a bit more about another aspect of HTML, which is their
attributes and understand that we're going to learn all about the anchor element, which allows us to
create hyperlinks.
This is what an anchor element looks like and similar to previous elements, we've got the opening tag
and the closing tag, but there's something a little bit special about this one because right now if
you wrote the code as it is here, this is not an active hyperlink.
What you need is to add an additional attribute, and the attribute for an HTML element goes in the
opening tag.
It goes into the part just after the name of the tag and just before the end of the opening tag where
we have the closing angle bracket.
And what an attribute does is it adds additional information to this HTML element, such as in this
case where this link should link to.
Now, the way that we structure an attribute looks something like this.
So we have the name of the element and then we have a space and then we have the name of the attribute.
And afterwards we have a equal sign.
And after the equal sign, we have the value of the attribute.
Now you can have as many attributes as you want and all you have to do is simply separate each one of
them with a space and make sure that they all go into the opening tag.
Now, in the case of our image element, if you take a look on the Mozilla developer network documentation
for the anchor element, then you can see it has the special attribute of href and href is the part
where we add the URL that the hyperlink should go to without the attribute.
This is what you would see.
It is an anchor element and you do see the content in between the tags, but you do not see an active
link when you click on it.
Nothing happens.
Now.
As soon as you add that href attribute and you provide it with in this case a target.
So where should this hyperlink go to then?
This link actually gets styled to show you that this is now an active link in the familiar blue with
the underline.
And at this point, if you click on it, it is going to go straight to this URL that we've specified
in addition to the specific attributes.
So for example, in the anchor element documentation, we saw that it has all of these specific attributes
which are relevant to this particular element.
Now we're not going to be using all of them and some of them are also deprecated and no longer in use
in HTML5.
But in addition to these specific attributes, there are also global attributes that every single HTML
element has access to.
And if you look through some of these, an example is something like draggable, right?
And it basically allows us to set true or false to say whether if the element may or may not be dragged,
you can apply a global attribute to any given element.
So in this case, we can apply it even to our anchor element.
Again, we have the name of the attribute, we have the equal sign and we have the value of the attribute.
So in this case, the name of the attribute is Draggable, and we've set it equal to true.
So once this attribute is set, what happens is you can click and drag that anchor tag around.
Now, if that attribute wasn't set, then when you try to drag it, it's just going to highlight the
line and it's not going to allow that behavior.
So we've learned that there are specific attributes which are reserved for only certain elements, such
as the href for the anchor tag, and there are global attributes which can be used on any HTML element.
So now let's try an exercise and see if you've understood how to use anchor elements and more specifically,
see if you've understood how the HTML attribute is written in HTML code.
In this exercise, we're going to create a website that shows our top five favorite websites.
I've got the H1 already written for you, but what we're aiming for is something like this.
So you have a list here and notice that this is actually an ordered list because it goes from one all
the way to five and the fact that the list is not highlighted.
Is in blue should show you that this is actually created using a list element and not a part of the
anchor tag.
It's not a part of the content.
And the anchor tag only starts here.
I want you to document your top five all time favorite websites and feel free to Google or check mine
if you want to see what they do.
These are some of the websites that I go to when I'm bored or when I'm trying to look for some new ideas
and new inspiration.
So I want you to use what you've learned previously about creating lists.
And within those lists, I want you to create five anchor tags, each of them pointing to a different
website that you like.
And if you've got everything working, then you would end up with a website that looks like the goal.
And when you click on any of these links, then they should take you to the correct website.
Pause the video.
Now, give this challenge a go, and once you're done, come back here and I'll go through the solution
with you.
All right.
So how did that go?
The first thing we wanted to do was to create a ordered list.
We already saw how to do this in a previous lesson.
We create our tags and inside we add our list elements.
Inside the list element is where our anchor tag is going to go.
It's an anchor tag, which is inside a list element, which is then inside a ordered list.
So several layers of nesting that's going on here.
Now, once you've created your anchor tag, then in between the open and closing tags, we add the text
for our link.
So in my case, it will be the name of my website that I'm linking to, which is called Product Hunt.
And this is a place where you can see all the latest product launches and great websites and start ups
that people are building every day.
The important part comes here when we create the attribute for that anchor tag.
So remember that the attribute for linking a anchor tag is called the href, and we're going to add
it after the equal sign.
As you start typing, you might see code, start suggesting what you're looking for.
So if you pick the ref and hit enter, then it will format everything for you ready for you to enter
the URL.
If you're wondering why there are these quotation marks here, well, that's because it's actually a
piece of text that we're going to add in here.
So this is treated slightly differently in code.
So whenever you have text, normally you will see them enclosed inside a set of double quotes.
This is to differentiate from the reserved words like, you know, I or a or h ref.
These are all special words.
And in order to show that you're not creating anything special, you're just pointing to our URL, which
is just a piece of text.
We have our double quotes around it.
Inside here, I'm going to paste in the URL of product hunt, and now I have myself a link and if I
go ahead and show preview, then you should see that we've got our list item one.
And when I click on it, it goes to the website that I have linked to.
You can repeat this process and link to all of your five favorite websites and you should end up with
something that looks like this.
And as an extra challenge, I want you to head over to the developer documentation for the ordered list,
which you're using in this current code exercise.
And look at the attributes.
I want you to see whether if you can change one of the attributes, the start attribute, so that your
list, instead of starting from one starts from five.
This is what you're aiming for.
Pause the video, give that a go, and then afterwards we'll go through the solution together.
Let's take a look at the documentation.
We can see that for the ordered list.
One of the attributes is called START.
And in the explanation, it says, All we have to do is to set this attribute to a number for it to
start from.
So that's pretty simple.
But we need to remember where our attributes go.
So they go in the starting tag, which is here, and the name of the attribute is Start, and we can
set it equal to five.
Now once we've done that, if we take a look at our website, you can see the order list now starts
from five and ends at nine because we've changed that attribute.
Hopefully that wasn't too difficult and you managed to get it to work.
Have a quick review of the concepts that are covered in this lesson.
And remember, we're always trying to repeat things that we've learnt before just to make sure that
we reinforce those pieces of knowledge from earlier on.
And one thing I like to do as I learn is to make some notes on the things that are new to me that I
didn't realize before.
So if there's something new in this lesson that you want to write down, take a quick note of it and
then head over to the next lesson where we talk about image elements.
For all of that and more.
I'll see you there.
Now, a website would be pretty boring if it had no images on it, right?
So in this lesson we're going to learn how we can add images to our website using the image element.
Now this is what it looks like.
It's pretty simple.
And you'll notice that similar to the anchor tag or the anchor element that we learned about in the
last lesson, the main component of an image tag that renders the image is this attribute, which is
called source or SRC.
And what this does is it tells the image element what is the source of the image.
And that's why after the equal sign, the value is going to be the location of the image.
One last thing to notice about the image tag is, unlike the anchor tag, it doesn't have a closing
tag.
Instead, it is a self closing tag, also known as a void element.
Remember, previously we learned about void elements where we learnt that you can have horizontal rule
elements, you can also have break elements.
And similarly the image element is also a void element that doesn't have a closing tag.
Because if you think about it, what is the text content of an image?
Doesn't really make sense, right?
The main content is actually the image that will be rendered from the source.
What does this look like?
Well, here's an example image element where we've set the source to a real life live photo on the Internet.
Now, when this code is rendered in a website, it will display a random image.
So in this case, the random image I got was a forest.
And the reason why it's random is because I'm getting these photos from a source called pixham.photos.
So if you type this into your browser, you should see a website and the idea is kind of like the Lorem
ipsum for placeholder photos.
So when you don't really care what the photo is, but you need a photo on your website as you're creating
it in order to see what it would look like, then you could use this website and you could put in the
URL, which is the standard one like here.
And then after a forward slash, you can add in the size of your image.
So in this case, I'm saying I want a square that is 200 pixels by 200 pixels.
It gives me a random image from its data bank, for example, in this case of a forest.
The other attribute for an image tag that's super important and one that you should always have is the
alt attribute.
And the alt attribute stands for Alternative Text Description.
This is really important because people who are blind or visually impaired, they don't look at the
Internet the same way we do.
They often use something called a screen reader.
And what the screen reader is going to do when it hits an image is it will look at the alternative text
provided.
So in this case, I've provided that this is a forest at sunset or sunrise.
I'm not quite sure, but that means that the person with visual impairment will get this read out to
them and it will help them understand what the website's all about.
So what is this process like?
As an example, I'm using the Silktide Toolbar, which is a Chrome browser extension, to simulate what
a person with visual impairment might hear as they're browsing.
In this case, the BBC website.
As I click through next, you can see it describes the different things that are on screen.
And if I go over to the image, it describes the image for me.
Item two Dolphin leaping from the sea image.
So where is it getting this description from?
Well, if we right click on the image and inspect it, and if we look for the image, which I think
should be down here, you can see as I highlight different parts, it shows me which part.
So in this element, I'm probably going to find an image at the end right here and you can see the alt
text saying dolphin leaping from the sea.
And that is what gets read out from the screen reader helping somebody with blindness.
Be able to understand what's on this website.
Now, if you want to check out this tool, it's a Chrome browser extension called Silktide and it should
be a free plugin, but it might only work on Mac or certain versions of Windows, but it's not so much
about the tool, but I wanted to show you how important it is the alt text that you provide for accessibility
and for disabled users browsing your website.
Now let's try.
An exercise and create some images of our own.
Download the zip file from this current lesson and go ahead and drag it into your web development project
folder and open it inside vs code.
If you take a look inside the index.html, you can see I've provided to you two image URL examples that
you can use.
And what we're aiming for is to find out if you're a cat person or if you're a dog person.
I want you to create a H1 that says I'm a cat person or I'm a dog person.
And also I want you to add a image element straight afterwards.
Now you can use the URL for the dog or for the cat.
It doesn't really matter at the end of the day, as long as you've understood how to create images.
That's the challenge.
Pause the video and give that a go.
All right.
So personally, I'm more of a dog kind of person.
And if you're also a dog person, then you might see my little Easter egg that I've buried in there.
So first, let's go ahead and create our H1, and then we're going to create our image.
Remember, we create a image tag and it's a self-closing tag.
Then we add in our source as the image source, and we're going to put our URL right inside there.
Now, already, if we go ahead and show preview, you can see our little dog digging in the sand.
Because if you've noticed, this is actually a gif image.
GIF images work exactly the same way as normal images, JPEGs or PNGs.
As long as you put it into the source, it will be rendered in a website and it will start animating
or by itself.
And you get a cute little dog digging through the sand.
Now if you're a cat person, then this is just a static jpeg because cats are more chill.
So I hope you manage to get that part right.
But we haven't finished creating our image element yet.
Remember what I said about the alt tag?
It's a good idea to always add an alt tag to describe our image when we can.
Now, there are some cases where you don't create an alt tag because it's not really relevant to somebody
reading through the content of a website and you can in fact leave it blank.
But in this case, it's very simple.
We've got a puppy who is digging through the sand.
And now when we take a look at our preview, then nothing visually for us changes.
But behind the scenes, we will help our visually impaired friends to be able to understand our website
just a little bit better.
So I hope you managed to achieve either of these goals.
And once you're ready, we can head over to the next lesson where we've got the final project to create
a birthday invite website using all the skills that we've learned so far.
So all of that and more.
I'll see you there.
All right.
It's time to put everything we've learned so far together and create a project.
In this project, we're going to create a website for your next party to help you invite all your guests.
Because paper invites and WhatsApp invites are only for people who can't create websites.
Am I right?
We can do it better.
This is what we're aiming for.
We're aiming for a retro 90s look website because we haven't learned about styling websites yet, which
is yet to come, but this is already pretty nice.
We're going to create a website to tell people that it's our birthday, which day it is, and we're
going to add some images.
We're going to tell people what to bring using lists.
And also we're going to add an anchor tag to show people where they need to go.
Hopefully, we're going to combine a lot of the things that you've learned in previous lessons.
And once you're ready, head over to the course resources for this lesson.
Download and extract the zip file in order to get started.
When you take a look at the index.html, you can see I've provided an example image URL and an example
Google Maps link.
So if you take a look inside the goal, you can see what the example image will take you to.
And if you're ready for an Easter egg slash mini surprise, you can head over to the Google map link
and see where it's located as well.
So this is a project and it's not a coding exercise.
It's not something that I'm testing you on.
Everything I'm saying.
It's just a guideline.
I want you to at minimum, have an image in there, have a list in there, and also have an anchor tag
in there.
Everything else is totally up to you.
You can mess around with it as much as you like or change as much as you like, or keep it as simple
as you like.
It doesn't really matter.
Pause the video and give this project a go and happy birthday if it is your birthday today.
All right.
So want to walk through one possible solution?
I just want to say this is just one possibility.
You can change it as much as you like.
There is no right or wrong in the project.
It's all about practice and also your own personal style.
So in my case, I created an H1 for the top level heading, which is the most important thing.
It's my birthday and then I've got some h2's and some H3.
So for what to bring and where you need to go in the image tag.
I've added a source to that image I provided in the starting code, and also I provided an alternative
text to show people what this image is all about.
If you manage to get the image source and the alternative text and your image shows up, then congratulations.
You did a great job.
Now the next part I've got is a unordered list to tell people what they should bring with each item
in its own list item element.
And finally, I created an anchor tag to tell people where they need to go.
So I've added an href attribute and I used the link that I supplied in the starting code and I told
people that the link text is a Google map link, which hopefully will take them to where they need to
go, which is somewhere in Tokyo where all the pigeon people meet, apparently.
So if you found that Easter egg, then congratulations.
But if you're really proud of what you managed to do for your project, then be sure to take a screenshot
of it and post it in the Q&A to share it with the rest of us.
I would love to see what you came up with, but that's all from me for this section.
I hope you enjoyed learning more about HTML elements and I'll see you soon.