Hey guys, welcome to the introduction to CSS section.
And in this very first lesson, we're going to be introducing you to CSS.
You'll be learning what it is, how it works and why we need it to be able to style our websites and
make them look beautiful.
What exactly is CSS?
Well, it stands for cascading style sheets.
It kind of conjures up the image of a cascade.
Right.
And a cascade is simply like a waterfall.
You have water at one level that then drops down through a waterfall into another level.
And we're going to see as we start to use these cascading style sheets, why that analogy is so apt.
Because the way that the style is applied cascades like a waterfall.
We start from the most general all the way down to the most specific styling requirements, and we're
going to see that in use as we use these cascading style sheets.
The other part of this name is the style sheet.
A style sheet is a type of language similar to how we had the HTML, which is a markup language.
That's what the part of stands for.
We have the style sheet, which is what the SS part stands for, and this is a language that allows
us to specify how things should look in our website.
And there are many different types of stylesheet languages.
The one that's most important and what we're going to be learning all about in this section is the cascading
style sheet.
But there's also others like Sass, which stands for syntactically awesome style sheet and Less, which
stands for Leaner CSS and many, many others.
But the most important one that every web developer needs to know is CSS.
And that's what we're going to be focusing on today.
So why did we need CSS?
Where did it come from and what exactly is the history of this whole thing?
Well, in the very beginning when the Internet was very, very new, there was no CSS, there was only
HTML.
And one of the things that developers started wanting to do is they wanted to style their website and
make it look the way they want it to, but they were really, really limited by HTML.
And this is a now famous email sent by Marc Andreessen, who is the founder of Mosaic, which is one
of the earliest Internet browsers who later founded Netscape and now the very famous Andreessen Horowitz
VC Fund.
And in this email he famously said that the answer he has for so many developers who want to simply
control what their documents look like, meaning what their websites look like in a way that would be
trivial, say in Microsoft Word.
His answer to these developers is just sorry, you're screwed.
There is no way to do it very easily at that point in HTML.
That's why all the website looks pretty much the same.
Pretty boring.
And there was no variation.
So what happened next?
Well, the W3C consortium responded by releasing a new version of HTML, HTML 3.2, and this came out
in 1997, so it was still in the very early days of the Internet.
And what this 3.2 HTML allowed was it introduced new HTML tags such as the font tag, which allows you
to define the font size, the color and the font face.
So the type of font you would want to use for your document.
Similarly, there was also the color attribute for font.
There was the face attribute, the size attribute, and these attributes allow you to change all sorts
of things about the way the text looks on your website.
And then there was also the center element which allows you to format your document and define how it
would be laid out on the screen.
Now, what you'll notice in all three of these Web pages is the deprecated symbol next to it.
All of these are deprecated, which in programming lingo, simply means you should no longer be using
these attributes and elements.
And the reason for this is because, as you can imagine, our HTML is supposed to be for content.
Now, if you add in a ton of styling into all of that content, you tell the website how it should be
centered, how it should be laid out, how the font should look, what color it should be, what kind
of border your tables should have, and a whole bunch of other styling effectively.
Then this is going to massively clutter up all of your HTML.
And you can imagine this is a really, really short website and it's already got so much junk in it
that we can't really tell what exactly is the structure and the content of the website and.
If you extend this to a larger website and you just want to do some simple things like give it some
colors or put things into the center, then your whole HTML file is going to be many, many, many thousands
of lines long and it's impossible to differentiate the content from the styling.
So what happened next?
Well, in 1996, a new recommendation was proposed by the W3 consortium, and this was led by Hakon
Wium.
How come?
How come by how come?
And he's basically the father of the cascading style sheet.
And what this recommendation allows us to do is to allow us to attach styles such as font colors and
spacing to our HTML documents.
And this is the breakthrough that allowed us to separate our styling from our content.
And as in many different situations, a separation of concerns so that somebody is responsible for putting
together the car headlights and somebody else is responsible for dealing with the wheels rather than
one person making an entire car.
This kind of modularity, as you'll see in coming lessons, is super important, not just in manufacturing
and in real life, but also in programming.
If you want to see what CSS is able to achieve.
I've built this website for you to be able to do that.
If you go over to App Brewery, Github.io and then forward Slash, just add CSS, you should be able
to see this website.
And when you first go over there, you'll see that it's just a very, very simple website, pretty bland.
All it's got is HTML.
And now if we go ahead and press this button to toggle and turn on CSS, then you'll see the entire
website transform and look way more beautiful.
It's now got different fonts, different colors and different layouts.
But you'll notice that if you go ahead and right click and view the page source in these two versions,
the HTML does not change at all.
So let's toggle our back and then let's go ahead and view page source again.
You'll see that in these two versions.
As you see me switch it on screen, nothing changes in our index.html.
The only thing that is different is the CSS that gets added.
Now don't worry too much about the script tags down here or how we've created our buttons.
We're going to learn all of that later on when we learn JavaScript.
But I created this website so that you can play around with toggling the CSS on and off to see how it
can transform a simple HTML website without touching any of the code inside the HTML.
And all that we're doing is adding style to our website in a completely separate language.
The cascading style sheet.
To learn more about how CSS works, head over to the next lesson where we're going to get started styling
up a website.
Now, I hope you had to play around with this example website where you could toggle the CSS on and
off.
How exactly did I add CSS to this plain HTML website?
Well, that is what we're going to be learning about in this lesson.
There's three ways of adding CSS into an HTML website.
Inline, internal and external.
We're going to be exploring all three of these different styles of adding CSS, and I'm going to show
you why they're important and in which situations you would use which one.
Now, the first one is the inline style of adding CSS.
As the name suggests, it goes into the same line as a particular HTML element.
So in this case, you can see we've got an HTML open tag and an HTML closing tag.
Now, we know from learning about HTML boilerplate, this is an element that goes into all of our HTML
documents.
There's nothing special about this particular element.
It just tells the browser that this file is made up of HTML.
Now, in this case, the inline CSS goes into the opening tag of the HTML.
This is where the CSS exists.
It's in the same line as the HTML tag.
What the inline CSS looks like is something like this.
You've got a style attribute, which is an attribute that is globally available to all tags, not just
HTML, but anything else.
Image or break or anything you can think of.
You can add the style attribute to it.
As we know, normally attributes look like this.
They have a name of the attribute.
Then we add the equal sign.
And then finally we add a value for the attribute.
In this value section is where we add our CSS code.
Our CSS code is broken down like this.
The first part of it is the property that you want to change.
And the second part is the value of that property that you want to set it to.
So in this case, what we're trying to do is to set our website's background to blue.
And if I go ahead and run this code and load it up in a browser, you would simply see a website that
has a blue background.
And this is achieved using our inline CSS.
Inline elements are really useful for adding CSS style to just a single element on your HTML page.
But normally that's quite cumbersome because as you can imagine, there's tons of different HTML elements.
If you have more and more of them and you wanted them to share similar styles, then you would have
to add these inline styles to each and every single one of them, which is pretty tedious.
It's not normally recommended to use inline styles in your entire document.
It's only for specific sections or when you're testing or when you only want it in one single element
or one line in your HTML document.
Now, the second way you can add CSS is through what's called internal CSS.
Now this is done through a special HTML tag called the Style Element.
We've got an open style tag and a closing style tag.
And in between those two lines is where we add all of our CSS.
All of this is our CSS.
The CSS looks a little bit different from what you saw previously, right?
Because previously all we had was this line.
Now, in this case, we've got something a little bit extra here.
Why is that?
Well, this is because last time when we had the CSS rule, we had it inline inside a particular element.
So we said for this HTML element, we want to apply a background color.
Now, in this case, it's a little bit different because our internal style can apply to anywhere within
the same HTML document.
So it could go into any of these elements, the HTML or the head or anything that you've got coming
up later on as well.
What we have to add in addition often is what we call a selector, and this selector comes before a
set of curly braces and then the CSS goes in between these two sets of curly braces.
Now, when I say in between a set of curly braces, you have to imagine it a little bit like this.
This is the opening curly brace and this is the closing curly brace.
And if you had it all on one line, then it would look something like this with your CSS going in between
on multiple lines.
That's why we open and close them on separate lines.
But if you imagine it as one line, then it would look something like this.
Our internal styling can apply to anywhere in our HTML document, and inside we can target or select
as many elements as we want.
We could say let's apply the background red to the HTML, and when this code is rendered in the browser,
you will see the background of the entire HTML turn red.
Internal styles are really useful for applying it only to one HTML document.
As you can see, this style and any code that goes in there is limited to the HTML that it sits in.
So it means if you have a multi-page website, then you probably shouldn't be using the internal style.
Instead you should be using something called an external CSS styling.
Now the biggest difference between the external and the internal and inline styles is that this actually
lives in a completely separate file, which you'll normally see as Styles.css or Main.css or anything
that has a dot CSS extension inside this CSS file is where we write our CSS rules.
So we've got our selector, we've got our property and we've got values and we can make many, many
of these inside this file.
Now how do we link up the style sheet file with our index.html?
Well, inside the head section of our HTML, we would add a link element which you'll notice is a self-closing
tag.
So it doesn't need a closing tag.
And we have two things that we normally write.
One which is a relationship which refers to what is the role of this thing that we're linking to?
And the second thing is the href, which is where is it located?
In this case, we're saying it's in the same directory and it's inside a file called Styles.
CSS, which points to this file right here.
And when we go ahead and run this and show it in the browser, you'll see it turns our HTML background
to a green color.
And this style of external CSS is what's used most commonly in web development.
And this is what we're going to be focusing on most of the time.
But it's important to be aware of the other two styles the inline, the internal, because you'll see
it out there in the wild in other people's CSS code.
So remember, inline is really useful when you only want to target a single element.
And internal is really useful when you only want to target a single web page.
But for most cases and when you have a multi-page website, then what you're going to need is the external
way of adding CSS through the use of a separate file, which will be called something, something dot
CSS, and it's inside this file where you're going to be writing the CSS code that can target an entire
website with all of its multiple web pages.
So these are the three ways that you can add CSS to your HTML documents.
And don't worry, we're going to be practicing this and all of its forms many, many times so that you
understand how it works.
Let's try an exercise and see how to add CSS in various different ways to our HTML file.
All right.
So once you've downloaded and extracted the project file and open it inside vs code, you should see
this folder.
And here notice that our five files that have already been created for you.
And in this exercise there is a little bit of revision about creating multiple web pages about file
paths.
But more importantly, we want you to practice using the three different ways of adding CSS inline,
internal and external.
So starting inside index.html, the first thing I want you to do is to create three links to the three
different web pages.
This one, this one and this one.
And once you've done that, then you can go inside each of those web pages.
So starting with the inline and then internal external, and you're going to follow the instruction
that the H one tells you to.
So in this case, we want to use inline styling in order to style this h one in blue and then you get
to go to the internal and do the same thing, but this time using internal styling and styling the H
one in red and then finally using external styling using this style.css file and styling the h one in
green.
If you want to take a look at what the final outcome will look like, you can go into the solution folder,
right click on the solution, dot HTML and show preview and then make sure that you collapse this solution
folder.
Because having all of it out, two versions of each file is very confusing.
So I recommend just collapsing that folder so you don't get confused and this is what you're aiming
for on the index.html, which is the home page.
We've got an H one and then we've got three links.
And if we click on each of these, you can see they've got an H1 that says style me in blue style,
me in red and green and we're going to achieve that using the three different ways of adding CSS.
Once you're ready, go ahead and download the starting files and give this challenge a go.
Pause the video now.
All right.
So how did that go?
I'm going to run through the solution code with you to explain some of the things that you would need
to do to complete this challenge.
The first thing we said was to style the home page.
So we added in three anchor tags, which is how we create links.
And once we did that, we were able to use the href of each of the anchor tags in order to link to the
relevant web page.
The first one links to the inline web page, inline HTML, internal external, and we use the dot slash
notation in order to reach within the current folder.
So solution dot html lives inside solution.
And in this case, in order to get to inline dot html, we use the dot slash to get to this folder and
then we forward slash to go to inline dot html right here.
Now once you've created your three links, the next stage is to go into the first web page inline and
here we want to style the H1 using CSS, but adding it inline.
As I said, it's in the literal line of the H1 element, so it only applies to this H1 element and we've
added it in right here saying that the style should be set so that the color of this text is blue.
And remember that the inline style goes in the opening tag of the element that you want to target.
The next one is internal, so we add internal styling, usually by putting it inside the head section.
So between the open and closing tags of the head element, and this is a convention that most developers
will stick to, although this will work no matter where you put the style element.
So here we've got an open and closing style tag and in between we've added in our CSS.
So we're saying that our selector is going to select all the H1 on this page, of which there is only
one, and we're going to change its text color to red.
And finally we've got the final version, which is the external HTML.
And we do this by creating a link element right again, inside the head section of your website.
We establish the relationship is we're setting up a style sheet and then we provide a href to the location
where our stylesheet is located, which is in the current directory, and then it's in a file called
Style.css.
So we can see that right here.
And inside here we've again targeted the H1 and we've set the color to green and all of that together
creates these different web pages in our multi-page website with the code that sets the style in three
different ways.
So did you get that right?
If you had any issues at all, be sure to go back into your code and fix anything that was wrong and
make sure that you've understood the three different ways of adding CSS.
In the next lesson, we're going to learn more about the different selectors that we can use to select
different parts of our HTML file.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Hi guys.
Welcome to another lesson on CSS.
In this lesson, we're going to be talking about CSS selectors, and this is going to help us choose
where to apply our CSS.
We've seen previously that we can create CSS rules by simply specifying two things.
One is the property we want to change and after a colon we get to specify the value to change that property
to.
In this case, what we're saying is we want to change the text color into a blue color.
Now we've come across some of these rules already and I'll be showing you in a later lesson in the next
section how to find out more about these rules.
But more importantly, in this lesson, what I want to talk about is the part outside of these rules.
It's the part that comes right here.
And this is known as a CSS selector.
What is a CSS selector?
Well, it's the part that selects the HTML in order to apply whichever rules go in between these curly
braces.
How do we know which part of our HTML file to make the text color blue?
Well, we look at this part and we can see we're targeting the H1.
Now, this style of selector is one of the simplest CSS selectors.
It's called an element selector.
And all it does is it selects a particular HTML tag.
So in this case it's targeting all h ones.
If your HTML is any good, you should only have a single H1, but it will be different for other tags.
If you had anchor tags or if you had paragraph tags or h twos or any of the other HTML tags.
Then when you select each of these in your CSS, it means apply to all elements that have that particular
tag.
Let's see this in action here.
I've got two files.
One is the index.html and another is our stylesheet.
And inside our index.html we've just got three H twos, red, green and blue.
And when displayed or run they will look like this.
Three headings.
Now if we go ahead and add a little bit of CSS and target our H two element, in this case we're using
an element selector which is simply the name of the tag.
And then after the curly braces, we can define whichever CSS rules we want.
In this case, turning the color of the text red.
If we go ahead and run this code, I want you to imagine what you expect to happen.
Which of these texts will turn red?
So let's go and run the code.
And once this change is incorporated, this is what we see Red, green and blue all turn red because
they are all h twos.
And this element selector here selects all of the h twos turning them red.
So pretty simple so far.
Now let's look at another type of selector, a class selector.
This requires a special symbol, which is the dot.
And then after that dot immediately with no spaces right here, then you have the name of the class.
So this is the actual name of the class that we're selecting.
In this case, I've called it Red dash heading.
And then after the curly braces again, we have the same CSS rule to apply.
Change the text color to red.
Now, what is a class?
Well, a class is something that we can add as an attribute to any HTML element.
And this attribute is kind of like saying, well, let's group these particular elements into a class.
So it's used for grouping elements in your HTML file to apply the same CSS rule to all of them.
So in this case, we've only got one H2 that has a class and the class is set to red text.
Now when I go ahead and write some CSS and I target the class, which remember requires the DOT and
then the name of the class, which is this, and it has to be spelled exactly the same.
These two cannot have any differences.
So you can't have, for example, a capital R or a capital T, This will not work.
Instead, what we have is our class selector and our CSS rule.
What do you expect will happen when the code is run in the browser when this CSS gets applied?
Well, it'll look like this.
It selects the only element that has that class and turns the text color red.
Now what if we had multiple elements with the same class?
So here you can see we've actually got two different types of HTML elements.
One is an H2 and another is a paragraph element.
Even though these two are completely different elements, we can tag them using the same class.
We're saying the H2 should have the class of red text, as should the paragraph.
Now if we write our CSS and we select again all the classes that have red text, then what do you think
will happen?
Well, in this case it doesn't matter if it's an H2 or if it's a paragraph.
As long as they've got that class, they've been converted into red text and the style has been applied
to these two HTML elements.
As you can see, the class selector is really versatile.
It allows you to group different parts of your HTML file into having the same styling.
And this can be really, really useful on multi-page websites with lots of different elements.
And you don't just want to select a particular type of HTML element.
The next one I want to show you is called the ID Selector and the ID Selector.
It has its own special symbol, which is a pound sign or a hash tag, and you put that pound sign and
again, no spaces in between the pound sign and the actual name of the ID, and this selects all elements
with a particular ID attribute.
This is what an ID attribute looks like, it's simply the words ID, and then after the equal sign,
we can give it a particular ID and it works similarly to the class selector, because if I go ahead
and select this ID of Main and I apply these changes, then you can see it will add the styling and
apply it to the only element that has that ID.
So then what is the difference between the ID and the class selector?
Well, the class selector can be applied to many elements, whereas the ID should be only applied to
one element in a single HTML file in a single HTML file like our index.html.
There should only be one ID of this particular name main.
It should be completely unique and this is the difference.
If you had say three h2's you can't select all of them using the element selector like this because
that would select all of the h2's.
Instead you apply the ID to the unique element that you want to apply your style to and it selects it
in the HTML file.
Again, remember, IDs are unique only one element per file and classes you can put on as many elements
as you like to group them together.
Another way that you can select parts of your HTML is using the attribute selector so we know that we
can create a HTML tag and add as many attributes as we like.
So we had attributes such as ID or class or draggable or source for the images or RF for the anchor
tags or alt for the images and a whole bunch more that will get to see in the future as well.
Now we can select these elements that have particular attributes or particular attributes values by
using this notation.
Notice the first part here is the HTML element that you want to select, and then using a set of square
brackets, these ones right here.
Then inside we can include the attribute that you want to select.
What this entire selector says is select all paragraph elements with the attribute draggable and then
apply this CSS style.
To it.
What does this look like in HTML code?
Well, here we've got three paragraph tags, but only one of them has the attribute draggable set to
true.
If we go ahead and apply the CSS style where we select the paragraph element with the draggable attribute
and give it this CSS style, then when this CSS is applied to our HTML, this is what will happen.
It will find the unique paragraph tag with that particular attribute.
Now you can go one step further with attribute selectors.
You can actually select the value of the attribute that you want to apply your CSS to.
So in this case, you can see we've got all three paragraphs with the same attribute.
All the draggable attributes are set, but the set to different values.
So the first one is set to true and the other two are set to false.
So now we can actually write our CSS like this.
We can select all the paragraph elements which has an attribute of draggable set an equal to false.
And what this selector is going to do all of this is it's going to look inside our file and it's going
to find these two paragraph elements in order to select and apply the CSS when this CSS is applied instead
of the first one, which previously was selected, we actually have the other two selected and turned
red.
This is again a really versatile way of applying CSS, but as you can see, it selects on different
things than what we've seen before.
The element, the ID or the class selectors, the final selector.
I want to talk about is the universal selector.
And it's really simple.
It's just an asterix.
And after the Asterix you have your CSS rules.
But what this means is it means select all.
And when you apply this, it doesn't matter what class you've got, what ID, what attribute set, which
different elements.
If you select all, it's going to apply the style to everything where the stylesheet is active.
And this is probably one of the simplest selectors to understand.
So now that we've seen all the different ways that we can apply our CSS to different parts of the HTML
using selectors, let's try an exercise where we experiment hands on and see if you've understood all
the concepts in this lesson.
Now, once you've downloaded and extracted the starting files and have it open in vs code, then I want
you to go into the index.html file and here you'll notice a couple of things.
Firstly, we've already set up the stylesheet for you, so we've got an external stylesheet set up using
a link and it's pointing to this file right here, the Style.css.
The part that we want you to do is to revise what you've learned about CSS selectors.
And I've set up five to do's for you and I want you to do them in order.
So start from one and then go to two and continue downwards.
What this is going to involve is for you to write actual CSS code.
I don't want you to actually touch anything inside the index.html because I don't want you to change
any of the HTML with the classes or values or IDs.
I want you to leave it exactly as it is.
And instead your job is to write the selectors in the style dot CSS.
Notice when you open up the style.css there's a little bit of CSS already here for you and I want you
to leave this alone.
Don't touch it, don't change it.
It's important so that the final styling looks right when we haven't covered all of the different CSS
styling rules.
In the next section, we're going to be talking about all of this in a lot more detail.
Where to find out about different rules and how to use them.
But for now, I want you to ignore this part and write your CSS below.
Similarly, I'm not expecting you to know which CSS rules to use because I'll provide all the rules
for you in to do one.
I want you to change the text color to red and to do two, I want you to change the font size or change
the text align and this is all going to be provided for you completely formatted.
So it's got the property, the colon and the value I want you to set it to.
Now, the part that you need to think about and where your challenge comes in is how to select.
The correct paths.
So how to select all the paragraphs, for example, or how to select parts with a class of this or an
ID of this?
So that is the challenge.
And this is what you need to do in this exercise.
And if you take a look at the preview right now, it's very plain, all black, no styling at all.
But if you take a look at the goal PNG, you'll see this is what the final outcome will look like.
It's going to be centered, it's going to have different colors and you can almost even use this website
as a revision tool because each of the bullet points are linked to a particular style of CSS selection.
This hopefully will be quite a fun challenge for you and if you get stuck, be sure to rewind a little
bit in the video to see how to do the different things as seen in the previous examples.
And I want you to really give it a good go before you continue and watch the solution.
Pause the video now.
Give this a go.
All right.
So the first thing we're going to do is we're going to pull up our preview to make sure we are doing
the right things.
And to begin the first to do is to set the CSS for all paragraph tags to this color.
Now, remember, I said we're not writing any code or changing anything in the HTML side.
We're doing it all in our CSS, but it's still really important that we look at what's in our HTML code
in order to complete each of the steps of the challenge.
The first one's easy.
We're going to target all paragraph tags and we're going to apply this CSS style.
So let me copy the CSS style, paste it in, and now I've got an error because I haven't selected what
this style should be applied to.
In this case, we're applying it to all the paragraph elements, so we're using the element selector
and all we have to do there is simply add the name of the tag and then apply it and you can see the
first line of our bullet is now read.
That's to do number one.
Done.
Let's move on to the next to do so.
In this one, we want to set the CSS for all the elements with a class of this to this CSS rule.
So let me again copy the CSS rule and then paste it below.
And now we're going to use a class selector and select all the elements.
So notice how we've got many elements with the same class, even though they're applied to different
elements, but we can select across them using the class selector.
The class selector, if you remember, requires the dot, and then immediately afterwards we add in
the name of the class, and then we enclose our CSS rule in between the curly braces again.
And what this has done is it's applied a larger font size to all of the HTML elements that have that
class applied to them, which is all the bullets here, but not the H one or H twos.
So that's to do number two done.
Next one is to set the CSS for the element with a particular unique ID and the ID is this one.
So which one has that ID?
It's this particular list element and we're going to set it to have access rule to turn the color green
with ID names or class names or attribute names, any of that.
It's very important that you don't make any spelling errors.
What I normally do is I normally just copy it and then paste it in so that I don't actually mistakenly
add a capitalized s or something else that I could write incorrectly.
So remember, the ID selector is a pound sign or a hashtag.
And once we enclose our rule inside that selector, you'll see bullet number three turn green, because
that is the only item and it should be only one item that has the same ID.
Now let's move on to To-Do number four, which is to set the CSS for the elements that have the value
attribute set to four.
And notice now that all of the items in the ordered list, I've set a value attribute.
And what this does, if you take a look at the web docs for the list item element is this attribute
can indicate the current ordinal value of the list item.
When you have a list item inside a ordered list by default, it starts numbering from one like so this
is this list item.
But because I've got that paragraph tag above and I want to format this so that we have an interesting
CSS exercise, I've set the value attribute so that the list starts from two, which is totally valid
and I've set it for all of the other items as well so that we continue the list.
In this case, we're going to use the attribute selector to select this value attribute and turn the
text blue.
Let's paste in the CSS rule and then remember, the way that we use the attribute inspector is we first
select the element in this case list item, and then we add some square brackets.
And inside the square brackets we add the attribute that we want to select, which in this case is called
value.
And if right now I already close these curly braces, so we select on that attribute is going to turn
all the list items that have a attribute of value set, which is basically all four of these.
Now, some of you might have noticed that bullet number three, which.
Remain green instead of turning blue like the rest of the list elements.
Now, if you're curious about why this is, this is to do with something called CSS specificity relating
to how specific the rule is.
Now, we're going to be covering this in Section seven for our advanced CSS module.
So that's something you get to look forward to in the future.
Now, if we want to set the attribute that we want to select to a particular value, which in this case
is the one that's four, then I have to go a little bit further and set this equal to four.
And now you can see it's only selecting this fourth bullet and turning it blue.
Now attribute selectors can be a little bit tricky.
So if you didn't understand this at all, be sure to rewind in the video and watch that section of the
video again, just to make sure that you fully understand what's going on before you move on.
The final to do is the easiest.
All we have to do is set all the elements to text, align to center.
When we want to select all the elements, we use our universal selector, which is the asterisks.
And then once we paste in this rule, you'll see now our preview looks exactly the same as what we wanted
for our goal Everything center aligned.
There's lots of different styling being applied and we've now managed to achieve all of the to do's
in our exercise.
So hope that made sense.
And it helped you review all the things we learned in this lesson.
Once you're ready, head over to the next lesson where we've got our final project for the section.
All right.
So now it's time for our final project of the section.
And in this project, we're going to be building a website to help you learn Spanish.
Now, you might already know Spanish, but I'm currently learning Spanish, and there's so much vocab
to get through.
I thought, Why don't we build a vocabulary flashcard website?
But a really, really simple one.
Using everything we know so far in this project, we're going to be creating a website where we list
the words in, well, in this case in Spanish.
It could be any other language you choose, and we're going to match it with an image of a particular
color so that we learn all the colors in our foreign language.
This is what the final website should look like.
We've got our word which is foreign in the color that matches the image.
And we've got our images all lined up as nice little squares so that we can scroll through this website
and learn the words for the colors in Spanish.
Once you're ready, go ahead and download the color vocab project starting files, extract it and open
it up inside vs code in the index.html.
You'll see that I've already set you up with some starting code.
If you go ahead and show it as a preview, you'll see some words for the colors in Spanish and the different
images for the different colors.
Now don't worry about the fact the images are all different sizes.
We're going to fix that with CSS very soon in the project.
First thing to note is we've already set you up with a link to an external stylesheet which is inside
Style.css.
But notice that we haven't created that file for you, so I want you to create a new file inside the
correct location by using this button in VS code and then name it once you've created it so that it
actually works.
And one of the things that I often check to make sure that my external CSS is linked up is to target
everything on the page and to set the background color to red.
That way you know that if actually does work, then it's linked up correctly and it's really obvious
when it doesn't like right now.
And the reason here is because my style.css is actually outside this folder.
It's just floating about somewhere and I have to get it so that it's at the location that I specified
in the external stylesheet link.
So I don't want you to change anything inside the index.html.
Instead, all of your work is going to happen inside the CSS file, which you will create and you will
incorporate into your project using this file path to make sure that you understand how file paths work
and how you can create this for yourself in the future.
Now, if we scroll down, you can see there's five different colors, five different images, and there
are some h2's and H ones.
In order to complete this project, I've created some steps for you in the to dos which you can follow.
Alternatively, you can simply look at the goal image and try to figure out yourself.
You can either use a stepwise approach in the to dos or you can use the goal and do everything yourself.
It totally is up to you.
But what you're aiming for in the final version of the website, which you can view by right clicking
on solution dot HTML, opening it up in the preview.
And the most important things I want to point out is that the images are squares.
They are 200 pixels by 200 pixels, so 200 pixels high, 200 pixels wide.
Secondly, the font weight of these h twos are different from normal h twos.
They're actually a lot lighter.
So we've set the font weight to be normal rather than the default, which is h to get bolded.
The next thing is that the color of the text should match the meaning.
So rojo means red azul means blue.
And because in our index.html I've matched each of them up together.
But also you can look at the IDs if you don't know Spanish words because we're learning them after all
right, so yellow is Amarillo, green is Verde and so on and so forth.
So I want you to make sure that these h twos have a text color that matches whatever it is supposed
to be.
So blue or orange or green or whichever.
So if you get confused, look at the goal dot PNG.
If you want to go step by step, then look at the to dos at the bottom.
But importantly, don't write anything or change anything in the index.html.
All your work goes into the CSS file.
Pause the video and give this a go now.
All right.
So let's run through the solution together.
So the first thing we're going to do is we're going to make sure that the solution folder is collapsed.
So it's not confusing.
And then we're going to select this folder and then add a new file, which I'll call style dot CSS.
Remember, the file name has to match what it's referred to here.
Exactly.
Sometimes you'll see people have styles.css, sometimes you'll see main dot CSS, but as long as the
file name matches, it doesn't really matter.
It's up to you how you want to name it.
Once I've created that, let's just make sure that my CSS file is properly linked up by doing that background
color change.
So let's change it to Red and then let's go ahead and preview this.
And if the background is red, then it means that it works.
So I can now delete this and get rid of that horrible background.
The next step is to go ahead and use CSS to style each of the color titles so that the color matches
the meaning.
The first one that we want to select is this H2, which displays Rojo and it has the ID of red.
So remember, IDs are unique, so we can simply select that.
So let's select the element with an ID of red and set its color to red.
And so we can do the same thing for the rest of the colors.
So now they're all matching with their meaning.
The next step is to use CSS to change all the color titles, to have a different font weight.
And this is what we want the font weight of normal.
If we want to select all the h2's, then we're going to have a problem because this one is also an H2
and we don't want that one to have a normal font weight.
We still want that to be bold.
We want these to have the lower font weight.
So what is unique to all of these?
Well, we've applied a class of color title to each of them, which this H2 does not have.
Then that means that we can simply select color dash title and then apply the font weight to all of
those with that same class.
And you can see that differentiates between this H2 and this H2.
And instead all of these which are grouped together have that style applied.
Now the final thing we need to do is to use CSS.
No, not HTML to make all the images 200 pixels high and 200 pixels wide.
How can we do that?
Well, we can simply select the image element.
So this is using an element selector and we can set the height to 200 pixels and the width to 200 pixels.
And there you have it.
All of our images are now squares matching the height and width that we've specified.
You can of course change this and personalize it as much as you like.
Change up the colors or change up the words, learn the colors in a different language, make things
even more beautiful using the styling that you've learned.
But in the next section, we're going to be covering more about different CSS rules and you'll have
more tools at your disposal in order to style your websites.
So I hope you have fun in this section where we introduce you to CSS once you're ready.
Maybe tomorrow, maybe the next day, head over to the next section and continue learning about intermediate
aspects of CSS.
For all of that and more, I'll see you there.