Now we've already used some CSS properties in order to apply to our different HTML elements, but in
this section we're going to do a deep dive into some of the most important CSS properties that you'll
see and use.
And we're going to start with CSS, color properties, some of the color properties you've already seen
previously.
I've shown you how you can set the background color of a particular HTML element by using the background
color property.
And previously we've been setting it to basic colors like red or blue or green.
And remember that the way that the CSS rules work is the first part is the property.
And the part that comes after the colon is the value that you want to set that property to.
So in this case, we're setting the background color of the HTML element, which remember contains everything
on our website.
So the entire web page to a color of red.
That's what that rule does.
Now, there are different types of color properties.
There's the background color, but you can also simply use the color property.
And what this does is it sets the text color.
So always check the docs.
If you're not sure which property does what.
Notice that in this case we've got two colors, which we've named Red and Blue.
Well, how do we know that we can use these colors?
And what exactly are they?
Well, they're called named colors.
And there's a whole bunch of them out there with poetic names like Cornflower Blue or Cadet Blue or
dim gray or olive drab, etcetera.
And you can find all of them by, of course, going to the developer documentation.
If you Google for docs named color, the first link should take you to this web page.
Alternatively, you can use this URL as well, and the syntax is pretty simple.
You simply use the name of the color and if you scroll through this table you'll see all the different
colors.
And don't worry too much about the CSS level one or level two or level three.
It just describes historically when each color was introduced.
So these were introduced first because it's basically the rainbow.
And then over time we got some more fun colors like cyan and dark khaki and all of these different colors.
So you can simply copy the name of the color and paste it into your code and you'll be able to see that
rendered in your website.
Of course, even though there's many colors available in the default CSS named colors.
But you still sometimes might want to have a more unique color palette.
So what do you do in that case?
Well, one of my favorite color palettes is color hunt.co.
It's a free tool that's created by designers for designers and of course, for us as well.
Here you've got professionally designed color palettes for colors stacked together that would look perfect
on any website.
You can imagine that if you select any of these random websites, maybe this could be the background
color of the website.
This could be an H1 color, this could be a subtitle or H2 color.
You have accent tones, you have main tones, and you can use all of these colors in your website.
But how do we use them if we don't have a name that's attached to it?
Instead, we've got all these numbers and letters.
What exactly are these?
Well, these are hex codes and they are a way of representing a larger number code for that particular
color.
So, for example, in this case, this is a color purple which is formed of three fractions, red,
green and blue.
And these are colors out of 255.
So if you imagine a fraction, 93 out of 255 red, 56 out of 255 green and one for five out of 255 blue.
And when you mix all three of these primary colors, you can get so many different types of shades.
So in this case, we've got 93, 56, one four, five.
So 93 out of two, five five, 56, green out of two, five, five and one, four five.
So a little bit more blue and we end up with exactly the same shade as this purple you see right here
converting that RGB into a hex code.
So a different way of representing that number.
We get this particular hex code.
What does this mean for you?
Well, when you're using something like color hunt and you want to apply these different colors to your
website, you can simply copy the hex code and use it instead of the name.
And even on the docs for the named colors, you can see their hex codes lined up next to the names,
and in code it looks pretty much exactly the same.
Instead of the name, you just put the hex code.
So now it's time to try an exercise.
Go ahead and download this zip file from this current lesson, extract it and open it inside vs code.
Once you're here, you should see it's a pretty simple website with just two elements inside the body
an H1 and H2.
And if we look at the preview, then you can see it's clearly a drab, black and white world.
We're going to change all of that by adding in CSS colors.
So you've got five steps that you need to complete here and you should follow them one by one and by
the end of all five steps, you should have a website that looks something like this with lots of different
colors and different background colors as well.
Pause the video now and give this challenge a go.
All right.
So let's walk through the solution together.
We've got the background color of the body, which is set to antique white, which is this color right
here.
And we've got the text color of the H one set to white smoke.
But you can also set the background color of the H one.
It's a property that's available on any of the elements and it simply takes the existing area of that
element and colors the background.
Now, that might have required a little bit of lateral thinking, but hopefully you got there in the
end.
And notice how in the H one we've got all named colors and in the H two, I've asked you to use hex
colors and this is just so that you have practice adding colors using the two different methods.
Hopefully you got there in the end.
Once you're ready, head over to the next lesson and let's learn more about formatting fonts using CSS.
Now, in this lesson, we're going to talk a bit more about the different CSS properties that we can
set for fonts so we can change the appearance of the text in our websites.
And we've already seen some of them, for example, the color property which sets the text color, but
there's other ones as well, such as the font weight, the font size and also the font family, which
is the typeface that we want to use.
Let's explore some of these newer ones.
The first one I'll talk about is the font size.
We can change the size of a font by simply using the font size property and then setting it to a particular
pixel size, as you might have seen me do already.
But if we think about it, what exactly does a 20 pixel font size mean?
How big is it really?
Well, this is how big it is.
One pixel is about 1/96 of an inch.
And the reason why we're using imperial units is because a lot of the sizing for websites and for design
work actually comes from the olden days of book printing, book binding.
And it was very traditional.
If you know how big an inch is, then you know how big one over 96 of an inch is.
It's absolutely tiny, but if you have no idea how big an inch is, then in metric units it's about
0.26mm.
That's about how big a pixel is.
It's 0.26mm wide and 0.26mm tall.
So it's a small cube that's very, very tiny.
There are other ways that we can represent the font size when we're writing CSS.
One common way that you'll see in addition to pixels is using something called a point.
A stands for a pixel and a P stands for a point.
Now how big is a point?
Well, it's a slightly bigger than a pixel.
It's about one over 72 second of an inch.
So that's just slightly bigger.
If 1.96 of an inch is 0.26mm, one over 72 of an inch is about 0.35mm, just a tiny bit bigger.
Now the point is actually often used in many different applications.
So when you select a 12 size font in, say, word, you're actually selecting 12 points.
So that means when you're using 12 points on your web page, you can expect that when a website is at
100%, it will look about the same as a 12 font on your word document.
In addition, there are some other ways of representing font size, the M and the M.
What are these units?
Well, the M is actually not pronounced M It's pronounced M, so it's pronounced in the same way that
this letter is in the alphabet.
Why is that?
Well, one M is defined as the full width of an M.
The letter M is probably one of the widest letters in the English alphabet, and this unit simply represents
that entire width.
But what does it actually mean when we use it?
Well, what it means is that when you set an H one to have the font size of one M, your CSS code would
look something like this.
Then it means that if it had a parent, for example, if we had a body tag that enclosed this h one
tag, then if this body had a font size of say, 20 pixels, then this h one if we set it to one M or
one M, then it means it's going to be a 100% of the parent size.
So it means it's going to be 20 pixels.
Now, however, if we set it to two M instead, then in this case it's going to be two times the parent
size.
So two times 20 pixels, which is going to be 40 pixels instead.
It's basically a relative size.
And I'm going to explain to you why this is important very shortly.
But closely related to the M or the M is the M, and it's got that extra word.
Ah, And basically it works the same thing.
It's a relative size, but it's now relative instead of to the parent.
It's relative to the root of your HTML file, which if you remember, the root is usually an HTML element
that encloses everything inside.
What is the difference then, between the M and the M?
If we take a look at this code where we've got a body tag that encloses an H1 and then we've got a footer
tag, which is one of the tags that you can use to define a section in your code for the footer area
of your website.
Then inside here we've got an H2 that's enclosed.
If I set my H2 to have a font size of two M and my footer had a font size of 20 pixels, then two M
is two times 20 pixels, which is equal to 40 pixels.
So this H2 is now 40 pixels.
However, if I go in here and I change this footer to have 80 pixels, then all of a sudden this is
going to change and it's no longer going to be 40 pixels, but instead it's going to be two times 80,
which is now equal to 160 pixels.
So it's moving relative to its parent size.
On the other hand, if I had set this H2 to have a size of two REM and I change the size of my footer
from 20 pixels to 80 pixels, then it does not affect this.
Whatsoever.
It still remains the same size.
It's only if I change the root element, which if you take a look, it's the thing that encloses all
of the rest of the code, which is normally the HTML element.
If I change this size to something larger, say 90 pixels, then that is the thing that will affect
this sizing.
So the main difference between the M and the M is the fact that this is a more consistent way of changing
the sizing.
So I normally recommend that everybody who develops websites when you're setting the font size to use
the REM, because the way that you have different things embedded in others.
So this H two is inside a footer which is inside the body, which is inside the HTML.
Then the relationship to the parent can very quickly get very confused and you don't know whose parent
you're referring to, especially when you're working in a separate CSS file.
So understand how the REM works.
Remember, it is a scaled size of the root one.
M is one x, the root size two M is two x, the root size.
And this is a much easier way to control the different sizes of various elements on your screen and
have more clarity around what's going on in the starting file that you downloaded previously.
I've got some sample code for you.
If we take a look at all the different ways of setting font size, you can see that we can use the pixel
size, we can use point size, we can use M REM, and we can also use named font sizes such as extra
large or large.
And when all of this is rendered, you'll see the different sizes in play.
The fact that a pixel is much smaller than a point, but these two are static font sizes and then the
M is relative to the parent and the M is relative to the root.
But these are relative sizes.
If you want to see this code and be able to edit it and change it and see it working, then download
the zip file from this current lesson called 6.1 font properties.
Once you've extracted it, open it up inside vs code.
Head over to font size dot HTML and you'll see exactly the same code as in the demo.
But in this case it's of course in VS code.
So you can change things such as the REM, the m, the different font sizes, the root font size, and
you'll see it reflected on the screen.
For example, if I change this root font size from extra extra large down to say, 20 pixels, then
you'll see that this paragraph change accordingly because its size is based on REM.
So have a play around with that so that you can understand what's going on.
There are some other font properties that I want to briefly cover.
One is the font weight, which is relatively simple.
You can have normal or you can have bold, and we all know what that means.
It just makes the font look a bit heavier.
But out in the wild you might see some other ways that people use to change the font weight.
In addition to the basic keywords, you can have a relative font weight which is relative to the parent
to have the font lighter or have it be bolder.
In addition, you can also use a number from 100 up to 900 to determine how light or how bold you want
the font to be.
And similarly, when we say lighter it basically minuses the number by 100.
And if we say bolder, it just makes it bolder by 100.
Somewhere along this range, in addition to font size and font weight, there's also the all important
font family.
And this determines what you want your text to look like.
For example, in this first example, we've got the font family that is set to Helvetica.
This is a particular typeface and the name is called Helvetica, but this is a mac specific typeface.
So there are many Windows computers that do not own this typeface.
That's why very often when we write a font family, we don't just write the font name, we have a comma
and then we have a backup generic font type.
So in this case it's a sans serif.
A sans serif is simply the type of font where all the edges are pretty much at right angles.
If you had these little feet or these little decorations at the edges.
Of your letters, then very often what you're looking at is a serif type font.
So that's the main two types of different typefaces.
And in later lessons, we.
Cover typefaces in more detail.
So you can either search for that lesson or wait until it comes up to learn more about that.
What is important, though, is having this generic typeface.
This means that when you have this set that Mac users will see this font, but Windows users will see
something that's relatively equivalent and it will be automatically displayed for them when it doesn't
work.
Now what if you have a font that has many words in it?
For example, times new Roman consists of three words.
Well, in this case, we can't simply just type it out like this and then have a comma.
We actually need the quotation marks around it so that we can tell the CSS file that there are spaces
in the name of the font family.
So just be careful about that when you're using it.
And because times new Roman is a serif type font, then the backup, the generic type is also a serif.
Now what if you want a completely custom font that maybe the user doesn't have?
Well, one of the best places to find free fonts is going over to Fonts.google.com.
And here you can find all sorts of different fonts and there are so, so many for you to choose from
and you can browse to your heart's content.
Now I want you to do this with me.
Go over to Fonts.google.com, find a font that you like.
So maybe I really like a particular font and if you click on it, sometimes you'll see that it has different
font faces for the different weights.
So there's Bold, which is 700 or regular 400.
But then other fonts you might see in here doesn't actually have any weight other than just the regular
one that you can use depending on which of these type you have.
Simply select the weight that you're interested in.
For example, with this font, maybe I want the medium size, and with this font, maybe I'm just going
to select a regular one.
And once you've selected that, if you go to the top right corner, you can see all of your selections.
So you can remove all or you can remove the ones that you're not interested in.
But either way, you should end up with a font that you want to include.
Now make sure that that link is selected and then copy that over to your starting file.
So select the font family dot html inside the head element just after the style tag.
Go ahead and paste all of that in and this is basically a link that is going to pull in the Google font
for any user on the internet.
So it doesn't matter if they have a mac or a PC or which fonts they have downloaded on their computer,
they'll all be able to access this font because we're including it in the link.
And then let's go ahead and copy the CSS rule, which Google has very helpfully included for us.
And if you scroll up, you'll see that I've again got an internal style set in here so that we can more
easily see the CSS alongside the HTML on the same file.
While we're doing the exercise.
Let's go ahead and create an H1 here and I'm simply going to write the words font family because that
is what this page is all about.
And then let's right click and show it in the preview.
Now I want you to set the H1 CSS style to the one that you just copied over.
Pause the video and do that right now.
All right.
So we need to target the H, one of which we've only got one so we can use the element selector and
then we paste in our CSS style as easy as that.
And you'll notice immediately that updates that font into our custom font from Google.
And it doesn't matter what you've chosen, this should always work as long as you've included all of
the links that are required and added in the relevant CSS.
Also on this page you'll see the different font families, for example, the Helvetica and the sans
serif.
Or on a windows.
The default sans serif will be an Ariel type font.
And then you've got serif type fonts, which are the ones with the little feet that I mentioned.
You've got these sans serif fonts and you've got all of these other generics such as cursive monospace
and fantasy cursive is a little bit curly.
That's how I remember it.
Monospace has all the letters occupying the same width, so similar to a typewriter or code, and fantasy
is usually something kind of wild.
And these generic fonts will be different depending on the computer that you use and the browser that
you use.
So you might not see the same type of fonts that I have here, but if you specify a specific font and
you make sure that it's linked to, then we should all be looking at the same font face right up here.
And notice how when we copy that over it specified the specific font, but also a backup font in case
these links didn't work or something messed up and it would default to a cursive font.
The generic cursive font would then look like this.
So the final thing I want to talk about in terms of text styling is alignment.
So text alignment.
And this, this property called text align where you can set it to say centered or you can set it to
the left or to the right.
And you've also got some values like start and end.
And basically start is when you have text that maybe starts writing from the right to left, such as
in Arabic.
And so in this case, the start is actually here and the end is here.
But then if you're working with Western text, then the start will be right here and the end will be
right here.
That's just a more flexible way of determining the text align.
But all in all, this is a pretty simple property and you can take a look at it in the docs to learn
more about what the other values in addition to start end are and try the demo to see how they work.
Now once you've done all of that, I've got a final exercise for you and that's located in the index.html
here.
There's a number of to do's I want you to complete and I want you to go through them one by one.
It involves changing some colors, changing some font sizes, font weight, font, family, the text
align and also changing a root element font size.
The important thing is that you don't change any of the CSS that's already included, but instead write
your CSS below in this internal style element so that you can quickly refer to the to do's and see what
you need to write in the CSS.
Don't worry too much about setting external CSS.
We're just completing this as a quick exercise.
And remember, while you're doing this, if you want to see what the end result should look like, go
ahead into the goal dot PNG.
To see all the colors and layout and relative sizes of everything.
Pause the video now and go through each of these two dos.
All right.
So let's go through the solution together.
Now, step one was to change the color of this particular element to a named color called coral.
And the solution should look something like this.
The second one is to change the font size of this element to two times the size of the root element.
Remember, to do that, we have to use the REM and two times the size is two REM.
I've selected it based on the size ID and I've changed the font size to that.
The next step.
I've changed the font weight of this element to 900 by using the font weight property and then we change
the font family of this element to use the caveat font with a regular font weight.
So I selected that font from there and then I added in all the required links just before the end of
the head section.
But outside of the style section, this is very important in terms of placement.
And then I added in the font family and a backup font in case it goes wrong.
Next I changed this particular paragraph element so that it's right aligned.
And finally I change the route, which is the HTML element to have a 30 pixel font.
And when that was changed, then the two REM one, which is the font size element here, actually changes
with it.
So it gets bigger or it gets smaller depending on the route size.
So hopefully that was easy enough for you to complete and it tested you on all the things that we learned
in this lesson so far.
Once you're ready, head over to the next lesson where we're going to learn more about CSS inspection
and how you can find out what is happening with your CSS using the Chrome developer tools.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you there.
Hey guys, welcome to another lesson where we learn more about CSS.
Now in this lesson, we're going to deep dive into CSS inspection and learn about the Chrome developer
tools that allow us to figure out what our CSS is doing and potentially diagnose any bugs or resolve
any issues.
As I mentioned before, the Chrome developer tools are a really powerful suite of tools that is completely
free and comes bundled with the Chrome browser.
If you are not using a Chrome browser, you won't get access to it.
And it's really important, at least for this course, that you've got the same browser as I'm using
so that we can go through these tools together.
If you head over to this URL, which we visited before in the last section where I showed you how CSS
works and how we can simply add CSS to make our website look beautiful, then we can use this as an
example to learn more about CSS inspection.
In order to bring up the Chrome developer tools, we go over to these three dots and then we go to more
tools and we go to developer tools.
Now you'll notice that on the right hand side of this selection, you have the shortcut for your computer
on how you can bring it up quickly.
On a mac.
It's usually set by default to command option and I on Windows it's normally control plus shift plus
I.
So holding down those three keys together.
But if you have the function keys up here, pressing F12 usually also brings up the chrome developer
console.
But the shortcut could be totally different for you.
So make sure you take a look over here to figure out what your precise shortcut is.
Another way of bringing up this developer console is simply to right click on any element you're interested
in.
For example, this button and then click on inspect and it will do the same thing.
But in addition, it will highlight in the HTML that element that you selected.
Now what if you wanted to select a different element while you're here?
Well, you can use this button up here to select an element visually so you can click that and then
say, okay, I want to look at the footer here, this paragraph, Well, then it will select it for
you in the HTML.
Or I want to look at this H1 so you can select it visually or you can select it using the HTML.
This is the Elements tab and we're going to be exploring a subsection of this, which is the styles
section.
Notice that when I select any of these elements, it shows me the styles that have been applied to those
elements.
For example, if we take a look at this button, at least in the CSS on version, you'll see that it's
got a background color that I've set.
I've set a color for the text and lots of other things that we don't need to worry about too much right
now because in the next lesson we're going to learn more about different CSS properties.
But the important thing is that notice if I go ahead and press that button and switch off all the CSS
and I select that button again, then you can see that most of the element style is actually all automatic.
Whenever you insert a HTML element, it comes with automatic preloaded CSS and that's what you're getting.
By default, it looks something like this, but when you actually apply your own CSS, then it gets
shown here and you can even see which file it's coming from.
In this case, it's the Styles.css right here and you can click on it to view the source code of that
CSS.
The next thing I want to show you is how you can actually change the CSS live in the Chrome developer
tools.
Right now you can see I've got my H1 selected and by simply clicking add I can add a style to this H1.
So I could say let's change its color instead of white to um, maybe black instead.
And you can see that reflected live over here.
Now I can switch that off by hovering over here and clicking on the button to put a slash through it
and it deletes that CSS.
Now, the important thing to remember is any of the changes that you make in the Chrome developer tool
does not affect your original file.
Previously, remember we looked at TechCrunch using the Chrome developer tools and we were able to change
the text by simply typing in the Chrome developer tool.
This does not change Techcrunch's website and some of you have asked Is this illegal?
Am I doing something bad?
No, it doesn't.
It's just you affecting your local copy that's loaded up inside the Chrome browser.
It doesn't affect any of the other users and certainly doesn't change anything on Techcrunch's servers.
Similarly, back over here, when we're editing the CSS, when we are selecting or unselecting or adding
new rules, it doesn't affect the actual website.
Even if you load up one of your local websites that you're developing and you change a whole bunch of
things, this is just temporary.
It's for you to look and try things out and.
See how you like it before you add these rules into your actual CSS source code.
And you can further confirm this by seeing that I've got an H1 that says color black.
But if I go into the sources, my style.css for this file and I look in this file, you can see that
nothing has changed here.
There is no H1 that has a color of black.
Again, I recommend don't worry too much about the different properties.
There's lots of them that's coming up that we're going to talk about.
But the main thing to focus on here is how to use the inspector to understand other peoples as well
as your own websites and how the CSS is laid out.
If you go ahead and inspect on one of these anchor tags.
So when you click this and hover over it, you should see an A tag show up.
So click on it and it'll select it in the HTML.
Now, if you look over here, you can see that it's got some default properties that have been striked
out and the reason for this is because when we apply a CSS rule that conflicts with some of the automatically
applied rules, such as the color of that anchor tag, remember, by default, the color of any anchor
tag is blue to start with.
But here we've got one that's white.
Well, we've overridden it simply with this line.
So if I switch this off, you can see the other one switched back on.
But if I do have my own rules, then it can override other existing rules.
So how do you know what's actually being applied to your CSS element?
Well, that's where the computer tab comes in, because when you click on it, you'll see the actual
color in terms of RGB.
So how much red, green and blue is being applied to the text color and other properties as well.
And it removes all of the craziness of all this crossing out stuff.
And you can actually see in one place what is being applied.
Now another feature of Chrome Developer tool that I find really useful is to go over to the three dots,
go to more tools, and remember, this is the three dots for the settings of the Chrome developer tools,
not the one for Chrome.
This is easily confused, but when you go here and you go to more tools, you should find CSS overview.
And this is a neat feature where you can select capture overview and it will show you a bunch of useful
things like, for example, that there are two background colors here.
There's a sort of whitish gray and there's a sort of purple going on.
There's two different text colors, white and black.
And we've also got information on the different fonts that are being used on the web page.
I find this really neat when I come across a website that I really like and I'm trying to figure out,
Oh, what font is that?
Well, it seems like they're using Helvetica Neue or What color is this green Exactly.
Well, I can actually find out simply by looking at this inspector and maybe I can copy it for my own
use later on.
So you can see the colors, you can see the fonts.
And for now, we won't worry too much about the last two.
We'll come to that in later modules.
Have a play around with the CSS inspector and I want you to take a look at selecting different elements,
looking at their styles, trying to add some styles in the Chrome developer tool and looking around
at some of the other things we've mentioned.
Once you're happy that you know how to do that, I want you to head over to this URL at Brewery dot
Github.io slash CSS dash inspection and I've created a website for you to inspect in this website.
We've got some things that are on the screen and this is an H1 and H2 and a paragraph tag.
Now I want you to use the CSS inspector to answer these four quiz questions and once you've put in the
answer, click submit and you'll see if you got it right or if you got it wrong.
Pause the video and try to complete this challenge.
All right.
So the first question is, what is the named color of the body?
Well, what is the color?
So let's go ahead and pull up our inspector and let's select the body element if we haven't already
got it selected in the HTML.
And let's take a look at what styles are applied.
You can see it's got a background color that's being applied.
And if we switch it off, you can see it changes it to the default, which is white.
So this is the background color of the body and it's called Alice Blue.
If I type that in here and click submit, then I get my answer correct.
Now let's move on to the second question.
What's the font size of the H1?
Let's select the H1 right here and let's take a look at the font size that's mentioned here.
Well, it says it's three REM, which makes it a lot bigger than the default.
So let's type three REM in here, hit submit.
And we got that question right to number three is what is the font weight of the H2?
Select the H2, look at the font weight, its font weight 500.
Okay.
And hit submit.
And finally, what's the font family of the paragraph tag?
So let's select the paragraph tag and then look at the font family.
And this is a little bit tricky because it's actually not applied directly to the paragraph, but it's
actually one of the automatically inherited parts.
So you can see down here it says the font family.
And also if you go to computed where everything's all stacked up together, as I mentioned, where you
don't have to go through the entire list of what's being striked out, what's being applied, etcetera.
You can see the font family is Ariel comma sans serif.
So Ariel comma, sans serif and hit submit and we get all our answers correct.
So did you manage to do that?
Did you manage to use the inspector to figure out the answers to these questions?
If not, be sure to review the previous parts of this video so that you understand exactly what's going
on before you move on to the next lesson.
Hey, guys.
In this lesson, we're going to talk about some other really important properties and the ones that
you might have already seen if you've been doing a little bit of inspection around the Internet.
And these are margin padding and the border properties and these three properties, along with width
and height, form a really important CSS concept known as the box model.
So what exactly is it?
Well, if you think about a typical website here, I've created one called I Love Bacon.
Then you've got different components that are on screen, different HTML elements.
And even though we can't really see it effectively, each element is a box in itself and we can change
the dimensions of those boxes by changing things such as width and height.
So in this case, I've made my bacon much, much bigger.
And that invisible box around the element describes how it would be laid out on screen.
If we have an element that has a height of 300 pixels, we can change that height to allow our element
to take up more vertical spacing on the web page.
And when this happens, it pushes the box of any other elements lower on the web page.
Now, similarly, we can also change the width of an element to allow it to take up more space horizontally.
And we can either do this using pixels as defined here or we can use percentages.
So in this case, we've gotten our blue element to take up the entire width of the website and that
can be done using percentages in addition to width and height.
We can also set a border on each of the HTML elements.
If you imagine, again each HTML element being a box, then this would be the border of the box.
And the way that the border property works is a little bit different from what you might have seen before.
It can take three values separated by a space.
The first value that you should provide is the thickness of the border.
And this, as you can see here, is the thickness of this line.
If I made it thicker, then it would look like this.
And so we can provide a pixel value for the thickness as the first item.
Now, the second item is the style of the border.
You can have, for example, solid, but you can also have a dashed line, in which case the border
would look something like this instead of a solid line as we've gotten here.
And finally, we've got the color of the border in which you can set to any named color or hex color
as we've covered in the color properties lesson, These are three items together determine what the
border should look like.
So if I was to change the border from ten pixels to 30 pixels, then we would get a lot thicker of a
border.
But remember, the important thing is that the height and the width of your HTML element, your box
does not change.
It's exactly the same as what it was before.
So this border actually goes outwards rather than inwards.
And that's the important thing to remember here.
Now, once you've defined a border, you can further modify it with more specific rules.
So, for example, in this case, I've got a around 30 pixels solid black border around my element.
But then afterwards on the next line and this is very important where this line goes, it has to go
after the point where we've created the border.
In this case, I'm saying I want the top of that border to be zero pixels instead.
And, well, the way that these rules are evaluated is first they will look at this line creating this
border, which is 30 pixels all around.
But then once it lands on the next line, it evaluates this rule and sees that actually I should amend
the top of the border to have zero pixels.
So effectively getting rid of the border at the top here.
This border width works similarly to the way that the border property works, namely that it can take
a maximum of four values.
The first value is the top, the second is the right, third is the bottom, and the fourth is the left.
It goes in a clockwise direction.
In addition, you can also just provide two values for the border width.
And what that does is it sets one and three.
And then it sets two and four.
For example, if my border width, I had set to zero pixels and 20 pixels, then what that would do
is it would set two and four, which is the left and right to 20 pixels, and then it would set one
and 3 to 0 pixels.
This then becomes top and bottom.
And then we've got our left and right.
Now, another property I want to talk about in regards to the box model is something called padding.
And this is most easily seen when we have content such as text.
So in this case, imagine that this blue box is a paragraph element.
And in the paragraph element we've got Hello world repeated many, many times.
This paragraph element has got a border property and it's a solid black border, measuring 30 pixels
wide all around.
If at this point I add a padding property to this element, then what would happen is it would push
my border out by 20 pixels.
And in this case, I'm pushing it by 20 on all sides.
And notice how, again, in this situation, the height and the width of this box does not change.
It's still the same.
The padding simply adds this padding or space between the element and the border.
In addition to the padding, there's also something known as a margin.
And the margin is actually the part that's outside of the border.
So here again is the border in between the border and the width and height of the element.
Is the padding and the part between the border and any other content that's on screen is the margin.
So in this case, we've added a margin of ten pixels on all four sides.
If you imagine, we had two elements, each with the same padding, margin and border, then this margin
or this distance between the two elements in this case will actually be 20 pixels because it's ten pixels
from this side and ten pixels from this side.
And it adds this spacing between elements that you would not get with the padding.
So that is the main difference.
In your inspection, you might have seen the box model already shown in the inspector, and it shows
you the margin, the border, the padding and the width and height.
So that's what all of these different colors represent.
And when you take a look at the box model on inspection, then you can actually change each of these
values to see how it would look differently if you head over to this address.
App dot Github.io forward slash box dash model, and then we go ahead and open up the developer tools
and we select on the first image here, which shows a daytime world and we go into the box model that's
under the Styles tab.
If I go ahead and add a margin right here, let's say, I don't know, 100 pixels, then it's going
to add that gap.
Did you see it just now, that gap between that image and anything that's below it?
And similarly, if I add a little bit of a margin above, say, 100 pixels, then you can see it adds
a gap between that image and the next element above, which is that paragraph tag.
However, if I added the padding as 100 pixels, then you'll see it add the space as well.
But it's actually inside the border of the image.
If this element actually had a border which will set as a ten pixels solid black, then you can see
how that padding goes to a different place versus where the border goes.
And this box model is going to come really, really handy when you start to try and lay out different
items on your website determining how they look and where they're placed Relative to each other.
The final thing I wanted to mention is that padding and margin, similar to what we saw for the border
and also the border width function in that same way where we've got one, two, three and four values
that we can provide and if we provide a different value for each of them, so zero, ten, 20 and 30
pixels, then this will determine how it looks on all four sides.
And you have to remember that this is where the first value is second, and it goes around in a clockwise
direction.
Again, with the border width, you can change to only provide two values.
So say ten pixels and 40 pixels, then this is going to be applied to the top and the bottom and also
the left and the right.
So this is just a particular way of how these three properties can accept multiple values.
If you only set one value, say ten pixels, then that's going to affect all sides in addition to the
boxes that are created by elements, we can actually create our own boxes independent of that, and
that's really useful when we want to group different bits of content together so that we can style it
together.
Or maybe we want to lay it out together.
For example, here we have an image and maybe I would want the image to have a caption and I would probably
want to style these two bits together so I can wrap a box around these two elements.
And the way that I would create these artificial boxes is through the use of a HTML element, which
is called the content division element.
There was no point learning about the div element before we could learn about CSS because these are
completely invisible unless you apply CSS style to it and the whole purpose is to act as an invisible
box that can contain content in between the opening and the closing tags.
In the middle, we can put as many elements as we want and we can group them into separate boxes known
as Divs.
So here I've got the HTML code from that website I showed you earlier with the two versions of our world
the Morning and the Evening View.
And it's really simple and I've only just taken the body section of the HTML.
But here notice that we've got a paragraph tag and an image tag and they're grouped together through
the use.
Of this div element and notice that the div element doesn't really do anything else other than act as
a container to group this section together so that it's separated from other content.
For example, this section right here.
And now we've not only added meaning to our HTML by saying this is one section of content and this is
another section of content, but in addition we can style them differently in CSS.
When we run our code, this is what the website would look like.
You would not see any of these div elements, but if we were able to see them then they would look like
this.
Grouping our elements together because these divs are invisible.
Sometimes it can be really hard to debug them and understand what's going on or more likely what's going
wrong with your CSS.
So there's a free Chrome extension that I recommend you download to make this process of debugging a
little bit easier and hence that's why it's called pesticide.
We're going to use it to get rid of bugs in our CSS.
I'll add a link to this Chrome extension and all you have to do is click add to Chrome and then add
extension.
And once you've got it, then you should be able to look inside your extensions and then open it up
to activate it.
Now what does it do?
Well, let's demo it.
In addition to the suite of developer tools you've got now, you've also got the pesticide working for
you.
And once you activate it, you can see these div boxes now show up on screen and you can also see the
different elements highlighted in boxes and it really helps you diagnose what's wrong with your box
model when it does go wrong.
In addition, if you close down the Chrome developer tools and hold down the control key, when you
hover on each of these boxes down at the bottom of the screen, you can see how it tells you which node
you're actually hovering on.
So in this case, I'm inside a div and it shows you if there are any classes or IDs on that div as well.
And then here I'm hovering on an image element and here I'm hovering on a paragraph element and this
can be really helpful for you to see exactly what's on screen and almost like put on night vision goggles
so that we can see our divs and our elements and their alignment and their sizing.
Finally, we're going to use everything that we've learned and put it all together in this exercise.
We're going to write some code and apply our knowledge.
Go ahead and download this zip file from this current lesson, extract it and open it inside vs code.
Now, once you've done that, open up the index.html and you should see a bunch of to do's.
I want you to follow each of the steps one by one, just as if you were a web developer following client
instructions.
And we're going to use everything you've learned so far in order to create something that looks like
this.
Now, I've marked up this page a little bit so I can show you the important parts of the requirements.
For example, notice that here I've said 20 pixel padding, and that applies to the distance between
that paragraph tag and the border.
And then here I've said it should have a 20 pixel border at the top and at the bottom, but then only
a ten pixel border on the left and the right.
And notice that the layout is very specific here.
Each of these boxes should be touching corner to corner.
So you're going to have to figure out how to use the margin property in order to push these boxes around
so that they're literally aligned right up to each other on the same pixel.
I'm going to leave you to pause the video and go through each of these requirements and hopefully you
will be able to create a website that looks like the goal image.
Pause the video now and complete this challenge.
All right.
So let's go through the solution together.
Now, the first thing you'll notice is we've created three Divs and I've added a paragraph tag into
the first div so that we can see our padding a bit more easily.
The next thing is we've set each of the divs height and width to a pixel size, namely 200 pixels.
Next I've added a paragraph element inside the first div so that we can see any padding that gets added
very easily.
And I've set the first div to have 20 pixels of padding all around with a black ten pixel border and
that you can see under here.
Now notice how I've used different IDs for the different boxes or divs, and this way I can uniquely
identify each div and set different styling to them.
Next step.
I've targeted the paragraph element so that I remove any of the margins that go on it, because if we
preview our solution and open this up inside Chrome, you can see that by default, each paragraph element
actually gets one m of margin at the start and the end.
So if I cancel this, you can see how it pushes that away from the containing div.
So we wanted to add the zero margin so that we would have it centered and it would not be affected by
its default styling.
Next we had you set the second div to have a 20 pixel border, top and bottom and ten pixel border left
and right.
And if you remember from the lesson this is achieved through that multi-value method of setting border
width.
So the first value is top and bottom.
And then after space we have the second value for the left and right.
And even if you hover over this, usually the code is quite helpful for pulling up the reference on
this and it tells you how the rules work.
So that's a quick tip.
Finally, we set the third div to have a ten pixel border and I wanted you to set the margins so that
they would each touch corner to corner.
Now that could be done either by trial and error.
Alternatively, you can also work it out because if you think about this first div right here, it's
got a width of 200 pixels, so this part is 200.
But in addition it's also got a border of ten pixels all around.
So then we have to add ten and ten here.
Now that takes us up to 220.
But in addition, remember that we added 20 pixels of padding all around.
So then there's 20 here and 20 here.
So then if we add it all up, 200 plus 20 plus 20 plus ten, ten, that ends up with 260 pixels.
So then we know that we have to push the second div over by 260 pixels and we can do that using the
margin left setting, which is how we manage to push this box over.
And in a similar way we can work out how much to push this third box as well.
I hope this challenge was sufficiently challenging enough for you, but don't worry if it's not because
there's way more challenging layouts are coming up in the rest of the course and you're going to be
able to flex your box model muscles in the coming sections as well.
But once you're ready and you've reviewed your code and fixed any errors, head over to the next lesson
where we've got the final project for the section.
All right.
So for the final project, we're going to be building a motivational poster website and we're going
to make our own memes.
You might have seen some of these around the Internet.
There are the serious ones which are based off these 90 seconds motivational posters where you have
some sort of title and you have some sort of motivational text like potential.
We all have the tools for greatness within us, and I believe that is true.
And you've got a cute little Arctic fox.
But also there are some pretty hilarious ones like Coolness.
You may be cool, but you'll never be for popped collars.
Cool like this guy.
So the goal is to make our own website where we can create our own motivational poster.
The important part of a motivational poster is there is a image that is going to be big.
There is a border around the image.
So we now know all about borders and we can do that.
We have a black background and that is easy because we know all about CSS color properties.
We have a big main title, which we're going to use a custom font for to mimic this font a little bit
better.
And finally, we have a paragraph at the bottom and we're going to figure out how we're going to center
things on the screen, how to add borders and how to apply basically everything that we've learned so
far in this section.
Go ahead and download the starting project files for the Motivation Meme Project and extract it and
then open it up inside vs code.
I've created the task in a sort of to do list breakdown for you.
Now the main thing is that it's your website, it's your project, and as with all the projects in the
course, it's totally up to you how you want to create it.
But there are some caveats and it's important that you touch all of the learning points.
So these six points are important, and after completing these six points, you can change your website,
you can mess with it however you like, but want to make sure that everything you've learned so far
has consolidated and it all makes sense.
We're going to use a custom font from Google called The Libre Baskerville, which looks somewhat similar
to the motivational main title font.
You should add your own image into the images folder under the assets folder.
I've got an example image in here for you just in case you want to use it, but I recommend putting
in your own images just for practice.
And that image should have a five pixel white border and the text should be center aligned and you should
adjust the margin so that the image and text are centered on the page.
Now, this is going to be the trickiest part because centering elements using CSS is a whole science
in itself, but we're going to do it simply.
We're going to horizontally center the div by giving that div a width of 50% to take up 50% of the screen.
And then if you think about it, there's only 25% left on each side.
So if we have a margin left of 20% on that div, then it should push it into the center.
In addition, you might find it useful to set the image to have a width of 100% so that it fills the
entire container div so that you're not having to center the image along with the div.
Some of these hints are only going to make sense once you get started writing the code for it, so don't
worry too much about it.
Now I'm just highlighting certain points in the to do so that when you get to it, to pay more attention
to these parts and these helpful tips, which you'll probably need because especially at this point,
number five, it's quite a difficult task and it will take some time for you to figure out how to get
it to look like this.
And if you want to push the div down vertically, then I recommend just adding a top margin to push
it down by a pixel amount.
It doesn't have to be spot bang in the middle of the center because as I said, that is a whole science
in itself and we're going to be covering it in coming sections, but it's just a little bit more complicated.
So we're going to judge it by eye for this project for now, in order to get something that looks like
the goal image, I recommend putting the H1, the paragraph and the image inside a div.
That way you can center the div on the screen and you won't have to mess with all three elements and
their centering, which is already a hard enough task.
Finally, you're going to use your developer doc reading skills and learn by yourself about a property
called text Transform and figure out how to make the H1 look uppercase like what I've got in the solution
goal website.
All of these elements are on screen.
We've got the white board around the image, we've got the black background, the white text, the custom
font, and our H1 is totally in uppercase without us having to type it in uppercase.
So that's where that text transform property comes in.
And notice how this entire content div is roughly somewhere in the center, horizontally and vertically,
just judging it by eye.
It's not perfect, but as long as you find the perfect avocado, everything else is easy in life.
Pause the video now and complete this project and once you're done, come back and I'm going to walk
through the solution code with you.
All right.
So hopefully that wasn't too hard.
If we take a look at the solution HTML, you can see that I've completed all of those tasks with a small
HTML and a small CSS file, so it shouldn't be too hard.
Now, some of the steps are pretty self-explanatory, but there's a couple of things I want to just
briefly touch on.
One is you will need the Google font links in the head section if you want to be able to have that custom
font on screen.
And this is the custom font.
In addition, we want to have all our elements inside a div so that we can style it all together.
And that's quite important in terms of positioning.
So I've created a class for the div.
In this case you could have also used an ID, but if you were going to extend this website then it's
safer to use a class.
So you might be able to reuse the CSS in the future.
The poster is the part that is more or less center aligned and we use that trick with setting its width
and setting its margin, using percentages to get it more or less in the horizontal center.
And then I simply set a 100 pixel margin top, just judging it by eye to get it somewhere in the middle.
And I added the custom font and the border to the image and made the image 100% wide so that it would
fit fully into that poster div if you had any problems.
This is a time where you can look at the solution code and look at your own code and see if there's
any fixes you want to make.
And once you have, then you can also modify the website any way you like to personalize it and make
it your own.