Hey guys, welcome to day 53
of 100 Days of Code. Today
it's time for your capstone project.
And it's time when you review everything that we've learned over the last 10
days or so... everything to do with web scraping.
The project that we're going to be tackling is a data entry job.
Now there's a lot of data entry jobs out there where you're kind of just meant
to transfer data from one format to another.
So maybe you have it in a physical print copy,
or maybe it's on a website, maybe it's on
a PDF and you just have to transfer it somewhere else,
usually typing it into a spreadsheet.
The inspiration for this project came from, um,
when I was browsing Reddit actually on the /r/Python subreddit
which is a really good community for you to actually look at and see what other
people are doing with Python and seeing the latest and greatest things built or
news about Python. Now,
one of the posts I saw was asking whether if anyone has automated their job
completely, basically using Python.
Now we've seen how powerful Python can be
especially when we apply it to web scraping using Beautiful Soup and Selenium.
And looking through or the comments
there's actually a lot of people who have done this,
including this one guy who basically pretty much automated his entire job. And
the jobs that tend to be easily automated using Python
are data entry jobs, moving data from one format to another.
And if you think about it, if that job is in fact remote,
so if you search on indeed.com for a remote data entry job
and you get up and running with the company and you start doing it manually,
and then once you've understood what it is you have to do. For example, um,
gathering statistical data,
preparing reports and maintaining these spreadsheets.
If you realize that this is a large part of your job
and you can automate it pretty much with Python,
then you could probably get Python to do 70% of your job
and you spend the rest 30% of the day doing the rest of the job,
but still being paid as a full on worker with full benefits.
So this is something that a lot of people in the Python community has talked
about and explored,
and this is something that we're going to be trying out using both Beautiful
Soup and Selenium in this project. In our case,
we're going to be tackling a research data entry job where we're researching
house prices that fit a particular criteria for a client on the Zillow website.
And then we're going to be transferring that data into a form
which will create a spreadsheet in Google sheets
and that is usually how as a data entry person,
this is how we would make our money. Now,
because this is a capstone project, we're going to be using everything that we've learned in
this section. So that means Beautiful Soup as well as Selenium.
So you might have to revise up on some of the things you learned
especially the stuff on Beautiful Soup which we covered a few days ago.
And we're going to combine all the skills that you've done so far.
And this project really is going to test all of your web scraping skills that
you've acquired so far and see how far you can run with it. Because it's capstone
project there's not going to be a lot of guidance.
So you're going to have to persevere and try to see if you can solve your own
problems and see if you can get to the end outcome.
This is what we're aiming for. We're going to go to Zillow,
which is one of the largest real estate listing sites in the US, and we're going
to search to see if we can find a place to rent in San Francisco. Now,
San Francisco is notorious for really expensive housing,
and it was also really difficult often to actually find somewhere that you want
to live.
Let's say that you have a client who wants you to compile a list of all the
places that they can rent in San Francisco up to $3,000 per month
and it has to have at least one bedroom. On Zillow
you can already filter on these things. So for example, you could say
this is the area San Francisco California, that I want to rent.
And then of course changing it to for rent
rather than for sale switching the maximum price up to $3,000,
and then adding in the extra requirement that it must have at least one bedroom.
So once you've added all of those filters in, then all of those filters will go
into the URL
and this is the URL that you will be able to use to try and find properties that
match our client's criteria. Now,
in addition to using that URL,
you are also going to be using Beautiful Soup to scrape through all of this
data. And what we want is the price, the address,
and also the URL that this will link to. So, for example,
when I click on this, it will link it to the actual listing of the place.
And then once you've scraped all of that data using Beautiful Soup,
then you are going to be using Selenium to autofill in a Google form.
So we're going to be adding in the address of the property,
the price per month and the link to property. And of course,
we're going to fill out one of these forms per listing that we have on Zillow.
And once all of that form's been compiled,
then you will have the option to turn it into a spreadsheet.
Whenever you create a form in Google forms,
you can see that when you go to the responses tab,
you can click on this button in order to create a Google sheet from the
responses that have been submitted
and this is what you end up with: a spreadsheet with the address of the property,
the price per month, and a link to the property. So this way,
once you've done this research,
then you can send it to your client so that they are going to filter down on
each of the listings that match their criteria and decide which one they want to
go and make a viewing. So this of course makes their job a little bit easier,
and this is our research task that we're going to complete today.
So the first part of scraping the data for the relevant listings is going to be
done using Beautiful Soup,
and then the second part where we're going to be filling in this form is going
to be done using Selenium. So that is the project.
And once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and take a look at the requirements of the
project and we can get started with the capstone project.