Hey guys, welcome to day 54 of 100 days of Code.
And today we're going to be moving on to a new topic and that is going to be web
development.
And we're going to be working on this for the next few days as well.
Now there's quite a lot to cover today.
We're going to be talking about the command line, Python decorators,
as well as web development using Flask,
one of the most popular frameworks for creating websites using Python.
Now, before we get started though, you might be thinking, well,
I already know how to make websites.
I learned about HTML and CSS on days 41 through to 44.
So I really know how to make websites.
So what exactly is it that you're teaching me now? Well,
if you think of a website,
a simple website just contains HTML and CSS.
Now that is also what we call the front-end.
This is the beautiful mermaid that the user gets to see. Now for the website to
actually have some functionality, for example, if you're building a web app
instead of just a simple display website,
then it's also got to have a backend.
And the backend is the part that we're going to be learning how to build right
now.
So if the front end is just the part that displays information to the user,
the backend is the part that does a lot of the business logic,
a lot of the calculations,
and a lot of the things that we've been doing with Python. Now,
when people talk about full stack web development
which is a term that you would've heard of
if you were searching for web development jobs. Now full stack basically just
means frontend and backend.
So somebody who can deal with both frontend and backend technologies. Now,
usually there's quite a few languages that are used for the front and the back
end. So the front it's usually HTML,
CSS and JavaScript. HTML gives the website structure,
CSS gives it style and JavaScript allows it to have some sort of interactivity.
Now the backend can also be created by a bunch of different languages,
and here is more of a choice. Um, you could choose between JavaScript, Java,
Python, Ruby,
there's whole bunch of different languages. To make it even more
complicated, in addition to languages,
there's also different frameworks that you could use for the front and back end.
So some popular frameworks you might have heard of
are things like Angular and Rreact from the front end and Node and Flask or Django
for the backend.
So these frameworks are basically tools that really come with a lot of code
prebuilt for a lot of the common functionalities that you find when building
the front and back end.
So that way, we don't always have to reinvent the wheel and we can simply just
use the wheel and build a bicycle or build a car or built a scooter and whatever
it is that we want. Now,
when we're considering Python backend,
there's a whole myriad of different frameworks that you could choose from.
For example, Flask, Django, Bottle, Cherry pie, pyramid,
and a whole bunch more. But the most popular ones, if you look at job search
anyways,
is Flask and Django where Flask is better suited to beginners and also small
projects and Django suited much more to larger commercial projects. In order to
build out a website which has a front end and a backend,
we have to kind of understand what exactly is the backend.
There's three components that you really need to understand when it comes to the
backend. And that is the client,
the server and the database.
These three components together will determine how your backend will work.
Now, firstly, the client,
you can sort of imagine just as a user going onto a browser,
this is the client's side. This is the part that faces the user.
And then there's the server.
So you can think of the server as basically just a powerful computer
that's hooked up to the internet and it's on 24/7
always ready to receive requests over the internet. Finally,
you've got the database
which is kind of like a souped up spreadsheet where you are storing all the
information related to your website.
So let's say the client wanted to go to google.com. Well,
when they type that into the URL bar and they hit enter,
that gets sent to the server as a request,
and this goes across the internet to this other computer.
And this server has to respond. And it responds by sending over the HTML, CSS and
JavaScript files that it has for that particular website.
And once that gets sent back to the browser,
then that can be rendered by the browser as the actual webpage. Now,
if you're a website that has a lot of use of data or different types of data
that could be requested by a user, then usually you'll have a database.
So when the client requests, for example,
to see all the tickets they have on Eventbrite, well,
the page that they're viewing, that is the front end. That is the client side.
But in order to render all the tickets they have,
the client makes the request to the server and the server fetches the data from
the database. Once it gets the data back from the database,
it puts the data into the HTML, CSS and JavaScript files,
and it sends the whole bundle back to the browser to be viewed by the user.
If this whole process seems a little bit convoluted and complex, don't worry.
We're going to be diving deep into creating our server, creating our database,
and we're going to be creating all of these parts from scratch step-by-step
ourselves. So at the end of the web-dev section,
you'll find that if you come back to this video,
everything's going to make a lot more sense.
Now in order for you to have a good overview of what the whole system looks
like, I'd like to use the analogy of a restaurant.
So imagine if you have a restaurant and you've got the front of house
which is where the tables are,
when the customer sit. And then
you've got the kitchen
which is where the chefs work and where you're creating all the dishes.
And finally, you've also got the larder
which is where you store all the ingredients in the fridge or on the shelves.
Now this front of house part
which is where the user seats in is the client site. Now in the middle,
we've got the kitchen, which is the server. And finally we've got the larder
which is basically the database of ingredients.
Now the client side is completely separate from the rest. So as a user,
when I go onto a website,
I'm not interacting with the server or the database directly. Instead,
I'm interacting with my browser, which is on the client side. Now,
when you go to a website and you request to see some piece of information,
for example, you log in to Spotify and you want to view your playlists,
what actually happens is, you know,
you don't have the chef sort of cooking up the dish in front of you on the
client side. No,
instead what happens is that the server fetches the relevant ingredients from
the database, so the data that's related to your Spotify playlist,
and then it takes that data and it renders it into a HTML,
CSS and JavaScript files.
And then once that endproduct is created,
it ships it out to the browser on the client side, which you
as the user, can now view.
So this is basically an overview of how our frontend and our backend interact in
order to create a website experience for people. And in the coming lessons,
we're going to be building out each of these parts and you gonna see in greater
detail how they work together. So head over to the next lesson
and we'll get started building our very first website.
All right. Let's get started developing websites using Flask.
Now Flask is one of the most popular web development frameworks,
but what does it mean to be a framework? Well,
we've seen libraries before like Beautiful Soup. Tools that we can use and tap
into whenever we need a particular piece of functionality. Now,
a framework is a little bit like a library in the sense that it's a package of
code that you didn't write, but it also got some differences.
So here I've got a graphic from the differencebetween.net and one of the
biggest differences is the fact that a library is something which you call upon
to do something specific.
Whereas a framework is something which you have to abide by their rules,
you have to use their architecture.
And when it comes to triggering some sort of functionality,
it's the framework that calls upon your code.
So what does that mean? Well,
remember when we used the requests library and we would say something like requests
.get and then we would tell it which webpage to go and fetch.
Well,
this is us tapping into that library and then giving it a command to do
something. Now, when we're working with a framework,
it doesn't really work like that. We don't really say, hey framework,
do this thing for us. Instead,
we make sure that our code is defined in a way that the framework wants it to
be. And then when the time is right,
the framework is actually going to call our methods
instead of us calling the framework.
All we have to do is to plan ahead for certain situations.
If it was this situation, what do we want to happen? If it was that situation,
what code it should be run?
So it might be that all you have to do is just write some functions like hello
world and when the user goes to the website,
then it's going to display this text Hello world.
Let's try this in practice. Now by
now you would of known that as developers,
especially now that we're in the advanced stages of becoming a Python developer,
the most important thing when we approach a new tool or a new technology is to
read the documentation.
So Flask actually has a really good piece of documentation in order to tell us
how to get started quickly using Flask. As you can see,
they've described what a minimal Flask application looks like.
And this is a very simple server set up with flask.
So let's go ahead and copy this code. And I'm going to create a new project
which I've decided to call hello_flask. And then in this project folder,
I'm going to create a new file which I'll call hello.py.
Now it's important that the name of your file does not conflict with the name of
the framework or library in fact. So for example,
if I was to create a file called requests.py
and I had, um,
imported the requests library.
And then I tried to do something like requests.get.
Now when I run this,
because the name of my file conflicts with the name of the module, what will happen is
I will get this error. And it might be a little bit confusing
cause it says, well, request has no attribute get. Well
we know it does because it's in the documentation.
And the reason why we're getting this error is because we've named this file
the same name as the module.
So this is something that happens to a lot of people
so make sure that you don't commit this mistake and you could name it anything
like main or server or hello in our case. Notice that now
if I change the name, it actually automatically changed the import
which is not what we want. We want the import to be requests
and we want to make sure that we install our package  requests.
And once that's done,
you can see our module and our file have completely different names.
So now, if I run this file,
it works perfectly and it ends with exit code zero,
which means everything was successful.
So now I'm going to go ahead and delete this file
and go back to our hello.py. Now inside our hello.py
I'm going to paste in the minimal Flask application from the Flask
documentation. So paste that right here.
And as you might remember,
there's several ways that we can install new modules. So in this case,
the module is Flask and we can either click on the red light bulb to install
this package. Alternatively, we can go to PyCharm, preferences,
and then go to our project and into the interpreter to add the Flask package like
this.
Right.
Now, if you have the PyCharm professional edition,
there's additional tools to make it easier to install Flask into a project and
to work with Flask projects. But because we're using the free community edition,
I'm just going to go ahead and dismiss that popup.
So I've shown you two ways of installing a package.
Now I want to show you the third way,
which you might come across if you're looking at the installation.
So notice here, in order to install Flask,
they're using pip install Flask.
So pip is something that allows us to install Python packages from pypi.
So any package that you on pypi.org, you can install using pip.
And what we have to do is to type in the name that you see right here.
For example, if we want to install Flask,
then it's pip install and it's the capital F for Flask.
So we can copy that into our clipboard.
And if we go to the terminal tab at the bottom,
we can paste that instruction in here and hit enter.
Now it should have successfully installed Flask . And once I dismiss that,
you can see my errors go away. So all three methods work.
I personally prefer the red light bulb, just because it's much quicker.
It's just two clicks rather than typing a lot of code. Now,
once we've installed Flask,
we can go ahead and add some space to get rid of all the warnings from Py
Charm. Um, we can go ahead and run our project.
Now, as soon as I run the project, you can see
it tells me the process was finished with exit code zero,
which means everything was successful,
but where's my server and where's my website.
So let's go back to the Quickstart to see what we actually have to do in order
to set up our server. So to run our Flask application,
we're going to firstly, need to export a environment variable.
So in previous lessons, we've talked about environment variables,
but basically this is going to tell the Flask framework
what is the name of the file that contains our server.
So in our case, as well as in the Quickstart,
the name of that file is hello.py.
So we basically have to point to that file to get Flask
to be able to recognize it and to use it as the server. So on Mac
we're going to type export space
and then we're going to put in the name of the environment variable
which is FLASK_APP and its all caps.
And then with no spaces, we've got a equal sign
and then the name of our file, which is hello.py.
So now when I hit enter,
that's going to add that environment variable under the name that Flask is
expecting, which is flask.app. Now,
as it mentions in the Quickstart, if you're on Windows
the keyword is not export, but instead it's set.
So again, inside your terminal down here, you're going to type set.
And then you're going to put in the name of that environment variable
which was FLASK_APP and then with no space equals and it's our hello
.py. And once you hit enter,
it should give you the prompt again indicating that everything went smoothly.
Now, once we've done that,
the next step is to simply use the Flask command called run.
And when I hit enter, you'll see that it's created my server.
So it's serving up the Flask app that I've created in hello.py
and we're get a warning telling us that this is a development server and telling
us that if you want to actually launch it as a product,
don't use this development server. There's a few steps
you have to carry out if you actually wanted to make this production ready and
ready for the internet and customers. But in our case,
we are developing. So this is perfect.
And it tells us where to go and find our website.
So if you imagine that Google is at https://
www.google.com. Well,
this is the address of our website and it's being served by our computer.
So when you're trying to get hold of a website on the internet,
then you have to point towards the IP address
of that particular webpage.
But because we've created our server locally and it's being served on our own
computer, then this is basically the local address
of that website.
Now a neat thing about PyCharm is if I simply just click on this link,
then it's going to launch my website in my browser and you can see right up
here, we've got hello world showing up
which is the same as what we've got here in this method.
So that proves that we've successfully managed to create our very first web
server using Flask.
And it's able to serve up our very first Flask website. Now,
if you go ahead and open up the Chrome developer tools and you go to elements,
you can see that what we wrote here which is just a string
was actually converted by Flask into full HTML.
It's got the HTML tag, it's got the head tag,
it's got the body tag and we didn't have to do any of this.
We just told Flask what we wanted to be returned onto the page
when the user goes to the homepage,
which has just the web address plus a forward slash.
Now the very last thing to remember is once we're done with our server,
because it's still ongoing
it's still waiting for a client to hit up this website,
we have to get it to stop waiting. So we can quit by holding down control and
then pressing C. And you can see this takes us back to our prompt
where we've got our name and our project. Now,
if you don't stop it and you try to run two Flask applications to the same
address then the second one is simply not going to run.
So just be aware that once you're done with your server, hit control+c to quit.
Now in the next lesson,
I want to talk a little bit more about the commands that you can use in the
terminal because this is called the command line.
And just as here we use the command line to run our Flask application, to export
our environment variables, we can also do other things like create folders,
create files, move files around. It's actually a very,
very powerful way of interacting with our computer.
That's what we're going to do in the next lesson. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you there.
Now,
in the last lesson, we saw how to get up and running with our brand new Flask
server. In this lesson
I want to take it back a little bit and talk briefly about some of these
commands that we put into the terminal here,
because the terminal is actually a really powerful tool.
And it's something that's also referred to as the command line and its a way of
typing in commands one line at a time in order to control our computer.
The command line is also known as the shell.
So what exactly is a shell?
If you think about your operating system as a pistachio nut,
then the kernels of the actual pistachio, the thing that you're going to eat,
I'm really sorry about all the food analogies.
You can clearly tell I'm pretty much hungry most of the time when I'm recording
these videos, but let's get back to the topic.
So if your operating system is a pistachio,
then the actual nut is the kernel. And in computing
the kernel refers to the actual program that interfaces with the hardware.
So it's the core of your operating system. Now,
the shell of your pistachio or the shell  in computing refers to
the user interface for you as a human
to be able to interact with the kernel and in turn with the hardware of your
computer. And there's two variants to the shell.
There are graphical user interface shells, so for example,
when you open up finder
you're using a graphical user interface to access and find your files.
But there's also a command line interface
which is what we're going to be talking about and what we're going to be
learning about in this module.
So this is an alternative way of interfacing with the kernel.
Now it can seem intimidating at first,
but I want to show you that it's actually super simple.
And once you understand it, you're going to see that it's actually really,
really useful tool at your disposal.
A lot of the things that you can do with command line can be done using the
graphical user interface. So why use
the command line at all? At the end of the day,
what it all boils down to is about greater control.
And in your journey of becoming a better developer,
you will need to understand and exert more power over your tools,
that is the computer hardware. But on a more day to day basis,
you will find that if you're a regular command-line user
that it's actually easier and faster to do a lot of really common things.
If you're a Mac user, you've actually got a dedicated terminal application.
So if you go to spotlight and hit the search button and look for the terminal
and hit enter, you can see that this is the actual terminal application.
Now I've styled it up to look a bit more like a hacker because I like scaring
people in Starbucks, but that's not the only you can change.
You can change the color of your terminal,
you can also change the type of shell you're using. Currently,
if you are running macOS Catalina or above, so Big Sur
or any of the future operating systems, you're going to be using zsh
which has now the default Mac shell.
All right,
Now, if you're on Windows however, the default shell is the command prompt.
So if you type in to search for the command prompt, you can see
this is the app you need to launch and this is your command prompt.
For the most part, you can type in the same commands on Windows and on Mac
and it will work on both.
I want to show you some common things we can do in the terminal. Here
I've got my terminal and the address of the terminal is determined by the part
that's just before the prompt. So at the moment, it's a ~ on my Mac.
There's a couple of things I want to show you that you can do with the terminal.
The first thing that's really useful to know is where am I in my file path?
And to do this, we have to write pwd, print working directory.
And this tells me where I am. Once you open up your finder
as you can see up here, go to view and then go to show path bar.
And this is showing us the path from our hard drive/ users/angela,
which is exactly the same location as what I've got now in my terminal.
So the print working directory is really useful for you to locate where you are.
Similarly, on Windows, you can see when I do print working directory,
it tells me that I'm in the C:\users\username.
So C drive, users, username... right here.
The next command that is really useful is ls,
which stands for list.
And what this does is it will list all of the files and folders at your current
working directory.
So it's going to list everything that's in this current location where I am at
basically this. So if I go ahead and hit enter,
you can see all of the same folders showing up as it does
in finder. Pwd and ls are really useful for finding things out, for displaying
things.
But we can also use the terminal to move around in our computer.
And we do that using the CD command, which is changed directory.
So if at the moment, my working directory is users/Angela
and I want to get into my desktop folder
which is clearly one of the folders that I can access, then I can simply say
change directory to desktop. Now,
one of the things you can do to prevent yourself from getting repetitive strain injury and
typing a lot is you can type the start of the folder, so for example desktop-
De and then hit tab,
and it will narrow down on the possibility that you can go to so there's
development or there's desktop.
So if I add one extra S and I hit tab,
it's now going to automatically insert the folder that I'm looking for,
which is desktop. So now if I hit enter,
you can see that this part before my flashing prompt has changed and it's
changed to the desktop. So now, if I do pwd,
you can see I'm now in users/angela/Desktop,
which is the equivalent of double-clicking on this basically.
Okay.
On my desktop what if I wanted to create a new folder? Well,
we can do that using the make dir or make directory command.
So we're saying make directory and then we give it a name. So let's say
I want to call this Test then I'll just say mk
dir Test. And notice the location while you are at.
So I'm going to be making this test directory on my desktop.
And as soon as they hit enter, there you see it.
It's created that folder from scratch.
So now here's a question. If you wanted to navigate into Test so that when you
print the working directory,
it's going to output users/yourusername/desktop/test.
What would you do? What would be your command? Pause the video and
have a think about that. Alright,
of course, we have to change directory coz at the moment we're in the desktop
which is this, and if we want to go inside this test folder,
then we have to cd into it. So cd into test,
and now we're inside the test folder. And if I hit pwed, you can see
this is where I'm at. Now,
once I've cded into this new directory,
I'm going to create a new file in this directory. To create a new file
the command is a little bit different from creating a new directory.
The key word is touch. And after the key word, there's a space
and then we can provide the name of our file.
So let's say that we want to create a new Python file
which we'll call main.py. Now,
what it's going to do is create this file code in main
which is a Python file and it's going to do that inside the Test folder.
So let's hit enter and there you see it.
There's our Python file created without any clicking or dragging completely done
with our command line. So we've seen how we can create folders,
how we can create files. And by the way,
if you want to create a different type of file that you just change the
extension. So it could be .text,
or it could be .docx or whatever file format you want to create. Now,
what if we wanted delete our file? Well,
all we have to do is make sure we're in the correct directory to be able to
access that file. So when we hit ls,
we should be able to see the file we want to delete.
And then all we have to do is type rm which stands for remove
and then we could put our main.py. So there it is, it's gone.
Okay.
Now, what if I want to delete the Test folder? Firstly,
I have to navigate one step up. Instead of being inside the Test folder,
I can't delete the Test folder while I'm inside the Test folder.
I have to go one step up, which is the desktop folder.
Now of course I could say cd into the full path
which is /Users/angela/Desktop.
Now this would work, but this is really wordy.
A really simple shortcut for navigating
just one step up is writing cd and then two dots.
This is going to take us to the parent folder, which is now Desktop.
Right.
From here I'm going to delete this folder. Now to delete a folder
we can't just put rm. We also have to put a flag.
So a - and then rf. So this is going to recursively, forcibly, remove this
folder that we're going to add here, which is the Test folder.
Now the thing you have to be really careful about rm -rf is it does things
recursively. So if there were lots of folders inside this Test folder,
then it's going to delete everything in there.
And if, God forbid, you actually have this and you put it onto your whole computer,
well then that's going to be a real disaster.
Because the thing you have to know about the terminal is that it's a very
powerful. And what did Spider-Man's uncle say? With great power comes great
responsibility.
There's some pretty funny stories about people who accidentally deleted
everything on their computer just by messing with rm -rf.
So be really careful that you are in the correct location to delete the folder
and to double check that it's the right folder.
Because when I hit enter,
you can see it's not going to ask me for a confirmation
and it's also not going to put that folder or the containing files into the bin.
So be really careful when you're using the terminal.
There you have it.
There's an introduction to the command line using zsh on a Mac and using the
command prompt on Windows. Now,
when you open up PyCharm and you go to this emulator terminal,
so it's a sort of application within an application,
you can see that it looks pretty much the same.
Basically, all that PyCharm's done is just bundled the command
prompt into the PyCharm on windows and the zsh terminal into the PyCharm
on Mac. So you can do everything that you can do in the terminal
inside PyCharm as well
which makes it really easy to pip install modules or to run our Flask server.
Now,
if you want to know about other things that you could do in the Windows command
prompt or the Mac terminal, you can simply just search for command prompt
cheatsheet or terminal cheatsheet.
And what it will take you to are lots of addresses
which contain basically a lot more things that you could do with your command
line. But the ones that we've talked about today
are some of the most common ones and 99% of the time,
those are going to be the commands that you're going to be sticking to.
So write them down if you need to review them regularly.
And if you just use them on a regular basis,
you won't have any trouble remembering them.
Now that we've understood a little bit more about the terminal commands,
let's come back to our Flask code and understand what the code is doing in a
little bit more detail. For example, what is this name?
Because we're creating this app from this Flask class
and in order to initialize a new Flask application,
there is only one required input,
and that is the import_name.
Let's go ahead and print it out.
So if we print this __name__ and comment out the rest of our
code and hit run,
then you can see that it prints out __main_
_.
This name is one of the special attributes that's built into Python.
At any given point,
you could tap into the name to find out what is the current class, function,
method, or descriptor's name.
And when we get main, what it's telling us is
basically we're executing the code in a particular module.
So that means it's run as a script or from an interactive prompt,
but it's not run from an imported module.
It gives us this code here, if the name is equal to main,
then execute something only if it's run as a script.
This also takes us to
one of the common ways that you'll see people run Flask apps.
You'll see if __name__ is double equal to _
_main__ as a string,
so exactly what was printed just now when we printed out this name,
well, if this is the case,
then that means we're running the code from within this current file.
We're running hello.py. So in that case,
we're going to tap into our app and we're going to call the run method.
Now this app.run
basically does exactly the same thing as when we went into the terminal and
we said flask run. But notice when we say flask run,
firstly, we have to provide the FLASK_APP environment variable
and secondly, we have to stop the code using control + c
instead of using our normal run and stop.
But if we use app.run, we can now use our standard controls.
So I can simply hit run to run this hello.py,
and it will start serving up our Flask app at this address just as it did
before, when we did flask run. And instead of using control + c to quit,
we can simply use the stop to stop our Flask application,
making it a lot easier.
Basically by providing the name to Flask, Flask
will check that this is the current file where the app code is located.
And we're not in fact using an imported module. For example,
if I was to import the random module and I was to print the random.name,
then you can see the first thing that gets printed is the name of that module.
But the name that's printed from hello.py
which is the file that's being run is simply __main__.
So this basically denotes the file that is currently being run
and you say, Run 'hello' Well then inside hello
name is going to be equal to main.
Right.
The next part of the syntax that might be unfamiliar is this @ sign and
something that comes after the @ sign. Now we sort of know what it does.
It's basically saying when the user hits up this path
which is what's called the home route, basically when you go to a website,
for example, www.google.com
and you go to the first forward slash well, that is going to be the home.
And it knows that when you go there you want to see the home page.
So that's effectively what we're saying here.
When the user navigates to our URL with just a forward slash they want to see
the homepage and so we're going to show them hello world.
But what is this syntax exactly? Well,
this is code a Python decorator
and this is something that you'll see in more advanced Python projects.
So what exactly is a decorator? Well,
let's imagine that you have a bunch of functions in your class or in your
module
and you want to add some functionality to each of these functions. Well then you
might use a decorator function to do that.
Essentially you can think of a decorator function as a function
that's going to give additional functionality to an existing function. In order
to really understand this,
we have to understand a couple of other concepts as well.
So I'm going to do a couple of demos in this Repl.it
and if you head to this URL or find it in the course resources,
you'll be able to see all the code that I've written in this file.
So a long time ago,
we learned about Python functions and we know that a function allows us to
have specific packages of functionality,
allows us to add inputs, to increase the reusability of the function,
and also allows us to get outputs from the function which we can pass into
another function or do something with it. As an example,
we've got four very simple functions, add, subtract, multiply,
and divide that uses all three components of a function.
Now, what if we wanted to get a little bit fancier? Well,
one of the things about Python functions is that they are known as first-class
objects,
which basically means that you can pass a function around as an argument,
just like what you could do with an integer, a string or a float, it's treated
identically.
That means we can take these functions and we can build another function that
uses these functions. Let's say I create a calculate function
which takes a calc_function
and then the n1 and n2.
Inside this calculate function,
I'm going to call the function that was passed in and give it the values
n1 and n2 that was also passed in.
So now when I call the calculate function,
I'm going to pass in the name of one of these functions and then some numbers.
Those numbers are gonna become the input for this specified function
and then we're going to return the result of that calculation.
So now lower down,
I can call my calculate function, pass in the name of a function
so for example our multiply function, and then pass in some numbers,
for example, two and three. Now let the output that's returned
be our results
and let's go ahead and print this result. And you can see we get six.
So basically it has now multiplied two by three. Now,
if I change this to one of the other functions, add,
and I run this again, you can see instead of six, I'm now getting five.
The ability for us to treat functions as first-class objects basically means
that we can pass them around as if they were just any other argument
like a number or a string or a floating point number.
And then later we can activate them by adding the brackets around them and then
any necessary inputs. Now, the next concept
which you might've come across
but we haven't really used it a lot is the concept of nested functions.
Functions can also be nested inside other functions.
For example, if I create a function called outer_function
and this function is just going to print and say,
I'm outer. Now inside this outer_function,
I could create another function. So notice the indentation here
means that this function is now created inside this function and I'll call it
the nested_function.
So this function is simply going to print I'm
inner.
And now we have the problem of trying to call this function. Now,
because this function was declared inside this function,
its scope means that it's only accessible inside the confines of this function.
So if we were to go outside of the function, so by
indenting back to the beginning and we try to call this nested function,
then it's actually not going to work.
We're going to get a name error. It's not defined. However,
if we call this function inside this outer_function,
then it will now no longer generate an error.
So let's go ahead and trigger the outer_function by calling it in our main.
py. And when I run this, you can see it says I'm outer
and then it says I'm inner.
So this first gets executed and then this. And this I'm inner is being
printed when this line is being evaluated. Now,
one of the other things you could do is you can actually return a function from
another function.
Right.
Functions can actually be returned from other functions.
So if I make a copy of this previous function right here and comment out this
other function and all the steps before,
...
and we only have this bit of active code,
then you can see that instead of calling this nested_function here,
I could also return it as the output.
But the important part here is I'm going to get rid of the parentheses
which means I'm no longer activating that function right here.
So now when I call this outer_function,
the output that this line is going to evaluate to is going to become the nested_
function. So you could almost store it inside a variable.
So let's say I create a variable called inner_function
which is equal to the output of the outer_function
which is basically this nested_function that's being returned. Well
then, not only can I trigger the outer_function
which is just going to give me I'm outer,
now I can also trigger the inner_function separately by calling it
and then adding the activator which is the parentheses.
So now it says I'm outer after it evaluates this line,
I'm inner after it evaluates this line. Now,
if this is confusing to you,
I recommend heading over to the course resources where I've got a link to this
Python Tutor where I've entered all the code that we've seen just now
and we can execute this code line by line.
So you can see that the first thing that happens is it looks at this outer_
function and it creates a reference to that function. Now
next, it's on this line where our outer_function is actually being executed
because it has the parentheses at the end.
So now it's actually going to go inside this outer function and go through it
line by line where it prints I'm outer and then sets up a reference to this second
function, which is the nested_function.
The nested_function can now be called by its name
which is nested_function. But the very end of the outer_function,
that function is going to be the return value. So it's going to be outputted.
Finally,
we get to the end of this line nine and we set up a reference from this variable
called inner_function to this nested_function. And finally,
when we get to the line 10 we trigger that function.
So here is our inner_function which points to this nested function
and so when we trigger this inner_function,
it's the same as triggering the nested_function.
And that is when we end up going into this function
and printing out what it says inside.
Have a play around with that to fully get to grips with all the things that you
can do with a function.
And once you're happy with all of this and you've reviewed it and you understand
everything that's going on,
then you've got the foundations to head over to the next lesson where we're
going to talk about Python decorators.
In the last lesson,
we had a primer on functions so that we can understand the next step
which is the Python decorator.
So we've seen that functions can have functionality, inputs,
and outputs, functions are first-class objects and can be passed around as arguments,
functions can be nested in other functions,
and finally, functions can be returned as the output from another function
without needing to trigger it. With these four things in mind,
we're finally ready to tackle the Python decorator.
First of all,
I'm actually going to create a Python decorator for you so that we can talk
about how it works.
Here's what a Python decorator function looks like.
We started off by creating just a normal function.
Let's say I call it my decorator_function.
This function is going to take another function as an input.
Now, inside the decorator_functionn, I'm going to nest a wrapper_function.
And this wrapper_function is then going to trigger the actual function that was
passed in to the decorator function.
And at the end of calling all the lines in my decorator_function,
I'm going to return my wrapper_function. But remember
without the parentheses. Now,
basically what we've done is we've created a decorator_function
which can do some stuff and it could control the calling
of the function that was passed in.
Remember that a decorator_function is just a function that wraps another
function and gives that function some additional functionality.
That's quite a mouthful, but let's take a look at an example.
Let's say that I wanted to create a simple function
which I'll call say_hello.
Now this function is going to be the simplest form of function.
It has no inputs and it has no outputs
and all it does is just going to print hello. Now,
what if I don't want to run this immediately
the moment when I hit run, what if I wanted to add a delay to this function?
Well, one way of doing that would be importing the time module
and then before we print hello,
we can go ahead and run time.sleep
and we can sleep for a prespecified number of seconds.
So now when I call this method, say_hello,
and when I run it, you'll see that immediately nothing happens.
And then after a two second delay, you can see the print
hello actually gets triggered. Now,
what if I wanted to create a whole bunch of functions
like say_bye and say_greeting.
And I wanted to add a delay onto each of these. Well,
then I would have to copy and paste this code into all three places.
Now, this is a very simple example,
but frequently we'll want to add some additional piece of functionality to a
number of our functions. So this is where the decorator comes in handy.
What we could do is before we trigger the function that's passed in to
the decorator_function, we can add the delay.
So now whenever we decorate a function with this particular decorator_function,
then it's going to delay for two seconds before it runs the function.
So let's give this decorator function a little bit more of a descriptive name.
Let's call it a delay_decorator. Well,
now what we can do is we can simply use an @ sign
and we can call the delay_decorator in front of the methods
which we want to delay. So we can add it to all three of them,
or we can only add it to some of them.
But now when I actually run my function, say_hello
for example, you can see that this one
because it's got the delay decorator
it's going to wait for two seconds before it prints hello.
But if I call say_greeting
which is the one that doesn't have the decorator above it,
then you can see it gets triggered immediately.
So this is a really nice way of adding something that you could do before you
run the function,
Right?
or adding some functionality which you can do after the function. Or
alternatively, you can modify the function so maybe you wanna run it twice.
So now when I say hello,
it's going to not only delay by two seconds,
but it's also going to run it twice.
This syntax is what we saw when we were creating our Flask
app. It's got the @ sign and it basically decorates the function below with a
decorator function.
So putting this function through a machine that could modify the function or add
some functionality before or after. Coming back to our definition,
a decorator function is simply a function which wraps another function and gives
it some additional functionality or modifies the functionality.
Now, coming back to this syntax, this @ sign, it's
what's known as syntactic sugar.
It's some syntax that you can write to make it easier to write an alternative
line of code.
So let's say we wanted to add the decorator to this say_greeting. Well,
if instead of using this syntactic sugar with the @ sign
and then the name of the function,
we could also just call the name of the decorator and then we could pass in the
name of our function, say_greeting,
and then we would end up with the decorated function as the output from this
method.
And we can now call the decorated function with the parentheses.
So now we've triggered this say_greeting function
and we've passed it through the delay decorator.
But it's much easier to see at a glance what's going on by using this @ sign
because you can see now you can just trigger this method by its own name
and because the @delay_decorator is on top of it,
then it's going to go through that filter.
I recommend spending a few minutes looking at this code
which you can access at this URL which is in the course resources,
and then trying to recreate this functionality from scratch based on your
understanding of what we just talked about. And then once you're done,
when we head back to our Flask application
you can now see that pretty much all of the code is easily understood.
We know what this __name__ refers to,,
we know that this is a decorator
which is going to make sure that we only trigger this function
if the user's trying to access the URL
that is the homepage/.
If we wanted to create another function, let's call it say_bye.
This function could also get a decorator
and this decorator will check to see well, if somebody goes to the URL
/bye, well
then we're going to be triggering this method. Effectively
the Flask framework is the one that determines which of these methods to call
and these methods are only called when the decorator says that it's appropriate to do
so. Now, if I go ahead and run this code once more,
and we go to the URL that is our server,
so this we know is the home route or the homepage,
but if we go to /bye
then we go to the bye route and this method gets rendered.
Now in order to make sure that you get a chance writing decorator functions
yourself, if you head over to the next lesson,
I've got a coding exercise for you to challenge you
to create your own decorator functions.
And it's going to be a really useful decorator function because it's going to
measure the amount of time that it takes a particular function to run.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.