Hey guys, welcome today.
55 of a hundred days of code today.
We've got yet another jam packed day for you because we're going to be diving
right deeper into web development with flask. And along the way,
we're going to be learning some new concepts as well,
including how to render HTML on your website that you serve up using flask.
And in addition,
how to get hold of and pass the URL that the user typed in finally,
right? It also going to be looking into advanced decorators,
so decorators where we can pass in inputs as positional and keyword arguments.
And we're going to be doing some exercises around that.
But what all of this knowledge is going to culminate into is a guest,
the number of web, right? All right. When we go to the, a home route,
so just a single slash afterwards,
it asks us to guess a number between zero and nine.
And then if we type in eight guests into the path, let's say,
we decide to guess the number three, it tells us to low try again.
So this is HTML with styling with an H one,
as well as a gift being rendered. Now,
what if we try too high or, you know, a gift? And then finally,
if we land onto the correct number,
then we get a scene that tells us we found the correct number.
So that's the goal.
Once you already heard of it to the next lesson and let's get started.
Now, one of the first things I want to tackle is getting it out.
Hold on the user typed in too, the URL,
or rather known as parsing a URL in this case,
if the user typed in ww.mysite.com and then they had a forward slash with a
path, for example,
forward slash Angela or forward slash mail forward slash messages forward slash
pictures, then we want to be able to get hold of the information in that path,
because we might be able to do something different with it and render something
specific. Based on that URL previously,
we already saw that we could change the route of our website by serving up
different information. So if the user went to the home route,
which is just the URL and then a forward slash,
then we would show them something. But if they went to a different route,
for example, forward slash hello, then we could show them something else.
This is where we left off in our previous lessons.
If I wanted to create a BI function that just simply returns by
then I could set up the route decorator.
So this is the decorator function to look for when the user goes to a specific
path, for example, for what slash buy,
remember that this is a decorator function,
which lives inside a App Object,
which is declared in the flask class. Now,
if all of that sounded like it didn't make any sense,
then be sure to review the lessons that we did in previous days on classes and
methods.
I'm going to assume that all of this is pretty straightforward to you by now.
Now when we run this website,
we can now go to the URL and we can go to the homepage,
which says, hello world. And we could go to the buy route,
which just says, buy with an exclamation. Okay. What if we want,
I wanted to have a variable in that route.
What if we want to get hold of what the user types in him, for example,
let's say that instead of just catching by and forward slash what if we wanted
to greet our user,
let's say I create a greet function that takes their name and it returns
something like hello, but then it adds the name.
Let's turn this into an F string to make that work.
The question is how would we create the route?
Would it be forward slash name or would it be something else?
Well, this is what is described in this section of variable rules.
We can add variable sections to a URL.
So basically it's the equivalent of creating a variable that URL by marking it
with this syntax.
So putting some angle brackets around the variable name,
then all function is going to receive the variable name.
Once the decorator is done with it,
and then we can use it inside our function.
So for example,
let's say that we had a route which is forward slash username,
and then forward slash the actual name of the user,
which we'll put inside some angle brackets.
This means a flask is now going to turn, whatever it is that comes after.
Use a name forward slash into a variable for us to tap into.
And that variable has the name of name.
So now when our greet function goes through that decorator,
it's going to receive that value and we can use it in this greet function.
Now, if I go ahead and rerun my code
and go back to that URL and I go to user name forward slash,
and then I'll put in a user name, for example, Angela,
then that Angela is going to be taken and it's going to be rendered dynamically
into my webpage. So it doesn't matter what it is I put here.
It's always going to respond accordingly and treat this as if it was the value
to a variable.
Now notice how every single time we update our code. So for example,
if I didn't want this to be under the route forward slash username fall in slash
name,
instead if I just wanted to put it at forward slash name,
this is not going to work as it is. It's going to give us a four Oh four,
which is not found.
And the reason for this is because we have to stop and refresh all server for
these changes to be reflected.
So I have to stop and then rerun my server.
And now if I go to here and I start typing something like John,
then this update to the route is now live.
If we are testing and developing our website, this is really painful.
Having to stop and rerun the server every single time we make a change in our
server file.
So one of the things that you might notice here is that there is something
called a debug mode, and we can set this to be on or off.
Now there's a couple advantages of having the debug mode on and it's described
in the Quickstart. It allows us to activate the debugger,
which helps us narrow down on any issues.
It activates the automatic reloader so that whenever we edit off a file and hit
save, it's going to reload our server. And finally,
it also enables debug mode on the flask application.
Let's give that a go in order to change our app to run on debug mode.
All we have to do is to change right,
the debug property to true, right?
And now if I go ahead and rerun this application,
then you can see my debug mode is now on.
And I've got this debugger is active and also a debug, a pin,
which we'll come back to in just a minute. If I go to my website,
you can see that I can go there two, a route like this,
and it still works.
But if I was to change something in my code,
for example, just adding a new word into the return.
If I go ahead and hit command S on Mac or control us on windows to save this
file, then it will right.
Reload the server because it's tech did a change in that file,
and it's going to reload our server automatically so that we don't have to stop
and start all over again. So now,
if we go back over here and we refresh this page,
then you can see that update in the code is now reflected.
This is pretty neat. But in addition, we could also do other things.
For example, if we actually need to debug an issue, for example,
let's say that here in my variable path,
instead of saying name, I quote it username.
But then in my greed function,
I'm still trying to tap into this variable code name.
So now if I hit save,
it's going to reload my server and you can see that there's actually nothing
wrong with what I've done. This is all syntactically valid.
But if I go to my website here and I hit enter,
I actually get the flight task debug view.
So it's it actually telling me in this nicely formatted way?
What is the issue? So the main issue, right, is that I got a type II error.
Yeah, it happens.
If we scroll through the bottom is that the green function got an unexpected
keyword argument called username.
So that debugger might help us to figure out that, Oh, actually,
I've named this wrong.
Now this is an issue with the path here. But alternatively,
I could have made an error in my code as well. For example,
let's say that we want to take the name that's being passed in him.
We decided that we were going to add 12, two, it for some reason or other. Now,
if I hit save so that my server reloads and I tried to refresh this website,
you can see again, I've got a type II error. And this time though,
it's telling me that I can only concatenate string,
not an integer to a string. And if we go through these files,
you can see one of these lines, the first to a file that we wrote, hello, dot.
And it tells us that online 18 in the greet function,
this is the line. That's tripping it up. Now,
one of the things I can do at this point is I can actually open up the flask,
a debugger. And I do that by clicking on this button right here.
And what this is going to ask is for that pin that I showed you earlier on,
which is in our console.
This means that if somebody else is accessing your website,
live on the internet and you happen to have it in debug mode,
they can't just go and mess around with your code.
Let's go and scroll to the bottom and copy our debugging code and then paste it
in here as the pin, and then confirm to gain access to the debugger.
Now,
what it's done is basically its open up a console that is live on this line.
So now what I can do is I can print out for example,
the variables that it could access on that line, for example, name,
and it tells me that name is Angela. I can start diagnosing, well,
why is this wrong? So if I wanted you to add name to 12,
well I can narrow it down.
And it shows me that you can only add a string to a string or an integer to an
integer. You can't mix up the types.
So that might make me realize that actually I need to change this also to a
strength. Now,
if I go ahead and refresh,
you can see there's no problems there and I've managed to fix the problem with
the help of the flask debugger.
Now just a few more things on this URL.
One of the things that we could do is we could add some texts to the path
before. So you remember that I said username slash name. So that works.
We can also add paths afterwards.
So it could be one or two, whatever it may be.
And we can now access this route by going to our URL and then going to the first
part, which was username.
And then it was the variable that we could put in.
And then finally we can add even more to the path afterwards.
So we're in our case, the path is one. So now if I hit enter,
you can see it still goes to the same page,
but it's only this middle pot that's being taken as the value to this name
variable. Now,
if we go back to the flask Quickstart,
you can see that the final thing you mentioned is there is something called a
converter on the converter,
basically converts the URL into any data type that you specify by default,
it converts that variable value into a string,
which means it's going to accept any text without a slash. Now,
if you want to keep the slash, because if you are using a path,
then that might be quite important. So for example,
you wanted to get this entire part as your variable slash Juan.
Well then in that case, instead of using this, you would have to specify, well,
the data type is going to be a path and then I'm gonna save that as the name.
So now if I hit save and I use this same URL,
you can see the rest of that path is now being rendered in my variable and it's
being pulled in for whatever it is that I may need it for.
Now, alternatively, you can also have more than one variable, of course.
So maybe this first part, I'm going to keep it as a name,
which is a string. And then the second part, I want a number.
So maybe I'll keep it as the datatype integer and I'll give the variable a name,
a code number.
So now I can tap into the name and then I can also tap into a number like,
so now coming back here,
if I change this URL with a bit and I hit enter,
you can see it's taken this and placed it here.
It's taken this and placed it here.
So that's a quick little bit on how we can extract the parts that we want from a
URL by using these variable paths in the next lesson,
we're going to see how we can control the HTML that gets rendered instead of
just letting flask render what is the default.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now in the last lesson,
we talked a little bit about how to get different routes to work by using the
app dot route decorator,
as well as how we can create variable paths by using this angle bracket syntax
and how we can convert the path into a pre-specified data type by using this
particular structure. Now,
we also looked at how to run the App in debug mode so that we can auto reload
our server and also get access to the flask debugger. Now,
in this lesson,
I want to talk a little bit about how we can render actual HTML,
because at the moment,
what happens is we're simply just returning a string and we're getting flask to
do whatever it wants with it. And what that means.
If we go into the Chrome inspector,
by going to view and then developer and then develop a tools is we can see it.
It just stuffed that whole
F-string into a body tag without any real HTML tags that gives it structure.
So that's usually not what you would want when you're creating a website.
So let's see if we can start creating some HTML. Instead.
Now the simplest way to do this is flask actually accepts HTML in the return.
So we could just a simply say,
if we wanted to create an H one by adding an H one opening and closing tag here,
and if I hit save to refresh my server and then go to my home route,
then you can see this is now inside and H one inside the body.
Now, of course you can change this to whatever target is you want,
and it should still work. Now,
once we can start rendering HTML,
we can also start using the HTML attributes, by the way,
if any of this that I'm talking about HTML or CSS or attributes or tags sounds
unfamiliar, it might be because you've skipped the sessions on each balance CSS,
which we went through a few,
Two days ago. So have a quick search for that.
If all of this is confusing and it might be a good time to do a revision on
that. Anyways. Now coming back to my H one tag,
let's say I wanted to give it some CSS, which is just inline CSS.
So I'm going to set the style and give it some CSS code. For example,
I could set the text, the line CSS property to center,
and now if I hit save and I refresh on my homepage,
my text is now center aligned,
and you can see if I select this H one,
you can see that style being applied right here.
Anything that we can do with inline styling that you saw in the CSS modules or
changing the code to any sort of HTML tag we can do in the return.
Now, what if you wanted to render more than one HTML element? Well,
that's possible as well. All you have to do is just continue typing.
So let's say we wanted to create a paragraph tag. Well,
we could simply create it like this.
So if I hit save and refresh, you can see, this is my H one,
and this is a paragraph,
and this is the updated structure of my HTML file
now because pie charm doesn't really like you going too far over and creating
very long lines of code because it's difficult to read.
One of the neat tricks that it has is if you want to split a string at any
point, all you have to do is hit enter,
and it will add in this backslash for you,
which basically is the equivalent of the same code that we had before.
But it's now much easier to read.
So you can add in as many lines of HTML as you want in this fashion.
For example, if we wanted to add a another line,
then we would go inside the paragraph quotation Mark hit enter to insert another
line. And here we can add our image element.
Our image element is a self closing tags. We don't need the closing tag,
but it does need a source.
And this source could be a image that we find online.
So let's see if we can find a picture of a kitten.
This one looks pretty good.
Let's go ahead and copy the image address here by right clicking.
And then let's piece that in here as the image source. Now,
if I go ahead and hit, save and go back to my website and reload it,
you can see that is my little cat.
Now you can add other attributes, do the image tag. For example,
you can change the width to you only 200 pixels so that it would fit in to this
site a little bit better, or you can manipulate it in any way you want.
Now, the great thing about the image tag is we can also add gifts as well,
and it'll be rendered in our browser.
So Giphy is a great source of gifts from all over the internet.
So let's find an animated kitten on him.
This one is very cute. If we go to copy link and then copy the gift link,
and we replace this URL,
that's currently inside the source with this new URL,
then we would end up with our gift of being rendered as an image. Now,
one thing to note is that as we're changing these source attributes or the style
attributes,
the tax let's going in there is going in as a string with the quotation marks.
So this will clash with any outer quotation marks.
So be sure that if you've got a return as a single quoted string,
that in the middle, if you need to have quotes,
it will be double quotes basically has to be opposite of each other.
If you have single quotes on the outside,
then you're going to be using double quotes on the inside.
If you are using the opposite,
then it's double quotes on the outside that it has to be single quote on the
insight let's hit, save and see if this worked,
go back to our home page, hit refresh,
and you can see there is a fairy cute kitten being rendered in HTML from a flask
server.
So we've now leveled up a website a little bit more. We can now render HTML.
We can put an inline styling and we can add HTML elements to our heart's
content. Now in the next lesson, I've got a little bit of a challenge for you.
And the idea is for you to practice what you learned yesterday about decorators.
It's a bit of a advanced topic, but once you get used to it, it's really,
really handy. So for all of that and more head of it in the next lesson,
All right guys. So in yesterday's lessons that we talked about,
Python decorators, and we did quite a few exercises around that.
Now,
in order to test your knowledge and make sure that you haven't forgotten how to
use it, I've got a challenge for you to apply your knowledge of decorators.
Here's the challenge in this route that I've got here,
which is just forward slash bye.
One of the things that we learnt in the last lesson is that we can turn this
into an HTML element by simply wrapping it around HTML tags.
So for example,
if I wanted to turn this BI into a bolded,
by that I could add the B tag around it.
So now if I hit save and I go to my forest slash buy route,
then you can see that this text is now bolded. Like, so
now I can continue wrapping the text around more tags.
If I wanted a turn in a tallit, then I can wrap it around some emphasis tags.
So the EMT tag, and this will make it look like this.
And finally,
I can also make it underlined by wrapping it inside a you tag like this.
So now it's bold emphasized and underlined,
which looks like this. Now, what I want to do though,
is I don't really want to add all of this using strings because it's prone to
errors and it could be making typos, and it's just a bit of a pain to edit.
So what I want to do instead is under the first App dot route decorator,
which is important to identify the route to render what's in this method.
I want to be able to add some other decorators. For example,
let's say I added a decorator that I created somewhere up there called make
bolt. And if I hit save, you can see it's done the same thing.
It's added the B tag around that text.
I can also add some my other ones that I made earlier,
like make emphasis and make underlined.
So now I can add a whole bunch of decorators to my by function.
And once that's rendered, you can see it's got the bold,
it's got the emphasis and it's got the underline.
And that was much easier because I've got the auto suggest from PI jam.
And also I've got my decorator working in the background.
So your task is this,
your task is to create these three decorators,
which each will achieve the named effect.
So either making the text bold, making emphasize, or making an underlined.
So this is a bit of a revision and a bit of a challenge.
I'll let you pause the video and complete this challenge.
And in the next lesson, I'll reveal the solution code. Give that 10 minutes,
give it a good go and see if you can complete this challenge.
Previously, we looked at simple Python decorator functions.
And the reason why it's simple is because all that we're doing when we're
calling the function in the decorator is we're just calling it straight up.
But this doesn't take into account in the cases where, for example,
we want to add a condition before we called the function or even more advanced.
What if we needed to call the function with some sort of inputs?
How would we get hold of that? If it was inside a decorator?
So let's say that we had a class called user.
Now, if you are not familiar with classes,
I strongly recommend going back to the lessons where we covered classes and
Object in great detail.
We did over several days just to make sure that you're up to date with that
before you continue. But this is a pretty simple class.
All it does is it has two properties, a name, property,
and it is logged in property.
So basically what we're trying to simulate is a condition where let's say we had
a blog website and we had these user objects and the user has a username and
also some sort of property that keeps track of whether,
or if the user is going onto the website and not logged in,
or whether if they all have already logged in.
So certain methods on the website,
you can only be achieved by users who are logged in it's. For example,
if they wanted you to create a new blog post we'll,
then that user has to be checked.
And we have to make sure that they are in fact logged in and authenticated to
create a new blog post.
If I go ahead and create a new user from the user class,
then I can give it a name, which I'll put as Angela.
And then I could create the blog post and pass in my user.
Now, when I hit run, you'll see, this is Angela's new blog,
post being printed right here.
Now what if I wanted to create a decorator function that could be used to
decorate any function on our website that requires authentication.
So it requires that this users is logged in property is set to true.
So let's say that I decided to create my decorator function right here,
which I'll call the is authenticated decorator.
And this is of course going to need to take a function as an input.
And then inside, we've got our wrapper function.
Now inside our wrapper function is where we call this function.
That's the past and right here.
And finally to complete our decorator.
We have to return the wrapper as a function without the parentheses.
Now, in order to check for the is authenticated,
what we actually want to do is we want to say, well,
if the user.is logged in is equal to true will in that case,
we're going to trigger the function. But if it's actually not true, well,
then we're not going to trigger the function. Now,
the only problem here is that this user is undefined.
We were only able to pass in the function,
but what if we needed to pass in some arguments associated with that function?
Notice here that all function create blog posts, which is what we want to add.
The decorator to accepts an input in the form of the user. Object.
If I decorate this function with the is authenticated decorator,
and I tried to run this,
then it's not really gonna work because that user is not defined.
And it tells us that the wrapper function takes zero positional arguments,
but one was given.
And the one that's given is this user right here,
this era might already be a good hint for us to figure out how to fix this.
One of the things that we talked about in previous lessons is the concept of OGs
and clogs, unlimited positional arguments.
Normally all add it in as asterix,
OGs and unlimited keyword arguments are usually added in as two Astrix and then
Crocs. So now we can have all function,
which is decorated with this decorate to function.
And when we call the function,
we could provide some inputs and those inputs can be tapped into via these OGs
and Crocs. Now, in this case,
this is a positional argument and it's the argument App positions zero.
So instead of using this user, which is what we would do,
if we were inside this function, instead,
we would use the wrappers OGs,
and then we would use the position set to zero.
So now it's going to look at the function that is going to be passed in which is
going to have some inputs.
And it's going to take that first position input and then see if it is logged in
property is equal to true.
Now that my wrapper is taking positional arguments and keyword arguments,
and I can tap into the first positional argument by using Oxy zero.
Well inside the rapt function,
I can now also use this first argument in order to give it as an input to that
function.
Remember that this function is simply this create blog post function without the
decorator. Now, if I go ahead and hit run,
you will see that nothing happens unless I change this users is logged in
property to equal. True. And now that that's true,
then it's going to be checked right here.
And then it's going to call the function because that user is now logged in this
idea of being able to pass in positional arguments,
as well as keyword arguments,
by simply adding the odds and quarks to the wrapper function,
and then using it inside the wrapper or using it to call the function itself is
one step higher in terms of understanding Python,
decorator functions.
I recommend spending a few minutes looking at this code,
which you can access at this URL, which is in the course resources,
and then trying to recreate this functionality from scratch based on your
understanding of what we just talked about in the next lesson,
I've got a coding exercise for you so that you can try out this new advanced
form of Python decorators and try creating one yourself.