Hey guys,
and welcome to day 56 of 100 Days of Code. It's Angela here
and today we are diving deeper into web development with Flask.
We're going to be covering a bunch of things,
including how to include static files on your website
like local images or local videos,
as well as how to render HTML and CSS files. Previously,
when we looked into web design
and we learned about creating websites using HTML and CSS,
we were able to create it as a separate file with the proper structure and
styling.
And we want to apply that now to our Flask applications.
And we want to be able to show the user
a HTML website with CSS styling.
Now at the very end of today
we're going to be building out a beautiful personal name card application.
It's the 21st century and we no longer have to hand people name cards.
Instead, you could create a website,
put your name on it and have all the links to the relevant pages that you
need and to show off your beautiful design
as well as give people your contact details. That's the goal for today.
Head over to the next lesson and let's get started.
Now, the first thing I want to show you is how to render HTML files.
Go ahead and create a new PyCharm project. I've called mine my-personal-site,
but you can call yours anything you like. And in the project,
we're going to create a new file which is going to be our Python server.
So I'll call it server.py. And then inside our server.py
we're going to go through all the stages of building up a simple Flask server.
This might be a good time to revise how to do that. So go ahead,
pause the video and see if you can set up a simple Flask application
which just serves up hello world to the homepage.
All right. So let's start from the beginning.
We'll import the Flask class from the flask application.
And as usual, I'm going to use my red light bulb to install the Flask package.
Now, once I've done that,
I'm going to create my Flask application by saying app = Flask.
And then inside the initialization for my Flask application,
I'm going to put in the name of my current directory.
Next,
we're going to use the route decorator to target the home route.
And when the user hits up the home route,
we're going to render the home page.
So inside this definition,
we're simply just going to return hello world. And finally,
we're ready to go ahead and check to see if the name is equal to main, then in
that case we're going to run our app. That's it.
That's all there is to it.
Let's go ahead and run this application
which is our server.py. And if we head over to this URL,
we can see hello world when we go to our homepage.
The next step is to figure out how can we render an HTML webpage
which is crafted inside an HTML file rather than simply just returning strings
or small bits of HTML elements.
Let's go into our file and go ahead and create a new HTML file.
Now,
the reason why we creating it like this is because it's going to add in all of
the boilerplate code that is required to an HTML website.
So let's go ahead and call our web page index.html.
And you can see as soon as I create it, it's added in the doctype,
it's added in the HTML, the head and the body. Now,
if this is unfamiliar to you,
be sure to check out the lessons where we covered HTML and CSS in detail.
But I'm going to assume that all of this is pretty straightforward by now.
Now the first thing we're going to change in our new website is the title.
So I'm going to go ahead and give this a title.
You can put anything you want, but I'm just going to put my own name here. Now,
inside the body,
I'm going to create a h1 and you can see that the HTML files on PyCharm has that
tag completion that we see here. In my h1
I'm just going to write I'm Angela. Pretty straightforward.
This is a complete HTML file now. Now,
if I want to render this instead of just hello world, how would I do that?
Well, how do we find out? As always it's through
the documentation. In the documentation of the quickstart for Flask
there's a section on rendering templates.
And this allows us to render an HTML file as a template.
There's a couple of requirements though. Tthe first thing is that
remember that Flask is a framework and not a library.
So it will put certain restrictions and requirements on your code so that it
will actually work. And in this case, our HTML files,
which is known as our templates, must be inside a folder called templates.
That's where Flask is gonna look for it when we try to render it.
So let's first do that. Let's create a new directory
which we'll call templates, all lower case,
and let's move our index.html into that new folder.
So there is. The next thing we have to do is we have to import this method called
render_template from the Flask module.
So let's go back to our server.py
and in addition to importing the Flask class,
let's go ahead and import the render_template method as well.
The next thing we have to do is to,
instead of returning a string or a string that contains HTML,
we have to call this method render_template and pass in the file name that we
have and then that is going to be rendered into our website.
So let's go ahead and do this. Let's delete that hello world
and instead, let's return the output from this render_template method.
And inside here, we're going to put the name of our HTML file
which lives inside our templates folder.
That's going to be index.html because that's what we called it.
Now let's go ahead and run our code. Alternatively,
let's switch on the debug mode so that it will refresh and rerun our
server every time we make a change. So let's rerun
and now let's go to our website,
refresh the main page and you can see it's now got an h1 in here and in the
head, there is now the title, which is Angela,
which is the title of the tab as well.
Imagine if you had to type all of this HTML into this return as a string.
It's pretty painful.
It doesn't have any of the assistants that you get from your editor.
Now here's a challenge for you. Back in days 41 and 42
we learned about HTML and we created a CV website that looks something like
this, which we managed to publish and upload to GitHub. Now,
what I want you to do is to go and find your own CV website
and then go to the link either on your GitHub page or find the original HTML
file and I want you to go ahead and get hold of it.
So if it's on GitHub, then you can go ahead and simply save as
and save this webpage into your downloads.
Now, if it saved as a HTML file somewhere in your system, that's also fine.
But essentially what we want to do is we want to take this file,
which is an HTML file,
and we want to move it into our templates. Now,
one of the things that you'll notice is if you downloaded this file off the
internet,
then you might have to rename it because firstly it's really long
and we don't want to have to type that into our code.
So I'm going to shorten the name to angela. And then at the very end,
you can see the file extension at least when it comes off GitHub, is .htm.
And the reason for this is because some servers don't accept four-lettered file
extensions, but it's exactly the same as .html.
So we're going to change it to .HTML and then we're going to re factor that.
So now that we've got hold of this HTML page,
we're going to try and render it instead of the index.html.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this as a challenge.
Right.
All right. That's pretty simple.
All we have to do is just replace the index.html to the new file
which is angela.html.
And if that file happened to be inside a folder for example,
if we had a subfolder inside templates which we've called, I don't know cv,
and we had this inside here,
then we would have to specify that in the file path.
If we just have it in the top level of our templates folder,
then it's as simple as what we did with the index.html.
So now, while our server is running in debug mode,
we can go ahead and hit save on this website and it should restart our server.
And now if we go back to our main homepage and reload the website,
you can see it's now rendering our personal CV site with only one exception.
What has happened to this profile picture? It looks pretty broken.
Now in order to be able to render static images,
we're going to have to learn how to render static files
such as images like this. That's what we're going to do in the next lesson.
As we saw previously when we rendered the HTML page of our CV,
one of the components is an image tag and it has a image file that it needs to
render. But it looks pretty broken when we rendered HTML.
So if we go ahead and open up the Chrome developer tool
which is under view, developer, and developer tools,
then if we go to console
you'll see that we actually get a bunch of 404 errors and they relate
to the styles.css file as well as the angela.png file.
That is what this is referring to.
And you can actually see
we get the same 404 errors when we look at the debug log in here as
well. So we're missing some stuff basically. Well, firstly,
let's see if we can recover it.
We can go ahead and save this image from the website
which I'll just call angela.png.
And then we can drag this image into our personal site.
And there it is right there. Now, in my case,
my image actually happens to be a circular one
which I edited in Photoshop,
but you might just have a square one and it doesn't matter at all.
Now that we've got our image inside our project,
how do we make sure that that image actually gets rendered in our HTML site?
Because here is the image tag and it's looking inside Angela's personal site
files for angela.png, which is not what we have here.
In fact, if we had moved this PNG file to the same
folder so they're on the same hierarchy, basically inside the same folder,
well then we could probably just change this to angela.png.
If I go ahead and restart and rerun my server after I've added in all these
files and I go to my personal site and I hit reload,
you'll see that there's still no photo. So why is that? Well,
back to the Flask documentation we go.
The reason is because, just like our templates have to be inside a folder called
templates, Flask will look for all your static files
like your images or your CSS files inside a folder called static.
So you have to put it inside a folder called static.
They made the framework, they make the rules. So inside our project
my-personal-site, let's create a new directory called static and let's move our
image into that static folder.
Now inside our angela.html, when we want to point to that image,
then the path is going to be static/ the name of the file inside
that folder, which in my case is angela.png. Now,
if I go ahead and rerun my application,
then go back to my homepage and refresh,
you should see that image being rendered.
It was able to look inside the static folder and find that image.
Whenever you create a Flask application, 9 out of 10 times
you'll need to create it with the templates folder and the static folder.
And you put all your static files like your CSS files or your images or your
videos inside that folder
and your file path is relative to that folder.
And then when you create your HTML templates,
you're going to put it inside the templates folder.
Now going back to my project,
I'm going to delete all the extra files that we created just now in the demo.
Right.
And I should now only end up with my index.html
which is our simple website. Now,
the reason why I wanna keep it simple is just so that you really understand
everything from the ground up.
And the challenge I've got for you is to go ahead and create a CSS style sheet,
and then using the style sheet
change the background of the body of this index.html website to purple.
That's the goal. You are going to have to change the server.py,
you're going to have to change the index.html,
and you're going to have to create a CSS file.
Pause the video and see if you can complete this challenge.
Right.
All right. The first thing we're going to do is create a CSS file.
That is going to be a static file.
We're going to create it inside the static folder.
So I'm going to call it styles.css
and now I'm going to go ahead and target the body of my website to the body tag,
and then I'm going to change the background color to purple
like this.
So very simple CSS code here. Now that when it's run is going to target this body
tag which is basically the body of our website
and hopefully it's going to turn the background purple. Now,
in order for that CSS to work though,
we're going to have to add it into the head of our HTML file just as we've done
it thousands of times before when we did the lessons on CSS and HTML.
In order to add that in, we're going to create a link element
which is going to have a relationship. Now,
the relationship is going to be a style sheet.
So it's basically telling the HTML file that this link points to a style sheet.
And then the href of the style sheet is going to be inside static/
styles.css.
Now let's go ahead and save both of these files and go back to our server and
make sure that we're rendering that HTML template which is index.html.
And now if we go ahead and stop and restart this project so that it takes into
account all the new files, and then we go to our homepage,
hopefully it should show you a page that has a purple background
like you see here. Now,
one of the things you have to be careful about Chrome is that it likes to cache
your static files. So what does this mean? Well,
let's go back to the styles.css and I'm going to change that background-color
to red. Now I'm going to hit save on this file.
I'm even going to stop and rerun my file,
but you can see if I refresh this page, it's still purple.
And if I go into the Chrome developer tools and we take a look at our elements,
you can see that the body still has CSS saying that the background color should
be purple. If we go to the sources inside the static folder,
there's our styles.css. And you can see
this is an older version of our style sheet. So what's going on?
Is it because we didn't save this change? No, we definitely saved it.
What's actually happening is that to save your internet usage,
Chrome likes to cache the style sheets and other static files,
so images or JavaScript.
and the reason why it does that is because when you visit a website,
if you're visiting it on the same day,
these static files are unlikely to change.
A website is unlikely to update their CSS or their images over one day.
So once the browser downloads it,
it keeps hold of those static files.
This just means that you don't have to keep downloading these large files every
single time you hit up the same website.
That's kind of good if we are in fact visiting a real live website.
But when we're testing, it's a little bit confusing.
So one of the things you have to do is you have to get Chrome to hard reload.
And you can do that by holding down the shift key and clicking on this refresh
button, which is going to do a hard reload.
And it's going to get rid of all the cached files and pull in any new files.
So now the background changes to red. And we can confirm that by... let's change
this to blue hit save on that file, holding down shift, reload,
and we get the blue background updating.
So that's just something to be careful about when you find that your CSS files
or your other static files are not being changed or not being rendered.
All right guys,
it's time for another challenge to review what we learned in the last lesson.
Back when we learned CSS on days 43 and 44, the end project that we created
was a personal site that looks something like this.
It's beautifully designed with CSS styling,
images, gifs, and a whole lot more. Now,
what I want you to do is to take your version of this personal site and get it
to run with your Python server. And in the process,
you'll review what you learned about rendering HTML files
as well as serving up static files.
Hopefully, you've got all your files lying around somewhere in your computer.
If you don't,
you can go ahead and head over to the course resources where I've included a
link to download all of these files as a zip file.
Once you have unzipped that zip file,
you should end up with a folder that looks like this.
We've got our favicon, our CSS folder with our styles.css,
our image folder with all four images,
and you want to move these files to their respective places inside the personal
site.
Feel free to go ahead and delete the index.html and the styles.css
and see if you're able to use the files that you've got here to render it using
your Python server. Pause the video and give that a go.
All right.
So the first thing we need to do is to move the files in here to their respective
places. The index.html is going to go inside the templates folder,
but pretty much everything else is going to go inside the static folder.
So that includes the CSS, the favicon, as well as the images folder.
Now that we've moved everything in here,
there's actually nothing we need to do inside our server.py
because it's still trying to render a webpage called index.html,
which in our case, it's still called index.html. Now,
the thing that we do have to change though is inside our index.html
it's pointing straight towards css/styles.css,
and also for the favicon, it's pointing straight to the favicon file.
What we need to do is to take into account that it's now living inside a folder
called static.
So we're going to have to add the full file path to anywhere where we have a
local static file being used.
So that includes the CSS,
that includes the favicon, also any of the images that we're using in here.
And if you want for sort of convenience sake,
you can actually just copy this part
which is the source of the images and then you can hold down
Command+ R on Mac or Control + R on Windows to bring up the find and replace.
And we're gonna replace this with static/images/. So we're basically
adding static to this images/. And if we go ahead and replace it in all five
places, then we should now be done with all of our refactorings.
Now let's go ahead and restart our file so that it looks at all of these new
image, and let's go to our website
which is being served up by Python
and hopefully you have the same result as I do
which is the same personal site,
but now served up with our Python server.
Now this process has been pretty pain-free
I would say. We simply moved in the required index.html,
the CSS images and the favicons,
so all the files that make up a particular website.
And we simply added it to our Flask project.
Now,
what you can also do is you can get templates of HTML and CSS files from the
internet. For example, a website like html
5up.net,
where they have beautiful free templates that you can tap into.
Now consider if you were creating your own personal site,
then you can pick from all of these beautiful HTML templates
which you can then update and personalize. For example,
if we take this first one, we can go ahead and see it as a live demo.
So we can see this website as it is, and we can see how cool it looks.
It's got buttons, it's got JavaScript, it's got beautiful CSS styling,
and this might be a really good website for say, keeping track of our portfolio,
like the website's that we're building; to have images of the websites,
a link to the website, some brief description.
And then we could just put this up online and whenever we want to get hired as a
web developer, we could point people towards it.
So how do we make this work with Python? Well,
the first thing we have to do is simply hit download,
and it's going to download all of the files that make up this website.
Now remember that because we're getting it for free,
we need to attribute the designer who created this website.
If you don't want to attribute it and you want to use it for commercial use,
then you can pay just $19 and access all of their templates as well as support
from the creator. Now compare that to a service like Squarespace
where you're basically getting the same service templates for your website.
But in this case,
you're going to be paying anywhere between $10 to $30 per month
which is a lot more expensive, but it's great if you don't know web development.
But we're not going to be in that camp anymore.
Let's go ahead and unzip that file that we just downloaded,
which was called paradigm shift.
And we're going to try and transfer these files to our website over here.
So again,
I'm going to go ahead and delete all of the previous files that's inside my
static and templates folders,
...
and I'm going to try and move the relevant parts of this new website over.
So here, they've got an index.html,
a read me text and a license text.
So all we need is to move our index.html to the templates
and the images and assets over to the static folder.
Right.
Now, one of the things to note is when you're looking at the demo,
there's all of these beautiful pictures,
but of course the designer doesn't have the rights to these pictures to
distribute. So you'll notice that all the images inside the images folder
are these sort of gradients.
So don't be worried if when you run your website,
you just see a bunch of blurry gradients. It's not a problem.
Now what we want to do is we want to see if we can get this index.html to
work when it's being served up by our server. Now,
the first thing we can do is simply just restart our project,
rerun it and see what it looks like.
So let's refresh this static page and you can see it's got all of the HTML,
but no styling and no images.
So that is probably because we're not specifying the static folder in the path.
So here we've got our assets,
and here we've got an image, but they're both inside the static folder.
So we can do that quick trick with find and replace.
So for anything that's inside the images folder,
we're going to replace it with static/images and for anything that's
inside the assets folder,
we're going to replace it with static/assets.
Right?
And now if we go ahead and hit save and refresh this page,
you can see it's now rendering the images as these sort of gradients
and it also rendering the styling and CSS. Now,
how would you edit this? Well, the easiest way is of course,
to actually just edit this raw HTML.
So you can take any of this HTML and you already understand what most of it
does. You've got tables, you've got headings, you got h1s,
all sorts of tags in here.
And you can edit it just like that. For example,
if we scroll up to very top,
we can change the title to a name for example,
Angela's portfolio. And we can change the h1
which says paradigm shift to our own name for example.
And now when I hit save and I refresh over here,
you can see all of that being reflected.
Now there's an even better way of editing HTML in Chrome.
All thanks to the Chrome developer tools.
If we open up the Chrome developer tools and go to the console,
we can actually type a little bit of JavaScript to make anything on our webpage
editable. So to write this, we tap into the document
which is this entire HTML document, and then we tap into the body
which has everything inside the body tag, which is the content of the website.
And then we can call on a property called contentEditable,
and we can set that to true. Now note here that in JavaScript,
the true booelan is spelled out with a lower t, not capital T like in Python.
But the rest of it is pretty standard code
and we can all understand that. Now once I hit enter and that goes through,
I can close down this pane and now watch this.
I can now edit anything that's on this website.
Cool.
All of these paragraphs or any bits of text is now completely editable.
Now, what if you want to delete some of these elements,
what would be the easiest way to do that? Well,
you can simply open up the Chrome developer tools,
and then we can use this little button here to select any element.
So maybe we want to get rid of this paragraph here, select it,
it locates it in the HTML and I can just hit backspace. So I can select any part
of the HTML elements that I don't like for example,
if I want to get rid of this whole section well I would select it and then
delete it.
Maybe I could delete some more sections and make this a lot simpler.
Now you can see this website just has two sections,
my name and my contact details.
One of the unfortunate things though,
is that all of the changes that you're making here, even though you can see it
and it's great, as soon as you hit refresh,
all of those changes will disappear.
And the reason is because when you hit refresh,
what's happening is your browser is going to your server at this address and
requesting all of the HTML and CSS files,
which of course comes from over here.
So this is unchanged by what we've done just now,
it's completely not changed at all.
So if you want all of these changes that you've made in the HTML,
then what you have to do is actually save this webpage as it is.
And then you can move this HTML into your templates
and you can see that this is now a lot shorter with all of the changes that we
made previously.
And you can replace this with what's inside your index.html.
This is probably one of the easiest ways of modifying a prebuilt template.
And you can see that there's plenty of templates for you to play around with.
In fact, in the next lesson, when we're creating our final project,
you're going to be editing this identity template completely from scratch.
And you are going to be creating a digital name card.
So have a play around.
And once you're done, head over to the next lesson and complete the final
project.
All right, so let's go ahead and run through the solution.
The first thing I'm going to do is to head over
to the website and download the template.
Once I've downloaded the template,
I'm going to unzip the file and get access to all the files inside.
Now I've already set up my Flask server
which is pretty simple by now. I've created my app,
I've set up the home routes and I've set my app to run on debug mode.
Now I have to create the necessary directories.
So I'm going to need a directory called templates,
and I'm also going to need one called static.
With those two folders in place
I can now start moving over the relevant parts of these files; index.html
goes into templates, assets
and images go into static.
Right
Now,
one of the first things we're going to try and do is just to see if this works.
So we're gonna start up our server and try to render that index.html.
And if you've got another project running in the background
which is using our server address,
then you are going to get an error that says address already in use.
So just make sure you stop any other files from running and then run this again.
So here's our webpage with just the HTML. It's very,
very simple, and it doesn't have any of the styling or the images.
So we're going to have to fix that by going into the index.html and figuring
out which parts of it need to be changed.
Now notice that in the download, we got two folders;
assets and images which are now both inside static.
So we're going to have to find and replace anything that is assets and change
that to static/assets,
...
and also do the same with images,
right?
There's actually not a lot of code in here.
You can pretty much scroll from the top to the bottom and you can see there's
not a lot of stuff here.
So now that we've fixed those paths,
let's see if we can hit save and go back to refresh our website.
Now, if you are getting what I'm seeing here
which is the CSS file being rendered from the previous project where we got hold
of the portfolio site, that remember is because the CSS file is a static file and
it's being cached by the Chrome browser. So as I mentioned before,
you have to hold down shift and hit refresh in order to get the new static files
to come over. So now that we've got all of this,
it's time to actually edit the text and the links. Going into here,
we can see that here is the h1 which we can change quite easily,
...
and you can of course add your hrefs to these links for Twitter,
Instagram, Facebook,
copy your Twitter URL and change the Href here to that
if you wish.
And you can change the footer as well. Now,
remember because we didn't buy these templates and we're using it for personal
use, we should really attribute the source where we got it from.
So I'll just leave that as it is. Now, if I hit save,
you can see I've pretty much updated all the text to what I want.
And you can see that this avatar image has disappeared
and the reason is because when I was doing the finding and replacing,
I wasn't careful enough
and I didn't add in the final trailing slash
which should in fact be right here.
So this is going to now render the avatar image.
But of course at the moment,
it's just this blank gradient image inside the images folder.
So what we can do is we can simply replace it with our own image.
So, here in my downloads folder, I've got an image called angela.png.
So I'm going to move my own image into the images folder and refactor that.
And then back in our index.html,
I'm going to point towards that image by changing this file path.
So now I can go ahead and delete this avatar image.
And if I hit save and go back to my website,
you can see my photo now shows up inside the image.
The next thing I want to add is a background image under this gradient here.
So one of the best places to find great images for commercial use is a website
called Unsplash.
So if we look for some sort of image that we could put as the background,
maybe a beach or a sea,
you can see there's thousands of images that you can choose from.
And they all look incredibly beautiful, and they're all large, all HD.
I've decided to go with this picture of the seashore.
And if I go ahead and click on download free,
it should download the large JPEG image onto my computer.
So now I'm going to go ahead and rename that image to
the same name as the original background image
which is just a bg.jpeg.
Right.
Like that.
And now I can delete this file and replace it with my own background.
So remember that the background image here it is actually being rendered from
the CSS files.
And if you look inside the main.css you can see here where it sets the
background image,
it's actually generating a gradient and it's overlaying that on top of something
inside the images folder called bg.jpeg.
So instead of changing it all over here,
all we just did is just name our image the same as what they had before.
Now, if we go ahead and rerun our website,
go back to our website and hard reload,
remember by holding down shift and clicking on the reload button,
you can see that image has now been brought in behind this gradient.
Now the last step is to change that title so that it says our name instead of a
placeholder text. So let's go ahead and change the title
...
to our name and there we have it.
We're now serving up this beautiful website
which we got completely from a template that somebody else's developed.
And all we needed to do was to have enough understanding of HTML,
CSS and how Python servers work in order to customize it for our own purposes.
I hope you enjoyed building this with me
and I hope you'll look through some of the other templates and start messing
around with some of them to create your own custom websites.