Hey guys,
welcome to Day 6 of 100 Days of code. And well done from making it this
far.
So today we're going to talk about code blocks and indentation as well as
functions and also a different flavor from the for loops that we saw yesterday.
Today
we're going to talk about while loops as well. And to learn all of these things,
we're going to use the help of something
that's very similar to Karel the robot.
And this is something I use when I first learnt how to code
and it's one of my favorite tools for learning programming
especially as we get into more difficult concepts like functions and while loops
et cetera. And by the end of the day, we're going to be writing the code
that's required to instruct our little robot to be able to complete any
randomly generated maze. So that's the goal
and if you head over to the next lesson,
let's get started and let's start learning about some of these things.
The first concept I want to introduce you to is something called functions.
And just as we perform many different functions could be mother, father,
son, daughter,
we can also get our code to perform different pieces of functionality.
Now, if we think back,
we've actually already come across functions and I've been referring to them
every time we've needed to use one.
If you take a look at this link in the course resources
which takes you to the Python documentation,
then you can see that Python has a whole bunch of built in functions that we've
been using. For example, the len function,
which gives us the number of items in a collection or the int function
which turns something into an integer or the print function,
the range function, and other ones that we haven't seen yet.
If you head over to the Day 6
starting Repl.it and go ahead and forward a copy of it.
Then we can start typing one of the functions that we've been using a lot,
which is the print function.
And the reason why we know it's a function is because it's the name of a
function followed by a set of parentheses.
Now we know that if we put something inside these parentheses,
say, for example, hello, then when I run the code,
whatever is inside those parentheses
will get outputted over here in the console.
Now all of the functions work pretty much the same.
So if I wanted to use the len function to see, well,
how many characters are there in this word Hello? I, again,
put my hello inside the parentheses because of the parentheses
we know that this is a function and then I can save the outcome of this length
function to a variable, say,
let's call it number of characters, num_char.
And then I can go ahead and print it in order to view it inside the console.
So let's print the num_char,
and now you can see that this len function gets to work, calculates the
number of characters, it's five, and then it gets printed.
So all of this functionality has been achieved by these built-in functions from
Python, like print and len.
Now what if we wanted to make our own functions?
How would we do that? Well, if we want to make our own function,
we first start out with a keyword,
which is called def.
And this is because we're creating or defining our function.
Now, after the def keyword,
we can give our function a name and I'm just going to call it my_function.
Now, the thing that differentiates a function from a variable, however,
is the parentheses. So after the name comes the parentheses,
and now the final thing,
the finishing touch to our function definition is a colon because that says
everything that comes after that line and is indented belongs with the
function.
Let's make a really simple function that just has two lines of code.
Maybe it prints Hello and then it prints Bye.
So now I've created my function,
I've placed the lines of code that are associated with this function all indented
after the definition. But notice how,
if I go ahead and run my code, actually nothing will happen.
And the reason is because we haven't yet executed the function.
Now we can define lots and lots of functions ahead of time.
And it's only when we actually need it
do we go ahead and trigger it and to trigger it or in programming lingo,
we would say to call the function,
all we have to do is type the name of the function,
which is my_function
and then to add the parentheses and any necessary inputs. In our case,
our function doesn't require any inputs so we can leave the parentheses blank
again. And now if I go ahead and run my code once more,
then you'll see that by the time the computer reaches line 5,
it's going to search for this thing called my_ function.
It sees that it was defined right here on line 1
and it goes through all of the content and executes them in turn, line by line.
And that's why we get hello and bye being printed here.
So just to recap, this is how we create a function in Python.
There's two steps to it. The first step is to actually define the function,
to specify what it should do.
And we do that by first using the def keyword and then we give our function a
name. So for example, in this case,
I called it my_function and then comes a set of parentheses and a colon.
And then after that, we get to put the lines of code
which will be included in this function. And remember that these lines of code
which goes into the function
which will be carried out when this function is triggered
must be indented like this.
So once you've defined the function, you've created the recipe,
the next step is to actually use it, which in programming lingo,
we would say calling the function. And we call the function just by specifying
the name and a set of parentheses.
And once the computer sees this line of code it'll know to go and carry out all
the instructions inside
where we defined our function. And to learn about functions,
I'm to introduce you to something that's very similar to Karel the robot.
The robot is going to be something that is just going to perform the tasks that
we want it to, and no more and no less.
So for example,
if we wanted a robot to go to the store and pick up some milk for us,
we can't simply just tell it, Oh yeah,
just go and buy some milk because it won't know how to do that
unless
we give it specific instructions such as leave the house,
walk two blocks to the right, walk four blocks back and then two blocks to the right.
When you go to the store,
give them some money and then take the milk and come back.
We have to program each and every step. But say,
if this functionality of getting the robot to go and pick up some milk for us is
needed every single day
then we have to write out all of those instructions day after day,
day after day. And at some point our fingers are going to hurt, right?
We're typing so much code that's repeated because we don't have a way of bundling
all of those instructions together. And that's where functions come in.
Functions will give us a way of referring to all those instructions
at the same time.
That way we can give our robot a single instruction and it will carry out all of
those little steps for us and get us some milk.
Now to try this out yourself,
I want you to head over to the course resources and click on the link that takes
you to Reeborg's World.
Now Reeborg's World is very similar to Karel the robot that I showed you
earlier on,
but it allows us to write Python code. And it's very easy to get started.
Now we've got this area here which we're going to use to write our Python code.
And then once we're done, we can click on play to
run the Python code and see the instructions carried out by our robot.
But if you click on Reeborg's keyboard,
you can see all of the functions that we can use to command our robot,
like move or turn left, or build a wall, et cetera.
Let's see if we go ahead and run this line of code here, move.
What happens? When I click play
you can see that our robot moves forward in the direction that it's facing by
one step. So if we wanted it to move, say for example, three steps,
all we have to do is the call the move function three times.
Now let's reset by clicking the return button to return our robot back to the
starting position.
Now let's click play again in order for our robot to carry out the new
instructions.
Notice how all the instructions were carried out very quickly. To execute each
instruction one step at a time, line by line,
we can use this step-through button.
This button allows us to see how each instruction is executed and after each
instruction, it pauses and highlights the next instruction.
This is very helpful for debugging.
So notice how we're highlighting line 2. So if I click on step again,
it's going to carry out that function and then it's going to carry out line
3 and finally it reaches the end.
And that's the end of our code. Now,
in addition, we can use some of the other commands in the keyboard
for example, turn left.
If I decide to say move three times and then turn left and then maybe move three
times again, can you predict which square the robot is going to end up in?
Are you ready? Let's go ahead and run the code. There we go.
We end up on the square 4,4.
It moves three forwards turns left and then moves three steps again,
because that's what we told it to do with our Python code.
So now here's a question. If you take a look inside the set of commands,
you'll notice that there is move and there is turn left. But there is no turn
right and there is no turn around.
So how could we use a function to create those commands?
Because, of course, we could just simply write,
turn left and then turn left again.
And this would effectively turn the robot around, right?
But if we want to do that many times, say for example,
if we wanted to go to three, turn around, go back to one, turn around,
go back to three, then we would have to write code that looks a bit like this.
We would have to say move
two times to get to square three, turn left, turn left,
and then move two times again to get to one and then turn left,
turn left again in order to turn around.
This is all the code we would have to write to achieve this kind of effect.
But instead of all of this, we could just define a new function.
So we use the def keyword to say that this code is defining a new function
called turn_around
and this function is simply going to be turn left twice. And remember, all the
code that's going to go inside the function has to be indented.
And now instead of writing, turn left, turn left,
we can simplify our code by telling it to call the function,
turn_around, and we can do that here and we can do that here.
So now when we run the code,
you'll see that it does exactly the same thing as before,
but this time we've cut down two lines of code.
So instead of eight lines of code for our instructions,
we only now need six lines.
And you can see that the more that you need to use this function,
the more typing it will save you. But more important than reducing
the number of lines of code is that our code has also become a lot more
readable.
So the turn_around function is much more clear than having turn left twice.
Now let's see what happens when we use the step through button.
Look closely at how each line in our code is executed.
So now what we're going to carry out the move by one, move by one
and now it's going to call turn_around, that function. And it jumps over to find
this function and carries out the code inside in turn from the top to the
bottom. So turn left, turn left. And now once that function's done,
it goes back to where it was before and continues running, move, move,
and then turn around again.
So here's your challenge.
Try and create a separate function that turns our robot to the right.
Pause the video,
head over to the course resources and click on the link that takes you to
Reeborg's World
and then go ahead and create your own function called a turn_right.
Right.
All right.
So this should be pretty simple because all we have to do is to define a new
function called turn_right
and this function is going to simply be turn left three times
Right?
because turning left three times is going to effectively turn our robot
right.
So even though we only have this one way of turning our robot,
we can define our own functions to give it many,
many other commands that it could use.
So now using this turn right function,
see if you can write some code that makes our robot draw a little square going
from here to here then to here and back to the beginning.
Once you're done and you hit play, this is what should happen.
So pause the video now and see if you can complete that challenge.
Right?
All right. So let's go from the beginning.
We start out facing right at the position 1,1
one in order to draw the square, starting from this way,
we have to first turn left
and then we have to move one step and that should take us to here.
And now we have to turn right, move
one more step, turn right again,
move one more step and finally turn right for the last time and move one more
step.
So using our awesome function means that we don't have to right out turn left
three times each time we need to turn right.
So our code can just be eight lines long instead of 14 lines long
and we're using our function to cut down on a lot of typing.
But not only are there fewer lines of code,
look how much more readable our code has become thanks to our turn right
function. It's now so much easier to read, turn right,
and understand what it needs to do rather than seeing turn left three times in
the code.
So now it's easier to read and it's easier to follow the logic in our code.
In the next lesson,
I've got a challenge for you. Head over there and apply what you've learned
about functions to try and solve it. I'll see you there.
All right. So now that you've learned about functions,
I have a coding challenge for you. If you head over to this link,
which is in the course resources and head over to this challenge
which is called Hurdle 1,
the idea is that we've got a robot here which needs to do a number of hurdles to
jump over each of these barriers, to get to the final goal here.
Now you need to use your knowledge of functions
as well as some of the things you've learned before, such as the
for loop or the range function, to be able to achieve this.
Now, remember that you can tell the robot to move by typing, move(),
and when that's run, it will move by one space.
And you can also use, say,
turn_left to get the robot to turn left.
And in this case, when I run the code,
it's going to move one space and face to the left.
In order to complete this entire challenge,
you can see there's a number of steps that the robot has to go through before it
can get to this final goal. And if you were to write out each of these steps,
like I have done here one after the other, it would take many,
many tens of lines of code. And that's not what we're about. We're programmers.
So we're born to be lazy.
Try and see if you can minimize number lines of code while still keeping your
code readable and understandable by somebody else and be able to get your robot
to complete these instructions and take the robot to the final goalpost.
And once you've completed the challenge successfully,
you should get a green popup that says you're at the correct X and Y position.
So pause the video now,
head over to this link and give this challenge a go.
Right.
All right. So how did you get on with this challenge?
How many lines of code did it take you to tell this robot to get to the goal?
All right. Let's have a think about how we might tackle this.
We know that out of the things that we can tell the robot to do, the most useful
things are to move and to turn left.
But because the robot doesn't have a builtin turn right function,
then we have to define that ourselves.
And the reason why we need to do that is because you can see that at several
points during the hurdle, we'll have to turn right. For example,
when the robot is here at 2, 2, it will have to turn right,
and then move and then turn right again and then move.
So let's create a new function called turn_right.
So we start out with the def key keyword and then give our function a name which
is going to be turn_right.
And then we add the parentheses with nothing inside
because we're not passing any inputs to this function.
We're just going to use this function as a way of defining turn left three
times. So when you turn left three times, of course you turn right.
And now we have the ability to turn right.
So notice how this is the code block for our turn right function
and it ends at the last line, which is indented, which is line 4.
So every subsequent line
which starts at the very beginning of the code file next to
the left margin is outside this code block and it will act independently.
So in fact,
the first line of code that actually runs in our file is going to be this line
6. And you can see that when I press run,
you can see that's the first thing that gets highlighted.
And if I go through this step wise,
you can see the first line is going to be line 6 and it tells the computer to
go and find this function called turn_right. So if I skipped to the next step,
it's found that, and it's going to start going through lines 2, 3,
and 4,
turning our robot three times until it has turned right. Now that we have the
ability to turn right,
let's have a think about how we might be able to get our robot to make one jump.
Let's see. The first thing we'd probably want our robot to do is to move forwards
by one step, which should take it here.
And then the next thing we want it to do is the turn left so that it faces the
top.
Right?
And once it's in this position,
then we want to get it to move forward one step,
and then we'll probably want it to turn right. Now,
notice how I'm actually testing my code at pretty much every other line that I
write.
And this means that you don't end up in a situation where you get to the end and
you've written lots and lots of lines of code, and it doesn't work.
In which case you have to comb through all of the code you've written and find
out where the problem is. So in this case,
we've only got four lines and we've been testing it step wise.
So we can see that we're on track and our robot is now turned to the right,
ready to move one more step.
And then once it gets to here,
we have to turn right again and move one more step.
Right?
And now it should end up here, but let's just check it out.
So our robot turns left turns right, turns right again.
And it ends up here facing the bottom.
So the final thing we need to do is to get it, to turn left once more,
so that it will face the forward direction.
Right?
So once you've confirmed that your code is working,
then you should really think about what is the next step,
because we've managed to make one hurdle. And notice how,
when we're at this position, 3,1, this particular square,
it's almost the same as if we were at 1, 1,
because we have to move one step again, turn left, move, turn right, move,
turn, right, move, turn left.
So it's basically repeating all of these instructions, rather than executing
these instructions six times, because there are six hurdles.
So if I go back and I start,
then you'll see that this code actually will complete the challenge.
Right?
It says I'm done. And we're at the correct position,
but notice how many lines of code we've got.
We've got something like 58 lines of code.
I know I've left some spaces in their so that you can see which parts are
repeating, but still that's a massive amount of code for something very simple.
Now we know that we can use functions to package
a set of instructions together under one name,
just like what we've done here with the turn_right.
We've packaged the three lines of code turn left, turn left, turn
left into a single function called turn_right
so that when we need that functionality, all we need to do is just the call
the function and add the parentheses at the end.
So we can do exactly the same thing with this set of instructions,
which basically gets our robot to perform a single jump.
So let's create a def and let's call this function jump.
And then lets add the parentheses and the colon. And very importantly,
all of these lines of code must be indented. So to indent
a whole block of code together,
you hold down the command key and click the left square bracket or the right
square bracket. On windows it's holding down the control key and again,
the last square bracket or the right square bracket.
So now this basically says that all of these instructions live inside this block
of code called jump. And when we call jump,
then it will carry out all of these lines of code.
So now what we could do to complete the challenge is to simply call this
function jump six times.
Right?
And so now we could again solve this entire problem using just 21 lines of code.
And we managed to complete this challenge using two functions that have repeated
instructions and then calling the jump function six times.
But because we've learned about loops and the range function,
we know that we can actually cut this down even shorter.
So instead of calling jump six times,
we could actually write a for loop that loops through and calls this jump
function
six times. We could say something like for step in,
and remember that these two key words come from the
for...in loop and they always have to stay the same.
And then after the in keyword,
we define the rules for how many times we want our loop to repeat.
In my case, I'm going to use in range function.
And I'm going to say from 0 to 6,
but not including 6. So in this case it will be 0, 1, 2,
3, 4, 5.
So that actually going to happen six times.
And now I'm going to add the colon. And finally,
inside this for loop,
I'm going to call jump just once. Now,
watch what happens. First it starts off at the for loop,
it calls jump and it goes through this once and then it comes back loops again,
calls it the next time. And then again,
the third time in the loop, fourth time in the loop,
fifth time in the loop and six time in the loop.
How far did you manage to get?
Did you get stuck on this section where we needed to create the for loop?
Well, in that case,
I recommend going back to the lesson where we covered for loops and reviewing
the for loop and the range function in detail before you come back and try to
solve this challenge again. It's really,
really important at this stage that you've understood and you've mastered some
of these ideas because we're going to be using them more and more in the future.
Really make sure that you've understood things before you keep going.
In previous lessons,
I've already mentioned how important it is in Python to be aware of your
indentation. So we know that when we create a function like this,
that every line that comes after this definition
that is indented is going to be inside this function.
So by indented, I mean
it's shifted to the right by four spaces like this.
So if you imagine each dot as a space, then this is a single block of code.
And if we want to continue adding to this block of code inside my function,
then we would continue adding lines of code, which are indented.
So you have to almost visualize for yourself this invisible line around these
blocks of code, which are indented. Now,
if my code was written like this on the other hand,
then the block of code is in fact only this part. And this print statement will
not get triggered when this function gets triggered because it's independent
from this function because it's not indented. Now, a simple way
that I like to think about this kind of indentation is kind of like the file
structure you see when you go into finder on the Mac,
or when you go into Explorer on Windows.
If we have a function,
it's kind of like a folder and anything that goes inside the function,
for example, if I throw this file inside the function,
then you notice that it gets indented, right?
And this way it shows to you very,
very clearly that these two files print-
hello and print-world are living inside this folder,
my function. And this is the equivalent of this code.
We have this folder say, my_function, and it contains these two lines of code.
Now, on the other hand,
if I take this print world and I put it outside of the function folder,
then you can see that this is completely independent from that folder.
And it's now indented at the same level as the function.
So this is the equivalent of this code, where we've got this print-
hello being inside the
my_function and this print-world being outside and at the same indentation level
as this function definition. Now,
the indentation gets a little bit more complicated when we have other blocks of
code. So for example, the, if/elif/else statements.
They have blocks of code,
which need to be indented to be inside the block.
For loops need to be indented to be inside the loop.
And it's very important that you get used to looking at blocks of code like
this. So for example, if we were to expand our simple
my_function and add a whole bunch of code into it,
then we would have to indent all of those lines of code by four spaces
represented by the four dots here. Now, if we wanted to have
another block of code inside this if statement,
then this line has to be indented,
a further four spaces.
So this is the function block,
this is the if block,
this is the elif block and you have to be able to see all of this while just
looking at the indentation. If we wanted to represent this,
then it's almost like creating a new folder. Let's call it the
If sky == clear.
And this if block goes inside my function, so it's indented.
Now, if I wanted to have a print statement,
let's call it print-blue inside this if statement.
So this is what should be executed if this function gets called
and if the sky is equal to clear, well
then this line is indented twice.
And that is the equivalent of four spaces in our code, like this.
Now, every time I've talked about indentation,
I've been talking about spaces and actually there's two ways of creating
indentation. You don't have to just use spaces.
You can also use tabs and that's created using the tab key on your keyboard,
which can look a little bit like this.
Now there's a lot of debate around spaces and tabs where some people prefer
using spaces to indent, other people prefer tabs to indent.
And there's a lot of people arguing in the coding community.
And I think this excerpt from one of my favourite shows really demonstrates this.
Richard what's wrong? Nothing, nothing, literally. It's all good.
Come on. Oh my God. Your roommates are right. You really hate spaces.
No, no, no, no. I don't. It's not hate, hate is a strong word. Um,
truth be told I do have a slight preference for tabs,
but that's only because I'm anal
and because I prefer precision.
Well, not to pick a fight here,
but if you really care about precision why don't you use spaces?
But whatever, once it goes through the compiler, it's the same thing, right?
Yeah. Yeah. Technically, yes.
Right.
I guess I just, I just don't understand why anyone would use spaces over tabs.
Like if it's all the same,
why not just use tabs? Because it could look different on other people's
computers. Tabs create smaller file sizes. All right.
I run a compression company. Trust me.
I've devoted my life to minimalizing file sizes. It's what I do. I mean,
I do not get why anyone would use spaces over tabs. I mean,
why not just use VIM over Emacs? I do use VIM over Emacs. Oh, God help us.
Okay. Uh, you know what? I just, I don't think this is gonna work.
I'm so sorry. Uh, I mean like what,
we're going to bring kids into this world with that over the head.
Stuff's not really fair to them. Don't you think? Kids?
we haven't even slept together. And guess what?
It's never going to happen now because there is no way I'm going to be with
someone who uses spaces over tabs.
So should you be using spaces or should you be using tabs?
The age old question and the extent to which people obsess over this question,
it really shows in this 2017 Stack Overflow developer survey,
where they are asked the developers, do you use spaces or do you use tabs?
And then they compare it against their annual salary
and somehow have managed to show that the people who use spaces seem to earn a
lot more than the people who use tabs.
Now the official guide from the Python community is in fact to use spaces.
So if you click on the section, tabs or spaces,
they tell you in no uncertain words,
that spaces are the preferred indentation method.
And in fact, in Python 3,
you can't mix a code file that uses tabs and spaces for indentation in the same
file. And it also tells you that in order to indent a line of code,
it should be indented using four spaces,
so four hits of the space bar. Now,
for a lot of people, that may seem quite inefficient because I have to hit my
space bar
four times in order to achieve a single indent.
And you've seen how much we indent throughout our code. So it seems very,
very inefficient.
But luckily in most code editors,
they actually have a setting that allows you to indent using spaces,
changing the indent size to four.
And when you hit the tab key,
it will automatically insert four spaces,
which you can tell when you're trying to highlight this space,
you can see the cursor is jumping four times.
This means that you get to hit tab once and that your code is in line with the
guidance because the hind the scenes
your code editor is inserting four spaces.
So I hope that clears up a little bit on tabs versus spaces.
And I highly recommend you to head over to the course resources and click on the link
to go to the style guide for Python code and take a look through the parts about
indentation. Now in the next lesson, I've got a quick quiz for you
to test your knowledge on indentation. So for all of that and more,
I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right guys, in this lesson
I want to talk about the while loop, the loop that will continue going while a
particular condition is true.
This is a really simple version of a robot that's using a while loop.
So in this case,
the instruction would be while you are plugged into the wall and you have
electricity move forwards. So this is what happens.
It will stop once it pulls the socket out of the wall and it stops receiving
electricity. Let's compare this against the
for loop that we've seen before. So we've seen sort of two flavors of the
for loop: one where we're looping through a list of items to do something with
each item in the list,
and the other is using a range function where we create a range between a and b
and then we use every number in that range to do something. For example,
in this case would be to print it out. The while loop looks
something like this. And in this case,
while this particular condition is true,
then we go inside the loop and we do something repeatedly.
And it's only when the something becomes false does the loop stop.
So let's take a look at what the code would look like in real life.
So here I have the Hurdle 1 challenge that you did previously.
And for this
we created a for loop in order to get our robot to jump over the hurdle six
times to get to the final destination.
Now we could also do the same thing, but using a while loop.
And this is how we would do it.
Let's say we create a variable called a number_of_hurdles,
and we set that equal to six because there are six hurdles.
And then we use a while loop to loop through these hurdles until this goes down
to zero. So we can say while number_of_hurdles
Right,
> 0:
and then we get it to do something. Well in this case,
what we need it to do is to perform the jump function.
And at the end of the loop, just before we go back to the beginning,
we're going to decrease the number of hurdles,
Right
by one., -= 1.
So now let's go ahead and delete this version using the for loop. And in order to
better visualize what's happening here
I'm actually also going to add a print statement to print that variable.
Right?
So now let's step through this.
And the first time we enter the while loop, number_of_hurdles equals six,
six is greater than zero.
Then that is a go ahead to jump into the loop and execute these three lines of
code. So now we go in and it performs the jump function.
And then once that's done, it comes back, goes onto the next line,
number_of_hurdles minus equals one, so six should become five.
So now when it executes this print function, we should see five printed.
So lets move this little pop up away on the side and let's keep going.
So now it's gone back to the beginning of the while loop and it's testing this
condition once more: is the number of hurdles, five, still greater than zero.
Well, so if it's true,
then it goes into the while loop again and performs all of those lines of code.
So now it's minus one and it should now be four.
And it keeps on going until the point where this condition number_of_hurdles
greater than zero becomes false.
So now this is the moment where we're going to subtract a further one from our
number of hurdles, which is currently one.
So that should take it down to zero. And once that's done,
this condition is no longer true. Zero is not greater than zero.
Zero is equal to zero, but it's not greater.
So now this is false and we exit out of the while loop and we end our program.
This is what the syntax for the while loop looks like. First,
we have the while keyword and then we have some sort of condition that we're
going to test.
So previously you saw it was number of hurdles being greater than zero,
and whenever that condition is true,
then it's going to look inside the while loop at the indented lines of code to
carry out those instructions, to do this, then do this, then do this.
And finally, when it gets to the end of the while loop,
it comes back to the beginning and tests this condition again.
And if it's still true,
then it's going to go through and loop and loop and loop until this condition
becomes false at which point it ends an exits the while loop.
So now coming back to our Reeborg's World,
I want you to click on this dropdown and go to hurdle number 2.
Now this is a little bit different.
And if you want to see the explanation for this exercise,
then simply just click on this 'World Info' and you'll see the explanation.
So essentially this hurdle's race is a little bit different from the last one.
Whereas the last one
we knew that we had to always complete six hurdles to get to the goalpost.
In this case, we no longer know where the flag is going to be.
So it could be here, it could be here, it could be here, et cetera.
And it's going to be set randomly to one of these positions.
But what we now get is some sort of condition called at_goal.
And if this at_goal is true then it means our robot has landed on a flag.
But if this at_goal is not true,
then it means that it's not yet reached the flag.
So we can use our knowledge of while loops as well as this condition to use our
code that we had from previously to get our robot to complete this hurdle race.
So you should still have the code from the previous challenge up
and all you have to do is to think about how you would create a while loop so
that when you run this program and the flag is set randomly...
So this time it was set to be here, but the next time I run it,
you can see it's now set here. It doesn't matter where the flag is,
your robot should be able to detect if it's at flag, if its at the goal,
and if it's not then it should continue jumping.
Pause the video quickly and see if you can complete this challenge and then come
back and we'll walk through the solution together.
Right?
All right.
So first things first, we know that we're going to need to use a while loop and
the condition that we're going to be testing for is this one, at_goal.
This condition can be true or it can be false.
And basically we're looking to see while at_goal is not equal to true,
so while our robot is not at the goal,
then we want to perform the jump function.
So we're going to jump for as many times as it is required until this at_goal
becomes true.
Another way of expressing this at_goal is not true is to say while not at_goal.
So this is what they mean by the negation of this condition.
Either way of testing this will work. And now if I hit run,
you can see that even though we only need to perform one hurdle,
as soon as our robot gets here and it checks that at_goal is true then it will
stop this loop.
But if our loop goes on for much longer, say the goal is over here,
then once it reaches here and at_goal is still false,
then it's going to continue jumping until at_goal becomes true.
So that required a little bit of mental jujitsu
I think because this entire condition has to be true,
but this at_goal is actually going to be false until the moment where we
reached the goal. So by adding this not
we effectively flip this at_goal. So if it was true,
becomes false or if it's false becomes true in order to continue jumping while
we're not at the goal.
I prefer this particular type of syntax because it reads more like English: while
not at goal then perform jump.
And if it is at_goal then it will stop.
And one of the things you might be wondering right now is,
so I've learned about the for loop and I've learned about a while loop.
And if I can use both of them, why would I choose one over the other?
When would I use a for loop? And when would I use a while loop? Well,
what I would tend to say is that for loops are really great
when you want to iterate over something and you need to do something with each
thing that you are iterating over. So for example,
if you're iterating through a list and you're saying for each fruit in our list
of fruits and you want to be able to say, I don't know,
do something with each of these items in here. For instance,
it can be as simple as just printing it. Well,
then this will require a for loop.
You can't do this very easily using a while loop. Now,
similarly we've used the range function, right?
So for range from one to six print each number in the range.
Well this it's also easy to do with a for loop.
Now you want to be using a while loop when you don't really care what number in a
sequence you're
in, which item you're iterating through in a list and you just simply want to carry
out some sort of functionality many,
many times until some sort of condition that you set.
And this is also a good point to mention that while loops are a little bit more
dangerous than for loops because in for loops, you're setting ahead of time
how many times something is going to run.
It's going to stop once it reaches the end of the list of items in this case,
and it's going to stop once it reaches the upper bound of the range in this
case. But for while loops,
they will continue running until this particular condition switches to false.
So if you have some sort of condition that actually never becomes false, well
then your while loop becomes something known as an infinite loop. Because let's
say that our while loop tested while five is greater than three,
then carry out these three lines of code. Well,
five is always going to be larger than three until the end of time.
And so that means your code is also going to run until the end of time,
which is probably not what you want in most cases. If
instead of saying, while not at_goal, I said, while five is greater than three,
then you're going to see this robot perform this jump until eternity.
And it's basically going to stop only once it's crashed and timed out.
Now every single program at some point in their lives will create an infinite
loop. Don't worry about it. Just quit the program,
restart and try to prevent this from happening in the future.
And very often I find that it's really helpful when you don't know why you're
getting an infinite loop to simply just print out your condition.
So in this case, if I printed out five greater than three,
then it's always going to print true.
And it's never going to become false basically. In the next lesson,
I've got more exercises coming up for you, namely hurdles 3 and 4.
So head over there and put what you've learned about while loops into practice.
All right guys, it's time for yet another coding challenge.
And this coding challenge is going to put into use what you've learned about
while loops,
while also testing some of the previous knowledge you got on functions.
So I want you to head back to Reeborg's World and change to hurdle number 3.
And take a look at the premise for this particular race.
Right?
Essentially what's happened this time is that the wall placement has become
random. So let's say we restart this game, you can see that in this case,
there's a wall here, one here, one here, one here. There's four in total.
But if we try a different version,
then you can see that there is different wall placement each time.
Not only don't we know where the wall is going to be,
we also don't know how many walls there will be.
So code such as what we did before using a for loop
telling our robot to jump six times is not going to work.
And instead, we're going to have to use the conditions
whether if front is clear or whether if there's a wall in front or whether
if we're at the goal and also their negations,
so not front is clear, not wall in front,
not at goal. See if you can use what you've learned about while loops
as well as your previous knowledge on if statements and functions to complete
this challenge. When you have written the correct code,
no matter what kind of wall situation or hurdle setup they have,
it should always be able to get to the goal.
And while I've been looking at this challenge, I know there is a very,
very simple way of bypassing this challenge,
which is simply to get the robots go up here and all the way down here,
going past all the hurdles.
But that's not the point of the challenge. In order to complete this challenge,
you must get your robot to follow the path that set out in the dotted lines
instead of bypassing it and doing something completely different
just to get to the final goal. Pause the video, have a think about this,
have a read of the world info popup here,
and then think about how you can solve this challenge. So give it a go now.
Right?
All right. So essentially, if we don't know where the walls are going to be,
then we have to test to see if there is a wall in front,
or if there is no wall in front.
And if there is a wall in front, then we're going to jump.
But if there's no wall in front, then we're just going to move forwards.
And we're going to do this and test this for as long as we're not at the goal.
So we're going to need a while loop
that's very similar to our previous while loop that I showed you in the demo. While
we're not at goal or rather while
this particular condition is not true,
then we're going to repeat and loop some lines of code.
The first thing we're going to do is we're going to use an if statement to check
whether if there is a wall in front.
So I'm going to say, if wall in front,
if this is true,
then I'm going to perform the jump function and get it to jump over the wall.
But if there is no wall in front, so namely else,
well, in this case, we're simply just going to move forwards.
And because our jump function is always going to get us to face the right way,
which is this direction here towards the goal,
then this move forward by one function is always going to take us in this
direction.
So let's take a look at this code and let's step through it step by step.
So the first thing we're going to check is are we at the goal. At_goal is going
to be false. So not false is going to be true.
So while this condition is true,
we're going to carry out all the lines of code inside.
So that means we should jump into this if statement and check
is there a wall in front? So at this point,
this should be false because there is nothing in front.
So it should bypass the if statement and it should go to the else statement.
In which case it should move forward by one step. So that's the end of one loop
and we go back to the beginning: are we at the goal yet? Nope, we are not.
But now when we run into our if statement,
this check should now come up as true,
because there is a wall right in front of our robot. So in this case,
it's going to go into the if statement and perform the jump function.
Now our jump function that we defined previously actually gets us to move
forward by one step first,
before we actually hurdle over this wall. So in this case,
if we try to do the same thing,
then it's actually going to hit our robot into a wall.
We have to modify our jump function by removing this first move function.
So instead we get it to just turn left, go up, turn right,
go right, turn right, go down and then turn left to face the right direction.
This is a pure hurdle without that extra step in the beginning.
And instead we're going to only move if there is no wall in front.
So we've changed the code.
Let's back it up and try this again with a different setup.
And in this case, you can see as my code is going through the different steps,
it's checking to see if there's a wall in front. If there is,
then it's going to jump over it. If there isn't,
it's just going to move forward by one step and then it's going to reevaluate.
So this way, once it gets to here,
it's actually going to reevaluate the while loop quite a few times
and every time it's going to be the else statement that fires.
It's going to move, move, move, move, move until it hits a wall again
and then it's going to jump over and take us to the finishing line.
Did you manage to get this correct? Did you manage to get the solution right?
If not be sure to review the previous lessons on the while loop so that you
familiarize yourself with it
and also if you got stuck on changing the jump function,
then be sure to remember that whenever you get stuck,
it's important to test your assumptions. And in this case,
you could have pressed the step-through button many times to see which line of
code is being triggered at which point,
and which is the moment where our code actually fails
so you can figure it out and fix it.
Now on the next lesson, I've got yet another code challenge for you.
So head over there and give it a go.
All right guys, it's time for the final hurdle
before we get to our goal post. In this lesson,
I want you to switch over to the final hurdle challenge, which is hurdle 4.
And in this particular version of the hurdle,
the wall that the robot has to jump over to now has a variable height.
So the height of each of these hurdles is completely random,
the position of the hurdles are random
and also the number of hurdles is also going to be random.
You can see that every single time that this regenerates,
it comes up with a completely different set of hurdle profiles.
And now we can't just jump because we don't know what the height will be each
time.
So we have to use what we've learned about while loops to modify this jump
function and see if we can get the jump to jump as high as necessary
depending on the height of these walls. Just as a reminder,
in order to complete this challenge,
you should take a look at the Reeborg's keyboard window and go to this tab called
conditions and see that you can check if the front of the robot is clear,
if it's right is clear, if there's a wall on the front,
if there's a wall on the right and various other things.
The ones that are probably going to be the most useful is this top row here.
So I want you to take a look at these conditions,
see how they're spelt and how you can use them,
and then try to use them and test them out using your Reeborg robot.
Now, the goal is of course
to reach this final flag going over various hurdles
using this dotted line as the path, which is going to be different each time.
Just as a head up, this is going to require you to modify this jump function.
Have a serious think about it because it's not easy
and you're going to need to use more while loops to achieve this end outcome. And
try to see if you can solve this challenge in the least lines of code possible.
So I managed to do it in as little as 24 lines of code,
so see if you can aim to achieve that.
Pause the video now and give this challenge a go.
Right?
All right.
So the key difference between this particular hurdle and the previous version is
that the height of the wall is now random. Instead of just jumping over one
square, where we turn left, move, turn right, move, turn right move,
we have to now see if the right side has a wall,
or if it's completely clear. Now, in this case,
what I want to happen is I want to turn my robot to the left first of all,
and then I want to check if there is a wall on the right.
So I can use this condition wall on right to achieve this.
And if that is true,
then I want to continue moving forward until there is no longer a wall on the
right, in which case I'm going to turn right turn right
and then start going down. So let's modify this jump function.
We definitely need the robot turn left, but after it turns left,
we're going to use a while loop to say that while there is a wall on the right
then in this case, we're going to move forwards.
So we're going to go up in this direction basically
because we've turned left already.
Let's test this out and let's run this code.
You can see in this version of events,
my robot is going to keep going until the very end of the screen.
This is not what we want.
So what we want to do is when this is no longer true,
it's going to skip to line 10. So at this point,
there is no longer a wall on the right,
because otherwise it would have continued looping and calling this line 9
where it gets it to move forward. When there's no longer a wall on the right,
then we want to do what we did previously
which is to get our robot to turn right move,
and then turn right. Now at this point, we have to move down the wall.
And what we're going to check is whether if the front is clear,
because it's only when we reach the very bottom here, when the front is blocked,
do we actually turn left again and continue back to our while loop here to move
forward. To do this we're going to add yet another while loop.
And in this case, we're going to use the front_is_clear condition.
While the front is clear,
we're going to get the robot to continue moving forward.
So once it's turned to face this direction, and there's no wall in front,
it's going to keep going until this is no longer true.
And that is the end of our jump.
So now we've basically modified this jump function to take into account all of
these new things such as while there's a wall on the right
then continue moving upwards, while the front is clear when it's coming down
then continue moving downwards. And then at the very end,
we're going to get our robot to turn left so that we're ready to go and check if
we're at the goal. And if we're not at the goal,
then we're going to check if there's a wall in front,
if there is a wall in front that we're going to jump,
otherwise we're going to continue moving forwards or rather to the right to get
to the goal. So now this is the final code.
And depending on the number of spaces you've added in here,
obviously it's a little bit easier to read if you actually have it like this.
But depending on how you've spaced things out in your code,
you should end up with anywhere between say 20 to 24 lines of code.
So I want you to be able to see all of these lines of code on the right when we
run this code.
And I've actually got a typo in here that it's going to tell me.
So it's going to say invalid syntax
and the problem is just because I forgot a colon here. If you get that
pop-up invalid syntax
be sure to check if you have any problems in here and it can get a little bit
complicated if you leave your code for a long period of time before you test it.
So test your code after every little iteration
and then when you actually get something like an invalid syntax,
you'll be able to catch it more easily.
So now let's go ahead and regenerate our map and let's try it again.
So when we're going to make a jump and then we're gonna turn right,
and we're going to keep going down until we hit the wall and we turned left,
and now we're not out the goal, and there's still a wall in front.
So we make another jump and we go down this much, much larger wall.
And then we continue this process of using several while loops,
checking if there's a wall on the right, checking if the front is clear,
checking
if there's a wall in the front in order to achieve our goal and get to our final
destination. Now for your code to successfully complete this challenge,
the line that your robot draws should follow the line that started here,
just like what you see here.
So instead of going just over the top and getting to the final goal,
it should follow each of these steps and finally
you should get that green pop-up where it says it's at the right position.
So did you manage to complete this challenge?
If not, be sure to review the lesson on while loops and just have a play around
with while loops.
Try some of the different conditions and see what happens when you run the code
and see how the robot behaves so that you get a good grasp of how these things
actually work.
Now on the next lesson is our final project and we're going to get our robot to
be able to navigate a maze all by itself using what we've learned
including functions as well as while loops, as well as using good indentation.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right guys, it's time for the final project of today.
And the goal is to be able to write some code here in Reeborg's world,
to be able to get our the little robot
to be able to navigate to the goal and go through a maze
no matter what the maze look like. So if you go back to Reeborgs world,
if you already got a link open..
if you don't, then simply click on the direct link in the course resources
and it should take you here.
And we've got the maze selected in the dropdown, which is right here.
Here, we have a maze. And even though the maze doesn't change,
the robot does. The direction that the robot is going to face is completely
random, the position of the robot is also random.
So you can see every time I restart the game,
it will face a different direction. So in this case, it's facing up
But the next time it might be facing down, in this case.
And it's also always going to start at a random location in the maze.
If you click on the world info,
it will tell you that the secret to getting the robot to complete the maze is to
get it to follow along the right edge of the maze.
If it starts anywhere in the maze and it just continues following along
the right wall,
it should eventually get to the final destination.
For example, like this. Now in this case,
the robot is not making a beeline straight to the exit as if it could see what
we can see, but it is following a strategy or rather what you would call in
programming, an algorithm.
And the algorithm here is to simply follow along the right edge of the wall.
And if the right side is clear,
then continue going right until it's no longer clear at which point it should
just go straight. And if you can't go straight and you can't go right,
then the last option is to turn left.
It's almost like the robot is getting a set of instructions in terms of
hierarchy. The most important telling it to turn right if it can,
if it can't turn right then go straight ahead. And finally,
if it can't turn right or go straight ahead,
then to turn left as a last resort.
So you're going to need to use a lot of the functions that you saw previously
such as move, turn_left, and testing
whether if the front is clear or the right is clear,
or there's a wall in the front or a wall in the right. And whether
if the robot is the goal. Think about how you can use a while loop
and also the conditional
if, elif, else statements to achieve this goal and get our robot
to be able to go to the final destination
no matter where it starts out and what direction it's facing.
Pause the video now
and try to use what you've learned to complete this final project.
[inaudible]
All right. So did you manage to complete this challenge? If not,
let's work through the solution together. The first thing we need to do,
which we've always pretty much needed completing each of these challenges, is we
need a way to turn right. So I'm not gonna type it all out again.
This should be already pretty clear; turn_right
is just turning left three times. Now,
the next thing we need to do is we need to tell the robot to do things and to
check for things until it reaches the goal.
We know that we have this test called at_goal.
So we can use a while loop to get the robot to continue working until it reaches
the goal. To define that, we could say while not at goal,
so basically keep repeating the instructions inside this while loop until at_goal
becomes true and not true is false.
So once this condition becomes false, then our while loop stops.
So what we were told in the world info is we should follow along the right edge.
We should test to see if the right side is clear, and if it is,
then we should turn right and go straight.
So that basically means moving right.
Let's use an if statement to test
if right_is_clear and in this instance,
so in this if block, we're going to say well turn_right
using our prebuilt function up here.
And then once you're facing the right then move forwards.
This should achieve a right move, so from here to here
for example.
Now let's test this and see what happens. In this case, the right is clear
so it moved right The right is not clear
so it doesn't know what else to do
and it's now stuck in what we would call an infinite loop.
And it will never stop until the browser actually forces it to by crashing.
So what we have to do instead is we have to provide an alternative condition;
when the right is not clear, what should it do?
So we're going to provide that condition by using an elif statement.
And what we want to say is if the right is not clear,
well, then maybe you should check if the front is clear.
And if that is the case, then simply just move forwards.
Now, this would work unless we're in the situation that we're in right now
where we're boxed in
and the only side that's clear is actually the remaining one, which is the left.
That's why we have to put in the last line of code
which is going to be an else statement. So in all other conditions, um,
when the right is not clear and the front is not clear,
so once both of these have been checked and they're false,
then actually just turn left.
So now
you can see that when our robot is able to go right,
it will try to follow along the right wall.
But when it can't go right, it will go forwards instead.
And when it can't go right or go forward, then it's gonna turn left
and hopefully the next time it checks the loop,
the front will be clear and it will be able to move forwards.
So notice how our robot is somewhat haphazardly navigating through this maze,
but it is following the algorithm that we specified,
which is to follow along the right-handed wall until you reach the goal.
And that's what these few lines of code does using our while statements, our if,
elif, else statements and also our turn_right function.
Now, while everything seems to work all right,
there are select cases where the robot might start out in a position and face a
particular direction that gets the robot into an endless loop.
So here's an example.
Let's say the robot starts off at this particular position facing down.
If we go ahead and let the robot run the code,
you can see that firstly, there's over a thousand steps in the code.
And what happens is because the robot doesn't have a wall on it's right,
it's going to keep looping through the circle because after all we're telling it
if your right side is clear,
turn right and move. And the right is always clear when it's inside this
boundary box. So depending on where the robot starts out,
it might get itself into what we call it an infinite loop,
because you can see the code just goes again and again,
through this while statement, and the robot's never going to be able to escape
from this position.
So this is one of the things that happens to your programs.
Sometimes there are edge cases which you might not have thought of
but it's only through testing the code do you discover them.
Now this particular issue I would say is more of an intermediate debugging
problem.
So if you're somebody who's already really comfortable with Python and you want
to try out debugging this particular problem,
then I've included some problem worlds for you to test your code against.
Now,
if you are somebody who is still getting to grips with Python,
I would say this is not the right time point to tackle this challenge,
and I would go ahead and make a note to yourself that once you've completed day
15 and you're firmly within the intermediate territory of Python to come back to
this problem and to continue to debug this particular edge case.
Now, if you are a beginner, I recommend to skip the rest of the video
but make a bookmark and make a note here so that you know to come back. Now,
if you are more of an intermediate programmer,
then let's go ahead and debug this.
So what you can do with Reeborg's world is you can actually create a file to load
up a particular map and robot position.
So what I've done is I've created a bunch of problem worlds for you to test your
code against that we know if you use a normal code,
it's definitely going to get into an infinite loop.
So what you need to do is head to the course resources for this lesson
and then download the zip file
which contains three problem worlds for you to test your code against.
And then in Reeborgs world, you're going to click on additional options,
open world from file and you're going to select that folder
which hopefully you've unzipped, and go through each of these problem worlds
testing your code in all of the cases. Now, when you open this up,
you can close off this box and the robot will start at a particular problem
position, facing a direction that is going to cause it to go into an
infinite loop. And you can know this ahead of time
because when you actually go to start the robot and you hit play, when you
see the number of steps here over a thousand,
it usually means that you're probably in a situation where it's going to turn into
an infinite loop.
So write your code here and then test it to make sure that the step count goes
down below 1000 and your robot doesn't get stuck in this endless circle. Now,
because the different problem worlds can have different solutions,
but what you're aiming for is one solution code that solves all of the problem
worlds,
I want you to test your code against all three of these problem worlds I've
created for you.
So here's the time, if you want to tackle this challenge, to go ahead and pause
the video and see if you can debug this pretty hard problem.
It took me a while. So I think it's going to take you a while as well.
But you might be smarter. It might take less time. So good luck,
pause the video and we'll go through the solution together a little bit later
on.
All right. So first let's try and figure out what the problem is.
The problem here is that every time when the robot's right side is clear,
our code tells it to turn to that direction, move forwards,
and then check to see if it's at the goal. So it's not, and again
the right side is clear so it turns right and moves, turns right and moves,
turns right and moves. So basically in any of these four positions,
depending on the way it's facing,
there might not be a wall on the right side of the robot.
So that is the key to solving this bug.
We have to get our robot to a starting position where it has a wall on the right
side of the robot.
Now I've been thinking about various ways of doing this and the shortest most
succinct way that's also most understandable, I think, is this.
So if we create another while loop before this while loop runs,
so remember the code goes from top to bottom,
it's going to hit this while loop first.
And we check while the front is clear,
well then the robot is not next to a wall, right? Such as in this case.
Well, if that is the case, we're going to tell our robot to just move forwards.
So this means that our robot is going to seek out a wall. So in this case,
for example,
it's going to go forwards until it reaches a wall.
So it's going to loop through that loop twice and it moves twice until it hits a
wall in front. Now this is the point which we want,
because we want to make sure that now that it's hit a wall in front,
that it's definitely got a wall on the right side of the robot. So what do we do?
Well, once it's hit a wall, so it's exited this while loop,
we're going to tell it to turn left.
So this loop makes sure that the robot has a wall in front of it.
And once it's found a wall in front, we tell it to turn left
to turn that wall on to the right side of the robot.
So now you can see we're going through this while loop. First front is clear,
so it's going to move.
And then front is still clear after that one move
so it's going to move again until it's hit a wall in front. Now,
at this point,
it exits the while loop and it goes to the next line of instruction
which tells it to turn left. Now that the robot has turned left
it now has a wall on the right side and it enters the next loop.
So in this loop, if the right side is clear, turn right and move.
If the front is clear, just simply move forward, otherwise turn left.
So as long as the robot started in a position where there is a wall on the right
side of it, right next to it, it's never going to get into that infinite loop with
this code. So this is one solution to this problem.
Now there's lots of other solutions,
but you gotta make sure that your solution works in every single one of these
test cases.
So we can go ahead and open up problem world 2 where the robot starts at a
different position, facing a different position,
and we want to make sure that still we don't have an infinite loop. In this case,
it doesn't. So that's great. And finally, let's test the last one,
which is a problem world 3,
and now we can run our program and you can see it's also less than a thousand
steps. So, it works.
So this is a bit of advanced debugging because we're now testing our
code against various terrible scenarios where the robot starts off at a position
where it's really dangerous and can get into these infinite loops. Now,
if you didn't manage to get the solution,
don't despair and don't be too hard on yourself. This is a really,
really hard one.
And it took me a long time to find a solution that I think is readable and
explainable and sort of makes sense.
Now, it might be that you should put in a note in your calendar to come and
revisit this issue in a week
once you've had some time to think about it, and to really digest and understand
the solution, then write the code yourself.
Because you would have forgotten exactly what the code was,
but you will still remember how it works. So if that is a case,
this is what you should do. If you solved it by yourself, then congratulations.
This is really, truly quite a difficult task.