Hey guys,
welcome to Day 7 of 100 Days of code.
Now,
today we have a whole day dedicated to a really cool project.
And what we're going to be building throughout this day is basically Hangman or
the code equivalent of this game.
So the way the game works is you have to guess a word and for every wrong
letter you submit,
you end up taking a life away from this little man. And of course,
the longer it takes you to get to the word,
the more you put your little man in danger.
This is what the final completed project is going to look like.
We're going to have some really cool ASCII art like this hangman logo up here
and it's going to ask us to guess or a letter. So let's try A,
and you can see that's not in the word.
So we lose a life and it starts drawing our little hangman.
So let's try another letter, E. There's a lot of Es in there.
So we managed to get that. Let's try a T,
Right?
And I think I know what the word is now just before my little man is going to
die. I think it's beekeeper. There we go. We got it.
So if we had lost just one more life,
the leg would have been added and we would have lost,
but we managed to get there in the end.
So this is what the completed game looks like and how it plays out.
And you can go over to the final URL and run the code and see it in action if
you want to. But just by building this game,
we're going to be able to review and test ourselves on a bunch of concepts that
we've already covered,
like for and while loops or if and else statements, lists,
strings, the range, function, modules, and much, much more.
So I hope you're as excited as I am to get started on this project,
and once you already head over to the next lesson and let's begin.
All right guys. So before we get started with our project,
it's really important that we're all on the same page and we understand how the
code is going to work because we know how the game works.
So I recommend that if you've never heard of this game hangman,
then before you continue to just head over to the Wikipedia article on hangman,
and it might be even easier if you select your own language
because I know that it has a different name in different languages. Now,
if you've never played this game,
I always recommend just go and give it a go online.
So a link to this address, and if you click on single player untimed,
you can see that you have a word that you have to guess,
and then you start picking some letters. And if it's right,
then it goes in and if it's wrong,
then the hangman gallows start being drawn and our little man is at risk of
being hung. Once you understand how the game works,
it's time for us to examine what the logic for our program is going to look
like. And to do that, we're going to use flow chart programming.
So it's very simple.
It just means that we can draw out a flow chart to represent the logic of our
game. At this point,
I want you to pause the video and have a quick think about how you would program
hangman.
Try and come up with a flow chart that represents the logic of this game.
Break it down into little steps. What needs to happen first,
what needs to happen when the user makes a guess, and what should happen when the
guest is incorrect, when should the game end? Pause the video
now, take a pencil and a piece of paper, or use draw.io to create your flowchart.
Right?
So how did that go? Did you break down the problem?
It's really important to say that there's no single right answer here.
And there's loads of ways that you could have done this,
but let me show you my approach,
which is how we'll write our program over the next couple of lessons.
So this is what it looks like from start to end.
And if we zoom in a bit, let's go through this flow chart
step-by-step so we're all on the same page. At the start of the game
the first thing we do is to generate a random word. Let's say, in this case
it was the word mouse.
Now the next step is to generate as many blanks as the letters in the word.
So we have these blanks to show the user
how many letters are in this word that they need to guess. They don't get to see
this, but they get to see this. And the next step they get to
guess a letter.
So let's say the user in this case guessed the letter O. Well,
the next thing we have to check is, is the guessed letter actually in the word?
Well, in this case, o it is indeed in mouse.
It's the one at the second position.
And so we go down this path and we answer yes to that question.
So now we to replace that blank with the letter O.
Now the next stage is we have to check are the blanks filled, are all of these
blanks removed because in that case,
it means the user is guessed all of the letters correctly? Well at the moment,
it's definitely a no, cause we've only guessed one letter.
So then we go all the way back to the beginning and we ask the user to guess
another letter. Now at some stage of the game,
all the letters will be guessed. And then we can answer yes to this question,
which means it's game over. The user has won because they've guessed all the
letters correctly. Now,
if we go back to the part where we ask the user to guess a letter,
and they guessed a letter, say the letter z
which doesn't actually exist in this word mouse, while then in this case,
we go down this right path to answer no
and the user loses a life,
which means we start drawing out a hangman figure. Now,
depending on whether if they have run out of lives,
if the hangman man has been drawn completely, then they would go down this path.
But at the moment they've only lost one life and this figure is not complete
so the answer is no.
And that means we go back to the beginning and we get them to guess the next
letter. Now,
if at the stage where they've exhausted all of their lives and the hangman
figure is complete, well, then it's the end of the game
and they've basically just lost without having guessed
all of the letters in the word. So this is the logic,
and you might need to come back to this video a few times
if you get stuck along the way just to review how the program flows.
But it might also be worth creating your own flow chart or simply downloading
this completed flowchart I have here in the course resources.
It's a really useful tool to come back to and refer to as you're writing the
code,
because this will give you an overview of what you're trying to get your code to
do.
And hopefully this is going to make it easier for you to complete the upcoming
challenges in this project. Once you are ready, head over to the next lesson,
and let's get started.
All right guys. So to get started head over to the starting Repl.it file
which you'll be able to find in the course resources,
and you should see a pretty much empty file as well as three to-dos for you to
complete. All I've got here is a list of three words,
ardvark, baboon, and camel.
And we're going to be choosing a random word from that list
and then we're going to ask the user to guess a letter,
and then we're going to check if that letter matches one of the letters in the
chosen word.
So we're basically just tackling the first part of this flowchart up to about
here. Once you've completed all three to-dos here,
you should have something that will function more or less like this.
So this is the end result of step 1
and it should ask us to guess a letter. So let me try a.
And it shows me that this a matches with the first letter in the word,
as well as the fourth letter in the word.
So I'm pretty sure that the word that it picks randomly was actually ardvark.
Essentially, your code is gonna loop through each of the letters in the chosen
word,
and then check it against the word that the user entered and report back
whether if it matched any of the letters in the word. Now,
if you need a hint,
then head over to the course resources and you'll see a link that's marked as a
hint. And once you click on it,
it'll take you to this page where it talks about how to use the for loop
with a list in Python. Have a read through the section and then go back,
try to tackle the to-dos and see if that helps you. All right.
So have a play around with the final version and once you're ready,
go-ahead fork a copy of the starting file for day 7 step one,
and tackle the to-dos one by one. Good luck.
All right.
So how did you get on? Now if you got stuck or you want to see maybe how I did
it, then continue watching and I'll go through the solution with you.
So first things first, head over to the link and fork your own copy.
Once you've done that, we're going to tackle the to-dos one by one
in order. The first one
asks us to randomly choose a word from the word_list and assign it to a variable
called chosen_word.
So in order to randomly get an item out of the list,
we're going to need to import the random module.
And once we've got hold of that, then we can say random.choice
and if we put inside the parentheses
the list that we want to randomly choose from,
then we should be able to get hold of a single item from this list randomly.
And then finally, we're going to assign it to a variable called chosen_word.
So let's call that chosen_word and then set it to equal this result.
So that's to-do 1 completed. The next todo we have to ask the user to guess a
letter and assign their answer to a variable called guess. And finally make that
guess lowercase. In order to ask the user for anything,
we're going to have to create an input. And let's say,
"Guess a letter:"
And then we can assign their answer
which will replace this line of code with a variable called guess.
So we'll just set that equal to guess. And finally,
we're going to make this guess lower case and we do that by writing .lower.
Now step 3 ask us to check if the letter the user guessed,
which is this guess variable, is one of the letters in the chosen_word.
So this randomly chosen word could be any one of these: ardvack, baboon, or camel.
And we have to somehow check if this letter
which is stored inside this variable guess matches any of the letters inside
this list of words. So, as I mentioned as a hint,
you can have a look at this document from Google for education,
which talks about various things in Python.
And the part I wanted to draw your attention to is the for loop
which we covered previously. So we know that we can use the for loop like this
to loop through a particular list and get hold of each of the items in the list,
like this. So in our case,
all we have to do is say for letter in chosen word,
so this is going to go through this chosen word letter by letter
and each time the loop runs,
we'll get hold of one of letters inside the word.
So the first time that letter variable will equal a, the next time
it will be equal to r and so on and so forth.
So now inside our for loop
we can check to see if the letter that we're currently looking at is double
equals to the letter that the user guessed and in this case,
well then that means its a match, right?
So we're going to print either a match or in my case, I'm just going to write,
uh, Right. And else, namely if it doesn't match,
then we're going to print wrong. That's it.
That's all we have to do to complete all three to-dos.
And now if I run this code,
you can see it's going to ask me to guess a letter. So let's put a,
and then it goes through this loop line by line
to check against this letter that I've guessed. So I'm guessing in this case
the chosen word is aardvark.
So when the loop is running through the first letter a and a match,
so it says right. Then the next time it's looking at the letter
r, a and r does not match
so we get wrong and it continues until it finds all the matches and all the ones
that don't match. Now, if you want to check your code against mine,
simply head over to the URL that's listed in the course resources under app
brewery/day-7-Hangman-1-End
and here you'll be able to see all the code that I went through with you just
now. Now, if you had any issues
understanding how the code worked or how to get to the final solution,
and if you're at all confused,
I recommend putting the code through Thonny and just clicking on the debug to go
through each of the steps one by one. So in this line,
we're going to use the random module and get hold of a random item from this
list.
So, in this case, it's picked camel. And now that camel is going to be equal to
the variable chosen_word.
So on the next step we ask the user to guess a letter.
And once we step into that,
it's going to print that out into the debug console.
And if I put a and hit enter, then guess is now equal to a,
and there's our second variable guess, which is equal to a.
Now we fall into our for loop. And if we step into the loop,
then you can see that the chosen_word is going to be replaced with camel and
letter is going to be replaced with each of the letters in the chosen word one
by one. So the first time loop runs, it's going to be c,
and then it checks to see, well, if c is equal to guess,
which is a, does that match? No, it doesn't.
So it jumps to the else part and it prints out wrong.
And then the loop is going to restart from the top
and we're going to go to the next letter in the chosen word,
which is a. Now in this case, the letter is a
and the guest is a and so that should match. And so it should print,
right.
And then it basically steps through all of these again and again
until we get to the end of the word and we get this printed out.
So have a play around with that and the debug console to wrap your head around
it. And once you're confident, you know, what's going on,
then head over to the next lesson and let's complete step 2.
All right. So now that you've tackled step one,
let's continue building out our project by doing step two. Again,
we have three to-dos in the starting file.
And what we're going to try and do here is we're going to generate a list with
as many of these blanks
which is represented by an underscore string as there are letters in the chosen
word. So for example, if the chosen word was apple with five letters,
then we should be able to create a list with five items and each of them being
an underscore. So then in the next stage,
we can replace some of the items inside that list with the correct letter
if the user guesses it right. So for example,
if the word was apple and the user guessed the letter p,
then we should be able to loop through each of the letters in the word.
And for every letter that it matches,
we replace the underscore with the actual letter.
So then we end up with a list that looks like this. Finally,
you're going to print that out and we should be able to see it in the console.
In the starting file, you'll notice I've added a little bit of testing code
which is just a print statement telling us what the chosen wood is,
and this will make it easier for us to debug and figure out if our code is not
doing what we want it to do. So once you've completed all of the
to-dos in step two, then this is what you should get. In this case,
the chosen word is baboon. So if,
I guess the letter b, because I'm cheating
and also because I'm trying to test the code, and I hit enter,
then you can see that it should print out a list with one,
two, three, four, five, six,
six items in it because there's six letters in baboon,
and each of the letters which I've guessed correctly in the right
are replaced in the list in the correct position. B occurs in the first and the
third letter,
so that is what's showing up in this list and everything else is still the
underscore because they're blanks and still need to be guessed.
Have a play around with the final version of the code
and once you're ready, head back, fork
the starting project and complete the to-dos in order. Now,
if you need a hint and you get stuck,
be sure to check the course resources for a link that links to again,
a Google for Education page
and have a read through the section on the range function that we learned about
in previous lessons.
Remind yourself of how it works and then go back to your code and try to tackle
it and see if you can get it to do what it needs to. Good luck
and I'll see you on the other side,
All right, let's go ahead and run through the solution together. Firstly,
I'm going to fork my own copy of the starting file for step two
and then I'm going to take a look at to-do number one.
So the goal is to create an empty list called display,
and for each letter in the chosen word,
remember that a random word from this list,
we're going to add an underscore to this list called display.
So it tells us that if the word was apple,
then display should contain five underscores representing each letter the
user needs to guess.
Let's go ahead and just click run before doing anything first.
And this print statement will execute and it'll tell us that the solution is
ardvark. This is a seven letter word. So in this case,
we would need to create a list with seven underscores and seven items.
Let's go ahead and create an empty list called display.
An empty list is just a set of square brackets with nothing inside.
Now, for each letter in the chosen word,
we're going to add a underscore to this list.
How can we add something for each letter?
The simplest way is to simply use a for-loop. Now, in this case,
we have a choice.
We can either use the style of for-loop that we used previously down here,
which is a way of looping through a list.
So we could say for letter in chosen_word,
so it's going to run this for as many letters as there are in this word.
And for every single letter,
we're just simply going to take our list, display, and add a item to it.
And that item is going to be the string, underscore.
So now if we go ahead and print out our display and see what we get.
The solution is baboon
which has six letters and display gets printed with one, two, three, four,
five, six underscores inside.
Now notice how here we're not actually using this variable letter that gets
created. We're looping through every letter in the chosen word,
but we're not doing anything with each of the letters. So we can in fact
just replace it with an underscore. Now, alternatively,
we could have created this for loop with a range function as well.
And remember that the range function creates a range of numbers from zero up to
a particular number that you specify. So we could have also,
instead of looping through the chosen word, use range and inside here,
we could have put the length of the chosen word.
So then our range would be between zero and the length of the chosen word.
So it was a baboon then it would be from zero to six, but not including six.
Remember that's how the range operator works.
So it would be zero and then it would be one and so on and so forth until it
gets to five.
And so that would be a total of six loops adding six of these underscores.
So given that I've updated this for loop, if we run it again,
you can see its exactly the same,
it will create as many underscores in the list as there are letters in the
chosen word. So it doesn't actually matter in this case
which version you went for, either this version of the
for loop using the range function or the previous one
which just looped through the list. It's your choice. They both worked the same.
So now let's move on to to-do number two.
Now we have to loop through each position in the chosen word
and if the letter at that position matches the letter the user guessed,
then we're going to reveal that letter in the display at that position.
So basically we're going to replace the underscore with the letter that the user
guessed if they guessed it right.
So now this is probably the hardest part of this whole step because in order to
do this,
we actually have to change this for loop to
one that uses the range function because we need to get hold of the position
when the letter and the guess actually matched. That way
we can tap into the list and change only the item at that particular position.
So let me show you how the code would look.
Instead of saying for letter in chosen_word,
we would say for position in range
and the range is going to be between zero and the length of the chosen_word.
And once we've got that, then the
for-loop is going to run for as many times as there are letters in the word and
for each of those letters
it's going to give us a number, a position to work with.
So the first time it runs it position is going to be equal to zero because we'll
be looking at the first item in the chosen_word,
which in this case would be a.
And then the next time the loop runs position becomes one
and we'll be looking at the second item in the list.
Now we no longer have that letter to work with,
which is why we get an error here.
So how can we get hold of the current letter in the chosen word
given that we know the position? Well,
it would be as simple as saying letter = chosen_word
[position].
Now we can check to see if the letter is equal to the letter
the user guessed.
Then we can get hold of our display and get the item at the current position and
then set that to equal the letter.
And we can get rid of the else statement entirely.
So now notice that we're using the length of the chosen word in quite a few
places. So if you want to,
you can actually simplify the code by simply creating a new variable called word
length.
And now every time we need to use the word_length,
we can just refer to that variable
Right?
which should make our code a little bit easier to read.
Finally, all we have to do for step three is just to print our list
which is called display. And then when we run our code,
you should be able to see that if the solution was camel,
initially, our display starts out with five blanks because there's five letters.
And then once we've guessed a letter,
then it will replace that letter at the correct position in that display list.
So a only matches the second letter,
so that second blank gets replaced by this letter.
And again,
I recommend to review the code if it's at all confusing or if you didn't manage
to get it first time through the Thonny IDE just to see it step by step and see
what's actually happening. We've chosen our random word,
which in this case turns out to be camel.
And once we get into our display,
it starts out as an empty list.
But as soon as we calculate the word length,
then we can go ahead and loop through the range of numbers from zero to the
length of the word, which is five. And it will run the code in the
for loop
which is just to add the underscore to this list five times.
And finally, once it's done, it's going to print it out.
So this is what we get, five blanks for the word camel.
Now it asked the user for a guess.
So I'm going to guess that letter a and enters this final for loop.
This is where it's really interesting.
So we're going to step into it to see it in more detail.
So now the range is a range between zero and the word length.
So the word length is five
so that range becomes from zero to five not
including five. So zero, one, two, three, four.
And that is going to make the for loop run five times.
The position starts out with zero. And when position is zero
then it's going to go into this next line, line 18, and put zero here as the
position. And then we go into the chosen word,
which is camel and pick out the item at position zero.
And so this letter becomes equal to the letter c because that's the letter at
position zero of the word. So now in our if statement,
we check to see if the letter, which is c, is equal to the guess,
which is a. Well in this case, c does not equal a
so we go back to the beginning of the for loop and we go to the next number in
the range, which is now one.
And we're going to repeat this again and again. But in this case,
notice that the letter at position one of camel is equal to a.
So now letter is equal to a and guess is equal to a.
So if those two are equal, then this
if statement is true and we end up going inside it to carry out this
functionality. Our letter is equal to a,
and we're going to look at our list, which is called display, this one,
and we're going to replace that second character with the letter that was
matching. And it's going to do this again and again
until we've looped through five times through all of the letters in the chosen
word
and finally we print the final version of display with the correct letters
replaced. Have a play around with this
if you're at all confused and it might be that you need to look up some stuff on
Stack Overflow,
or you might need to review some of the lessons that we've done before on things
like range functions and for loops, just so that you're really,
really certain that you know
what's going on and only then should you continue to the next step.
Take a moment with this and I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right. So up till now,
our game is not actually particularly fun and it's because we haven't enabled the
repeatability.
So we need our game to allow the user to guess the next letter and the next
letter
and keep going until they either die or they get to the solution.
So in this case, the solution is ardvark.
So I'm gonna guess a letter, a,
and that gets replaced in the correct positions.
And now I'm allowed to guess again.
And I'm going to keep going until I've filled out all of the characters.
So I'm almost there just need a 'k' now
and we should complete the entire game.
And it tells me that it's complete and that I've won
and the game finally ends and exits out of the loop. In order to achieve this and
make our game more like a game, we have just one to-do.
Now,
the idea here is you're going to use a while loop to let the user guests again
after they've guessed before. Now the loop should only stop
once the user has guessed all of the letters in the chosen word,
and this means that the display list should have no more blanks in it.
And then at that point,
you can tell them that they've won. Now in order to do this,
and as a quick hint, you might need to have a read of, again,
the section which I'll link to in the course resources. And specifically,
I want you to focus on this 'in' key word,
because we mentioned it previously in the course only briefly.
So I want you to read through this part and see how that works,
because you'll need it in order to get this to work. Now,
the other thing to remember is that you have the negation in Python.
So you can say,
if something is not true and then to do something or other.
So the not is the negation and this basically flips whatever is here.
So it could be, um, a = 3.
If not a > 1.
So in this case, a is three, three is greater than one. So this becomes true.
But because there's a not in front of it, then this entire thing becomes false
and so this if statement won't be carried out in this case.
But if this was zero and zero is not greater than one,
so this is now false and not false becomes true
and now this if statement will be carried ouit.
So that's how you use the negation. And finally,
you might need to remind yourself of what we learned in yesterday's lessons and
how the while loop works. Essentially,
you want to be able to get this part to repeat itself again and again and again,
until
all the blanks in the display is gone and they're filled.
And at that point, the user has won. And remember,
you don't have to worry about punishing the user for wrong answers just yet,
we're going to do that in the next step.
But for now, focus on this one to-do and see if you can solve this challenge.
All right, so let's go through the solution together.
Now we know that the part that we need repeating is this part where we ask the
user to guess a letter again and again
until they filled out all the blanks in this display.
The first step is to wrap a while loop around this block of code so we can
select the entire block of code and you can either indent it individually or
just select all of it and hit command and the right square bracket.
And that will shift everything by one indentation level
and that effectively puts it inside our while loop.
So now we have to define our while loop.
So while something is true or while something is false,
repeat this code again and again. So what exactly is our condition?
We know that we only want our loop to end once there are no more blanks
contained inside the list called display.
Why don't we create a variable which we'll call end_of_game and set that to
false
to begin with because it's not yet the end of game. And while it's not yet at the
end of game, so while this is false. So you can either say while
end of game is equal to false or alternatively
and I think slightly easier to read is you could say while it's not at the end
of the game, then repeat this continuously. Now,
if we were to run our code right now
it would actually loop on until forever.
It would not stop because nowhere in our code,
do we actually flip the switch and change this true.
So when is it actually the end of the game? Well,
it's when display has no more blanks.
So why don't we check at the very end after we've printed the display to see if
blanks are not in display.
So remember this in key word comes from Python and it basically allows us to
check to see if a particular element exists inside a particular list. So in this
case, we're checking if curly exists in list and there it is.
I can see it as one of the elements. So this is going to be true.
Now, if blank
in list is no longer true, well,
that means that we've gotten rid of all the blanks and we replaced them with
letters that the user has guessed.
So now this is the condition for the user having won.
So we can flip the end of game to true
and this will mean that this is last time
our while loop is going to run and we're going to print "You win."
That's it, that's all we needed do. And if it's helpful,
you can again, take this code, put it into Thonny and run through it
using the debug step-by-step to see what it's doing. Now
the important thing here is to realize that while statements require some sort
of change to happen inside the while loop
that changes the condition that the while loop is dependent upon
and it means the code exits the while loop. So in this case,
it's when there are no longer any more blanks inside the display list.
But in later steps,
we're going to change that so that when the users has run out of lives,
then it's also going to be the end of the game and they will have lost.
So take a moment, review this lesson,
make sure you understand everything that's going on.
Then head over to the next lesson and we'll tackle the next step.
Well done for getting to step 4. Now in this step
when you take a look at the starting file,
you'll see that I've incorporated a bunch of ASCII art,
so art that's created using strokes of the keyboard.
And you can see that this represents the stages of our hangman game starting from
where they have all six lives and then going down in lives until they have
no more lives, where the hangman character is complete.
This has been included as a list and inside the list
each of these pieces of art is a single string.
So we're going to be printing it out in this step,
and we're going to be using it to give the user feedback.
So the to-dos for step four include creating a variable called lives to keep
track of the number of lives and lives should be equal to six.
Now in the next to-do,
we're checking to see if the guess is actually not a letter in the chosen word,
then we're going to reduce that variable lives by one.
So eventually it's going to step down all the way to zero.
And when that happens, the game should stop and it should print "You lose."
Now, this part is really important because we want the game to stop
when the lives has gone down to zero.
So the code should exit the while loop and print "You lose."
So in addition to winning as a condition to ending the game,
losing is also a condition for ending the game. Now,
the final to do is just to print the ASCII art from stages
which is this list up here,
and the stage should represent the current number of lives
the user has remaining. So this way,
when we actually play the game and we get all the letters wrong,
each time a new piece of the hang man is going to be drawn until eventually we
end up with the entire drawing complete and the game ends,
and it tells us that we lost. If it's helpful,
refer to the flow chart. And once you're ready,
go ahead and fork the starting code and tackle the
to-dos one by one. Good luck and I'll see you on the other side.
All right. So make sure you've given it a good go before you come over here,
because I'm about to reveal the solution. In terms of step 4, here
I've got a forked copy of the code. And if I scroll down to
to-do number one, this is pretty simple.
It just tells us to create a new variable called lives
and this variable is going to be the one that's going to keep track of the
number of lives the user has left. And to start off,
it's going to be equal to six. Now we move on to to-do number two.
And it tells us that if the guess is not a letter in the chosen word,
then we have to reduce the number of lives by one.
Now it might be really tempting to put this as an else statement here,
because if the letter is equal to guess,
then well obviously it matches. Well then else, that means it doesn't match.
But check out what happens here if I just print a simple statement.
So now if I hit run and we take a look on the right side,
you can see that if I guess a,
then you can see that we get 'no match' printed five times,
and that should show you that this is actually not where we want to write the
code for to-do number two,
because remember to-do number two says if the guessed letter is not a letter in
the chosen word, then we should reduce the lives by one. But actually in fact,
what's happening here is it's looping through the entire word length,
and for each of the letters in that chosen word,
if the letter doesn't match the guess,
then it's going to trigger this else statement.
This is not what we want because in this case
a does in fact match a letter in the word baboon,
but we're getting no match being called five times.
So instead, we wanna write it outside of the for loop,
so at the same indentation level,
and the hint is that the to-do is actually at the same level as where your
answer code needs to go. So here,
we're going to write an if statement and we're going to check if the guess is
not in the chosen word.
And basically this does a separate check.
It goes through this entire word and checks
if the guessed letter exists in there at all.
And if this is true,
then we're going to reduce the number of lives by one, so -= 1.
Now, if at this stage
after we've taken a life away and the number of lives goes down to zero, well
then the game should stop and it should print "You lose."
So let's add another if statement in here that checks whether if the number of
lives is equals to, double equal to, zero.
And if this is the case, then we should exit the game. And remember to do that
we need to exit the while loop.
And the while loop is dependent on this variable end_of_game
which starts out being false. And when we want to exit the game,
when it is in fact the end of the game, we switch it to true. Like,
for example, in this case, when the user has won. So here,
when the lives is equal to zero, we can say, end_of_game = True,
and we're going to print "You lose."
So that's all that's needed to tackle to-do number two.
So now let's run our code again.
And you can see that if I keep guessing the wrong letter six times,
then eventually I exit out of my while loop.
You can see my prompt showing up again.
And this means that we've now come out of the game and it's told us that we've
lost.
So now all we have to do is tackle to-do number three.
We have to print the ASCII art from the list called stages
that corresponds to the current number of lives the user has remaining. Now,
luckily for you,
I've arranged each of these pictures in descending order of lives.
So when you have a full six lives,
the image at index six is the starting image.
And when you have no lives,
so the image at index zero is the one where the hangman is fully drawn.
So all we have to do down here is to simply just the print
the stages,
and corresponding to the current number of lives.
So we put lives inside the square brackets.
And now if we run the code again and we keep guessing,
you can see that we're going through our hangman picture until we are fully
drawn and we lose and it's the end of the game.
Have a quick review of the solution
and if you want to see this code that I've written,
then as always, head over to the course resources,
and you'll find a link to Day-7-Hangman-4-End
and you'll be able to see all the code that I've written in there, including,
um, helpful things like a print statement that you can activate,
which just shows you the current position,
the current letter and the letter that's being guessed.
So you can see as the loop is going on
what's actually happening and it'll make it easier for you to debug any problems
in your code. So if you had any problems in the code that you wrote,
this is a really useful line to be able to help you debug what's gone wrong.
Hopefully you manage to do thi okay,
and once you've had a quick review and you're happy with everything that's been
covered in this lesson,
then head over to the next lesson and we're going to complete the final step,
step five of our hangman project.
Hey! Well done for getting to the final step of the hangman project.
Now in step five,
we're going to complete the project by improving the user experience of our
game. Pretty much up until now, we've already got the game functioning,
but we were working with just three words, right? Ardvark, baboon,
and camel. And at some point,
the game gets pretty tiring when you're only guessing these three words.
And in fact,
the words were chosen so that if you see seven characters and you know
it's ardvark,
six is baboon, five is camel to make it easier for you to debug the code as
you're creating it. And very often when we're writing code, it really,
really important to help yourself when you're creating the code.
And only once you've got all the logic down and everything's working as expected
then to actually add the full functionality.
So inside this step five starting code,
if you take a look at the files over here, you'll notice two extra files.
One is hangman_art.py,
and here I've moved the hangman stages and all the drawings as well as a logo in
ASCII art. So when we actually launch our game this time,
then we're going to get the high man logo printed out like this at the beginning
of the game.
Now the second file here it is hangman_words.py.
And this word list now expands on what we had before.
And it's now a huge list of words, sorted alphabetically
which we're going to draw upon and replace this previous very simple word list.
The first to-do is to update the word list
to use the one from here instead of this one.
So deleting this line and replacing it with that. And to do this,
you might have to look up on previous lessons where
we talked about how to use modules in Python and how to import different files.
Now, if you get stuck on how to do that,
take a look inside the course resources
and there's hints that take you towards documentation on how to do this.
Now, once you've tackled to-do number one, scroll all the way down to find
to-do number two, where we're going to import the stages from hangman_art.py
and this is the same thing using modules and import. To-do
number three is to import the logo.
So one, two, three are all to do with modules and import.
And then once you get to to-do number four,
we're basically going to improve the user experience to let the user know that
they've entered a letter that they've already guessed before.
And when that happens, we're going to print the letter and just let them know.
You don't have to punish them and
you don't have to take away a life and you don't have to restart the game.
It's just the gentle nudge and let them know that they've really guessed that
letter. Now on to-do number five and the final to-do, we're going to let the user
know if the letter that they guessed is not in the chosen word.
So in this case,
we're going print out the letter that they guessed and let them know that it's
not in the word,
just a little bit of feedback to make the game a little bit easier on the user.
So once you've done all of that,
then you should end up with a game that's like this. So,
because there's so many words, I think it's really,
really important that you actually have this line of testing code to tell you
what the solution actually is
so you can test all parts of your game because you know what the word actually
should be. So let's guess a letter that's not in that word.
Let's try a, and you can see the game tells us "You guessed the letter a,
that's not in the word. You lose a life."
And we end up with the head already drawn in the hangman.
So now let's guess a different letter. Let's guess a t.
Then you can see that works as expected. But what if we try guessing T again?
Well, then it tells us you've already guessed t and it shows us the blanks
including the t. Now if they guess a letter
that's actually not in the word, so say a, well, in this case,
they're gonna lose a life because it's actually not in the word and we're going
to take away a life.
So have a play around with the end version of the game. And as always,
all the links are in the course resources. And once you're ready,
then go ahead and fork the starting file and give this a go.
Alright. So let's go through the solution together for this final step.
The first step tells us to update the word list
to use the word list from hangman_words.
And it's actually got exactly the same name.
So we don't even have to change it all that much.
But what we do have to do is to make this error go away.
If you haven't already, go ahead and delete this line in your code
where you've got the word list using the previous three words.
And instead, we're going to import the hangman_words.
And now we should be able to tap into this word list by writing hangman_
words.word_list.
And this is the same way that we use the random module.
So we imported the random module and then when we needed it, we simply said
random.choice. So choice is a function inside the random module,
and we can access it like
so. Now if you want it to be a little bit simpler in terms of the code that you
write and you don't want to rewrite hangman_words
dot such and such, then instead of just importing hangman words,
you can actually instead write from hangman
words import the word_list.
So now we can get rid of this part and we can just use the previous code that we
had on line 7.
Using that you can do the same thing for
to-do number two. From the hangman_art
you can import the stages and that will make this error go away. And for
to-do number three,
you can again say from hangman_art
import the logo.
And then we can just print the logo.
Now notice how we're importing, um,
two different things from the same file, hangman art.
So if you didn't want to write it twice,
you can in fact also just say from hangman_art import logo,
stages, and this will import both the logo and the stages
and you'll see that there's no errors down here.
If that's at all confusing,
be sure to read through the documentation that I've linked to in the course
resources that talks all about Python modules and importing
so you can familiarize yourself with this once more. Now on to-do four,
we're going to check to see if the user has entered a letter that they've
already guessed. And if it's a letter that they got right,
then we're going to print the letter and let them know. To do this,
we're going to check through the display,
which is a list of letters that they've already guessed.
And we're going to check to see if the guess is in the display list,
well, in this case, they've already guessed that letter and it's a correct one.
So we're just going to print out the feedback that, um,
"You've already guessed
and then we'll put in their guessed letter."
Now, however, if the letter is not in the chosen word,
then we're going to print out the letter and let them know that
"You guessed this particular letter,
that's not in the word.
You lose a life." That's it.
That's all we have to do and if we run our app as it is now,
then you can see that the solution is stymied.
So if we just check, um,
against s then that's being added,
and if we get a letter wrong,
then we get told that's not in the word. You lose a life.
And our hangman is being drawn out.
And if we guess a correct letter that we've already guessed like s again,
then it tells us that you've already guessed that letter.
Now you can either choose to keep all of these print statements
if it helps you understand what's going on, or alternatively at this stage,
it might make things a little bit confusing and you can just comment it out.
Have a look at the final version
by going to the course resources where I'll link to the completed code that I've
written here. And you can have a read through it and compare against yours.
But essentially this is all there is to this project
and you've now completed it in its entirety. Once you're happy with your code,
go ahead and remove all the comments that are no longer useful like all the
to-dos and the testing code
because if you wanna play the game for real, then that's just cheating.
If you want to leave in some of the comments that lets you know
what each part of code does so that when you come back to it,
it's easier to understand, then feel free to do that.
But the final thing that I wanted to show you is what if you wanted it to be
able to clear the screen after every answer,
because you can see that some point you have to keep scrolling and it gets a
little bit confusing as to which stage you're in.
So one of the things that you can do is you can tap into the replit module
and you can import a function called clear.
Once you've imported this clear function,
then you can go ahead and add it just after the user has made their guess.
So you can call it just as you would any other function
now that you've imported it into this file. And when you run the code now,
you can see that after every guess, it's going to clear the screen.
So guess a letter, let's guess a different letter.
Now that means we don't have this backlog of previous guesses and we can
actually see what's going on at each stage. In the course resources,
you'll also find a link to the final completed code on the day seven hangman final,
and feel free to modify this code to, your heart's content, make it
do whatever it is that you want to do and push the boundaries of your
programming skills
if you want to. Well done for getting this far and well done for tackling this
challenge. Rest easy, and I'll see you tomorrow.