Hey guys, welcome to Day 8 of a 100 Days of Code.
And today we're going to be looking at functions that allow you to give them
inputs. And once we've learned all of that and we've grasped it,
then we're going to be building a cipher program.
And the cipher program is called Caesar cipher.
So Caesar cipher is a really quite ancient type of encryption.
So the story goes that, um,
when Caesar wanted to send highly sensitive military messages,
he would encode his message so that each letter would be shifted by a
predetermined amount.
So let's say that we wanted to encode the letter "A" and we shift it by three,
well
then A becomes D, B becomes E and so on and so forth.
And this is what the final version will look like.
Let's go ahead and encode something.
So I'm going to type encode to start encrypting a message.
And then I'm going to type my message with no spaces in between.
And then I'm going to give it a shift number.
So this is going to be a number that
the recipient and I are going to agree on so that we know how to decode the
message. Let's put that at nine.
And then it's going to give us the encoded results
which is something like this.
And this will be the message that I'm going to transmit to my friend,
either through a letter or through an email
and it means that whenever somebody comes across this message
they won't really know what's going on unless they knew the shift number.
So let's say that I am my friend. I've just received this message.
And I'm going to go ahead and type yes to go again
and in this case, I'm going to decode instead of encoding.
And then I'm going to paste the message and hit enter.
And of course, the shift number is nine and now I have the decoded results
which I can read and understand. By the end of today,
you would have learned about functions with input,
you'll know what the difference is between arguments and parameters.
Once you're ready, once you're loaded up on coffee,
then head over to the next lesson and let's get started.
To get started we're going to learn more about functions.
And previously we learned that functions are a really handy way of taking a
complex set of instructions and packaging them together inside a block of code
that has a name given to it.
And when we need all of the lines of code that's packaged inside this
function,
all we have to do at any point later on in our code is just to call the function
by typing its name and then a set of parentheses.
And when this line of code is run,
it's going to search for where this function is defined, which is up here,
and then it's going to execute all the lines of code that are contained within
it. Now it's been a little while since we've seen functions.
So I want you to go ahead and find the starting replit for day 8
which is at this URL
and then fork it to create your own copy. To begin,
I want you to create a new function called greet,
and I want you to give it three lines of print statements,
telling it to do three things. And finally, once you're done,
go ahead and call the function so that it gets executed in the console.
So pause the video and give that a go. All right.
So to create a function, we of course need a def keyword.
And we know it's a keyword, because as soon as we type it,
it changes to the blue color. And after the key word,
we get to give our function a name. So in my case, it's called greet.
Now after the greet, we add a set of parentheses after the name of the function.
Finally,
we add a colon and we enter into the block of code because we're indented over.
Now,
the first thing I'm going to do is to create a print statement that just says
Hello. And then I'm going to say, well,
how do you do? Nobody in England actually says this,
but I always see it in the learn English books, which is quite funny.
I think people will give you a very strange look
if you go to somebody at the bakery and say, well, how do you do? But anyways,
now finally, we're going to add a final print statement,
keeping in line with the Britishness of my function,
going to ask about the weather.
Now this line, on the other hand, is something that you will often hear a British
people say. They're obsessed about the weather,
mostly because it's terrible all the time.
So now that we've created our function,
it's time to actually trigger the function or what we see in programming lingo,
call the function.
And we do that by calling the name of the function and then adding a set of
parentheses. And now once the code reaches line six
it's going to search for this greet function, which it'll find over here
and then it's going to carry out each of the lines of code one by one.
So let's run the code and you should see each of the three print statements
being called. So that's pretty simple.
Notice that every single time I call the greet function,
it's going to do the same thing, right?
It's just going to print out those three lines of code. Now, in reality,
it's very rare that you'll want to repeat the same instructions every single
time when you call a function. It would be nice, wouldn't it,
if we could modify some of the parts of the code inside the function and allow
for a little bit of variation. For example,
it would be nice if we could greet somebody by the name so that it could say,
hello Angela, instead of just, hello. How do you do Angela?
So that it could change each time I call this function.
Maybe next time it will be, how do you do Jack Bauer, et cetera.
So how can we achieve this kind of functionality? Well,
we need to look more closely at these parentheses.
Now what we can do is we can actually add the name of a variable inside those
parentheses to start giving our functions some inputs.
So let's say that there's a variable called something that's going to be passed
to my function. And this something can then be used inside this block of code,
this function.
And I could do something with it. Now in order to actually pass this value
when I call my function, I have to add the data inside the parentheses.
So let's say I decide to pass 123 over, well
in this case, when this line of code gets triggered,
the computer is going to search for where this function is declared,
which is up here, and then it's going to pass over this piece of data,
123, over to this variable called something.
So now, effectively, inside this function called my_function,
we now have a variable called something that's equal to 123
and that can then be used inside the block of code to do something with that
piece of data.
Now it's a bit like plugging in a USB stick into a computer.
If we took a different piece of input,
we would end up with a different file being shown by the computer.
So this means the computer can do something different depending on the input that
we give it. And if we change that input,
then it will receive a different piece of data.
So in addition to a simple function,
we can also create a function that allows for input.
And to do that you saw earlier on the syntax is again the same as before we use
a Def to create the function.
And then let's just give it a slightly different name to differentiate it with
the previous function, greet_with_name.
And then inside the parentheses, instead of leaving it blank,
we get to create the name of the variable that's going to be passed over.
So let's just call it name because that describes the data that's going to be
received. It's going to be the name of the person that I wish to greet.
So now let's add a colon and finally we can create our print statements.
So I'm just going to copy these print statements from above and now,
instead of having these names hard coded in here, I'm going to delete it
and I'm going to replace those names with the value of this variable.
So I'm going to put it in using an fstring like this,
and then I'm going to do the same down here.
Right?
When we actually call this function,
it's also going to be a little bit different from previously on line six.
So now firstly, the name of the function has changed.
But notice how it's expecting some sort of input inside the parentheses.
And it tells me that it wants to receive a name.
It's when we call the function that we actually pass over the piece of data
that's going to be stored inside this variable. Let's give it my own name,
Angela. And now when I hit run,
I want you to predict what's going to happen,
what's actually going to be printed.
So let's go ahead and comment out the previous line of code and now run our code.
And you should see that it says, hello Angela, how do you do Angela.?
So this piece of data has basically been inserted under this variable name
and then it's been put into both of these print statements. Now,
if I go ahead and call this function with a different piece of data,
say a different name,
then it's going to use that piece of data to modify this function
so it does something a little bit different.
So this way we can create one function that carries out some instructions,
but every time we execute it, it gets a modify it a little bit
by changing the inputs.
When we're talking about functions with inputs,
there's two things that we're working with
that's really important to differentiate.
So we know that when we call this function and we pass over this piece of data,
effectively
we're creating a new variable called something and we're setting it to equal this
piece of data that we're passing it. Now in programming lingo,
you'll hear this being referred to as the parameter and this piece of data
being referred to as the argument. Now,
the argument is the actual piece of data
that's going to be passed over to this function when it's being called.
Whereas the parameter is the name of that data
and we use the parameter inside the function to refer to it and to do things
with it. Now very often on the internet when you come across
somebody explaining something
be it on Stack Overflow or in some piece of documentation,
you'll hear them referring to these two types of things,
the parameter and the argument.
So if you need to, come back to this lesson and remind yourself the difference
between those two things.
The parameter is the name of the data that's being passed in,
the argument is the actual value of the data. Now,
sometimes people also get confused on the internet between these two words,
but as long as you know what they means, then you'll be in a good place.
In the last lesson,
we saw a very simple form of a function that allows for an input.
Now in this lesson,
I want to take it even further and I want to create a function that allows for
multiple inputs.
So let's comment out of the previous line of code and let's create a new comment,
functions with more than one input.
And I'm going to create a new function called greet_with.
And in this case, it's going to take two parameters.
It's going to be name and location. If you remember,
this is how we added a parameter previously. Now, as a challenge,
I want you to quickly think about how you might add two parameters,
one's called name and one's called location, into this function
declaration. Pause the video, have a brief think,
and then we'll go through it together. All right.
So we know that if we wanted to add one parameter name,
then this is how we would do it. We would just add it inside the parentheses.
Now, if we wanted to have more than one parameter,
all we have to do is just add a comma and then add the second parameter which we
said was going to be called location.
So now this particular function is going to take two inputs,
the name and the location. And then inside this function,
we're going to use the name to print something like hello name,
and then we're going to print and ask them,
what is it like in their particular location.
See if you can modify this to use the actual parameters and to replace them with
print statements so that we use these parameters inside of our function.
Pause the video now and give that a go. All right.
So essentially we want to create a print statement here and print statements
print strings so we have to add some quotation marks around that text.
And then finally,
I'm going to use a fstring to replace this parameter name inside this string so
that the data that gets passed in gets replaced here, and it says,
hello, whatever their name is.
And then I'm just going to do the same thing over here
and notice that with replit and a lot of other text editors,
you can simply highlight a word or highlight or a sentence,
and then use the open curly brace to actually add brace around both sides of the
word. And you'll notice that I did the same thing with the quotation marks.
So it highlight the whole sentence and then hit the double-quote key
and it will keep adding quotes around both sides of your highlight.
But I only actually need one.
So that is our function completed.
And now it means I can call this function by calling greet_with,
and it's going to prompt me to add both of these inputs.
And the first piece of data is going to be the name
and you can see it's giving you a hint by underlining the name of the parameter
here. And let's put Jack Bauer
and then we can add the second piece of data and separate it with a comma.
And now you can see this underline has moved to the location parameter.
So again, a hint as to what kind of data it wants.
So let's say that Jack Bauer is nowhere. Now,
if we go ahead and run this code,
then you'll see that it's going to print hello and replace name with Jack Bauer.
And then what is it like in nowhere? So no
where gets replaced with this location.
So that means that you can now put in as many pieces of inputs as you want and
modify the functionality of your function to make your function do different
things each time. Now here's a question.
What happens if I call the same function greet_with,
but I switch the order of the data that I give it.
So let's say the first piece of data I give it is nowhere,
and then the second piece of data is Jack Bauer.
So we've just switched the order of these pieces of data. Now,
what do you expect to happen?
Pause for a moment and have a think about what you expect to be printed in here
and then continue. All right,
so let's click run and you can see that it's now complete nonsense.
Hello, nowhere. What is it like in Jack Bauer? And what actually happened here
is it takes the position of the data, looks at both of these arguments,
and the first argument gets assigned to the first parameter
the second argument gets assigned at the second parameter. So in this case,
when it's actually gone in here, name is now equal to nowhere,
which is why this line printed thi.sAand Jack Bauer is now assigned to location
which is why it printed this second line like so. And in Python programming,
this is called a positional argument because when we call the function,
we haven't specified anywhere which particular parameter we want to associate
these pieces of data with. So it's just gone and looked at the position.
Now this is the default way of calling functions, because on one hand,
when you're typing out the code,
you get the hints here as to which piece of data you need to enter.
But also you can refer to the function and look at the order of the parameters.
Even if we had more inputs, let's say in this case, we had a,
b and c, and we put the arguments one, two and three,
then it means that our variables that gets created
will be a equals one,
b equals two and c equals three.
Now, if we switch around the order of the arguments in the function call,
now what will happen is a is going to be equal to the first argument.
So a is now equal to three, b as equal to the second argument and c is equal to
the third argument. So it might be doing slightly unpredictable things in here.
So whenever you're creating code and you're using these positional arguments,
and you're just inserting the data one by one like this,
and it does something completely unexpected,
then be sure to check your positioning and to make sure that it matches with the
position of the parameters. Now,
what if you wanted to be more clear when you actually call the function
so you don't ever encounter this problem? Well,
you could use something called keyword arguments instead. So now,
instead of just adding the arguments into the function call like this,
we can actually add each of the parameter names and an equal sign to say that
the first parameter a
should be equal to one, b should be equal to two and c equals to three.
And now when we actually change the order around,
it doesn't matter how we order it,
it still going to abide by these bindings. So c
will still be three and a will still be one.
As a challenge, I want you to take this previous function,
greet_with_name and location,
and I want you to call this function down here, but this time,
instead of using positional arguments, I want you to use keyword arguments.
So pause the video and try and give that a go.
All right. So when we call the function, we still use the name.
So it's greet_with, so everything up to the first parentheses is the name.
And then we add in each of these parameter names,
and then we add an equal sign and finally, we give it the actual value.
So let's say Angela,
and then the location is going to be equal to London.
Now, when I hit run,
you can see it does pretty much the same as before. It puts Angela into the name,
London into location. But this time if I switch the order around it
no longer matters. And when I hit run again,
you can see it does exactly the same thing,
because it now knows which argument is associated with which parameter.
So this can make your code less error prone
but it does make each line of code longer.
I recommend using your judgment to figure out when you want to use which type of
argument and depending on the need, you can pick between these two.
Now in the next lesson, I've got a coding exercise for you to put into practice
everything that you've learned so far.
Head over there when you're ready and let's give it a go.
All right. So in today's coding challenge,
we're going to do a little bit of wall painting.
And the idea is we're going to create a program that helps us calculate how many
cans of paint we need to buy for a given surface area of wall.
The maths involved is very simple
and I'm going to talk you through it if you're not confident with maths.
But essentially we want it to be able to use our inputs
to modify our function so that it does something every single time we use it.
Go ahead and click on day 8.1 area calculation,
and we're going to complete this coding challenge. So firstly,
you'll notice that down here on lines, 10, 11, 12, and 13,
I've got some code that's going to help us check your solution.
And we're going to use your function to actually calculate the number of cans of
paint we need to buy.
You're basically painting a wall and the instructions on the paint cans says that
one can
can cover five square meters of wall. Given any height and any width, your
program needs to calculate how many cans of paint you need to buy. The maths,
as I say, is pretty simple.
All you have to do is multiply the height by the width to get the area of the
wall, and then you simply divided by the coverage per can.
We said that five square meters per can, so
it means you are always going to be dividing by five.
So let's say that we had a wall which was two meters high and four meters wide,
and the coverage, as always, is going to be equal to five.
Then the calculation would be a simple as 2 x 4 divided by 5,
which is 1.6. So we need 1.6 cans of paint,
but because you can't buy 0.6 can of a paint,
I've tried this in the store. They said no and they told me to go away.
So we actually have to round up to the nearest whole number.
So in this case, we need to buy two cans. Now,
the really important thing to draw your attention to is down here
I actually call the function.
So I'm calling the function and I'm giving in some named arguments.
So this is really, really important. If you review the previous lessons,
then you should know what name you need to give your function and what
name you need to give the parameters for the code to actually work without any
errors. Remember to take a look at the example inputs down here
and example output because you need to print out something along these lines.
So it should say you'll need X cans of paint depending on your calculation.
And finally, if you need a hint as to how to round up a number,
then you can either go ahead and Google for it, use Stack Overflow,
that's probably the best way, or you could give it a guess. And finally,
if you really get stuck,
take a look at the hint section. And once you're done,
then come back over here and we'll walk through the solution together.
Pause the video now and go ahead and complete this coding exercise.
Yeah.
All right. So, did you manage to get that right? If not,
take a look at this video and then once you're done,
take a look at the solution code and try to compare against your code to see if
there were any errors that you made. Now, this challenge is pretty doable.
All we have to do is to create our function and we create any function using def.
And how do we know what name to give this function? Well,
we take a look at where the function was called down here,
and you can see that it's called paint_calc.
So this is what we have to give our function as the name.
And then we of course have our parentheses, our colon, and then inside here,
we're going to do all the calculations. Now,
the next thing we have to look at is what name we should give our parameters.
And you can see I've got named arguments here.
So that means each of these are going to be the names of the parameters; height,
width, and cover.
So the parameters are going to go inside the parentheses height, width, and cover.
And it's only if we actually spell these parameters exactly the same as what we've
got down here in the arguments will our code actually work.
Now let's go ahead and take the height and multiply it by the width to get the
area. So area = height * width.
And then with that area, we can divide it by the coverage per can.
So let's call it num_of_cans = area
/ cover.
And now remember that this is going to be a decimal number occasionally like
here,
and we have two round it up to the next whole number.
If we take a look at this particular Stack Overflow,
you can see that the question is exactly what we want, right?
How do you round up a number in Python? And if you did some Googling,
then this might have been the Stack Overflow question you would have landed on.
And essentially it tells us you have to import maths, and from the math module,
you use a function called ceiling. And then inside the parentheses,
you put in the inputs. To do that,
we first import math.
It's math without the 's.' And then we can call it a math.ceil and wrap this
result around the parentheses.
So this is going to take the result here from a decimal number to
a whole number by rounding it up to the ceiling.
So now we're finally ready to give our output,
so we're going to do that by printing it.
So we're going to print and I'm definitely going to need an f-string.
So I'm going to put an F in there and paste this string.
And instead of having the hard-coded five here,
I'm going to put in the num_of_cans instead.
So now when this line of code on line 17 calls
paint_calc passing in each of these arguments,
then it's going to be able to run this function here and print out how many cans
of paint I'll need. Now, all we have to do is test our code.
So let's hit run and let's put in a random height.
Let's say it's five meters high and three meters wide.
And it tells us that we need three cans of paint.
So five by three,
the area is 15 square meters,
15 divided by five is three. Now,
what if we had a decimal number?
Let's say we had a height of 7 and a width of 13.
Then in this case, it tells us we need 19 cans.
So 7 times 13 is 91. 91 divided by 5 is 18.2 and 18.2
round it up is 19.
And we've now completed this challenge. Did you manage to get it right?
If not, be sure to watch this video and see if you can go back and fix your code
and you can compare it against the solution code I've got here by going to this
link right here.
And once you're done, head over to the next lesson where I've got a slightly
harder coding challenge for you.
All right, so in the next coding exercise, we're going to be building a prime number checker. And a
prime number, just to remind you, is a number that is only divisible by one and itself.
So, for example, two is a prime number because it can only be divided by one and two.
Three is also a prime number,
similarly, it can only be split into three equal sized chunks.
But four, however, is not a prime number because while it can be divided by one and four, it can
also be divided by two.
So two times two is four. Essentially a prime number is a number that can't be broken to smaller
parts other than one and itself.
And it's this property of prime numbers that makes them really useful to everything from cicadas to
Bitcoin and also encryption in the computer world.
So if you head over to day 8.2 prime number checker, you'll see the starting code including
the number that we're going to be sending over and checking.
And then, of course, the line eleven where we actually call this function and pass over the number. So
this part is really important when you are creating your function.
The idea is that you're going to be creating a function here that checks whether if the number that's
passed in is a prime number or not.
And if you take a look at this chart, then you'll see all the prime numbers up to 100 highlighted in
yellow.
There's a couple of things you need to remember.
One is that you'll probably need to use the modulus, which we've seen before.
And if you can't remember how to use that, then take a look at this link.
Now, the second thing is that make sure that you name your function and parameters the same as what
you see here where it's called.
And finally, try to use the same wording as the example outputs, namely, if it is a prime number print
"It's a prime number." in this exact wording.
And if it's not a prime number, then print "It's not a prime number." with this exact wording.
And finally, if you're still not quite sure how prime numbers work, then be sure to check out the
Wikipedia page.
And if your first language is not English, then be sure to switch to your native language just to know
what it is because I know it's called different things in different languages.
Pause the video,
have a good think about this and see if you can solve this problem.
All right, so let's think about how we might tackle this. The first thing I'm going to do is I'm going
to create a new function called prime_checker to be in line with this line, because I'm calling a
function called prime_checker
and then I'm passing in an argument to the parameter called number.
So now that we've created our function, the next step is to figure out, well, what do we do in this
function?
Now, I mentioned that every prime number can only be cleanly divided by itself and one.
So that means that if it's divided by any other number other than these, it will have a remainder.
So we know that we can use the modulus to check what the remainder is of a division.
So we know that, for example, if we divide six by two, then it equals three with no remainder because
six is divided into two three times, while seven divided by two equals one because there's a remainder
of one, because two times three is six and then six plus one makes seven.
So we can use the modulus to check whether if the number that we're passing in here can be divided by
all the numbers all the way down to two.
So, for example, if number was equal to seven, well, then what we would want to do is we would want
to do seven divided by two and then see if there is any remainder, and then seven divided by three and
see if there was any remainder, and then seven divided by four...
and then we just go up two, three, four, five, and six.
And now we've basically divided seven by all the possible values other than one and seven.
So if any of these has zero as the remainder, then it means that it does cleanly divide by one of these
numbers, which means that it's actually not a prime number.
But if all of these have a remainder, then that means seven is a prime number, which we already know
it is because we can see it on this graph.
So how can we go through this process of getting this number divided by numbers starting from two
all the way going up to the number minus one?
Well, we could simply just use a for loop, right?
So we create a for loop and say for i which is going to be this number that we're going to divide
by, in,
and that number is going to be a range of numbers.
And the range starts from two because we're not going to divide it by one.
We already know that all numbers can be divided by one. And we're going to put the range all the way
up to the number.
So now inside this for loop, we can start doing our divisions. So we could take the number and we can
use the modulo operator to divide it by i.
So it's exactly the same as each of these lines of division. If number divided by i is equal to zero,
so if it divides cleanly, well, then in this case, it's clearly not a prime,
right? Because if that number that we get passed in can be divided by any of the numbers between two
and number minus one cleanly with no remainder, then that means it's not a prime number.
However, if we get to the very end of our for loop and this if statement was never triggered, well,
then that means this is a prime number.
So how can we represent this with our code?
Well, we could create a variable called is_prime and set it to true.
If this if statement gets triggered, then we switch
this is_prime to false.
And finally, once we get to the end of the for loop, we can go ahead and check
well, is is_prime true or is it false?
And this expression is basically the same as just typing this because this is going to be true or false.
And if it's true, then we get to step into this block and we're going to print from this example output
and say that it is a prime number. But else or otherwise, then we're going to print the opposite
where  we say it's not a prime number.
There you have it.
This is the simplest way of checking whether if a number is a prime number. And all it does is it checks
through all of the numbers between two and the number.
And if it's divisible by any of those numbers, well, then it's not a prime.
Now, out there in the real world, there's a lot of other ways that you could implement this function.
And there's more efficient ways, there's faster ways and there's lots of algorithms that mathematicians
have come up with in the past. Now for our case,
what I'm really interested in is that you understand how inputs work and how you can use the argument
that's passed in to the parameter inside your function in order to do something with it.
As long as that's clear to you, then that means we can continue in the course and I can rely on the
fact that this code or this code will not throw you off and you'll know exactly what's going on when
it's being used inside the block of code and when it's being passed over into a block of code.
In the next lesson, we're going to be putting all of our knowledge that we learned into practice and
we're going to get started building our final project, the Caesar cipher.
So for all of that and more,
I'll see you there.
All right. It's finally time to tackle our final project,
the Caesar Cipher. As I mentioned before,
Caesar Cipher is this way of encoding text that,
um, was seen as early as during the times of Julius Caesar.
So when he had these top secret military messages,
what he would do is he would shift each letter of the alphabet by a certain
predetermined amount. I want to show you quickly how this works.
So we've got the alphabet here and let's say we wanted to encode the letter E. So
now we can line up the alphabet with a new set of alphabet.
And at the moment,
the shift is zero because the top alphabet and the bottom alphabet are lined up
with a zero difference. Now, let's say that we had a shift of one. Well,
then the alphabet moves to the left and A becomes B, B become C et cetera.
And we can keep going until we get to the amount of shift that we wanted.
So let's say we're going to encode all of our text with the shift of three.
Well, then E becomes H, F becomes I, G becomes J et cetera,
and so on and so forth.
And they've actually discovered these artifacts from ages ago
where people have created these sort of dials.
And by simply rotating the dial to a certain amount of shift,
then you can line up the letters with each other.
So A becomes N and Z becomes O and so on and so forth.
And this is a way that people actually encoded top secret messages.
By the end of this day,
you will have also built a digital form of the Caesar cipher.
And all you have to do is to type encode to start encoding a message.
Let's say something like Hello World.
And once we hit enter, we get to type the shift number,
which I'm just gonna choose a random one,
and it gives us the encoded result.
So now if I take this encoded results and I go ahead and type yes,
to restart my program,
and I'm going to use the decode function to decode my message.
Now, when I use the same shift number,
then I should be able to get back the decoded result.
So if there's people monitoring your phone, or you're trying to throw a message to
your friend in a paper ball,
then this is an easy way to ensure that if your message was intercepted then it
won't be understood by the other person. Once you're ready,
let's get started by heading over to repl.it/@appbrewery/caesar
-cipher-1-start. And this contains the starting code for this project
and this is part one of four.
So here I've already saved you the laborious task of typing out all the letters
in the alphabet and they're stores in a single list.
Now I've also got three inputs.
So this is what the user is going to type in.
They're gonna type in encode or decode,
and that's gonna be saved to the direction. Tey're going to type them message
which is going to be changed to lower case
and this is going to be saved in text, and finally,
they're going to input a shift number
which is going to be converted to an integer and saved inside this variable
called shift. So if you want to, have a run of the program as it is right now,
so that you fully understand what's actually going on before you get started.
And remember, don't change any of the code above,
but instead tackle the to-dos one by one.
The first step is to create a function called encrypt
that's going to take this text that the user typed in and the shift that they
typed in as inputs.
And this is going to use what you learned about functions with inputs,
from today's lessons.
And then once you're done with that, step 2 is to go inside the encrypt
function that you just created and shift each letter of the text forwards by the
shift amount. So, again, as we saw before a shift of one,
a shifter of two, a shift of three,
basically just moves the characters forward
so that each letter of the alphabet becomes a letter of the alphabet much
further down the line. Let's say that the user entered the text
Hello and if we tried a shift of five,
then the end result should be mjqqt
and the printed output from this function should say something like the encoded
text is this. And finally,
you're going to call the encrypt function and then pass in the user inputs from
over here
and you should be able to test the code and encrypt a message and see something
like this happen. Pause the video now, have a look through the starting code,
and once you're ready,
go ahead and tackle it and then come back and we'll go through the solution
together. Good luck. All right.
So I'm gonna fork a copy of the starting file and tackle to-do number one,
which is to create a function which is done using Def and it's called encrypt.
And this function is going to take two inputs. So inside the parentheses,
I'm going to put two parameters. Now you can,
of course use the same word as the inputs that you're going to put into it.
But in an ideal world,
you try to not confuse yourself between the arguments and the parameters.
So I'm going to call this plain_text,
this first parameter and the second parameter
I'm going to call it shift_amount. Now, of course, at a later date,
when we're sending the input to this function,
we're going to be sending the text to plain_text and shift to shift_amount.
Keeping the names of the argument and the parameter different will help us
later on to see which one is which. The next step is to go inside the encrypt
function, which of course means indenting by one,
we're going to shift each letter of the text forwards in the alphabet by the
shift amount, and then print the encrypted text.
This is going to be the challenging part of this whole exercise.
But essentially if we think about the problem,
what we want to do is we want to take each letter in the plain text.
So let's say all plain text is equal to hello.
Then we're going to take each of these letters in turn and then shift it up in
the alphabet by the shift amount. So let's say for example,
our shift amount was five and our plain text was hello,
the first thing we're going to do is we're going to take the H which is over
here, and then we're going to shift it up by five. So one, two, three, four,
five,
and we're going to turn it into an M. We can start off by writing a for loop that
loops through each of the letters in the plain text input.
And then we can take each of these letters and work out its position in the
alphabet list here.
And we can do that by using the index method.
So we can tap into a list, write .index,
and then put in the value that we want to get the index for
and we should be able to get that as the result. So back over here,
we're going to say,
alphabet, is the list, .index
and then inside the parentheses, we can put in our letter.
So we want to find out the index of the letter that we're looping through in
this alphabet up here. And once we've gotten a hold of that,
we're gonna save it into a variable called position.
Now, once we've got that, then we're going to calculate the new position.
Now the new position is just going to be the previous position,
which is going to be a number, and then plus the shift amount.
So while we're going through this code, let's look at this word
H. So the first time the loop runs letter's going to be equal to H, position is
going to be equal to zero one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
And then the shift amount is five,
so seven plus five is going to be 12.
So now the new position is going to be 12,
and we can tap into the alphabet list at position 12,
so seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve,
and get hold of the value at that position.
So we can say that new_letter is equal to the alphabet at the new_position.
And now once we've got this new_letter,
we can create a empty string here which we'll call the ciphertext
which is going to be the encoded text. And it starts out being an empty string
and then once we've gotten each of the new letters,
we're going to add it to the cipher text. Now,
the final thing we have to do inside this encrypt function is once the
for loop has run its course,
and we've added all of the new letters into the cipher text,
then at this point, it's a good idea to print out the output.
And it tells us that we should say something like this,
where we replace this final thing with the actual encoded text,
which has of course, called a cipher text in our case.
Now let's just make that into an fstring
so that it'll insert it when it runs and we're ready to tackle the last to-do. So
here,
we're going to call the encrypt function and we're going to pass in all of the
user inputs.
So it remember that our parameter names are plain text and shift amount.
So I'm actually going to use the keyword arguments, so I'm going to say
plain text is equal to the text that the user has typed in.
And then on the next argument,
I'm going to say the shift amount is equal to the shift that the user has typed
in.
So now we're ready to test our code and let's take a look at what happens.
So I'm going to use this example that we've done here by trying to encode hello
with the shift of five. Now the first thing that we type, the direction,
doesn't actually matter because it's not being used anywhere in our code,
at least not yet. So you can type anything you want,
I'm just going to type encode. And then the message is going to be hello.
And the shift number is going to be five.
And now it tells us that the encoded text is mjqqt,
which matches with the expected output.
You might think that we're done, right? This is perfect. This is great
and we've completed this entire exercise.
But lets consider a different scenario.
What happens if we tried to encode a word that had letters that were really
close to the end of the alphabet?
Let's say that we wanted to encode the message zulu.
Now I'm only doing that because if there's a z in that word, of course.
And we wanted to shift it by five.
Now let's think of what's going to happen right? In our code,
we're going to take each of the letters, we're going to take z first
and then we're going to get its position in the alphabet and add the shift
amount to the position to get the new position.
Now, this is already at the end of the alphabet. So if this number
which is going to be 25,
because there's 26 letters in the alphabet and we start the position at zero.
So this plus five is going to be 30.
And what happens when we try to get the 30th item from the alphabet? Well,
you'll find out when I hit enter.
We get an index error and it tells us that list index out of range, and it
occurred on line 15.
So just as we predicted, this does not exist.
We have to try and tackle this right? So if you haven't thought about this,
this is the time to think about how can you solve this problem.
I want you to pause for a moment and try to see if you can fix it.
All right.
So we know that this has a fixed length and what we want to happen when we have
a letter towards the end that we need to encode is to loop back to the beginning
of the alphabet. So to solve this,
all we have to do is just to copy the existing letters in the alphabet and then
just duplicate it once more.
So this means that if we find a letter that's z and it needs to be shifted up
by five letters, it's going to continue until it gets to e.
Now,
the really wonderful thing about this index function is it's going to give you the
first index that it finds.
So if we're looking for the letter a, it's going to give you the index zero
and then it's going to stop.
It's not going to look for all the indices and find this one at position 26.
So it means the our code will now work
even if we have a word that have a lot of letters towards the end of the
alphabet. Let's go ahead and give it a spin,
Right?
Let's type encode. And our message is again,
zulu. And we hit enter.
And then we have a shift number of five and we get our encoded text.
z becomes one, two, three, four,
five, it becomes e, and u, one, two, three, four,
five, becomes z. So now we've solved that small bug.
Now there's a lot of other ways that you could have solved this bug,
but I think this is the easiest way without disturbing our logic here and not
making our function even longer.
If you had any problems with your code, then this is the time to go back and fix
it and make sure that you really understand everything that's going on here
before you move on to the next lesson. But once you're ready,
I'll see you on the next lesson where we're going to decrypt our code.
All right. So now that we've managed to get our program to encode some text,
it's time to do the opposite direction,
which is how do we get our program to be able to decode a piece of text based on
a shift number.
So let's say that we try to decode the letter G and we had a shift number of
three. Well, in this case,
we actually have to work backward and shift backward in the alphabet in order
to get the letter that's three spaces previously.
So in this case,
that would be D. Go ahead and head over to caesar-
cipher-2-start and fork your own copy of it.
Alright, so we've got all the code that we had at the end of part one,
but now we have to create the decrypt function.
And the decrypt function is again
going to take the text that the user inputted and the shift number,
and both of these are going to go into the function as inputs.
And then inside the function,
we're going to shift each letter of the text backward in the alphabet
by the shift amount. For example,
if we started out with this code and we needed to shift each letter by five,
then we end up with the plain text, hello. And finally,
our function needs to print
the decoded text is, depending on what it is that we actually got. Finally,
in to-do part three,
we're going to use that direction
variable that we ignored previously, where we ask the user to type encode
if they want to encrypt and decode if they want to decrypt.
And then we're going to use an if statement here to check which one they chose,
and then we're going to call the corresponding function based on that direction.
And once you've completed all three to-dos,
you should be able to run your program and encode a message
as well as decode a message when you hit run again,
like that.
Have a think about how you might tackle each of the three to-dos and then pause
the video and give it a go.
All right. So how did that go? The first part should be quite easy.
All we have to do is define a new function called decrypt
and this decrypt is going to take the same inputs as our encrypt,
which is the text and the shift that the user entered.
But again,
I'm going to use some different parameter names to be able to differentiate the
arguments and the parameter. So in this case,
because the text that I'm getting is going to be scrambled,
I'm going to call the first parameter cipher_text,
and the second parameter I'll call it again, the shift amount.
Now, after a colon, I'm done with to-do 1. Now let's move on to
to-do 2.
So here I have to be inside the decrypt function,
so indented inside of the function,
and then I'm going to shift each letter of the ciphertext backward in the
alphabet by the shift amount
and then print out the decrypted text. To  do that I'm again
going to need a for loop,
and I'm going to loop through each letter in the cipher text.
And for each of those letters,
what I want to do is I want to get hold of the position that they are in the
alphabet. So I'm gonna check the alphabet and then use again,
that index function
and then tap into the position of the letter.
Once I've got the position, I'm going to define the new position
which is going to be the current position. Now,
remember, we're moving backwards in the alphabet now.
So I'm going to subtract the shift amount from the position.
Once that's done,
I can define a blank variable called plain text,
which is just going to be an empty string.
And once I've gotten hold of each of the new positions,
I can add to that plain text by tapping into the alphabet and then getting hold
of the letter at the new position. So now finally,
once that for loop's completed,
then I can print out the results and I'm going to use the same sort of output
structure as I've got in the example.
And we're going to replace that hardcoded text with the plain text that we've
decrypted. And finally,
I just have to turn this into an fstring so that it actually gets inserted.
Now, the last thing I have to do is the to-do number three.
So here we're actually gonna check the direction variable.
And we're going to see that if it's equal to encode, well
then we're going to call that encrypt method that we had previously,
so indented inside the if statement. But else
if the direction was actually equal to decode, well
in this case, we're going to call our newly created decrypt function.
And we're going to pass in the cipher text as the text and the shift amount is
going to be equal to the shift. So once again,
these arguments come from up here
when we ask the user to input those values.
And now it should go over to the decrypt function and do everything that's
inside to decrypt the text.
So now let's give our program a run and just make sure that it works as
expected. So I'm going to encode our message hello,
shift it by five, and then I'm going to run it again.
And I'm going to try and decode this message now.
So I'm going to type decode and I'm going to paste in that message we had before
and type the same shift number
and now we've got our text decoded.
So that's how you solve step 2 of our project.
Have a review of the code here and once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and we're going to cover part 3 of the Caeser
cipher. So for all of that, and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right. So now that we can encrypt and decrypt our messages, well,
you might be asking, well, what else is there? We've completed the project,
right? Well, let's think about how we can improve our code.
Because if you take a look at the encrypt and decrypt functions,
you'll notice that a lot of the things that they're doing in it are very
similar, right? We've got some piece of empty string to begin with,
we loop through each of the letters in the text that we get passed over and we
get the position from the alphabet, get a new position,
and then add the new letter to that empty string.
Your challenge in this part of the Caesar cipher project is to combine the
encrypt and decrypt functions into a single function called Cesar.
And we're going to get rid of these if and elif statements,
and we're going to get rid of two functions that are overlapping.
And instead, we're just going to have a single function and we're going to call
it just once passing over text, shift, and direction.
So it's going to have three inputs and it's going to save us a lot of repetition
in our code.
Have a think about what you learned about functions with inputs and see if you
can complete this challenge. So pause the video now and give it a go.
Okay.
All right.
So, let's first create a new function and we're going to call it caesar.
This function is going to take three inputs this time.
Not only is it going to get the text, the shift,
but it's also going to get the direction.
So I'm going to call the first parameter start_text because we could be passed
the plain text or the cipher text. So let's just set it as the start text.
The next one I'm going to call the same
so I'm going to call it shift_amount. And then the last one
which is the direction, in order to differentiate it from this direction,
I'm going to make it a little bit longer.
So I'm going to call it the cipher_direction.
And now after a colon,
we're done with defining our function and we can start figuring out how we can
combine these two functions together. We know in both of them,
we need some sort of way of storing a piece of text
which starts out as empty
and then it ends up being the entire encrypted or decrypted text.
Let's create a new variable called end_text to contrast with a start_text.
And we started out as a empty string.
Now, the next thing we have to do is identical.
We have to loop through this text that we get passed over.
So let's create a for loop; for each letter in the start_text,
we're going to do something with each those letters. Namely,
we're going to get hold of the position of the letter in the alphabet.
So this line of code is actually identical across the two functions; position
equals alphabet using the index function to get hold of the index of the letter
that we're currently looping through.
The next part is a little bit tricky because on one hand when we're encrypting text,
we're shifting that position upwards by adding the shift amount.
But on the other hand, when we're decrypting,
we're subtracting the shift amount from the position.
So one way of doing this is, of course, by using an if statement. So you could
check if the cipher_direction was equal to encode. Well then in this case,
the new position is going to be equal to position plus the shift_amount.
And then you could do the else statement.
But there's actually an even easier way of doing this.
We can just check for if the cipher direction was decode.
And in this case, we take the shift amount and we multiply it by minus one.
So remember this line of code is exactly the same as
this, but it's just way more succinct.
And now outside the if statement,
we can define our new position and set it to equal the previous position plus
the shift amount.
And the reason why this works is because let's say that we had a shift amount of
five and we wanted to encode our text, well the new position is obviously going
to be previous position plus five. Now on the other hand,
if we were decoding, well this
if statement is going to trip and our five multiplied by minus one becomes minus
five. So now when we add -5 to
the previous position,
so let's say the previous position was 12 plus -5,
then a quick check with a calculator should get you a 7.
It's exactly the same as subtraction.
So now that we've gotten over that hurdle,
all we have to do is to tap into our end_text and to add to it by getting hold
of the letter at the new position
in the alphabet. And finally, once all of that's done,
we of course need to print the results.
Notice how previously we said the encoded text is and the decoded text is,
well, let's copy this string and paste it in here.
How can we change this part to be dynamic,
so depending on the cipher direction,
and then this part is easy because we can just replace it with the end_
text.
So one way is, remember that when the user is typing in the direction,
they're typing in either encode or decode. So we can delete everything other than
that 'd' and then dynamically insert the cipher direction that we get passed.
And now if we make that an fstring,
it should be able to insert encoded text is whatever the end text is, or
decoded
text is whatever it may be. Now we can go ahead and delete both of these
functions
and also this if statement and we can tackle to-do number two
and we can simply just call the Caesar function
passing over the start_text as the text the user inputted,
the shift_amount as the shift that they inputted,
and finally, the cypher direction as the direction that they inputted.
Now, we've cut down our code by a lot
and we've gotten rid of all the repeated bits of code and we've used what we've
learned about functions with inputs to vastly simplify our code.
We're getting the same function to do repeated actions,
but depending on the different inputs,
it does something completely different.
So now let's give our code a run and let's just make sure that everything works.
Encoding.
Okay.
And decoding.
So there's a bit of an issue there because when we get our decoded result back,
it says holvo instead of hello. So what's going on here?
Well, in my code that I wrote for the Caesar function,
I've accidentally introduced a bug. And as programmers,
none of us are free from this fault. We create bugs, but then we fix them.
So why don't you use this as a good debugging opportunity?
If you've been typing along with me,
I want you to take a look at the code or take a look at the screen and see if
you can figure out what is causing this aberrant decoded result.
Why are we getting holvo back instead of hello?
Where is the problem in our logic in our code?
See if you can solve this and fix the code so that we get back the decoded
results of hello. Pause the video and give that a go.
All right.
So this bug,
if we think about the logic, is caused because our
if statement where we check the cipher_direction and change the shift_amount
by multiplying it by minus one,
this line of code lives inside the for loop.
And we know about for loops that it's going to keep going again and again.
So for every letter in the start_text of which there are five,
every single time, this code is going to get executed and the cipher direction
is always decode so we keep multiplying that shift amount by minus one.
So the first one becomes decode,
the next one becomes encode, decode, encode, decode.
And that's why we're getting some parts of our hello back, but the 'o'
and the 'v' are the parts that are not right.
So in order to fix this, all we have to do is take our
if statement out of the for loop, put it before
the for loop right here.
And now if we run this again and we try to decode the same message,
so that was mjqqt, and we use the same shift number,
but now we get back the correct decoded results. Brilliant.
So did you manage to get that right? Don't worry
if you use a slightly different way of coding this logic up.
It really doesn't matter
as long as you managed to get it to work in the end and combine the two functions
into one. Once you're happy with step three,
head over to the next lesson and we'll tackle the final part
part four of the Caesar cipher
where we complete our project. For all of that, and more,
I'll see you on the next lesson.
All right, we're about to cross the finish line. We're onto the last part of our Caesar cipher
and we're going to complete it in this lesson. First
go ahead and fork your own copy of part four of the Caesar cipher starting code.
And notice, firstly, we've got an extra file here called art.
And this, if you expand it fully, you should see an ASCII art of our logo.
Now, what we want to be able to do in this lesson is just to tidy up some of the loose ends, improve
the user experience and fix some of the bugs that you may or may not be aware of. To-do
#1 tells us to import and print the logo from art.py and this is going to show up when we first
load up our program like this.
Next, we're going to tackle this one. One of the things we haven't really thought about is if the
user enters a shift number that's actually really, really large like 100, then we're actually going
to run out of letters in our alphabet.
And so we're going to use what you've learnt before
and it might take a little bit of thinking around this to fix this particular bug right here.
And once you've done that, then we move on to over here and we think about what to do if the user wanted
to type a number, a symbol or a space.
So we want to preserve the symbols, space, or number that they typed in
and we're only going to use our cipher on the rest of the message,
so only the alphabetical letters. And everything else we're going to leave the same.
So, for example, if we had the text meet me at 3, then the end_text will keep the spaces where
they were, keep the numbers where they were.
And also if there were any symbols, we would also keep that in our final end_text.
And it's only the letters which will get scrambled.
And then finally, to-do #4, we're going to figure out how to ask the user if they want to
restart the cipher program.
So notice how in the final version, when we run this once, we can actually type yes
to go again.
This way we can keep encoding and decoding as much as we want until we're actually done when we can
type no
and it says goodbye
and that's the end of the code.
What we want to be able to do is instead of having to run our code again and again, we're going to
figure out a way of getting our code to be rerun
if the user typed yes to this question. And if they typed no, then and only then do we actually end
the program.
It might take a little bit of thinking to figure out how to solve all of these to-dos.
But once you're ready, if you're up for the challenge, then pause the video now and give it a go.
All right, so let's tackle them one by one. The first one you've already done before.
All it needs is to import the art file.
And if we want to be able to use the logo variable inside the art file, this one, then we can also
simply just write from art import logo.
So now we can print this logo right here.
So that's to-do #1 completed, now let's do the next one. This one requires us to figure out some
sort of clever solution so that when a user enters a shift that's greater than the number of letters
in the alphabet
over here, we have some sort of way of getting it back within the range of 0 to 25.
And I want you to see what happens when I type a message and I put a shift that's really large. You
can see we get an index out of range error because there is no letter at position 77 from the alphabet.
So that's why this line 14 over here actually breaks down.
If you have trouble with this, I gave you a hint where I wanted you to think about how you can use
the modulus.
So if we take 45 and we use the modulus operator to divide 45 by 26, which is the total number of letters
in the alphabet, then we should end up with the remainder.
Now, if you imagine we're dividing 45 by 26, then 26 goes into 45 once,
so we will get one, but we will have a remainder of 19.
So this is what we get from the modulus.
We would get the result to be 19, which is just the remainder.
And effectively, what this code does is it's going to divide a number by 26 as many times as needed
until we get to the final point where it can no longer be divided fully and we end up with a remainder.
And that remainder allows us to shift the shift number that's entered into something that fits in with
the number of letters of the alphabet that we have in here.
So then our code that we would have here is to modify the shift by taking the shift that the user entered
up here and then using the modulus to divide it by 26 as many times as needed until we get the remainder.
So now if we test this out, you can see that no matter how long my shift number is, let's try 87, we're
always going to get a result back because it's shifting that number down to fit within our alphabet.
And once you're done, let's move on to to-do #3.
So here we want to be able to allow any number, symbol or space, basically anything that's not within
the alphabet to go through and end up in the end_text.
But if it is one of the letters inside this list alphabet, then and only then do we actually want to
do the shifting and encoding.
In order to achieve this, we should probably use an if statement to say if the char...
So notice how I've changed the for loop to instead of writing for letter in start_text which kind
of assumes that everything in the start_text is a letter, to char which stands for character instead
because a character could be a number, could be a symbol, could be a letter, could be space.
And then once we get hold of the char or the character, we're going to check to see if the char is
in the alphabet.
So if it is indeed one of these letters and not some other random character, well then and only then
do we actually want this code to be executed.
So let me just make sure all the indentation is correct. And if it's not inside the alphabet, so else,
well then, in this case, we actually want to make the end_text append the actual character,
so without any modification.
Now, if we test this code by running it, so let's go ahead and encode. And I'm going to encode something
like Hello123%^ 321.
And now when I hit enter and I give it a shift, then you can see that the encoded result has all the
letters, all the things are in that list, the alphabet encoded.
But everything else, the numbers and the symbols are all left as they are, because more often than
not, your user might want to write a message like meet me at five or something, something exclamation
mark.
And this is just a very simple way of making it work.
Now, of course, there's a lot of other ways that you could have solved this.
So you could have, in fact, added a whole bunch of symbols and numbers and space and other characters
to this list
And instead of calling it alphabet, it could have been the characters list and then you could have
encoded all of that.
But that's actually not what the toO-do asks for. It wants us to let through the numbers, symbols, space
and only encode the letters.
So now all we have left is the last to-do, and this is probably going to be the most difficult one out
of the lot. What we want to do here is we want to be able to ask the user whether if they want to go
again, so whether if they want to encode or decode another message. And what happens in the final version,
the completed version of the app, is if we encode a message
and we get the result back, it doesn't just end, it doesn't exit because otherwise you would see that
message down here run again.
Instead it continues and it asks us, well, do you want to go again? So we could write
yes.
And it lets us again encode or decode a message.
We can basically go on and on and on and repeating this program until we want to exit.
And it's at that point when we can no longer type anything into our program and our code ends and we'd
have to run the whole thing again in order to use it again.
So at the moment, the part of our code that actually needs to be repeated if the user wanted to restart
it is actually just this part.
So the first thing I'm going to do is I'm actually going to shrink it down a bit.
And now all we're left with is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 lines of code which needs repeat if
we're going to get the user to reuse the Caesar cipher.
What if we go ahead and indent this and put it inside a while loop?
What are we going to check to make sure that our loop continues?
Well, we could create a flag called should_continue and we start this out to be true.
And then while this is still true, we continue to keep looping through this so that the user gets to
input a new direction, new text, new shift and call the Caesar cipher on that again.
When should we stop it though?
Well, if at the end of deciphering or encoding their message, we ask them a question, something like
type
yes
if you want to go again or type no
if you don't want to, we could put that inside an input.
Like so. And we can save their answer inside a variable. Let's just call that result. So now we can
use an if statement to check
well, if the results is equal to no,
so when they actually want to stop and they want to exit the while loop, well, at this point we can
switch
that should_continue to false.
And once that's done, then this means that this while loop, when it checks it, this is going to be
false and it will no longer continue.
Just as a final touch, we can even tell the user goodbye
so that they know that the program has ended.
Now let's go ahead and run our code and see if it works.
All right, so let's first encode something. And now I can type yes to go again, and you can see it's
allowing me to type encode or decode.
So let's encode something else.
Now, finally, if I decided I've had enough, I'm done with encoding and decoding, I'm going to type
no.
It tells me goodbye and I can now see my prompt, which means it's actually exited out of the program
and I would need to run it again in order to restart it.
Did you manage to get that right?
If you want to take a look at the completed code, then you can head over to caesar-cipher-4-end and
you will find the same code as I've got here.
And of course, feel free to play around with the code, modify it and make this program your own.
So if you wanted to add some extra features, if you wanted to make sure that the numbers and symbols
are all being encrypted and any sort of bells and whistles and anything else that you can think of,
this is the time to do it now.
But once you're done, be sure to get some rest, because tomorrow is yet another packed session where
we're going to talk more about Python dictionaries.
For all of that and more, I bid you good night and I'll see you tomorrow.