Hey, welcome back. It's Day 9 of 100 Days of Code.
And today we're going to be learning more about Python dictionaries
and nesting. And by the end of today,
you will have built a silent auction program.
We all know that there are auctions where everybody bids and you can see
everybody else's bid and the auctioneer gets you to bid higher and higher
values. Now there's also a type of auction called
a silent auction where everybody bids silently and no one knows the other
person's bids until at the very end of the auction where the highest bid is
revealed. That's what we're going to be building.
And if you wanna check out the final program,
then you can go to blind-auction-completed
.appbrewery.repl.run.
And here you'll not only see this amazing gavel built out of ASCII,
but also the secret auction program. So here's how it works:
let's say that I'm going to be the first person logging onto the program.
I'm going to give my name and my bid. Let's say
I'm going to bid a $53 for this item.
And once I'm done with my bid, it asked me whether
if there are any other bidders.
So if I type a yes then the screen clears and I can handover the laptop to
the next person who's going to make their bid. So let's say there's James
who's going to bid, um, even less than I did.
And then he's gonna make way for the final bidder who is going to bid $121.
So now at this stage, if everybody is done, then we type no,
and it's going to now tally up all the bids and figure out who bid the highest
and give us a winner, printing out 'The winner is Jenny
with a bid of $121.' There's a number of places that you could use this
if you are auctioning some piece of art or if you're trying to outbid your
brothers and sisters on who gets to go on the trampoline,
or if you're trying to start an auction with your friends or coworkers.
The silent auction has many, many uses. All right, in today's lessons,
we're going to be focusing mostly on the Python dictionary. But in addition,
we're also going to look at how we can nest say lists inside lists or
dictionaries inside dictionaries and also mixing lists and dictionaries as well.
Once you're ready,
head over to the next lesson and let's get started with the day.
All right.
So the first thing I want to talk about is dictionaries in Python. Now,
dictionaries in Python work kind of similarly to dictionaries in real life,
right? So if you were to look up a word in the dictionary
say the word code, then you might find the definition as something along the
lines of program instructions for the computer. And dictionaries are really
useful because they allow us to group together and tag related pieces of
information.
The way I like to think about dictionaries is in the form of a table.
Every dictionary has two parts to it.
On the left hand side is the key,
and that is the equivalent of the word in the dictionary,
and then it's also got an associated value. That would be the equivalent
of the actual definition of the word.
Now let's say that we took this variation simple table of definitions of
programming words that we've come across so far
and we go ahead and we try to convert it right into a dictionary,
how would we do that? Let me firstly
drop the last two rows and let's just start with the first one.
The first thing we want to do is we want them to create a dictionary. And to do
that in Python, this is what the syntax looks like.
We have a set of curly braces and everything that's inside
the curly brace is the content of our dictionary.
The key goes first followed by a colon and then followed by the value. In our
table we've got this word bug, which is the first key,
so we can replace that over here in our dictionary. And the value that's
associated with this key is the definition for a bug.
So an error in a program that prevents the program from running as expected,
that becomes the value and can be replaced here after the colon.
So now, we've created an actual dictionary using Python code.
What if you wanted to have more than one entry in your dictionary? Well,
you would separate each of the key value pairs using a comma,
and then you can continue adding key and value pairs until you get to the end of
your dictionary. All right,
let's take a look at dictionaries in action.
If you head over to the day nine start code file and go ahead and fork your own
copy to work alongside me, then you can see that in here
I've already added the dictionary that we were defining earlier on,
and I've stored it inside of a variable called programming dictionary. Now,
currently I've only got two entries in this dictionary,
the definition for a bug and the definition for function. Now,
the first thing I want to highlight is when you create a dictionary that has
more than one element such as in this case,
then you want to take care to format it properly so that it's more easily
readable.
So what you'll see Python programmers do by convention is they will start off
the dictionary with the open curly brace at the top
and then every subsequent entry is indented by one indent.
And then at the very end of that entry, there's a comma
and then we hit enter so that the next item goes onto the next line
and finally,
the last curly brace should go at the very beginning in line with the start of
the dictionary.
And another thing that's quite nice to do is to cap off all entries in your
dictionary or list with a comma.
This means that if you needed to add more items into the dictionary
you can simply just hit enter and continue typing the next thing.
And if we wanted to add another entry,
it's a simple as adding in the key, a colon and then the value and to cap it
off again with a comma.
So now our dictionary represents exactly the same data as we saw in our table
over here with a bunch of key value pairs and a total of three entries.
Now,
the next thing I want to do is what if I wanted to retrieve an item from the
dictionary, because we know that if we had a list
what we would do is we would use a set of square brackets
and then we would give the index of the item that we wanted.
So the item at index zero or one or two and so on and so forth. Now for
dictionaries, it's kind of similar in terms of syntax
but the only difference is that dictionaries have elements which are identified
by their key. If we wanted this piece of information, for example,
then all we have to do is tap into the dictionary and then add a set of square
brackets and inside the square brackets, we're going to provide the key.
So here the key is a string and it's the string bug.
So let's go ahead and put bug in here.
And now if I go ahead and print this,
then you can see that it is going to give me the value,
which is 'An error in a program that prevents the program from running as
expected.' Now it's really,
really important that you make sure that when you're fetching something out of a
dictionary by it's key that you actually spell the key correctly.
A really
really common error is when you're trying to retrieve something out of a
dictionary and you've just made a very simple typo. So instead of 'u'
I'm typing 'o' here and you'll see
we get an error. And the error tells us that it's a key error referring to this
particular key and it highlights this line 7 where we're trying to retrieve
something out of this dictionary by this key.
Basically it's telling you that this key doesn't actually exist and it can't be
found. So it doesn't know what it is that you want. Remember how
when we had lists and when we try to retrieve something that was not inside the
list. So for example, this particular list at index 4
doesn't actually exist because this is zero one, two, three,
and four is actually not a piece of data inside of this list.
Similarly with dictionaries, if we try to put in a key that doesn't exist,
then we get this key error.
Now another common pitfall that students fall down into is they don't actually
use the correct data type. So for example,
if we defined this dictionary without putting a string around each of these
keys, then it's going to error out and it won't even let us run.
It's going to tell us undefined named bug because it thinks that this is a
variable that you've declared somewhere,
but it's not. In fact, what you wanted are these strings for keys.
And so when you have a key that is a string,
when you're trying to retrieve the data from that key,
you also have to make sure that you provide the key in its actual data type.
So for example, if this was just a number, say one, two, three,
then, of course, all you have to write in here is just one, two, three,
and it would know that this piece of data is what you wanted.
So that's how you retrieve items from a dictionary by adding a square bracket
and then giving it the key.
And it will look for the key inside the dictionary and give you back the
value. Now,
what if you wanted to add a piece of data such as that loop that we had earlier
on, but you want to do it programmatically.
So instead of doing it
when you were defining the dictionary at the beginning,
what if at some later stage in your program you needed to add a new entry?
Well, to do this, it's also really simple.
All you have to do is to tap into the dictionary,
which is called programming dictionary in our case and again,
using square brackets, we define the key.
The key I'm going to add is our loop.
And then after a equal sign, I get to assign the value.
So in my case, the value is going to be the definition for a loop.
And now when this line of code is executed and we go ahead and just print the
programming dictionary after this has happened,
then we'll see that it's actually different from what we had before.
So let's hit run and you can see that previously we had a programming dictionary
that had only two items, bug and function.
And after this line 10, where we print our programming dictionary again,
you can see it's now got three items, bug, function, and loop.
Now very often when you're writing code,
it can be really helpful to start out with a empty dictionary. Just as you saw
previously,
you create an empty list by simply having a set of square brackets with nothing
inside.
You can also create an empty dictionary by simply creating a set of curly braces
with nothing inside. And then at a later stage,
you can add to your dictionary by using this method that you saw here.
Now, on the other hand,
you might actually want to wipe an entire dictionary. Here,
I'm creating a new empty dictionary by creating this pair of curly braces with
nothing inside.
But I can also wipe an existing dictionary by simply doing the same thing.
We know that this dictionary, programming_dictionary, has three items in it.
But on line 17,
I'm going to say programming dictionary equals empty dictionary.
And now if I move this print statement down here,
then you can see that when it prints out,
it's actually going to be completely empty.
That can be really useful if you wanted to clear out a user's progress
or for example, if a game restarts,
then all the scores and stats will probably have to be wiped empty.
So this is one way that you could do that.
Now this method of tapping into a dictionary,
using the key to fetch the relevant item from it
and then doing something with it goes beyond just adding.
You can also use this to edit an item in a dictionary.
For example, let me go ahead and comment out these two lines of code
so we don't wipe our programming dictionary and instead I'm going to tap into
the programming dictionary and I'm going to fetch the item that has a key of bug
and I'm going to redefine its value.
So currently it should be an error in a program that prevents the program from
running as expected.
And I can prove that if I just wrap this around a print statement.
If instead I wanted this to be a different value,
then I can simply use the same syntax as I did for adding new items
but in this case
I'm actually editing this entry because it's going to look through the
dictionary,
find a value with this key and then assign it to whatever I put on the right
hand side of the equal sign. Now, on the other hand,
if it finds nothing with that key,
then it's going to create a new entry with the value again
on the right hand side of the equal sign.
Now let's say that a bug is instead 'A moth in your computer.'
Now, if I go and print my programming dictionary once more,
then you can see that the definition for our bug has now just been changed.
The final thing with regards to dictionaries that I think is really,
really useful is how you loop through a dictionary. And using your knowledge from
lists you might think that to loop through a dictionary, you would,
let's say we are using a for loop. And we say for, um,
thing in programming dictionary,
let's go ahead and print this thing each time.
Here's a good moment to play computer and think,
what do you expect to be printed?
So let's comment out all of the other print statements
so we don't get confused. And when I click run,
what do you think will be printed?
Right?
All right. Is that what you expected? Because it certainly
wasn't what I expected when I first learned Python.
I thought it would give me each of the items in the dictionary with this key and
its value.
But instead this code actually just gives you the keys.
Now, of course, once you do have access to the key, instead of thing,
I should actually really say for key in programming_dictionary.
If I wanted to print the key, then of course I could just write print key.
But if I wanted to get hold of the value,
I could equally just as easily tap into my dictionary,
use the square brackets and pass in that key.
So now when I hit run, you can see it's giving me first
the key from this line and then secondly
the value based on this line.
I'm using that retrieval code in order to get the value.
Of course,
remember that you can get access to all the code that I'm writing here by
looking at the end code of the day
that you'll find on the course resources list.
And if you want to, have a quick review of everything that we've gone through so
far,
because a lot of this knowledge is going to be tested in the next lesson where
we do a coding exercise that will really solidify everything you've learned in
this lesson so far. So for all of that, and more, I'll see on the next lesson.
All right. So hopefully everything we've learned in the last lesson made sense,
and you're ready to put your knowledge to the test by completing the first
coding challenge today.
And what you're going to be building is a grading program.
So if you take a look at the day 9.1 grading program
Repl.it coding exercise, you'll see that to begin,
I've already created a dictionary with a bunch of student names and their test
scores. Now,
without changing any of the code above here or below here,
I want you to write a program that will be able to convert these scores into a
grade. So the grading criteria is over here in the instructions.
So if the student's scores above 91,
then they'll get the grade outstanding. If they score above 81,
they get exceeds expectations and then acceptable.
And then finally everybody's scoring 70 or a lower gets the fail grade.
Essentially,
what you're going to be doing is creating an empty dictionary from scratch
which is going to be called student_grades.
And you're going to write some code so that each of the students are represented
inside this new dictionary.
And instead of having scores as the value's in that dictionary,
you are going to have the grades that correspond to the scores that they got.
Have a read through the instructions and the hints if you need some help,
but once you're ready, go ahead and pause the video and give this a go.
[inaudible]
All right. So to begin, let's first tackle this to-do 1.
Let's create a new empty dictionary called student_grades.
And the student_grades has to be spelled exactly the same as you see here,
because otherwise this print statement will not work.
The student_grades is gonna be an empty dictionary,
which if you remember from the last lesson, we said
it looks like this with two curly braces and nothing inside.
Now let's move on to todo number 2.
So we're going to write some code below so that we actually add the grades to
this student grades dictionary.
And we of course can get those grades by looking at each of the student's
scores. How can we do this? Well,
we're probably going to need a for loop because there's lots of items in this
dictionary. Let's go ahead and loop through this student_scores dictionary,
and I'm going to call each of the items the student,
because remember when we have a for loop looping through a dictionary like we
are doing here,
each of the items that gets picked out is actually the key rather than the whole
item. So again, we talked about this in the last lesson,
but hopefully, this should really make it clear. But even if you didn't know,
you could always of course just print it, right?
So if we go ahead and use the for loop and print it,
you can see we get all of the keys from this dictionary when we're looping
through it. So for each of the students,
we want to get hold of their score.
We can calculate the score by getting hold of the value
using this key from this dictionary. And to do that,
if you remember, is tapping in to the dictionary,
adding a set of square brackets and then giving it the key. So in this case,
it's going to be each of the student names. And once we've got a hold of the
score, well then we can use our if statement to check well
if the score is greater than 90,
so anything above 90,
then that means they're going to end up with outstanding.
Now, this is the part where we add a new entry to this student_grades dictionary.
So let's tap into the dictionary, use a set of square brackets again
to give it a key. And the key,
of course, should still be the student name which comes from here,
which is going to be the same as this.
Then we can add a equal sign and followed by the value
which is going to be outstanding.
So now we can repeat this process for the rest of these grades.
Yeah.
Everybody who scored above 80 but not above 90, so remember that this
if statement once triggered, will skip all of the rest of the elif statements.
And then if they scored above 70, they would get acceptable. And finally,
for everybody else, which means they scored lower than 70,
then they're going to end up with a fail grade.
Now it's really important that if you want the test to pass that each of these
strings has to match what you see over here exactly.
Now that we've done all of this hard work, manipulating our dictionary,
it's time to actually go ahead and run our code and see what we get.
So now our code has converted
each of these scores to the corresponding grade.
Harry gets exceeds expectations because his score is between 81 and 90, Ron gets
acceptable because it's between 70 and 80, and so on and so forth.
Now, did you manage to get it right,
or did you have any problems working with dictionaries? Now,
if you go beyond this lesson
I'm going to assume that you are comfortable with editing dictionaries,
adding to it, creating new ones.
So if you are not yet fully there, then I recommend just going back to the last
lesson, just reviewing it once more.
Once you've done that, head over to the next lesson
and we're going to talk more about nesting in dictionaries and lists. For all of that
and more, I'll see you there.
Now that we've seen lists as well as dictionaries
I want to talk about a concept that you often see in both of these collection
types and that's something called nesting. Now,
if we imagine a list or a dictionary
being something like a folder where lots of things can be stored inside it,
then nesting lists and dictionaries is just a matter of putting one inside the
other. For example,
here;s a dictionary that is very simple,
it's only got one key-value pair.
Now we know that we can add multiple key-value pairs into the same dictionary by
just adding a bunch of commas to separate them. Now, what if
instead of having a simple value like a string or a number,
I could also put a list as a value as well.
Similarly,
I could also use a dictionary as a value. In this case
we've got a list as the value for key, this first one,
and we've got a dictionary as the value for key2. Notice how this is a list and
a dictionary nested inside another dictionary.
The structure gets a little bit more complex,
but it gives us more flexibility when we're trying to store more complex pieces
of data. Coming back to our code,
let's go ahead and create some sample dictionaries to see what this actually
looks like in real life. For example,
this could be a dictionary that contains the country as the key and the city,
that is the capital, as the value. So for France,
that's Paris, for Germany that's Berlin.
This is a very simple dictionary that you've seen already. Now,
if I wanted to nest a list in a dictionary,
then I would be able to represent even more complex data. For example,
if I had a travel log where I was going to collect a dictionary of all the
cities I had been for each of the countries I've traveled to. So for example,
if I had traveled to France and I wanted to say that I've been to multiple
cities, I can't simply just say Paris,
and then Lille, Dijon, that doesn't really work because each key can only have one
value. The only way that we can make these three pieces of data
one value is by turning it into a list, like so.
So now in our travel log dictionary
as represented by the curly braces,
we have one key value pair and it just so happens that
the value in this case is a list.
And of course you can go on and add as many entries as you would like,
and still preserving this kind of structure of key being a string and the value
being a list. Now,
this idea of nesting isn't limited dictionaries by the way.
You could also just nest a list in a list.
So you could have a list which is A
and then B, and then the third item just happens to be another list which has C and D.
This is perfectly valid Python code
but it's not quite as useful as nesting a list in a dictionary or a dictionary
in a dictionary, because the way that data is structured. Now,
what if you wanted to nest a dictionary in a dictionary?
Let's say that we wanted to expand our travel log.
And instead of just storing the cities that I visited in each country,
what if I wanted to also keep track of how many visits I've made to that
country?
Or what if I wanted to actually label what this piece of data is?
Because at the moment it's kind of like here's
a bunch of cities that's associated with the country,
but it doesn't really describe this list.
And I'd like to give this to you as a challenge,
have a go at changing the France entry so that it contains another dictionary.
For the nested dictionary use the key cities_visited,
and for the value you can keep the list of Paris, Lille and Dijon.
Pause the video now and see if you can get that to work.
Yeah.
All right, so here's the solution. By nesting a dictionary
we can label the Paris, Lille and Dijon lists as cities visited.
All I need to do is create the string,
"cities_visited" and add a colon after it. But there's one more step.
We have to add a pair of curly braces so that France is associated with a single
value, namely our nested dictionary.
Now that we have a dictionary of the travel log,
all the countries I've been to, and each country has a value that is a dictionary
in itself and it can store multiple pieces of data
including the cities I've visited in that country
as well as things such as the total number of visits,
which in this case would have a string as the key and a
number of as the value. Now
have a go at creating your own travel log or modifying the second part of the
travel log so that you also have a dictionary nested in a dictionary and you're
able to represent something like this,
the number of cities you visited in a list and another additional piece of data,
if you wanted to.
Right,
And hopefully would have done something similar to this.
And so now our data structure is such that we've got a list nested inside a
dictionary, which is in itself nested in another dictionary.
Now that we've seen nesting lists inside dictionaries, dictionaries inside
dictionaries,
the last thing I want to show you is nesting a dictionary inside a list.
So we could basically have multiple dictionaries inside a single list.
So remember that lists are ordered and they're accessed by the positions inside the
list. So this dictionary would be the item at index zero,
this one at index one and so on and so forth.
Whereas inside a dictionary,
the items are accessed by their keys like this France or Germany.
Now I want to do the last type which is nesting a dictionary
in a list.
And I'm going to be working with the same travel log that we had previously,
but I want to change it so that instead of having this being one giant
dictionary with key-value pairs,
I want to change it so that each of these entries are a dictionary in itself.
Instead of having France be the key of this dictionary here,
I want the turn it into its own key-value pair. Going inside this dictionary,
I'm going to create a new key
which is called country and then put France as the value for that key.
So now I have an entire dictionary that has three pieces of data.
The country visited, the cities visited,
and the total number of visits. Let's do the same for Germany as well.
So now you can see we've got two dictionaries and instead of holding these two
dictionaries inside a dictionary,
I'm going to change it so that it's now a list. I'm going to turn these curly
braces into square brackets
and this way we can add as many of these dictionaries inside the list and
iterate through them if we need to.
When we've been creating dictionaries that only have one or two key-value pairs,
we've kind of just kept it all on one line.
But once you've got more and more key-value pairs in the dictionary,
it's usually a good idea to go ahead and separate out each of the entries,
Right?
Like what I'm doing here.
Now it's a little bit easier to see that we have a list which contains two
items, and each item is a dictionary.
Each dictionary has three key-value pairs and they all contain different types
of data. The first one has a value which is a string,
the second one holds a list and the third one holds a number.
The data types inside a dictionary can be completely mixed up if you want it to.
But what can't change is you still need a key and a value separated by a colon.
Now the only downside to this is you want to make sure that you're actually
aware that later on when you try to pull out the number of visits,
it's actually a number that you're working with rather than a string or when
you're trying to get hold of the cities visited
it's a list rather than a dictionary, for example.
So now that we've the various different types of nesting,
it's time for you to actually really understand this and get to grips with this
concept by completing a challenge yourself. In the next lesson,
I've got a coding challenge for you based on this travel log and you'll need to
use what you've learned so far to be able to complete it.
So for all of that and more, I'll see you on the next lesson.
Now,
if you head over to Repl.it, click on day 9.2 dictionary in list,
this coding exercise should appear.
And you'll see that we actually have the same list that we created at the end of the
last lesson.
This is a list called travel_log and it logs the countries that we've been
to, how many times we've visited it,
and the cities that we visited while we were there.
This is a list of dictionaries
which contain a list of cities.
There's some heavy nesting going on here.
Now your job is to make sure that this line of code on line 20 and 21 actually
work. In order to make it work, you are going to have to write a program.
So it's going to be a function
that's going to go somewhere in here. And you're going to get it to be able to add
new countries, the name,
the number of visits and the cities that you've been to so that it gets
populated in the travel log. And when we print travel log at the end,
it should show us all three of these entries.
So remember, the goal is not to modify this directly. In fact,
I don't want you to touch this part at all. Instead,
it should be your function
that's going to somehow go through this travel log and add these new pieces of
data.
Have a think about how are you going to achieve this and then pause the
video and give it a go. All right.
So, because we've already defined the name of the function here, in order for our
code to actually work and for the tests to go through,
we also have to create the function using exactly the same name.
So it's called add_new_country.
And then the inputs that it's going to take are the country_visited, the times_
visited,
and finally the cities_visited.
So now that we've created our new function,
the next job is to figure out, well,
how do we add these pieces of data
that's going to be passed in to these parameters and get that into this travel
log?
So the first thing you need to notice is each of the entries inside  the
travel_log is a dictionary.
In order to add to that list,
we should probably start off by creating a new dictionary that has all of these
pieces of data in it. For example,
we could create a new dictionary called new_country, which is an empty dictionary.
And then we can add each of these pieces of data to the dictionary. So we
could say new_country[]
and then we give the key that we want to add. So in this case,
it would be the key country as a string,
and the data or the value that's going to go in that is going to be whatever
gets passed into country_visited.
So now all we have to do is repeat the process for the other keys in the
dictionary. So visits is the next one,
and that's going to be set equal to the times_visited. And finally,
we're also going to populate the final key which is cities,
and that is going to be equal to the cities_visited.
Now, at this point, if you were to print out new_country,
you should see a dictionary with the three key-value pairs and the keys will
always be the same,
but the values will depend on which arguments were passed in when this function
was called. So once we have that new country,
then we can actually take our travel log,
and remember that the travel log is actually at its base, a list.
So instead of adding to it like we have been doing
when we're using a dictionary, in order to add to lists if you remember,
you should probably use the function append. And inside here,
we can add a new item to our list.
And that new item is, of course, going to be this dictionary called new_country.
So now if we go ahead and click run,
then you can see when travel_log gets printed on now line 27,
it's now got three entries.
The first entry is the dictionary for France,
the second is the dictionary for Germany,
and the last one is the dictionary for Russia.
We have now a list with three items,
each being a dictionary, each with a nested list inside as
well. So if
you wanted to,
you now have a way of keeping track of all the places you visited.
And later on,
as we start building out more complex apps and web applications,
then you can easily see how logic like this might be really useful
if we were building a real-life website for tracking our travels.
Have a play around with nesting, dictionaries, and lists.
And once you're happy that you've understood everything that's going on,
then head over to the next lesson and we're going to start tackling our final
project.
All right. So now that you've learned all about dictionaries,
we're going to put all of that knowledge to test and to use by building a blind
auction program. So here's the program. When you first run it,
it's just going to show you the logo art and maybe a line that tells you what
program you're in. And then it's going to ask you for your name.
So let's say we have three bidders, right? So first go,
I go to the computer. I type in my name, I type in my bid and I hit enter.
It asked me if there are any other bidders, I look around the room,
I see two other colleagues. So I type yes.
And now it clears the entire screen.
So the other people can't see what my bid was.
So now I leave the computer and my colleague comes over.
They type in their name and also their bid.
And again,
they look around the room and they see this one other person who wants to bid.
So they hit yes, again, it clears their bid. And finally,
the last person makes their bid. At this point, everybody has bid
so she's going to type no.
And it's at this moment when our program is going to work out
who has made the highest bid and print out who the winner is and what their bid
was. This way, instead of competing with each other on bids,
we actually all just give the highest price we're willing to pay
and this is known as quite an efficient way of making a bid.
And you see that a lot in say the construction industry and government,
et cetera.
The important thing in this program is you're going to start out using the blind
auction start replit.
And the first thing you'll notice is that I've already imported this function
called clear from the replit module.
And you can basically call this function, clear, whenever you want to clear the
output just as you saw here. Whenever we typed yes after being asked
if there are any other bidders,
that just calls the clear
and then it gets rid of everything that's in the console. In addition,
we've also got the starting art of the gavel logo
which you're going to put into the program.
And the most important thing of all is that I want you to create a dictionary so
that each person's name will be the key and their bid will be the value.
And this dictionary is going to contain many of these key-value pairs
and at the very end of the program when everybody's done with bidding,
then we're going to loop through that dictionary and figure out who has made the
highest bid. If you want,
this is a good time to analyze this completed project and see if you can
create your own flowchart using something like draw.io that I've shown you
before, or just take a piece of paper and a pen and draw out flowchart.
Now, if you want a hint,
then you can head over to the course resources and you'll get taken to the flow
chart that I've created for this program. So spoiler alert,
I'm about to show you that flow chart. So if you don't want to see it
and you want to create your own because it's a relatively simple program,
then pause the video now and complete the challenge by yourself.
Now for everybody else, who's still here, I want to show you,
this is the flow chart I've created to represent this program.
So we start at the beginning. We first show the logo from that file, art.py,
and then we ask for a name input, we ask for their price.
Now we're gonna add the name and the bid into a dictionary with the name as the
key and the bid as the value. Now, once we're done with that,
then we get to ask the user for another input and see if there are any other
users who want to bid. So if they answer yes,
then we're going to clear the screen and we're going to go back to here,
ask for another name, another price, and so on and so forth. But if they say, no,
everybody's done with bidding,
then we're going to call some sort of function that we have,
which is going to loop through our dictionary that was created here and find the
person who had the highest bid value and then declare them as the winner and
print out their bid. So it's a relatively simple program,
at least compared to other things that you've built so far.
So this is the time to pause the video and give it a go.
I'll see you on the next lesson where we'll go through the solution together.
All right, so how did you get on with today's project?
Hopefully it went really well and you're just here to see how I did it.
As I mentioned before, it's really useful when you're trying to create a large project to break it
down into smaller pieces so that you can tackle each of the pieces one by one.
And a great way of doing that is by creating your own flowchart.
So as I've shown you before in the end of the last lesson, this is the flowchart that I've created
for this particular program, and I'm going to follow it step by step to create this final blind auction
program.
The first thing we're going to do is we're going to show the logo from this file art.py, and notice
how this logo is stored inside a variable called logo.
The first thing we have to do is to fork our own copy of the starting project, and then we're going
to look inside the art.py module and then we're going to import that logo.
So now I can go ahead and print my logo.
So that's the first step done. Next we're going to ask for a name.
So that's going to be in the form of an input.
So let's go ahead and create a variable called name and we're going to set it to be an input.
And the input is going to say, what is your name?
So they're going to type in their name and that's going to be stored inside this variable.
Now, the next thing we're going to do is ask them for their bidding price. We'll say that inside a variable
called price and we'll create another input to ask them what is your bid?
And at the end of this, I'm going to add a dollar sign just so that when they are typing their bids,
they'll see this line.
And when they start typing, the cursor should be about here so they can see the dollar symbol before
their price.
So now we're down to here and we have to add our name and our bidding price into a dictionary.
Let's go ahead and create it up here and we'll call it bids and it's going to start out as an empty dictionary.
And then later on, once we've got the name and the price, we said that the name was going to be the
key and the price was going to be the corresponding value. To add a new entry to our bids dictionary,
we specify the dictionary, we add a set of square brackets, and then we add the key.
The key is going to be the name and the value is going to be the price.
So we would write it like this.
Now, we get down to the slightly trickier part. We're going to ask if there are any other users who
want to bid. And if the answer is yes, then we're going to clear the screen and we're going to loop
back to where we ask for the next name and the next bid price.
How do we achieve this?
Well, we can put this into a while loop. Let's go ahead and indent this.
So I just typed command and then the right-sided square bracket. Or on Windows, it will be control and the right
side of the square bracket.
And then we can wrap this into a while loop.
If we had some sort of variable that would keep track whether if the bidding is finished.
So let's call it bidding_finished.
And of course, it starts out being False.
Now, while bidding is not finished, so while not bidding_finished, so basically while this is still
false, then we're going to keep running this until forever.
But of course, we need a way to stop this.
So we're going to create a new input where we ask the user, "are there any other bidders?"
Type "yes" or
"no". This way we get to get an input which is going to be either the word yes or the word no, and
we can save this inside a variable called maybe should_continue.
So this way we can check this variable and we can see, well, if should_continue is equal to "no",
well, in that case, that's when we're going to flip the switch and change this bidding_finished variable
to true.
So this means that when we get to the end of this block in the while loop, then when it checks this
bidding_finished, it's not going to continue to loop anymore.
Now, on the other hand, if should_continue was yes or in fact any other value, then we can keep continuing
and we don't actually have to change this variable because it's already false.
Now we have our code looping, which means that unless the user types in a 'no' at the very end and bidding
becomes finished, this is this path.
Otherwise then we're going to keep going through all of these lines of code which is basically all
of this until we get to the point where this switch actually gets flipped.
So if you notice that if the user actually answers yes, then we want to clear the screen before we
repeat the loop.
That means we can check to see
well, elif should continue is equal to.
yes,
well, in this case, we're going to call that clear() function that I showed you in the hint at the very
beginning.
So this function comes from the replit module and it allows us to clear the output in the console so
that the previous name and bid gets cleared on off the screen and it leaves a fresh start for the next
user.
The last thing we have to do is to actually address this right? So when they answered no, they get taken
out of the while loop, but we still have to find the highest bidder from our dictionary and to declare
them as the winner.
How do we do this?
Well, let's put this in a separate function. So we could create a new function called find_highest_bidder.
And this is going to get the bidding_record as the inputs, so this will be the dictionary that represents
all the bids, the names and the values. I think it's easier if we can visualize what this bidding_
record might look like.
So we know it's a dictionary of key-value pairs where each key is a name and each value is a number.
So let's say we had only two bidders, Angela and James.
Angela bid $123.
James bid $321.
So we can see who's clearly going to be the winner here.
But how do we get our code to figure that out?
We need to somehow loop through this dictionary, right? which is called bidding_record.
We know that we can use a for loop to do this so we can say for each bidder in the bidding_record,
and this is a good point to remember that when you use a for loop on a dictionary, instead of looping
through each item in the dictionary, like each of these key-value pairs, it actually loops through
each of the keys.
And we covered this in the very first lesson of today where we talked about how the for loop works
when we're looping through a dictionary. Now, we're going to get hold of each of the bidders inside
this dictionary.
So what do we do with it?
Well, we want to use the key to get the value.
Let's take the bidding_record and pass in the key,
and this should give us the value.
So now we can actually save this inside a variable which I'm going to call bid_amount.
So the first time this for loop runs, the bid_amount is going to equal 123
and the next time the for loop runs, the bid amount is going to be equal to 321. If we had some sort
of way outside of the for loop
that keeps track of the highest bid, well then we could use this number to check against the current
bidding amount.
We can use an if statement to check
well, if the bid amount is greater than the highest bid, well, in that case, then the highest bid
becomes the bid amount.
So what this means is that we start out with a zero. The first time the for loop is run, the bidder
is going to be equal to Angela,
the bid amount is going to be equal to Angela as the key passed into this dictionary, which is going
to get us the value 123. If 123 is greater than zero,
well, then this highest bid is now going to become 123. The next time the for loop runs
the bidder is now James and the bid amount is now 321.
Now we're checking if 321 is greater than the highest bid.
Remember this, in the last round, got set to 123.
So this is going to be true.
And this means James' bid, 321, is now going to be the highest bid.
In addition to keeping track of the highest bid, we can keep track of the winner. If this is indeed
true, if the current bidder has the highest bid, well then at the same time as setting the highest
bid,
we should also set the winner to the key,
so the current bidder.
And once we've gone through this for loop and we've looped through all of the records in the bidding record,
well then finally we can actually print
"The winner is..."
the winner that's stored in this variable. And we're going to say they won with a bid of... and let's add
a dollar sign and then we're going to pass in the highest_bid.
Now, we can turn this into an fstring and it will use both of these variables, which is storying
the highest bid and the winner's name to print out who the winner is.
So down here, when should_continue is no going down this path,
we can now print and declare the winner. In addition to saying that bidding finished is true,
we're also going to call that function, find_highest_bidder, and pass in all of the bids that we
have been keeping track of over here.
Now, just before we run our code, let's go through each line and make sure that everything looks all
right.
Firstly here, where it says, 'what is your name?'
maybe we can add a colon and then a space
so the user starts typing here.
Then it asks, 'what is your bid?'
We can add a colon as well and the user will start typing after the dollar sign.
Now, I can already see a problem that's actually going to happen because of this line 23.
I wonder if you can spot the issue here, especially if you think about what we're going to do with
this price later on.
But I'm going to add one more new line here and then I'm going to run the code and we'll see what actually
happens.
So now let's go ahead and run the code.
And you can see our gavel printed and then it asks us for our name, so I'm just going to put my name and
then 123. And then one other bidder who's going to be James, 321.
And now if I say no, there are no more bidders,
see what happens when I hit enter.
I get a type error
and it tells us that the greater sign is not supported between instances of a string and an int
and this happened on line 16.
If we take a look at line 16, basically we're comparing the bid amount, which is the value that came
out of the bidding record, which is what's being passed in here,
and that, of course, is a dictionary where the keys are the names of the bidders and the value is
the price.
So what's actually happening here?
Well, it's because when I took this price input in, I kept it as a normal input.
Instead, it should be turned into an integer.
So that way we can work with it as a number so that when we're comparing it against, say, zero or
whatever other number later on, it can actually do the comparison.
It doesn't actually make sense to the computer when you're comparing a string versus a number. That doesn't
actually work.
And this was covered when we talked about data types in Python.
Now, if we hit run again
and we do the same thing, and when I say no, you can see that it tells me the winner is James with
a bid of 321.
Essentially, the hardest part of this challenge is figuring out how to loop through a dictionary and
get hold of each of the bidders and each of their values and compare them historically against previous
values inside this dictionary.
If this function is confusing to you, then I really recommend either going over to Thonny, pasting
the code in and exploring it by going through it step by step.
Alternatively, if you can't install Thonny or you don't have access to your normal computer, then you
can also go to a website called pythontutor.com.
And this also lets you visualize your code, although in a slightly more simplified way. If I go ahead
and paste in my function, find_highest_bidder, passing in the bid record, let's go ahead and create
a new dictionary of bids.
So now we have a dictionary of bids with two key-value pairs just as we entered before,
and then I'm going to call this function, find_highest_bidder, and pass in these bids.
Now, if we go ahead and click visualize execution, you can see it's going to go line by line, and we
can click next to see how it's jumping through this.
Firstly, it's bypassing this function, creating this next dictionary.
So now it's got a function stored somewhere, which is this one,
it's got a dictionary called bids stored somewhere else.
And now we actually get to the line, which is going to execute that function and it's going to pass
over this dictionary of bids to this function.
And if you step through this line by line, you can see it creating these new variables and populating
them. The first time we run it
the highest bidder is zero, the winner is an empty string, and the bidder in the for loop is now Angela.
It's the first key from the dictionary as it points to here.
Now if we keep clicking
next, it works out the bid amount which is the value corresponding to that key, and then it works
out the highest bid by comparing whether if the current bid amount is greater than the current highest
bid.
So 123 is greater than zero
so when I click next, you'll see highest bid gets replaced with the bid amount and the winner is now
going to be set as Angela. The next time the loop runs the bidder is
now James, and if I keep going through this, you can see that James actually ends up with the highest
bid and becomes the winner.
So now the for loop is done because it's looped through all items in the dictionary and it's now going
to print the output, which is 'The winner is James with a bid of $321.'
This is another way that's really, really helpful to visualize your code.
And the other great thing is that even if while you're visualizing there's still something you don't
understand, you can actually click on this button to get live help from users across the Internet.
And if you want to practice your own debugging, just as we did in today's lesson, you can also click
to help some of these users who are looking for help with their code.
And you can practice reading code, understanding code and helping other people with their bugs and
their issues.
Finally, if you want to take a look at the completed code for today's project, then as always, you
can head over tor repl.it/@appbrewery/blind-auction-completed.
And it's important to remember that this is just one way of completing this project.
There are lots and lots of other ways. But as long as you test your program thoroughly and it works
in the same way, then it doesn't matter too much how you've done it.
But it's important that you've absorbed the knowledge in today's lessons, and the most important of
which is this concept of dictionaries, adding to dictionaries, and also looping through dictionaries.
So have a look through the completed code and also have a play around with Python Tutor, which is
a really great resource for your learning.
And I'll see you tomorrow for more lessons on Python.